<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_and_reform/2015-01-21/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_and_reform/2015-01-21/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2015-01-21" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/31/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_and_reform"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_and_reform/2015-01-21/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_and_reform/2015-01-21/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2015-01-21" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_and_reform/2015-01-21/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_and_reform/2015-01-21/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2015-09-06" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AideenHayden" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aideen-Hayden.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Aideen Hayden"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LiamTwomeyIND" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Liam-Twomey.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Liam Twomey"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaryLouMcDonald" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mary-Lou-McDonald.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Mary Lou McDonald"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelCreed" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-Creed.D.1989-06-29" showAs="Michael Creed"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulMurphy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Murphy.D.2014-10-10" showAs="Paul Murphy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PeadarToibin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Peadar-Tóibín.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Peadar Tóibín"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PearseDoherty" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pearse-Doherty.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Pearse Doherty"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RichardBoydBarrett" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Richard-Boyd-Barrett.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Richard Boyd Barrett"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanDBarrett" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Sean-D-Barrett.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Sean D. Barrett"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanFleming" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Fleming.D.1997-06-26" showAs="Seán Fleming"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ThomasByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Thomas-Byrne.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Thomas Byrne"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>COMHCHOISTE UM AIRGEADAS, CAITEACHAS POILBÍ AGUS ATHCHÓIRIÚ</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2015-01-21">Dé Céadaoin, 21 Eanáir 2015</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2015-01-21">Wednesday, 21 January 2015</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 02:30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS  PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#TomBarry">Deputy Tom Barry</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#SeanDBarrett">Senator Sean D. Barrett</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#RichardBoydBarrett">Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#ThomasByrne">Senator Thomas Byrne</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelCreed">Deputy Michael Creed</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#AideenHayden">Senator Aideen Hayden.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#PearseDoherty">Deputy Pearse Doherty</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#ReginaDoherty">Deputy Regina Doherty</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#AlanFarrell">Deputy Alan Farrell</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#SeanFleming">Deputy Sean Fleming</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#MaryLouMcDonald">Deputy Mary Lou McDonald</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelMcGrath">Deputy Michael McGrath</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_13">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulMurphy">Deputy Paul Murphy</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_14">
                  <person refersTo="#ArthurSpring">Deputy Arthur Spring</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_15">
                  <person refersTo="#PeadarToibin">Deputy Peadar Tóibín</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#LiamTwomeyIND">DEPUTY LIAM TWOMEY IN THE CHAIR.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
        <summary eId="sum_4">
          <i> The joint committee met in private session until 2.55 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Operations and Functions: Office of Government Procurement<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T14:50:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_1">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T14:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_16">I welcome Mr. Paul Quinn, chief procurement officer of the Office of Government Procurement, who is accompanied by Mr. Vincent Campbell, policy director, and Ms Theresa Ryan, communications manager. I also welcome Ms Gráinne McGuckin, principal officer at the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform. The format of the meeting will be that Mr. Quinn will make some opening remarks and, in view of the time constraints, I ask that he take less than ten minutes to do so. I remind members, witnesses and those in the Visitors Gallery that all mobile phones must be switched off.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> I wish to advise the witnesses that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, they are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee. However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they will be entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence. They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> Members are reminded of the long-standing ruling of the Chair to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> I call Mr. Quinn.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T14:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_20">I thank the committee for the invitation to attend this meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_21"> It is important to note that the new structures for procurement are still at a very early stage. As chief procurement officer, CPO, I welcome this debate, and the advice and guidance that committees such as this can provide, as we start to make significant changes to how procurement is done in the State and the policy framework that underpins the processes involved. I understand the committee is interested, in particular, in the possible impacts of the new suite of procurement directives that were agreed by the EU Parliament and Council earlier this year. I welcome this opportunity to provide it with an update on the transposition process and the procurement reform programme currently under way across the public sector.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> The procurement reform programme is an important element of the Government’s overall reform programme and is tasked with delivering increased value for money, more accurate and timely data and improvement in the capacity and capability of procurement across the public service. The State spends significant amounts of money on goods and services, with an estimated spend in 2014 of €8.5 billion. Of this, €5.8 billion was addressable by procurement. In addition, approximately €3.5 billion is spent by the State on capital works. This does not currently come within the scope of the operational reforms. A new model for procurement was approved by the Government in September 2012, with common goods and services to be procured by a new central sourcing organisation, the Office of Government Procurement, OGP, and with central sectoral sourcing organisations in health, education, local government and defence procuring sectoral-specific goods and services.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> In January 2013, I took up my role as the State’s first chief procurement officer.</p>
          <p eId="para_24"> In consultation with the key State sectors, I developed a high-level implementation plan for the new model. This plan was approved by Government in April 2013. In addition to its operational procurement role, the Office of Government Procurement, OGP, also provides the national procurement policy function, customer support services, and systems for all the sourcing organisations, including electronic tendering systems, business intelligence and electronic catalogues, etc. The new structural arrangements for the OGP and the sector-sourcing organisations are currently being put in place. Staff are being recruited into the OGP largely from the public service, thereby concentrating and leveraging the public sector's procurement expertise. Similar processes are taking place in local government, education and health in order to create the centralised sourcing organisations in those sectors. Transition arrangements are being managed across these sourcing organisations to realign responsibilities. It is anticipated that completion of structural changes will take place in 2015. The OGP has met with most of its key customers, namely, Departments and agencies, to commence the process of transferring their pipeline of sourcing projects to the OGP and to the other sector-sourcing organisations.</p>
          <p eId="para_25"> The new model is underpinned by a common governance model. The arrangements include a procurement executive to bring together the sourcing organisations at an operational level to co-operate and collaborate; a steering group to oversee the transition to the new model; and an interim board chaired, by the Minister of State, Deputy Simon Harris, to provide strategic advice on procurement matters to the OGP and to the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.</p>
          <p eId="para_26"> Accountability for the legal compliance of the sourcing process will rest with the sourcing organisation that undertakes the tendering. The OGP does not have the resources or mandate to oversee or audit the actions of other sourcing organisations. The OGP relies upon the existing governance arrangements in place for those public bodies, including the offices of the Comptroller and Auditor General and the Local Government Audit Service, to provide such assurance. Budget responsibility remains with the public service bodies. The contractual arrangements put in place by the new sourcing organisations will help these bodies to remain compliant and to deliver value for money. Any savings arising from procurement remains with these bodies, enabling them operate within their budgets, to deal with increased demand or to deliver new projects or services. Value for money is defined by more than price alone; it also takes into account the quality of the goods or services provided, the management of risk, such as the financial stability of the service providers, and the contractual protections suppliers are providing to the State, such as the warranties they are providing and the risks they are bearing.</p>
          <p eId="para_27"> There continues to be wide-ranging data quoted regarding procurement spend. There are thousands of State bodies spending money, the larger of whom have IT systems for processing spend, the smaller of whom are probably using spreadsheets or even paper to record their spend information. The State previously had no mechanism for collecting detailed data on the amount of moneys spent across the public service on goods and services. It has not been possible to determine in detail how much is spent, with whom, on what, and at what price.</p>
          <p eId="para_28"> I will explain to the committee what OGP is doing to bring about better data on procurement. In autumn 2013, the OGP initiated a project to begin collecting the spend information from the larger sectors, namely, health, education, local government and justice, which account for over 80% of the State's spend on goods and services. The OGP has collected approximately €8.7 billion of the State's spend in one central repository. This is a total figure from 2011 to 2014. The project has moved on to a second phase which, when complete, will include central government. For the first time this will allow the OGP in the coming months to publish far more accurate estimates of spend. </p>
          <p eId="para_29"> The OGP is fully aware of the significant role that small and medium enterprises play in the economy and it is strongly committed to ensuring that SMEs are fully engaged with public sector procurement and the opportunities presenting. The office works with State and industry representative bodies in developing and implementing policy initiatives and in driving supplier education and awareness. In that regard, it is important to mention Circular 10/14 which was launched in April 2014 in order to further assist SMEs and which accelerates the delivery of certain measures in the new procurement Directive 2014/24/EC. The OGP has also delivered a number of improvements in Ireland's electronic tendering platform - e-tenders - including changes to registration and recording of awards for contracts in excess of €25,000.</p>
          <p eId="para_30"> As part of my submission to the committee, I have attached a report from the EU Commission entitled, SMEs' Access to Public Procurement Markets and Aggregation of Demand in the EU. The report, which was published in 2014, outlines the increasing drive towards centralised professional procurement and the administrative and competitive benefits arising. The report highlights the competitive nature of the Irish marketplace and the open nature of Irish public procurement in that context. The report - on page 71 - highlights measures which Governments can undertake to assist SMEs. Many of these have been implemented in Ireland. </p>
          <p eId="para_31"> I will speak about the legal framework for public procurement. The main purpose of the EU public procurement regime is to open up the market and to ensure the free movement of supplies, services and works within the EU. The legal framework for public procurement is drawn from the core Treaty of Rome principles, including openness, transparency, proportionality, non-discrimination and equal treatment. These principles shape the detailed rules governing the regime and as set out in the directives.</p>
          <p eId="para_32"> A new suite of public procurement directives was politically agreed under the Irish EU Presidency. The three new directives will govern general public procurement of goods, services and works, procurement in the utilities sector and new rules for concessions procurement. These new directives will repeal the existing rules governing the conduct of procurement across the EU but the overall framework of EU procurement remains intact. The implementing regulations will continue to uphold transparency in money outcomes for contracting authorities and entities. </p>
          <p eId="para_33"> The changes agreed in the directives are intended to help to make the public procurement process more efficient and to seek more simplified and flexible rules for the selection of suppliers in order to allow contracting authorities to carry out procurement in a more timely manner and with less red tape. In broader economic policy terms, the changes are intended to achieve better value-for-money outcomes for the taxpayer from public procurement; to facilitate greater SME participation in the public procurement market across Europe by improving access to public procurement opportunities; and to reinforce adherence to applicable obligations in the areas of environmental, social and labour law. It is important that in transposing EU rules into national law, contracting authorities and tenderers are not unduly burdened by requirements that increase their administrative overhead and bureaucratic load. The planned approach, therefore, is to avoid creating unnecessary legislative burdens on contracting authorities or in placing Irish economic operators - the suppliers - at a competitive disadvantage when compared with their EU neighbours. Where appropriate, contract conditions can be used in pursuance of policy objectives if related to the subject matter of the contract and if clearly set out in the tender documentation. </p>
          <p eId="para_34"> While most of the changes in the new directives are mandatory for Ireland and all member states to implement into national law, there is some limited policy latitude permitted to member states in transposing the new regime into national legislation. This office is exploring policy choices as part of the transposition process and has carried out internal consultation with key stakeholders and initiated a public consultation process. The public consultation on the new directives was launched on 31 October 2014 by the Minister of State, Deputy Simon Harris. Responses on the key policy questions posed in the document were required by 12 December 2014. Given the importance of public procurement, we received submissions across a broad spectrum of areas, including legal, SME, academic and industry representative bodies. This office is currently examining the submissions received and consideration will be given to the responses received when drafting the statutory instruments to implement the EU rules into national law.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">The new directives are required to be transposed by 17 April 2016-----</summary>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_3">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">Will Mr. Quinn come back to the core issues because we may get stuck for time? We will come back to the other issues he wishes to raise in detail if questions are asked on them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_4">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_36">I will not go through the rest of the report and I will take it as read for the meeting. I will highlight a couple of points.</p>
          <p eId="para_37"> Circular 10/14 was a key policy instrument that we launched in April 2014. It is critically important in terms of implementation across contracting authorities because it opens up and sets the rules for them as they address the marketplace and it is SME friendly. We did that in consultation with the industry groups, including ISME, SFA, IBEC and CIF. We consulted broadly with them before implementing the circular.</p>
          <p eId="para_38"> I will talk further about social clauses during the meeting but considerable work is under way. The Minister launched a group in 2014 to establish social clauses policy work and it has identified 11 projects to date to further test and develop social clauses in contracts. We also mentioned in the report positive developments on the schools bundle programme where existing social clauses are being rolled out. There have been positive and welcome developments in that context.</p>
          <p eId="para_39"> We can discuss PPPs and concessions during the question and answer session.</p>
          <p eId="para_40"> We mentioned the community and voluntary sector. This office has met The Wheel, in particular, as a key representative of that sector. We had a positive meeting in the context of understanding where the sector is coming from and helping people to understand the new changes being brought to bear by the directives and legislation introduced at EU level.</p>
          <p eId="para_41"> Public procurement is still incredibly important to the State and the taxpayer in terms of the value for money it can generate. We are bringing new structures to bear in this respect but we are at an early stage. The OGP is still only building its capability and capacity; 2015 will be a key year of transition. It is important during the transition, though, that we listen to all our stakeholders. We have good mechanisms for that and we have put in place good structures. I welcome further discussion with the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Deputy Sean Fleming<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">I welcome Mr. Quinn and his colleagues. I will not make an opening statement. I will ask questions and if Mr. Quinn does not have sufficient time to respond, I ask him to forward his responses to the committee in the next day or two. He said €8.5 billion out of current expenditure is spent annually, €5.8 billion of which is addressable by procurement. Will he explain the other €2.7 billion that cannot be addressed by procurement? He said the capital expenditure programme, which is valued at €3.5 billion, is not included in his office's work. Why not?</p>
          <p eId="para_43"> He stated the EU Commission report "highlights the competitive nature of the Irish marketplace and the open nature of Irish public procurement in that context". That is the particular problem Irish companies face. "Open" means open to companies outside Ireland to bid. That is where Ireland is losing out. I tabled a parliamentary question asking the Minister why we were not at the European standard in terms of businesses in Ireland getting business from Irish public bodies and he replied that this was because all our documents are printed in English. Companies in every country are familiar with English and are well able to tender and bid for our contacts whereas in Italy, France, Greece and Spain procurement documents are printed in the home language, which is not as readily accessible by companies in every other member state. I would like Mr. Quinn to address that issue because I was surprised by that comment. If we published the documents in Irish and helped Irish people to translate them in some way, we might keep some of the others out, as they successfully do in other countries by using their native language.</p>
          <p eId="para_44"> Will Mr. Quinn confirm that commercial semi-State bodies are not covered by his office? That is the largest gap in his operation. I acknowledge these bodies have a commercial mandate. I will not even mention how much Irish Water is supposed to spend but if that does not come under procurement rules, where are we going?</p>
          <p eId="para_45"> Mr. Quinn mentioned the Department of Health but another significant gap relates to the procurement of drugs and medicines. The HSE, which is not covered by the OGP, is not competent and it is afraid of the large pharmaceutical companies. It goes cap in hand to them because they are significant employers. Has Mr. Quinn examined his office taking over responsibility for procurement in this area and perhaps working with an equivalent officer in another member state to jointly procure? I do not accept, nor does anybody in Ireland, that we are getting value for money in this regard. Part of the reason for this is we feel a little insecure in putting it up to large employers and we are afraid to upset them. Perhaps if the OGP worked with a similar office in England, France or Spain, a better deal might be achieved.</p>
          <p eId="para_46"> Mr. Quinn made no mention of the cost of his office, the number of staff and the break even period. It obviously cost tens of millions of euro to set up the operation. Will he provide the figures?</p>
          <p eId="para_47"> Everybody wants social clauses included in contracts. When will he review the 11 projects under way? Will that be at the end of the contracts, which could be a few years away?</p>
          <p eId="para_48"> When Mr. Quinn visits the Department of Education and Skills with a procurement list, there is a breakdown in communication between his office and some schools. The procurement list includes photocopying paper, pencils, rulers, IT equipment and so on and schools are told they must operate from the list unless they can get a better deal locally. Schools use the supplier on the list as the nominated supplier when they want items that are not on the list that were tendered for. The school principals are being rolled over for the additional items not on the list when they order online. Will Mr. Quinn address this?</p>
          <p eId="para_49"> I refer to the links to payment. It is fine for the OGP to have a role in procurement but does it have a role in making sure the payments correspond with the procurement contracts, given there are overruns all over the place?</p>
          <p eId="para_50"> Shame on the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation because the Construction Contracts Act 2013 has not yet been implemented. There is, therefore, no protection for subcontractors in public procurement contracts. The Act was passed two years ago, having been on the legislative list for five years. Officials are fluting around over which Department should be responsible or who should be the chair of the bodies that come under it. The industry came under the remit of the Department of Finance for years but it is now under another Department and years later there are no agreed chairmen and mediation procedures in place. The OGP is deliberately dragging its feet. If there was a will to implement the legislation, it would have been implemented.</p>
          <p eId="para_51"> When will the public contracts review be completed? Mr. Quinn said that perhaps this might happen next year. Are zero energy contracts being considered in buildings such as schools? The office should be working towards energy efficiency.</p>
          <p eId="para_52"> Does his office examine the payment record of companies that tender? That has been a problem. It is known that directors of many of the companies that won contracts operated through different shelf companies and did not pay people in the past. They produced financial statements, accountants' reports and tax clearance certificates but one will know in one's heart that these are not honest people but the OGP is trapped in having to award them contracts. The payment record of the principals of companies must be factored in. The office should have a mechanism to track that.</p>
          <p eId="para_53"> That is my series of questions. I am happy with that and if Mr. Quinn runs out of time, I would like the answers to the other questions forwarded to the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_6">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">I thank the Deputy for the questions. The first item might be better handled in a tabular format through a separate written response. We believe we can make more progress quickly with regard to main goods and services. Capital is included in the office's remit from a policy perspective and Mr. Campbell's policy team deals with procurement policy across both goods and services and capital works. Operationally, capital works are typically large bespoke projects, where the procurement bit is a small aspect of the overall tendering process. At this time, from a taxpayer perspective we would be best to focus on working on goods and services, which is a major part of the transactional activity - and repeat transactional activity - taking place within the State. I would not rule it out at a later stage but where we are in our development, I do not think it will happen.</p>
          <p eId="para_55"> If the committee has the PwC report that was circulated, I will give some very useful information relating to the open nature of Irish public procurement. A document from the EU was its genesis and it was drafted by PwC and other parties. It is the first time it has contrasted not only works awarded by the Irish State to businesses outside the State but it also brings into play contracts awarded to Irish companies by other jurisdictions. Pages 66 and 67 of the report give the relevant figures. In summary, between 2009 and 2011, for above-threshold procurements or large procurements that must go into the EU Journal, 14.3% of the expenditure by value went outside the Irish State. In contrast, 17.2% of the value of goods and services that the Irish State has as above threshold came into the economy. Being open is not a one-way street and Irish businesses are winning more in Europe than is flowing the other way.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Deputy Sean Fleming<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_56">That is not from the Office of Government Procurement. It is nothing to do with it. They do it for Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_8">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_57">I am saying the net picture for Ireland is good as there is an open procurement regime. I will speak a little more about what we are doing about that. I have already mentioned Circular 10/14 and there are a number of various initiatives to try to help not only from a policy perspective but to enable small and medium enterprises, SMEs, by breaking larger contracts into lots by reducing turnover requirements and by being flexible in not requiring SMEs to submit lots of documentation in advance. These are good initiatives as well but on the other side we are doing much with building awareness and education within the SME community. We work very closely with Enterprise Ireland and Intertrade Ireland. Some Deputies were able to attend the event we had in October or early November in Citywest which had approximately 700 suppliers in attendance. That was great as those attending could meet people from our office and other sectoral organisations in the new structures. We are doing much in helping awareness and education in Irish companies.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_9">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">I must ask that the witness have the answers to the remaining questions forwarded to the secretariat and we can get them to the Deputy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_10">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">That is okay. I will comment on another issue that is worth mentioning. I regret that semi-State bodies are not included from an operational perspective. From a policy perspective, they are obliged to follow the policies set by the Government and the office. With regard to the HSE and drugs in particular, that arrangement is overseen, by and large, by the Department and not the HSE. We have offered our assistance, as was mentioned to the Committee of Public Accounts, to the Department of Health to help it procure those goods and services.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Deputy Sean Fleming<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_60">We support the office with that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_12">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_61">I will revert with the replies to the other questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelCreed" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Deputy Michael Creed<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">There is little I can ask that has not been raised by Deputy Fleming. The State spends a lot of money on procuring goods and services, with the objective of driving efficiencies in that sector, which is beneficial for the taxpayer. My experience at a constituency level is that nobody has come in to me to tell me a business is thriving because of the Office of Government Procurement; I have had the opposite experience, with small businesses in my constituency squeezed out of contracts they had in the public service. Will the witnesses flesh out how this is beneficial for service providers? I appreciate the point that given the European aspect, we could gain business on that level. That refers to individual companies which are doing business for themselves with opportunities. On the other hand, many indigenous small Irish companies who are not in a position to avail of the big opportunities in Europe are being squeezed out by companies coming in and taking Irish business.</p>
          <p eId="para_63"> It is important to have assistance in place for people buying and selling, whether we are talking about toilet paper, paper clips or school books. It is also important to have systems in place. Let us not become preoccupied with having systems in place if there is no delivery for business, workers, employees and the State in general. Will the witnesses give me the good news story as it exists for Irish SMEs, as I have not seen it? As I noted, in my constituency I have seen the opposite. I know two companies, one of which was involved with education and one which dealt with hospitality, that have lost substantial business in this process. They would be highly critical of what has happened with regard to the businesses that replaced them. When we look behind a company facade, it amounts to import substitution, as it may be bringing in products from China as opposed to using indigenous products. It is not all about price and should not be all about price.</p>
          <p eId="para_64"> If there is any remaining time, I would be interested in getting answers to some of the questions raised by Deputy Fleming.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_14">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">The Deputy's colleague will have that opportunity first.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_15">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">I thank the Deputy for the questions. I can give a better flavour of some of the performance statistics and spend information. The PwC report I mentioned relates to above-threshold expenditure. As part of my submission, I mentioned that the office has been gathering spend information since October 2013. We now have a fairly good picture of expenditure, although it is still a sample. We have a fairly good picture of the profile of expenditure which now takes place across the State.</p>
          <p eId="para_67"> In that regard, out of our approximately €12 billion, we have analysis at a detailed level for approximately €3.2 billion for 2013. It is approximately a quarter of the total for the sample size. It is statistically valid because it is such a big sample. There is detail of expenditure for some key sectors, including health, education, justice and local government, so it includes much of the infrastructure of the State. It would include gardaí and local authorities, and we have much information for health and the education sector, albeit not small national schools. This provides a good understanding of how the State spends its money.</p>
          <p eId="para_68"> I can give some headlines on what that means as the above-threshold section only provides a view of the bigger picture. The PwC report draws attention to this.</p>
          <p eId="para_69">In terms of small goods and services contracts, they are almost all won within the State. The information I will provide will reinforce this statement. The Minister read into the record of the Dáil the fact that the Office of Government Procurement, OGP, had estimated that approximately 95% of all goods and services spend remained within the island of Ireland and approximately 75% of that expenditure was with small to medium-sized enterprises, SMEs. From the sample that we have in place, we have associated statistics. There was €2.7 billion of a spend in 2013. The good news is that, while this is not quite 95%, 93.34% of all expenditure stayed within the island.</p>
          <p eId="para_70"> Procurement is all about driving competition and some suppliers that might have had long-standing relationships with small public bodies do not like having to go through public competitions. From the perspective of the taxpayer and procurement, it is a question of fairness, openness and transparency and of bringing a competition to bear, be it small or large, in which people routinely participate. Sometimes, those long-standing relationships must be put to the test on behalf of the taxpayer. Ultimately, this is why the directives and legislation are there. On behalf of taxpayers, they require public bodies to go through this process and buy their goods and services in a fair, open and transparent way. Our competitions often see anywhere between five and ten bidders. As there can only be one winner, sometimes business moves. We do not see the profile changing substantially at an overall level, however, so the business will stay on the island. We are working with the business representative bodies to try to support Irish businesses to understand public procurement so that not only can they win business here, but also look to export more.</p>
          <p eId="para_71"> I will discuss the statistics on SMEs. Our previous estimate from a small sample was approximately 75%. From this sample size of €2.742 billion, 79% remains with SMEs and just under 21% goes to large businesses. Relative to other countries, SMEs in Ireland do well. Then again, Ireland has many small businesses relative to other European countries.</p>
          <p eId="para_72"> There is a great deal of good news for Irish SMEs and other businesses, but we want to help them to become better. Ultimately, our office is concerned with delivering value for money for the taxpayer via a competition process. We want to assist SMEs in understanding that process and in developing their skills and capabilities so that they can compete fairly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelCreed" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Michael Creed<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">I wish to ask a supplementary question on that point. Mr. Quinn referred to SMEs but it might be beyond many micro businesses that service Munster, for example, to tender elsewhere because they do not have the distribution networks and personnel to bid for the national supply of education material, etc. How effective has the regionalisation of the market been? We must be unapologetic in our structuring. We must get prices, but we can also be creative so as to tilt the pitch more in favour of indigenous companies. Micro and small businesses in particular could remain in service provision if the country was carved up in a way that suited them. This cannot be done if prices are exorbitant, but many businesses with long-established records of regional service provision are finding that they cannot compete nationally because of scale.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_17">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">One of the key aspects emphasised by the office and the Minister is that this is a question of value for money, not price. Price is only one small aspect of the overall formula when assessing value for money. We need to ensure that there is quality in the goods and services that are delivered, that the service level associated with that delivery, for example, after-sales support, is good, and that contractual protections are in place to protect the State. The standing instruction from the Government under circular 10/14 is that it is not just a question of price. Rather, the valuation should be based on what is called the most economically advantageous tender.</p>
          <p eId="para_75"> In terms of regionalisation, many services that are delivered within the State are provided on a local basis. For example, solicitor services for local authorities are delivered locally. One would not find someone who would travel from Donegal to Dingle to provide a legal service. It does not work that way. Many of the goods and services that are consumed by the State are often consumed locally. Consider cleaning. One would not find people who would travel long distances to deliver that service. However, there are other sectors in which services are delivered at a national level. For example, energy and electricity are not delivered locally. Neither is software.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_18">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">I apologise, but this session must conclude and I must move on to the next contributor.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryLouMcDonald" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Deputy Mary Lou McDonald<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">I welcome Mr. Quinn and am delighted to see him. I would like to believe that this will not be a one-off event. The work that the office is doing is of such significance that we need to get into a rhythm of exchanges, feedback and oversight.</p>
          <p eId="para_78"> I will not ask for a direct answer now, but I will say something for Mr. Quinn to consider. He mentioned how the community and voluntary sector had been caught under the procurement process. Many in the sector are concerned that they will be outplayed by for-profit organisations. Those in the sector work to a different ethos. While the committee has an extensive work programme, it would be interesting to tease this argument out and to hear from The Wheel and other such organisations. I urge Mr. Quinn to watch this situation carefully so that we do not throw out the baby with the bath water.</p>
          <p eId="para_79"> I will make an observation on circular 10/14 relating to a matter that I have raised with Mr. Quinn and Mr. Campbell previously, namely, access for SMEs and micro businesses to the tendering process. The office's exhortations to them to form alliances and networks do not always work and have caused them considerable difficulties. Some of the businesses in question are in Deputy Creed's neck of the woods and elsewhere. People have lost business. This approach needs to be reworked, as it does not work for everyone and no amount of training courses or encouragement will alter that.</p>
          <p eId="para_80"> What, if any, engagement, oversight or role does the office have in the flagship infrastructure enterprises, for example, Grangegorman and the children's hospital? What linkage has the office with NAMA or other organisations in respect of the development of Dublin's docklands?</p>
          <p eId="para_81"> The witnesses are aware that, like others, I am keen on social clauses in large contracts. Mr. Quinn referred to piloting 11 projects. While this is to be welcomed, it strikes me as being timid.</p>
          <p eId="para_82">The new European regime recognises in a more expansive way that it is not solely a question of price because there are consequences and knock-on effects for State expenditure from a social point of view, in terms of long-term unemployment, poverty and environmental concerns. Beyond the 11 projects, what is the game plan for implementing these clauses? Can we be assured that, within the boundaries of the law, the office will be as imaginative and expansive as it can in getting a return for society and the community?</p>
          <p eId="para_83"> In his opening remarks, Mr. Quinn stated that responsibility and accountability for legal compliance rests with the organisation which undertakes the tender because the OGP lacks the resources and mandate to perform this crucial task centrally. Is that a desirable state of affairs? I ask that in light of the experience of school building projects overseen by the Department of Education and Skills, which gave rise to worrying controversies with, for example, Rhatigans and Kishogue college in Lucan. There are similar cases elsewhere in Dublin. I am concerned that while the office maintains rigorous standards of compliance for those who enter the tendering process, without a tight oversight mechanism the process could become sloppy and wide open to abuse.</p>
          <p eId="para_84"> I have many other questions but the Chairman will not tolerate anything that stretches the committee's time unreasonably. The definition of value for money is not just about price; it also includes quality and other factors. I ask Mr. Quinn to set out the definition of value for money to which the OGP works.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_20">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">As part of our meetings with the community and voluntary sector, including The Wheel, we encouraged organisations to make a submission on the transposition process so that they could have their say on the new framework.</p>
          <p eId="para_86"> In regard to our involvement in infrastructure and capital projects, the office has no operational remit with regard to the procurement of large capital works. The Deputy referred to Grangegorman, the docklands and the children's hospital as examples of such projects. We are not running procurement at an operational level for those individual projects. In terms of policy, we have a clear remit in that regard. Through our government construction contracts committee, we pull together the key stakeholders involved in executing capital works on an ongoing basis to examine the issues arising. This could include the review of public works contracts or various other emerging requirements identified by the committee on behalf of constituent stakeholders, including the Department of Education and Skills, the Office of Public Works and the Department of Health. From a policy perspective, we push out policy through that committee and consult it on the development of policy. However, the office does not get involved with the day-to-day procurement activities of the individual projects. I am a board member of the children's hospital and, as such, am intimately involved in procurement for that project but that is restricted to my personal role on the board. As part of larger infrastructure projects, the policy team in particular works closely with the relevant organisations. Thus, for example, our key construction advisor, Mr. David O'Brien, has a close working relationship with the CEO of Grangegorman Development Agency, Mr. Michael Hand. We work hand-in-glove on bigger projects in the State because our advice is often sought in regard to various policy matters. Implementation is left to the bodies concerned, however.</p>
          <p eId="para_87"> On the question of social clauses, 11 projects are a reasonable start given our previous position. I do not agree that it is a timid number because one of the key aspects of what we are trying to do is move outside of the construction space. Internationally many social clauses focus on construction and employment. We are trying to look beyond that to consider other services in respect of which ongoing social clauses can be implemented at an operational level. We want to test this mechanism because we may need to consider specific aspects of individual goods or services, including in particular services for which social clauses might be difficult to implement in some cases but easy in others. One of the reasons for setting up the group was to learn how we can do this well. We can then publish guidelines and take the findings on board in developing legislation. There are positive indications for what can be achieved from social clauses but there are also concerns about issues such as SME costs and the potential imbalance between the obligations of national and international parties. If, for example, a tender obliges a construction firm to increase employment and the contract is won by a firm from outside the country, the workers could potentially be hired from outside of the State and the training could be provided outside of the State. We do not want to create an uneven burden for national firms. Concerns also arise in regard to displacement of jobs. While we could force employers to hire, that could also require them to shed jobs. We want to act carefully in regard to the advice we give to the Minister on how this policy will be formed. We intend to learn a lot from expanding those arrangements.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_21">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">I am aware that Mr. Quinn has another question to answer but as the Deputy's allotted time has concluded, I ask that the reply be submitted in writing to the committee secretariat.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AideenHayden" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Senator Aideen Hayden<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">Judging from the contribution of members thus far, it is fair to say that a number of us are concerned to ensure local firms have a reasonable chance to compete for local contracts. There is a point at which the old adage, small is beautiful, is true. I was at first quite pleased with circular 10/14, which issued on 16 April 2014. Appendix 2 to the report sets out a matrix that can be used as a general guide to setting insurance level requirements for routine low to medium risk goods and services. What is a low to medium risk good or service? In other words, what value would it comprise and what type of service is potentially involved?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_23">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">Low to medium risk is associated with the risk that the procurer, whether in the Office of Government Procurement or a local contracting authority, takes on those matters.</p>
          <p eId="para_91">For example, I may take a view that buying a personal computer to sit on a desk in an office is relatively low risk.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AideenHayden" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Senator Aideen Hayden<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">May I give an example and will Mr. Quinn tell me if it falls within the category? Were I to buy €26,000 worth of consultancy, would that fall into the category of low to medium risk goods and services?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_25">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">It depends on the decision I am making relative to the advice I get.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AideenHayden" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Senator Aideen Hayden<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">Is low to medium risk the lowest category?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_27">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">Low to medium risk would be the lowest category of risk.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AideenHayden" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Senator Aideen Hayden<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">That is what I wanted to establish. For the sake of argument, if I am providing low risk goods and services, what is the minimum level at which public and employer's liability insurance is irrelevant? Would one need such insurance for a contract of €25,000 or could it be below €25,000?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_29">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">It could be below €25,000.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AideenHayden" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Senator Aideen Hayden<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">Is it necessary to have employer's liability insurance of €12.7 million, public liability insurance of €6.5 million and environmental indemnity of €2 million if I were providing training for my local school? The reason I raise this is because I have come across situations in which people have been providing management consultancy services and have been asked for public liability insurance of €6.5 million. Does Mr. Quinn know how much it costs to procure public liability insurance of €6.5 million?</p>
          <p eId="para_99"> I know from reading the guidance notes that those tendering for business have to be able to get the insurance, without having to have it in place at the time they apply for the tender. I know this to be the case because I have been approached on this point by people in my constituency who say they would not apply for a tender which they would be able to perform because as, say, a two-person company they would not be able to afford the cost of public liability insurance of €6.5 million or €12.7 million. Unless I am losing the plot, although I do not think so, those levels of public liability insurance are outrageous. What is the logic of it? For the sake of argument, let us suppose I am providing arts and crafts material to the local school then under the public procurements requirement I am required to have this level of public liability insurance. That does not make sense.</p>
          <p eId="para_100"> In respect of professional indemnity, I am aware of contracts below the value of €50,000 that have been put out to tender which required professional indemnity insurance of €3.6 million. It is stated in the documentation that the level of insurance must be proportionate to the job that is being done, that the level of turnover has to be related to the contract. I was very pleased initially to see this but when I read the conditions on the back page they made no sense.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_31">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">Let me remind the Senator that the sentence above the table states that it is a general guide to setting insurance levels. It is not specific. Some of these items may have no relevance to the good and services being procured. The Senator mentioned advisory and consultancy services but environmental liability insurance has no relevance to those services and would not be required. It is a general guide.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AideenHayden" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Senator Aideen Hayden<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">What about public liability and employer's liability insurance?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_33">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">Public liability and employer's liability insurance would be required.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AideenHayden" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Senator Aideen Hayden<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">Would insurance cover of up to €12.7 million be required?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_35">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">Let me draw the Senator's attention to page 6 of the guidance notes that public bodies may contact the State Claims Agency to get advice on these matters. The reason we put in place this guidance and in particular appendix 2, is to deal with professional indemnity and product liability. Some of the numbers that were appearing in tenders were extraordinary relative to the procurements that were taking place. The general guidance on employer's liability, public liability and environmental liability, where they apply, are typical and having spent many years in procurement these are typical values and would generally be put in place by professional firms that are undertaking works in those areas.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AideenHayden" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Senator Aideen Hayden<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">On that point, not everybody applying is a professional firm. Deputy McDonald made the point about micro-businesses. We are trying to put the economy back on its feet and encourage people into business. Not all of the tenders will be from large professional firms that would have standing insurance in place but might, for the sake of argument, be from people who are trying to set up a business.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_37">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">Yes. Prior to the issue of the guidance advice, if in the past one were to pick up a tender that would have included professional indemnity and product liability insurance the person concerned might have had to deal with extraordinary values. We have brought the values down and this has been welcomed by bodies such as IBEC because previously firms were being asked to procure ridiculous levels of insurance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AideenHayden" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Senator Aideen Hayden<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">I asked Mr. Quinn if he knew how much it cost to procure employer's liability insurance to the value of €12.7 million or public liability insurance of €6.5 million. I take his point, and I raised with the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform on a number of occasions the fact that outlandish amounts of insurance, in particular professional indemnity insurance, have been required for contracts. With regard to one size fits all, I note Mr. Quinn's point in section 6 that those who considered tendering could obtain advice but from my experience I suspect that what is happening is that the one size fits all is in the public domain but it does not fit all. It certainly does not fit small, sole traders or very small companies trying to bid for contracts.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_39">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">I agree with Senator Hayden that it is not a one size fits all. This is general guidance, it is set out and written down as general guidance. It provides an opportunity for contracting authorities to go back to the State Claims Agency and have a conversation with them about the limits they should actually put in place. It was broadly welcomed by industry because it brought down the level of professional indemnity and product liability insurance. It brought the numbers down very considerably from what went beforehand. People did not know what levels to apply and typically took an extraordinarily conservative view, whereas most contracting authorities simply need to cover a basic level of risk. Risk is a specific area and there are people who far better trained in that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AideenHayden" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Senator Aideen Hayden<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">Does Mr. Quinn know how much it costs to get that type of insurance?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_41">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">It varies depending on what one does. I suspect that if one were to ask an insurance underwriter to quote for the business, the first question they would ask is the nature of the business. I do not think there would be a single price.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AideenHayden" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Senator Aideen Hayden<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">Mr. Quinn should keep those limits under review and he should go a little further in his investigations than consulting IBEC.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_43">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">Deputy Tóibín has five minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">Go raibh maith agat. With regard to the collation of information, Mr. Quinn has stated that he is not collating information from capital projects now. Is it his intention to collate this information in the future? If not, will it be the case that the Departments will collate the information because there is an information deficit? The second question concerns a report on the review of performance of public works contracts. The construction industry is in chaos in many ways. Construction at Kishoge Community College is a prime example. On this project workers have been out on picket on a daily basis for nearly a year. I understand the review looks at industrial disputes between the main contractor on the site and the people who are contracting the tender.</p>
          <p eId="para_115">However, the problem is much deeper than this with subcontracting. There are subcontractors on the site at Kishoge who are not even paying the minimum wage. All of the issues associated with terms and conditions are completely ignored. In such a case, the main contractor throws up his hands and says it has nothing to do him. What is happening is further down the contracting food chain. The problem is arising on the site at Kishoge and we know that it is arising on other sites also. Owing to the broken nature of the construction industry and the fact that most new contracts are State contracts, what I describe is becoming the norm in the case of private contracts. Therefore, there is a contagion effect. Is it important that the Office of Government Procurement seek to ensure what I have described does not happen and fix this element of the system? Will it be able to ensure contracts between a contracting organisation and the main contractor are actually adhered to? My information is that the contracts determine that all responsibility falls on subcontractors further down the food chain.</p>
          <p eId="para_116"> My second question is on the performance of public works contracts. Will the CPO formally include the workers' aspects in the performance of public works contracts in the future?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_45">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">On the Deputy's question on collecting data, we will be collecting expenditure information on construction, just as we do in respect of goods and services. However, we will not be collecting data associated with each and every project to understand its nature, etc. That is not the intention.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">Will the Departments be doing so?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_47">
          <from> Mr. Paul Quinn<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">I understand Departments are responsible for collecting information on their own construction arrangements and I am advised they have to publish it.</p>
          <p eId="para_120"> The Deputy asked about the review of public works contracts. We published, just prior to Christmas, a set of interim recommendations for implementation. These recommendations have been welcomed broadly by the construction industry, which is good. In fact, the industry is anxious that we implement the recommendations quickly, which is welcome. The majority of the interim recommendations will involve changes in the first calendar quarter. One of them will extend into the second calendar quarter because of its complexity.</p>
          <p eId="para_121"> The Deputy has mentioned, in particular, that there is a new role envisaged within the public works arrangements, namely, a dispute convener. For larger contracts, I understand the process applies for values in excess of €10 million. A dispute convener would be appointed at a very early stage in the contract and his or her role would be to try to resolve disputes as they occurred during the life cycle of the project, rather than hitting a brick wall, which would involve the walls coming down and the project stopping. In such circumstances, people walk off site and difficulties ensue from everybody's perspective, not only that of the workers but also those of the State and contractors. When works stop, it is very difficult and costly for everybody.</p>
          <p eId="para_122"> The dispute convener's responsibility is to keep the parties talking and become familiar with the project, the arrangements and progress made. Another duty is to iron out issues as they arise and keep momentum going in a project. This may stop issues becoming part of more formal contract dispute arrangements, conciliation, arbitration and, ultimately, court proceedings. I guess the colloquial term would be "nipping things in the bud" in trying to have them resolved early and on site.</p>
          <p eId="para_123"> In regard to the site at Kishoge, we discussed the matter previously. There are a number of layers of protection that the State ensures within the procurement process. These place obligations not only on the main contractors but also on subcontractors. They apply at tender stage in terms of declarations that the parties will adhere to and are clear on parties' obligations regarding social welfare contributions and tax, in regard to which there is clearance. At award stage, the parties must certify their tax clearance certificates. Most importantly, at implementation stage, the contractors and subcontractors have to adhere to all legal obligations. To continue to be paid, they must submit on an ongoing basis a certificate, under clause 5.3, stating they are continuing to adhere to all obligations. They must maintain records indicating they are discharging these obligations. The State has the right to audit the payments and withhold payment if certification is not provided. Ultimately, it can terminate the contract if the contractor fails to remedy a problem.</p>
          <p eId="para_124"> The Deputy asked, in particular, about my office's ability or oversight of these matters. On occasion, we are drawn into arrangements such as those mentioned, but we do not have a mandate or operational capability to oversee the thousands of projects in train. On oversight, we rely on other bodies such as NERA which has expertise in matters of payment and the payment of social welfare, etc. It is the compliance body in these matters.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">Unfortunately, it does not have the ability to work in a timely fashion. With regard to the site at Kishoge, the process has been ongoing since last July and we are no further on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_49">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">We have run out of time. I apologise to Mr. Quinn, as I must stop the conversation. On behalf of the committee, I thank him for attending. The information he has provided is excellent. We will be seeing a lot more of each other and I hope circumstances will bed down.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryLouMcDonald" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Deputy Mary Lou McDonald<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">Will the Chairman confirm that the questions Mr. Quinn did not have time to answer will be answered?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_51">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">The responses will be sent to the secretariat and we will refer them to members.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i> Sitting suspended at 4.10 p.m. and resumed at 4.20 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Annual Growth Survey 2015, Alert Mechanism Report 2015 and An Investment Plan for Europe: Discussion<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:10:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_52">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">The purpose of this part of the meeting is to discuss the Annual Growth Survey 2015, the Alert Mechanism Report 2015 and An Investment Plan for Europe. I welcome from the Department of Finance Mr. John McCarthy, chief economist, and Mr. John Hogan, assistant secretary, banking division. The format is that they will make some opening remarks which will be followed by a question and answer session. I remind members, delegates and those in the Visitors Gallery that all mobile phones must be switched off as they interfere with the broadcasting of proceedings.</p>
          <p eId="para_130"> By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the joint committee. However, if they are directed by it to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence. They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person or an entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable. Members are reminded of the long-standing ruling of the Chair to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable. </p>
          <p eId="para_131"> I ask the delegates to restrict their presentations to a maximum of ten to 15 minutes, if possible, so as to answer the maximum number of questions from members.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_53">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">Certainly; there will be a division of labour. I will make a short statement on the annual growth survey and the alert mechanism report, while Mr. Hogan will speak about the investment plan for Europe. Our opening statements will be very short.</p>
          <p eId="para_133"> I thank the joint committee for the invitation to discuss the annual growth survey and the alert mechanism report for 2015. I am the assistant secretary in charge of the economic division of the Department. The European semester is the annual cycle of policy co-ordination in the European Union, the aim of which is to improve policy making in member states, taking into account the greater interconnectedness among them. The starting point of the semester is, as always, publication by the Commission of the annual growth survey each November. The role of the survey is to highlight the general economic priorities for the European Union for the coming year. It is debated by both the Council and the Parliament and subsequently endorsed by the March European Council. Once endorsed, the priorities are supposed to be taken into account by member states in their national reform plans and stability programme updates which are submitted to the Commission and the Council in April. The Council subsequently adopts country-specific recommendations for each member state in June. This year's survey was published last November, thus beginning the fifth cycle of policy co-ordination in the semester, and it is the second time Ireland has formally participated in the process. As a programme country, it was exempt from the process until 2013.</p>
          <p eId="para_134"> Three interrelated reform priorities were identified in the 2015 survey, namely, a renewed commitment to structural reforms, a co-ordinated approach to boosting investment in the European Union and a pursuit of fiscal responsibility. The Commission argued that action was needed in all three areas. It also adopted the so-called alert mechanism report, AMR, an early warning system that is embedded in the macroeconomic imbalances procedure. The origins of the procedure lie in the fact that economic imbalances, not just fiscal imbalances, were at the heart of the euro area crisis. Therefore, the role of the procedure is to identify and address imbalances that hinder the smooth functioning of monetary union. The AMR is an initial screening device based on a scoreboard of 11 economic indicators, each with indicative thresholds. The indicators cover both internal and external imbalances. Based on an overall assessment, rather than a purely mechanical reading of the scoreboard, the Commission may decide an in-depth review is warranted in order to assess whether a policy response is needed in a member state. The in-depth review forms the analytical base for dialogue between member states and the Commission on the appropriate policies to correct the imbalances.</p>
          <p eId="para_135"> For this year, based on the scoreboard, the Commission has decided that in-depth reviews are warranted in 16 member states, including Ireland. In the Irish case, the imbalances are legacy ones. They are stock variables, rather than flow variables. I have included the list of 11 variables as an appendix to my presentation to the committee. When I refer to stock variables, I refer to imbalances that accumulated during the bubble years and which are in the process of unwinding, although the unwinding will take time. The new Commission has proposed a streamlining of the semester, which means the publication of a single analytical in March this year, incorporating the results of the in-depth review. The rationale for this is to allow member states to engage in a more meaningful way with the Commission before publication of the CSRs in June.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_54">
          <from> Mr. John Hogan<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">I thank the Chairman for the invitation to address the joint committee on the investment plan for Europe which aims to address the low level of investment in Europe in recent years, thereby promoting economic growth and increased employment. Although European Commission estimates put the drop in investment at about 15% compared to 2007 figures, within this there are variations across member states. In response, the Commission has brought forward its proposals for action in the form of the investment plan for Europe. Launched on 26 November last and endorsed by European leaders in December, the plan proposes a number of measures to unlock public and private investment in the European economy of some €315 billion in the next three years.</p>
          <p eId="para_137"> The plan has three key strands, namely, actions to mobilise finance for investments, ensuring finance reaches the real economy in Europe, and measures to improve the investment environment in Europe. In order to mobilise finance for investment, as the key action, the European Commission and the European Investment Bank, EIB, have proposed the establishment of a new European fund for strategic investments, EFSI. Seed capital for the fund will be provided by the Commission in the form of an EU guarantee of some €16 billion, together with an investment of €5 billion from the EIB. While other possible public and private contributions may add to this total, the Commission and the EIB estimate that the initial funding of €21 billion can be leveraged to facilitate a total investment of some €315 billion, with €240 billion earmarked for long-term investments and €75 billion channelled to SME and mid-cap companies.</p>
          <p eId="para_138"> A legislative proposal in the form of a regulation to give effect to the EFSI has been published and this week member states began discussions on the instrument in Brussels. The Latvian Presidency has set out an intensive programme of meetings aimed at working through the proposed regulation in order to reach common agreement across member states in time for the March ECOFIN. Building in discussions with the Parliament, the timeline for adoption of the regulation is envisaged for the summer, which means that, with the establishment of the fund, the formalisation of the governance arrangements, etc., the first activity by the fund is not likely to happen until the autumn. It is expected that advance work will be undertaken to warehouse projects which can be assessed as being supportable <i>vis-à-vis</i> the EFSI’s criteria. These could be funded quickly under the EFSI once it is active.</p>
          <p eId="para_139"> Under the second strand to ensure finance can reach the real economy, a special task force was established last October to develop an EU project pipeline of viable investments of European significance. The task force was jointly chaired by the EIB and the European Commission and included a representative from each member state. The task force had a key objective of compiling, by the end of the year, a list of economically valuable strategic investments across the public and private sectors. The aim was to try to identify and highlight projects across Europe that are not being advanced owing to economic, regulatory, financial or other reasons. The task force also sought to identify barriers and bottlenecks to project investment and propose solutions. The complete list contains approximately 2,000 projects from the 28 member states, with a total investment value of €1.3 trillion.</p>
          <p eId="para_140"> As part of this process, Ireland submitted a list of 70 projects, valued at approximately €23 billion. The Irish project list represented a compilation of potential investment projects as put forward by the Departments with policy responsibility for the relevant sectors but without any overall assessment or prioritisation of the projects from a national perspective. Inclusion in the list submitted to the EU-EIB task force does not confer any particular status or guarantee of funding for the projects in question, either at a national or European level. It represents a compilation of potential investment projects in the relevant sectors, any of which could potentially be commenced between 2015 and 2017, subject to being evaluated and approved by the relevant sanctioning authority, typically the relevant Government Department, in compliance with the public spending code and subject to funding being available. There is no prioritisation of projects within the list. The Irish projects were not assessed or endorsed by the Departments of Public Expenditure and Reform and Finance prior to their submission to the EU-EIB task force as the urgency attaching to the European request did not allow time for Ireland or other member states to do this.</p>
          <p eId="para_141"> Similar statements attached to almost all of the lists submitted by the 28 member states and any proposal to proceed on Irish projects would be subject to the normal capital expenditure and cost-benefit assessments and having regard to Government priorities for investment. The overall list does, however, serve the useful purpose of highlighting for potential investors a pipeline of projects across Europe which, with some risk support from the EFSI, could proceed. The EFSI is intended to provide support through the provision of debt funding, not grants for such projects. This has implications for the debt and fiscal position of member states in the context of public investment projects.</p>
          <p eId="para_142"> As the committee is aware, the Commission published guidance on the existing flexibility under the Stability and Growth Pact rules, following through on a commitment given at the June 2014 European Council and given concerns voiced by member states in the lead-up to the December European Council. The Commission's release accompanying its guidance stated member state contributions to the EFSI would not be counted when assessing the fiscal adjustment. This will be the case for all member states, whether in the preventive or corrective arm of the pact. The Commission’s release also stated for countries benefiting from the so-called "investment clause", co-financing with the EFSI of projects or investment platforms would also benefit from favourable treatment under the pact. The Commission also stated that, irrespective of the EUROSTAT accounting treatment, it would take a favourable position towards such voluntary capital contributions to the EFSI for the purposes of the assessment of the debt and deficit criteria under the Stability and Growth Pact.</p>
          <p eId="para_143"> We are still considering the exact value of this guidance to Ireland in the context of the positive developments in the Irish economy in 2014 and the expectations for 2015. Finally, in promoting the final strand of work on the plan in the area of improving the investment environment, the Commission is committed to improving the predictability and quality of regulation in Europe and to removing sector-specific and financial barriers to investment.</p>
          <p eId="para_144"> Ireland is approaching work around the European investment plan in as open and constructive a fashion as possible through full participation in the negotiation of the European fund for strategic investments regulation and any continuation of the work under the project task force. This is necessary to ensure that we take appropriate opportunities which make economic and budgetary sense if they arise as part of the final political agreement on the EFSI proposal.</p>
          <p eId="para_145"> I thank the committee members for their attention. We are happy to take follow-up questions and provide further clarity if required.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_55">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">We will open with our first round of questions. We will have ten-minute slots in the beginning to ensure that everyone gets an opportunity to speak. I realise you are under time pressure, Deputy Doherty. Do you wish to go first?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">I appreciate that, because I have another commitment.</p>
          <p eId="para_148"> The Department officials referred to the annual growth survey. Can the officials explain why GDP growth is ahead outside the eurozone countries? Why is there greater growth outside the eurozone by comparison with the eurozone? We have the figures. Is this the trend we have been seeing in recent times?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">Does Deputy Doherty mean why there has been a difference between the euro area and the rest of the EU?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">Yes - between the euro area and the rest of the EU.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_59">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">The main reason is that we have seen a strong rebound in growth in the United Kingdom. Obviously, that has a large weight in the overall EU figures. The UK is generally perceived to be further down the line in terms of balance sheet repair. The UK was ahead of the curve in respect of monetary policy being more supportive of growth and so forth. It is a more flexible economy. The UK does not have some of the issues that arise in the euro area as a whole in terms of the fragmentation of financial markets or the debt overhang to which I referred. I will put some figures on it. For this year, the IMF is forecasting euro area growth of 1.1% and EU growth of 1.5%. The main difference between the two is due to the rapid growth in the UK.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">One of the Commission's proposals is what is termed an integrated approach. It is a more aggressive approach to tax evasion. Is the Department's position still that there is nothing to see here in respect of the Commission's investigation into the activities of a multinational company here? Has the Department formalised an approach on whether it will co-operate with the European Parliament investigation into deals in this member state and others?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_61">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">Yes. The Department is co-operating with the European Commission in terms of the investigations that are ongoing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">Does the Department expect an outcome of "nothing to see here"?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_63">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">We do not think so.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">Will the Department of Finance co-operate with the European Parliament investigation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_65">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">Of course, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">The Commission refers to growth-friendly fiscal consolidation. We hear the term time and again. During the budget, the Minister for Finance and other senior Ministers referred to how reducing the tax rate at the highest level would create so many jobs over so many years. Is it the case that an investment or social transfer of equal value would create the same amount of jobs? Has any analysis been done in that area?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_67">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">I emphasise that the annual growth survey is very much a Commission document and these are the Commission's recommendations. Deputy Doherty is correct. The document refers to growth-friendly fiscal consolidation. This applies on the revenue side as well as on the expenditure side. On the revenue side, essentially the Commission is referring to a budget-neutral shift away from taxation of labour towards more environmentally friendly areas, including indirect taxes and so forth. On the expenditure side, the Commission is referring to maintaining investment in physical capital as well as human capital. The research in this area suggests that we can do this in a budget-neutral way and that it would have a favourable impact on potential growth in the economy through, for example, participation rates on the labour supply side. Moreover, the thinking goes, if we are investing then we are boosting our capital stock. This is essentially where the Commission is coming from in respect of this recommendation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">That translates into what I have referenced in respect of the statement on budget day to the effect that reduction of the top rate of tax would create X jobs over X years. If an investment or social transfer of equal value were to take place, would it have the same impact in terms of job creation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_69">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">It depends on the type of investment undertaken. We published some analysis approximately 18 months ago showing the impact of different types of reform, including changes in labour tax. The analysis included the impact they might have on the economy, the impact on the supply side and the impact on job creation. The specific answer to Deputy Doherty's question is that it depends on the type of investment. For example, if we opted to import more trains and so on it would have no impact in terms of job creation because they are sourced from abroad. However, if we do more investment in building and construction then we will get typically more bang for our buck.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">Given the time constraints, we will not deal too much with that.</p>
          <p eId="para_163"> Reference was made to the alert mechanism. One of the EU budgetary rules is the expenditure benchmark, something the Irish Fiscal Advisory Council has raised several times, as have I. This limits new spending, including tax cuts, to the rate of growth. Can the Department officials set out the legal basis of this rule? How does it differ from rules such as the 3% deficit rule and the 60% debt rule? In drafting next year's budget with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, will the Department of Finance consider the rule binding? What are the penalties if the Government were to breach it? I am keen for the officials to comment, given the fact that in a reply to a Parliamentary Question the Minister provided figures suggesting that sticking to the benchmark would mean that any adjustment in budget 2016 would be limited to €400 million. Is that figure still accurate?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_71">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">The legal basis for the expenditure benchmark is Article 126 of the treaty. That is the primary legislation. The secondary legislation is Regulation No. 1466. This is the preventive arm of the Stability and Growth Pact, which was reformed in 2011. Essentially, the anchor of the preventive arm is the so-called balanced budget or medium-term budgetary objective. In the past, this was assessed on the basis of changes in the structural balance and how fast countries were approaching their medium-term budgetary objective. The reforms to the Stability and Growth Pact in 2011 introduced the concept of the expenditure benchmark. The legal basis for that is Article 126.</p>
          <p eId="para_165"> The overall objective of the benchmark is to set spending in line with the potential growth rate of the economy. It is averaged over a ten-year period. If a country is not at its medium-term budgetary objective, there is a so-called convergence margin. The country must have expenditure below the benchmark and must be converging sufficiently rapidly to the medium-term budgetary objective.</p>
          <p eId="para_166"> In respect of what it actually means in monetary terms, I am simply not in a position to answer today, I am afraid.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">Is it binding in nature? Is it one of these rules that are somewhat fluffy around the edges? What if we breach it? I realise things can change in terms of revenues and growth rates and so on. I expect the Department's information was correct late last year when it produced a figure of €400 million. What if the Government were to surpass that in terms of expenditure or tax cuts? The Government has already announced that it will cut taxes. This will suck up some of the €400 million. What would actually happen if we break this rule? What kicks in?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_73">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">The answer to the first part of the Deputy's question is that the rule is very much binding, as are the overall rules of the preventive arm. We must be approaching the medium-term budgetary objective based on either a change in structural balance or an assessment of the benchmark. Finally, an overall assessment is undertaken, and we must be approaching the medium-term budgetary objective at a sufficient pace. That is binding.</p>
          <p eId="para_169"> The reforms of the pact in 2011 introduced what is called the sanctions regulation, which provides for sanctions in the preventive arm of the pact. They never existed previously. They were only ever in the corrective arm of the pact. In terms of what that means, the rules are very much binding.</p>
          <p eId="para_170"> With regard to the draft budgetary plans of euro area member states that were assessed last November and December, the Commission kicked to touch on a number of countries, including Italy. Italy has to revert to it in March because it is breaching the requirements of the preventive arm. Italy has to sort it out and come back to the Commission. Otherwise, potentially there are sanctions coming down the line. </p>
          <p eId="para_171"> I stress that financial sanctions can only apply in an <i>ex-post</i> manner. In other words, a country cannot be sanctioned on the basis of projections. It is only on the basis of outturn data. However, there is a regulation that has introduced financial sanctions and those sanctions are quasi-automatic, in other words, one is guilty unless one is proven innocent. The Commission will adopt a decision to impose sanctions and that cannot be overturned unless a reverse qualified majority of member states overturn it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">Regarding the investment plan, when we are dealing with the excessive deficit procedure we cannot breach those targets but we can now because the European Commission has just decided to change the rules on investment. Is that correct? If we couple this with investment from Commission President Jean-Claude Juncker's plan on the use of state resources, it will not be accounted for.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_75">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">I take issue with the fact that they have changed the rules. The Commission is very strong in saying that the changes that were adopted in the communication last week are within the rules. They do not want to go down the line of rule changes. It was highlighting the-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">If we consider the 3% deficit rule, is it correct that at this point in time EUROSTAT is the adjudicator in regard to that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_77">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">However, the Commission is now saying we should not worry about what EUROSTAT says and that if we use some of this money that takes us above the 3% deficit rule it will not account for it. EUROSTAT is no longer the final adjudicator in this regard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_79">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_177">EUROSTAT purely measures the deficit position. The legal and procedural implications are in the remit of the Commission and the Council. I stress that the investment clause we are talking about here only applies in the preventive arm of the pact. If a country's deficit is greater than 3%, it cannot apply the investment clause. Even within the preventive arm of the pact a country must have negative GDP growth or a negative output gap in excess of 1.5% of GDP. It needs to build in a safety margin with respect to the 3%, therefore, it is not a free for all on the investment side.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_178">Given the restrictions on it, if this money ever comes on line, and we know it has to be leveraged 15 times, will Ireland be in a position to use this money and not have it calculated by EUROSTAT as expenditure?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_81">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">We will not move into the preventive arm until next year, assuming we correct this year which, in the absence of any shock, I believe we will do. A good deal of clarification is needed from the Commission as to how this is applied but it is something we need to consider in further detail. The communication was only adopted last week so there is still a lot of water to go under the bridge.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">I ask Mr. McCarthy for his best guess. In his contribution Mr. McCarthy raised the alarm that there are rules, that it is not simply a case that this money is coming on board and we can-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_83">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">Mr. McCarthy might give us his best guess at this point in time, bearing in mind that things can change. It is his job to look to see where we will be in the future, and the Department has got very good at doing that. I ask for Mr. McCarthy's best guess. Are we narrowly inside or outside in that regard? Do we have further to go or does he believe we will be okay?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_85">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">My suspicion at this stage is that we probably will not qualify for the investment clause. The reason for that is the conditions the Commission will apply in terms of the investment clause. I refer to negative growth next year, and we are not forecasting negative growth, a good deal of slack in the economy and an output gap of 1.5% of GDP. It is estimated currently that our output will close this year. My preliminary assessment, and the Deputy will appreciate that it is subject to change, is that we will not qualify for the investment in the very short term.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_86">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">We will have to suspend the meeting because a vote has been called in the Dáil.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 4.45 p.m. and resumed at 5 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_87">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">I have one or two questions for the witnesses. As we heard, Ireland submitted 70 projects for inclusion in the investment plan. Will Mr. Hogan provide a breakdown of the projects? Has a list of projects been published?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_88">
          <from> Mr. John Hogan<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">It is publicly available.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_89">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">Will Mr. Hogan have a copy sent to the joint committee?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_90">
          <from> Mr. John Hogan<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_91">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">The annual growth survey refers to the streamlining of the semester process. In what respects will the process be different in 2015? Why has the European Commission decided to change it? Has it done so in response to weaknesses that were identified in the process in recent years? What is the thinking behind the changes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_92">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">This is the fifth cycle and the process is evolving over time. Each Presidency has tried to improve the operation of the semester. In terms of this year, the overall streamlining involves the publication of a single analytical document. Until now, two documents have been published, namely, the in-depth review and what is known as the staff working document, which was published every June. The intention is that these documents will be rolled into one document that will be published in mid-March. This will allow member states and the Commission to better prepare the country-specific recommendations. These are the types of concrete changes being made; I would not describe them as "game changers". The new Commission has proposed a little streamlining and the Latvian Presidency is running with its proposal. The purpose is to allow member states and the Commission to engage in a more meaningful manner and come up with more appropriate country-specific recommendations, which form the policy plank, if one likes, for the following 18 months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_93">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">In the 2015 annual growth survey, the Commission refers to how member states and national parliaments can increase their ownership of the process. This is important because the growth survey and other information on developments in the European semester refer to the European institutions and national governments. However, the joint committee could also be more involved in the process. Is that not the case? I am concerned that the committee could become a little detached from the process. Should it seek more resources and do more on this issue?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_94">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">Absolutely. The two concrete pieces of work that are done by the Irish system in the European semester are the publication of national reform plans, which are overseen by our colleagues in the Department of the Taoiseach, and the publication by the Department of Finance of the stability programme update in mid or late April. Last year was the first year that Ireland was formally involved in the process. The Minister appeared before the committee to present in draft form the main results of the stability programme update. At that time, he indicated he was open to taking on board comments from committee members. Subject to the Minister's approval, we would certainly be willing to do that again. The Chairman is correct - this point is stressed by the Commission in the survey - that there is greater scope for national parliaments to engage in this process.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_95">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">I believe this will become a key issue. I wrote to the former President of the European Central Bank, Mario Draghi, following his refusal to attend the banking inquiry, which is taking place in the adjacent committee room. I indicated to Mr. Draghi that his decision would be a lost opportunity for the ECB to present its case to Irish people via the Irish Parliament. There is always the risk that people will not have a sense of ownership of the budgetary process if it is primarily dealt with in the European institutions and they do not see a public pathway for Parliament to deal with the budget.</p>
          <p eId="para_194"> Mr. McCarthy indicated that the Minister, as part of the Executive, may seek the considered opinions of the joint committee. The committee does not receive much in the way of resources to fully address issues of this nature. Given how important the European semester will become in the years ahead and as this process is new to the joint committee, perhaps a mechanism should be established to involve the committee in the process at the deepest possible level in order that it will be viewed as a participant in the semester procedure. This is the only way the process will gain public acceptance in the long term.</p>
          <p eId="para_195">This process might be beneficial and seen as an area of co-operation between us rather than the EU imposing its opinions on us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_96">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_196">I agree with everything the Chairman said. I understand that the Commission has always made itself available to come to national parliaments to explain what the semester is about, including the rationale for the various recommendations and so forth. That option is available but I need to get the specifics around it. I take on board everything the Chairman said.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_97">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">Mr. McCarthy might inquire on the committee's behalf if the Commission would like to make a presentation to it at some point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_98">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">Yes, I will do that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMurphy" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Deputy Paul Murphy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">My questions are focussed on the European investment plan. In regard to the global figures, obviously, there is a great deal of criticism of the fact that there is no new money in that the €8 billion, multiplied by two, for existing projects and €5 billion from the EIB, is being leveraged up until the figure of €315 billion is reached. Is this a serious weakness in terms of the investment plan? The focus on investment is welcome. This was absent from the mainstream analysis of the crisis up until a couple of years ago. However, does this plan really address the problem if no new money is being invested in it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_100">
          <from> Mr. John Hogan<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">The Deputy is correct in regard to the level to which the figures have fallen, as indicated in my opening statement. The Commission estimates that the drop in investment will be approximately 15% as compared with 2007. The incoming Commission was very focused on how to get investment moving again in Europe and at looking at new and innovative ways of doing this. What we see here is an attempt to do it on a number of different levels, including through the putting in place, through the ESFI, of a fund, which as the Deputy rightly says, can be leveraged up. I will ask Mr. Petris to comment later on the mechanics of that. </p>
          <p eId="para_201"> The Commission also wanted to find a mechanism by which private finance could be encouraged to invest in the future of Europe. It is seeking to facilitate this through making available this project pipeline to enable investors to get a real picture of large-scale projects at a European level, which by virtue of the fact that there may not be sufficient finance available through traditional means, may be open for new and innovative forms of financing. These are projects in which the European authorities were prepared to invest, take a first-loss piece in or guarantee during the initial phase of the investment and in respect of which they are now seeking to unlock private sector investment. The building blocks to allow this are being put in place. Mr. Petris will speak a little now about the transformation of the €8 billion from the EU budget and the €5 billion from the EIB.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_101">
          <from> Mr. Nico Petris<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">What Europe is trying to do is use the resources it has in a more efficient manner. It is seeking to do this by leveraging its resources to de-risk projects which, in turn, will attract private sector co-investment. In terms of the mechanics around the cash contributions, the EIB and the Commission are seeking to put in a total of €21 billion, €16 billion of which will come in via guarantees from the Commission and €5 billion will be provided by the EIB using own resources. Some of the media headlines have taken the €21 billion and the end project pipeline of €315 billion and come up with a 15 times leverage, which is considered bonkers. I will try to explain the dynamics of this which, to me, makes more sense. The EIB takes the €21 billion and leverages that internally in order to bring the €21 billion to €60 billion. This is something that banks do all of the time. They issue bonds and they raise their capital and then have more money to invest. The EIB-Commission bucket of investment is in the context of a three-times leverage, €63 billion. What the EIB-Commission are seeking to do is leverage this a further five times with private sector co-investment so as to reach an end total project volume of €315 billion. A five-times leverage is not that unbelievable.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMurphy" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Deputy Paul Murphy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">Mr. Wolfgang Munchau said it reminded him of a synthetic collateralised debt obligation. We have just been through a financial crisis which arose because of fictitious capital and this is our answer. In the context of a social revolution across Europe and a Government committed to public investment, would it not be preferable to have an actual €300 billion investment as opposed to a notional €300 billion based on €13 billion?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_103">
          <from> Mr. Nico Petris<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">I agree with the Deputy. He is correct that it would always be preferable to have the cash available waiting to be deployed. What the EIB and Commission are seeking to do in this case is use their limited resources in a more efficient way and to try to de-risk projects and attract in private sector co-investment. As I understand it, and based on my experience having attended EIB board meetings, there is no shortage of private sector co-investors seeking to invest at a senior level. Institutional investors and funds are interested in investing now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMurphy" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Deputy Paul Murphy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">In terms of the use of the word "de-risk", I agree that does get to it because, in effect, what happens is that the private investors are treated as the senior tranche and the public is the lesser. As such any losses incurred will in the first instance hit the public and, second, the private investment. Risk still exists. A project will either have risks or no risks on its own merits so that risk is being transferred from private to public.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_105">
          <from> Mr. Nico Petris<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">The answer in a nutshell is yes. To the extent that we use a certain amount of resources and we provide a first-loss protection and make an equity investment then yes there would be an associated risk with that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMurphy" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Deputy Paul Murphy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">There is a socialisation of risk and privatisation of resources. In terms of dead-weight, how do the Commission and EIB know that these people would not have invested and risked their own money in any case? In other words, the investors, because of the public offering in the form of the Commission and the EIB, now propose to take the risk on and allow the public to take the risk in what they would have invested in any case.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_107">
          <from> Mr. John Hogan<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">We need to look at the government structures which are being suggested around this. We are at early stages in terms of the negotiation around the European fund for strategic investment. I can tell the Deputy, based on the regulation that has been published, that a steering committee, consisting of the European Commission, the EIB and other participants, for example, from member states, is to be put in place. There will also be an investment committee which will include market experts and a managing director and will assess the projects from an investment perspective. The investment guidelines have yet to be determined and drafted. As we understand it from the early stages of the negotiation on the regulation, they will be drafted by the steering committee when in place. At that stage, it will be possible to make a more sensible assessment of what is being done in terms of the approach by the investment committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_209"> It is fair to say that the EIB has been involved in this particular venture over a long number of years. The European Investment Fund has previously looked at taking first-loss pieces and has been able to unlock valuable private sector investment in projects in Europe for a number of years. As Mr. Petris said there is to a certain extent a fairly safe track record at Europe level in some of the approaches that are being suggested in this regard. It is an attempt by the Commission, taking account of the dearth of investment in Europe over the past number of years, to find some mechanism to unlock it against what we still see as a background of economic uncertainty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMurphy" eId="spk_108">
          <from>Deputy Paul Murphy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">I have not seen the list of 70 projects. I presume many of the projects listed are infrastructural projects. Mr. Juncker referred in his speech to a school in Thessalonika in Greece and other grand projects in the public services area that could now be properly funded as a result of this. I presume the projects about which we are now speaking are projects that previously would have been paid for by the State or through public-private partnerships. How do the private investors get a return?</p>
          <p eId="para_211">To take the example of a school building project, the money presumably comes directly from the taxpayer. How does this work when a project is not generating revenue? Where is the return for private investors? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_109">
          <from> Mr. John Hogan<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">Before I answer that question, it might be useful to inform the committee about the breadth and extent of the projects that have been included in the list without going through the individual projects. In sectoral terms, in the energy sector, the total investment in the projects put forward by Ireland was approximately €2.55 billion; it was estimated that €2.25 billion of this could possibly be invested between 2015 and 2017. In the knowledge and digital economy the total investment suggested was €730 million, with €500 million possibly being invested between 2015 and 2017. In the broad area of resources and the environment the total investment suggested was approximately €1.86 billion, with €460 million possibly being invested between 2015 and 2017. The figure for the transport sector was €11.32 billion, with €1.71 billion possibly being invested in the next two years. The figure for social infrastructure was €5 billion, with the last category being SME lending, in respect of which a total investment of €800 million was suggested, with a further investment of €800 million being possible between 2015 and 2017.</p>
          <p eId="para_213"> In terms of a return on its investment for the private sector, it depends on the nature and construct of the proposal being put in place. It really depends on the outcome of individual operation agreements but is not without precedent. We have a number of PPP projects in Ireland involving private sector investors. Such projects have been under way here for a number of years and I do not see any major difference in the approach taken.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_110">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">I apologise for being late; I had to attend two other meetings. </p>
          <p eId="para_215"> Deputy Paul Murphy mentioned a list of projects. Is that list available?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_111">
          <from> Mr. John Hogan<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">Yes, it is available. It details not just the projects in Ireland but also the projects across Europe. We are happy to supply the committee with the details-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_112">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_217">Is it available on a website or can the delegates send us a copy?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_113">
          <from> Mr. John Hogan<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">Yes; it is available on the European Commission's website, but we can forward copies to the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_114">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">My points may have been addressed; if so, the delegates need not respond again because I can read the answers in the transcript of the meeting. I ask the Chairman to guide me in that regard. </p>
          <p eId="para_220"> The issue of house prices in Ireland was flagged, but when I read the report, I could not see it highlighted hugely by the Commission. A concern about house prices is highlighted in the Department's briefing note. I consider it to be a big issue and would like to know what the Commission is saying about it.</p>
          <p eId="para_221"> On the question of structural reforms, there are four examples given on page 11 of the annual growth survey of structural reforms that have been implemented in Spain, Portugal, Poland and Italy. While I accept that Ireland's economy has been reformed and that a lot of reforms have taken place, there is still a lot more to be done. I contend that since the end of the troika programme we have been extremely slow to reform and open up the legal profession and to deal with top-level consultants in the medical profession. We have also been slow in dealing with the issue of pharmacological products, although there have been some changes made in that area. Italy, for example, has implemented measures aimed at increasing competition and transparency in the gas and electricity markets. We have not done a whole lot in that regard and are certainly not being singled out by the Commission as a good example.</p>
          <p eId="para_222"> Another issue raised in the annual growth survey is responsible, growth-friendly fiscal consolidation. On page 15 of the report the Commission highlights the fall in investment expenditure. Capital expenditure has dropped dramatically here. I argue that it has dropped much more under the Government than was envisaged under the troika agreement and the national recovery plan of the previous Government. This was done to avoid more politically unpalatable decisions on current expenditure, but it means that we are now less growth-friendly in terms of fiscal consolidation in that we have cut expenditure that would have helped us to grow. Do the delegates have any view on the matter?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_115">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_223">I will try to address those points. The Senator made a very valid point about house prices. I stress that the scoreboard is backward looking and only based on data from 2013. I strongly suspect that when the Commission engages in this exercise next year, the indicator for Ireland will be flashing red because, in all likelihood, we will be above the threshold.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_116">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">We know that now, but what action is being taken at Government level? What action is being taken before the European Commission starts to give out to us and before the red light starts to flash?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_117">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">On house prices, the Government's strategy is to increase supply. That is being done in various ways within the Construction 2020 framework which includes 75 time-bound actions to help to address various issues, including planning, access to finance, regulations and so forth. There are a number of initiatives under way. Unfortunately, increasing supply is not something that happens over night. There is a long lead-in time, which is just the nature of the beast.</p>
          <p eId="para_226"> On structural reforms, I will not be specific, but I tend to agree with the Senator that there is scope for further structural reforms in the economy. There is a need for more competition and to reduce regulatory barriers and so forth. The Senator has also correctly made the point that we already have a flexible economy. If one looks at the OECD's research in this area, one will find that Ireland tends to be at the more flexible end, both in product markets and factor markets, but that is not to say there is not more to be done. I tend to agree with the Senator in that regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_227"> On growth-friendly consolidation, if I recall correctly, we were the subject of a country specific recommendation, CSR, last year and could easily be the subject of one again this year, that the composition of the fiscal adjustment or our fiscal stance be more growth-friendly. I am 90% sure that was the case last year and it is not inconceivable that we could receive the same recommendation this year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanDBarrett" eId="spk_118">
          <from>Senator Sean D. Barrett<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">I welcome our visitors. I have misgivings about what the Commission is up to. The fiscal council has shown that, in terms of gains being made in a small, open economy, there is no multiplier. On Senator Thomas Byrne's point, we had to cut capital spending because of the debt burden, partly due to the bank guarantee. Prior to that happening, however, we did not run too many Government deficits, but there were many capital projects which did not yield a return. We need an appraisal from people like our guests to be published in advance to determine if projects would be worthwhile. We must determine if they would be the fruit of lobbying by those looking for soft financial conditions or a sop to the construction industry, as happened frequently in the past. Spending on such projects reduces the efficiency of the overall economy.</p>
          <p eId="para_229"> I was a member of a cross-Border committee which was told that the first cost estimate for the construction of the Narrow Water bridge was €12 million. Someone then heard that the European Union was involved in providing finance and the estimate jumped to €40 million. The money is now being spent instead on the Enterprise service, but they are probably both dud projects in terms of yielding a return. </p>
          <p eId="para_230"> Interest rates are at a record low level in Europe, but the private sector is not investing. Is this just the provision of a subsidy for the banking and construction sectors by a different route? Will it really stimulate output?</p>
          <p eId="para_231">Is it the problem in the United States of Wall Street versus Main Street? As for a strong public sector with good project appraisal, I have written some appraisals for the Institute of Public Administration and so on, but in respect of the mixtures, I always fear that the taxpayer gets stuck with the dud ones and stuck with the debt. I am particularly concerned about the off-balance sheet financing of Irish Water. While it has not yet been sanctioned by EUROSTAT, there is an element of illusion about it. In the past, I thought that Transport 21 was the worst one in that it was just grandiose projects whereby engineers feel better, the construction industry thinks they are great but nothing happens in terms of the growth of the economy. While one can assume these are great projects and so on, after all that has happened to us since 2008 one needs really strong evidence that they are.</p>
          <p eId="para_232"> I do not know what will happen in Greece on Sunday but how much of the economy in a place like Greece would be stimulated by having a flexible exchange rate to get into the market economy or if it had the ability to set its own interest rates? It is the economics of being locked into something that obviously is not working and, unfortunately, we came at the very end. Is there any way in which we can substitute for the rigidity the eurozone imposes on us while thanking the Lord that the United Kingdom and United States are buying lots of stuff from us? As a country that has just come out of a rescue plan, it is very difficult for Ireland in particular to reform Europe but, as it stands, the system is highly deficient. Projects are determined by who lobbies or by who has the biggest public relations department. Perhaps the studies have all been done and are being kept in secret somewhere in Brussels or Frankfurt but when some of them are announced, people just think there will be a massive cost overrun, there usually is and it does not really have any great impact. When one robs Peter to pay Paul, although Paul, his accountant, his tax lawyer and his banker usually think it is a great idea, what about the rest of us?</p>
          <p eId="para_233"> While I do not know what will emerge tomorrow when Mr. Draghi is to decide, it should be something other than being construction-based. As housing has been mentioned, I note that Mr. Brendan Burgess appeared before the joint committee recently and sat in the seat currently occupied by Mr. John McCarthy. He reckoned that approximately €67,000 of the average house price is accounted for by taxes, levies, planning and so on. Would reducing the price of houses by €67,000 not be the best way? That would get the markets going. However, if one pours in more demand, one starts out with the problem with prices and I support Professor Honohan on the 20% deposit. I am not sure that Brussels and Frankfurt inspire the brightest ideas for what is wrong with the Irish economy at present. That could be a reaction to Monday's conference at which we were patted on the back, told we were very good and so on. Not many people in the audience felt very good; the last session sort of collapsed. There must be something better coming from Brussels in respect of economic policy. I know what the Minister, Deputy Noonan, seeks tomorrow and I wish him well in that regard. These projects are almost a Joe Stalin kind of economics, except that the private sector gets a substantial bailout from them. I do not know how the projects are chosen, how they are evaluated or where one can read what they are worth and so on, but I must express disquiet about the process. I will leave it at that and thank the four witnesses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_119">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">If it is all right with the Senator, I will make one or two comments. I tend to agree with the first point he made about how it was necessary to cut capital. I agree because, in 2010, the OECD undertook a survey of the Irish economy, as it does every two years. It stated there were a number of projects in the pipeline that only just crossed the cost-benefit analysis line. However, that cost-benefit analysis had been done on the basis of growth rates of 4% or 4.5% coming down the line and once there was a reassessment of the position to the effect that the potential growth rate of the economy was lower than had been assumed, many of these projects were not viable. As the OECD recommended that some capital projects should be cut, there is research to support one argument the Senator is making. I should stress that what the growth survey does is very much European Union-wide and within that, when fiscal responsibility is being talked about, it is not simply aimed at consolidation. There are implicit recommendations to some countries that have fiscal space. I think the Senator knows which country I am talking about. It has large infrastructural needs and, as the Senator quite rightly noted, can pretty much borrow at record lows. As a result, the rate of return on the investment would be very high relative to its cost. That would stimulate its economy, would boost its potential growth rate and would have a spillover effect to the rest of the European Union by helping to reduce imbalances. It is not just about fiscal adjustment on the way down and so forth. These are a couple of preliminary comments in response to the Senator's observations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_120">
          <from> John Hogan<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_235">On the projects - so the Senator can understand the process we undertook in this regard - in the autumn of last year we were asked at short notice to compile a list of projects or potential projects that could feed into an overall list at European level. The approach was that the Secretaries General of the Departments of Finance and Public Expenditure and Reform wrote to the relevant Departments asking for their suggestions in this regard. The project list was chosen from that but, to be frank, the Senator will note our understanding is the exercise was also conducted by the other 27 member states across the Union in a similar way. From the lists and the production of the publication from the European Commission on the 2,000 projects on the overall list, it is clear that no particular status or guaranteed funding arises from the presence of a particular project on the list. Ultimately, from both the European and national perspectives, a cost-benefit analysis must be done to ascertain whether the approach and the particular project merit any funding. Ultimately, if there is private sector involvement, the participants must themselves be sure that the expectation of returns is there. I do not think anyone wishes to be building highways to nowhere or white elephants. That is not what this particular process is about. We have a list that has been put together at short notice across all the member states. It may well be that this list will evolve over time. Certainly, from what we see, it will be rationalised and is something that will be perceived as the end of the beginning of the process, to describe it that way, and ultimately, it will be revisited with a review as to what is a potentially viable and sustainable project being funded from the available resources.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_121">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">I contest strongly the assertion made by Mr. McCarthy in response to Senator Barrett - who was making similar assertions - that cutting capital when the crisis hit was anything but stupidity and folly. There was absolutely no rationale for it because it cost us more to do that. I will provide two examples, the first of which is housing. Cutting the budget for social housing in 2008 has cost us more. Obviously, it has cost us in terms of homelessness and an increased housing crisis, but it has also cost the Exchequer more because the State has been obliged to fork out a hell of a lot more to the private sector to cover the housing crisis. We must pay more to private landlords because we did not provide council housing. Is this not a classic example of how, when the market turns down or crashes, we need things that are not linked to the ups and downs of the economy because they always are needed, such as housing?</p>
          <p eId="para_237">It is not to do with the ups and downs of the market but how many people need roofs over their heads. Whether the market goes down or whatever it does, we need roofs over people's heads. One way or the other, it must be done. The question is whether to do it cheaply or expensively. What is the best value for money in doing something that simply must be done? Is that not one example that runs completely contrary to the assertion that we had to do it? We are paying a huge price for a massive mistake in that area.</p>
          <p eId="para_238"> Can anyone explain to me how the leveraged investment model does not end up costing ordinary people, the taxpayer, more for whatever project? The difference between this and doing it with 100% public investment for vital infrastructure and services, such as housing, is that there must be a profit for the private investor so it costs us more. It is not even disputable. It must cost us more because someone else is in the picture who wants a cut. In order to get in the money, we must provide guarantees that we will take the first hit if there are losses. If things go belly up, we promise, in order to get in private investors, that we will take the first hit. Second, we must promise enough profit and return for the private investor to come in in the first place. Our answer to the fact that we have a dysfunctional economy where the market decides it is not profitable to invest is to get down on our knees and say please invest and we guarantee, if anything goes wrong, that the taxpayer will cover the losses and the return is guaranteed. How can that possibly be a better way to invest than us doing it ourselves, where we do not have to give a cut to someone else? We invest in something because we need houses, roads and water infrastructure. These are vital and, regardless of the ups and downs of the markets, we must have them.</p>
          <p eId="para_239"> One can possibly make a different argument for areas of the economy that are not vital and we can debate where that line begins and ends but in certain areas we just must have certain things. Bringing in the private sector, where it must have a profit, cannot be as good value for money as us doing it ourselves.</p>
          <p eId="para_240"> How confident can we be that we can get this investment? We have big announcements about how we will get an investment with our €8 billion seed capital, which will increase to €21 billion and magically turn to €300 billion. How do we know that it will be coming in? Is it possible it will not appear? Is the list of projects publicly available? Does social housing feature in the list of projects?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_122">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">When I referred to cutting capital, I most certainly was not referring to a blunt instrument of cutting capital across the board. There are priorities and we need to maintain issues on the social housing front. I was simply pointing out some projects were based on a rate of return that was no longer viable once the economy hit. With some projects, the costs exceeded the benefits and they were the projects that had to be cut. I was not talking about an across the board cut in capital investment. We had to prioritise once the recession hit and the research shows that a number of projects were no longer viable on the basis of 2% or 3% trend growth rate as opposed to the 4% or 4.5% trend growth rate assumed when the projects were being compiled.</p>
          <p eId="para_242"> I will hand over to my colleagues to speak on the investment plan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_123">
          <from> Mr. John Hogan<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_243">The list is publicly available and we have committed to supplying the committee with the Irish list. On the Commission website, the list for all member states is available so the committee members can have full details of the 2,000 projects. Included on the list are two social housing references, one of which concerns the social housing measures linked to the budget announcement, and an energy efficiency measure to reduce the carbon footprint.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_124">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">Is there a figure for social housing?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_125">
          <from> Mr. John Hogan<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">The broad order of number is similar to what was in the budget and I think the total package in the budget was €2.2 billion. It appeared in the list as part of the overall global number. On the question of whether it is better or worse to have private sector involvement, it is a philosophical issue depending on one's view of the world.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">I am not asking a philosophical question. Is it not a self-evident statement of fact that if the private sector is to be lured in, it must get a profit. If we do the investment, we do not have to give someone a profit.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_127">
          <from> Mr. John Hogan<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">I am not sure I agree that it is as straightforward as that. There are a number of issues about how the private sector might fund the initiative and how it might organise the project. Perhaps the private sector is more operationally efficient in terms of the administration of a schools programme. It is difficult to make statements about whether it is more problematic or more difficult to have the private sector involved where there would be an upfront and immediate capital investment from the public sector. These are some of the issues at play in terms of how the Commission envisages unlocking the available private sector capital to meet investment projects across Europe that, by themselves are unable to avail of funding to have them completed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMurphy" eId="spk_128">
          <from>Deputy Paul Murphy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">I am interested in an insight from the Department of Finance on how the European semester works in practice. We know there are set pieces whereby member states produce certain things and these are discussed by the Commission and at Council level. It happens in parallel across member states. In practice and culturally, has there been a shift after the introduction of the European semester in terms of interaction on a regular basis outside the formal set pieces with the Commission? Does the Commission have more of a hand in the drafting of budgets than was previously the case? Is there more informal contact or contact on a regular basis between civil servants?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_129">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">Yes. This is our second cycle of surveillance and we had more interaction with the Commission from 2010 on as part of the programme but everyone is now in the same boat. There are three bilateral meetings with the Commission leading up to the adoption of the country-specific recommendations, CSRs, the first of which took place in December. If memory serves me correctly, there is another at the end of this month and a bilateral meeting after publication of the single analytical document.</p>
          <p eId="para_250">This single analytical document is published in mid-March. That is all about where the Commission and the member states see the priorities and what can be done. There is far more engagement with the Commission.</p>
          <p eId="para_251"> There is also a noticeable change at committee level, by which I mean the various European committees such as the Economic Policy Committee, EPC, the Economic and Financial Committee, EFC, and so forth. There is far more multilateral surveillance than would have been the case in the past. In the past, a state would have drawn up a policy and the Commission and that member state would have discussed it across the table, with the representatives of the other member states on their BlackBerries. Now, because there is a greater recognition that policies adopted in one member state have implications for Ireland and policies adopted in Ireland have implications for other member states, there is much more peer review, peer pressure and multilateral surveillance. It is not just between the Commission and the member states, but the member states trying to act in unison.</p>
          <p eId="para_252"> There has been a change. I would not call it a sea change, but as I mentioned earlier the process is evolving over time with incremental changes each year. For example, all euro area member states must have the same budgetary timelines, so they all submit budgets by mid-October. They are peer reviewed by officials, which then leads up to a ministerial assessment of every country's budget. There is far more interaction between the member states and also between the member states and the Commission.</p>
          <p eId="para_253"> I am sorry if I have spoken for too long.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMurphy" eId="spk_130">
          <from>Deputy Paul Murphy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">No, it is precisely what I am interested in. I have another question on the collapse of investment. The witness gave a figure of 15% at EU level and it is a multiple of that in the Irish level. It is probably still 50% or 60% down on what it was.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_131">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">It is 60% in real terms.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMurphy" eId="spk_132">
          <from>Deputy Paul Murphy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">Obviously an amount of the 2007 level of investment was in construction, not all of which would be viable. Mr. McCarthy says that is the main reason for the scale of the collapse, but why are we still bumping along the bottom? Obviously, there was an uptick in investment but according to the latest quarter for which we have reports, it went down again slightly and certainly did not rise. Why is Ireland lagging behind? As a percentage of GDP, we are at the bottom or very close to it in terms of investment. What is Mr. McCarthy's analysis of that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_133">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">Off the top of my head I do not know where we are in terms of the league table, as it were, but the Deputy is correct that there was a huge collapse in investment. The investment to GDP ratio fell to a level where the acquisition of new capital assets was only just sufficient to cover the depreciation of capital stock, which is more or less unheard of. It fell to 10% or 11% of GDP, which is absolutely unheard of. It is also fair to state that it came after a period of over-investment, producing 90,000 to 92,000 houses. As the Deputy says, it was simply unviable and unsustainable. That must be borne in mind as well.</p>
          <p eId="para_258"> However, we have bottomed out on the investment side. Over the past 18 months we have seen very strong double digit growth, although I will enter caveat on that in a moment. For example, the data we have for last year shows that in the first three quarters overall investment is up by just under 11% relative to the previous period. However, the caveat I must stress is that this is the law of small numbers. In absolute terms it is not a big increase in investment. It is simply because the base is so low. The improvement in investment that is undoubtedly under way is broad based. It can be seen in the building and construction sector as well as in housing. Again, the law of small numbers applies here. We produced 11,000 units last year. In absolute terms, that is too low, but it is still 30% above the previous year. Other forms of building and construction are very strong. The other component of investment we examine is the so-called machinery and equipment investment, that is, investment in software and so forth. That has been running at 30% for the past 18 months.</p>
          <p eId="para_259"> I will not say we are back to where we should be. As an advanced economy we would typically allocate between one fifth and one quarter of national income to capital formation or investment. Our numbers are based on investment growth last year of approximately 14%, and 12% this year. That will only bring the investment to GDP ratio back to 17% or 18%. We are still a long way from what one might refer to as equilibrium or the norm.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMurphy" eId="spk_134">
          <from>Deputy Paul Murphy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">Is research and development now included in investment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_135">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMurphy" eId="spk_136">
          <from>Deputy Paul Murphy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_262">However, it does not necessarily affect the percentage figures because Mr. McCarthy is counting backwards and including research and development.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_137">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_263">No, it was retrospectively included in the figures. The Deputy might recall that there was much discussion last July, when the Central Statistics Office, CSO, introduced methodological changes. It focused on black economy type activity. That was quite small. The big methodological change was the capitalisation of research and development spending. Overall, it increased the level of investment by approximately €10 billion, and approximately €8 billion or €9 billion was due to research and development. However, it was included retrospectively. I believe it fell slightly last year, but it is very volatile on a year to year basis.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMurphy" eId="spk_138">
          <from>Deputy Paul Murphy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">It means the percentage of GDP is therefore distorted. We were talking previously about a 10% or 11% figure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_139">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">The Deputy is right.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMurphy" eId="spk_140">
          <from>Deputy Paul Murphy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">If we had had the new mechanism of accounting, it would not have dropped to that level.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_141">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_267">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_142">
          <from> Mr. Shane Enright<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_268">Under the new statistical treatment procedure we do not look as bad in relative terms in the league table as we did. The previous ratio was that it fell to 11% and now we are up to approximately 15%. It does not look as bad in comparative terms.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_143">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_269">It also means the equilibrium is higher, so the distance is still the same.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_144">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_270">Has the Commission looked at how the collapse in oil price will affect forecasts for 2015?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_145">
          <from> Mr. John McCarthy<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_271">No. However, it will publish its winter forecasts at the beginning of next month and I strongly suspect it will include an analysis of what the lower oil price means. The IMF published its interim world economic outlook last Tuesday and it stated that the overall impact of falling oil prices would be to add between 0.4% and 0.7% to overall world output. From an Irish perspective, our rule of thumb is that each €10 per barrel reduction in oil prices increases the growth rate by between 0.1% and 0.2%. It used to be higher, but the dependence on oil is much lower now because we have become a software driven economy rather than heavy manufacturing. That is the rule of thumb we would typically use. The fall we have seen since last summer will have a positive impact, as will the depreciation of the exchange rate. However, as Deputy Doherty mentioned, there have been downward revisions to the euro area and so forth, so they are operating in opposite directions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LiamTwomeyIND" eId="spk_146">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2015-01-21T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_272">We will conclude. On behalf of the committee I thank Mr. McCarthy, Mr. Hogan, Mr. Enright and Mr. Petris for attending the meeting. It is always a valuable experience for the committee and I appreciate the frank exchange of views you always have with us.</p>
          <p eId="para_273"> As there is no other business, we will adjourn. </p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8"> The joint committee adjourned at 6 p.m. until 2 p.m. on Tuesday, 27 January 2015.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
