<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_the_constitution/2003-07-16/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_the_constitution_/2003-07-16/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2003-07-16" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/29/joint_committee_on_the_constitution_"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_the_constitution/2003-07-16/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_the_constitution_/2003-07-16/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2003-07-16" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_the_constitution/2003-07-16/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_the_constitution_/2003-07-16/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference showAs="Vol. 1" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/1" eId="#vol_1"/>
          <oir:numberReference showAs="No. 2" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/1/no/2" eId="#no_2"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AengusOSnodaighSF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aengus-Ó-Snodaigh.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Aengus Ó Snodaigh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AnnOrmonde" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ann-Ormonde.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Ann Ormonde"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ArthurMorganSF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Arthur-Morgan.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Arthur Morgan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BarryAndrewsFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Barry-Andrews.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Barry Andrews"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BrendanDaly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Brendan-Daly.D.1973-03-14" showAs="Brendan Daly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CiaranCuffeGP" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ciarán-Cuffe.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Ciarán Cuffe"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DanNeville" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Dan-Neville.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Dan Neville"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DennisODonovan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Denis-O'Donovan.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Denis O'Donovan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DinnyMcGinley" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Dinny-McGinley.D.1982-03-09" showAs="Dinny McGinley"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JamesBreen" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/James-Breen.D.2002-06-06" showAs="James Breen"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JanOSullivan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jan-O'Sullivan.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Jan O'Sullivan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JimmyDevinsFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jimmy-Devins.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Jimmy Devins"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoannaTuffy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joanna-Tuffy.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Joanna Tuffy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnDardis" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Dardis.S.1989-10-01" showAs="John Dardis"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaryHenry" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mary-EF-Henry.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Mary E.F. Henry"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PadraicMcCormack" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pádraic-McCormack.S.1987-04-25" showAs="Pádraic McCormack"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TimDooley" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Timmy-Dooley.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Timmy Dooley"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chair" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chair" showAs="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chairman" showAs="Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>COMHCHOISTE AR AN mBUNREACHT</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>JOINT COMMITTEE ON THE CONSTITUTION </docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2003-07-16">Dé Céadaoin, 16 Iúil 2003</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2003-07-16">Wednesday, 16 July 2003</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="volume">
        <docNumber refersTo="#vol_1">Vol. 1</docNumber>
      </block>
      <block name="number">
        <docNumber refersTo="#no_2">No. 2</docNumber>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 10.30 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">Members Present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#BarryAndrewsFF">Deputy B. Andrews,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#DanNeville">Deputy D. Neville,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#JamesBreen">Deputy J. Breen,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#JanOSullivan">Deputy J. O’Sullivan,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#CiaranCuffeGP">Deputy C. Cuffe,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#BrendanDaly">Senator B. Daly,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#JimmyDevinsFF">Deputy J. Devins,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#JohnDardis">Senator J. Dardis,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#PadraicMcCormack">Deputy P. McCormack,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#TimDooley">Senator T. Dooley,*</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#DinnyMcGinley">Deputy D. McGinley,*</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#AnnOrmonde">Senator A. Ormonde,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_13">
                  <person refersTo="#ArthurMorganSF">Deputy A. Morgan,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_14">
                  <person refersTo="#JoannaTuffy">Senator J. Tuffy.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">*In the absence of Deputy D. Neville and Senator B. Daly, respectively, for part of the meeting.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#DennisODonovan">
   DEPUTY D. O’DONOVAN in the chair.
  </person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Property Rights: Presentations.</heading>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_15">Is the schedule for today's proceedings agreed? Agreed. I take this opportunity to ask all visitors and members to switch off their mobile phones, if they have not already done so. The first item on the agenda is the presentation by Sinn Féin, represented by Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh and Mr. John Dwyer. You are both welcome.</p>
          <p eId="para_16">Before we begin, I must remind visitors that members of this committee have absolute privilege but this same privilege does not apply to witnesses appearing before the committee, with the exception of Deputy Ó Snodaigh. Members are reminded of the long standing parliamentary practice to the effect that members should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House, or an official by name, in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">I invite the Sinn Féin representatives to make their presentation. The time limit for each group is six to eight minutes and I hope they can adhere to that. We have already got your submission, which we have studied. I suggest you synopsise the submission and perhaps you will take any questions that may be asked.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Mr. John Dwyer</from>
          <p eId="para_18">Thank you, Chairman. I apologise on behalf of my colleague, Mary Nellis, who is unavailable today. I also thank the committee for hearing our submission.</p>
          <p eId="para_19">Sinn Féin believes that the right to housing is a fundamental right which must be enshrined in the Constitution. It is also our assertion that the Constitution must be amended so as to clarify the Articles which deal with the rights of private property. Property rights should be dealt with in a single, self-contained Article, and social justice must be given pre-eminence to the rights of private property.</p>
          <p eId="para_20">In looking at the way various issues are affected by the Articles in the Constitution which deal with private property, the recurrent theme is that, in practice, the social justice component has been subordinated to the needs of private property.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_21">Sorry to interrupt, Chairman, but is Mr. Dwyer going to read what we have in front of us?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Mr. Dwyer</from>
          <p eId="para_22">I will only read the introduction, with the permission of the Chairman.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_23">Bearing in mind that you only have six to eight minutes, if you read the whole submission it will take another half an hour.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Mr. Dwyer</from>
          <p eId="para_24">I have no difficulty, Chairman——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_25">I do not want to interrupt you but perhaps you could synopsise the main points of your introduction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Mr. Dwyer</from>
          <p eId="para_26">If we deal with housing as a right, Sinn Féin believes that the right to housing is a fundamental right which must be enshrined in the Constitution. We believe that the State, in failing to amend the Constitution to include the right to housing, has failed to fulfil its international commitments and we contend that any referendum which may arise as a result of these proceedings should include that right to housing.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">With regard to access to the countryside, our party believes that the legislative mechanism available to local authorities to deal with this issue has been shown to be overly cumbersome and has not served the people of the State well. We believe the landowners should not be held legally responsible for compensation claims arising from the use of these pathways by members of the public, and that there should be free access to property.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">On house prices, the current housing crisis is a real crisis. Attempts have been made to play down that crisis but the people who come to us daily are the ones who are suffering. Sinn Féin believes that Government intervention is necessary to deal with rising house prices through taking measures to control the price of building land. It is a straightforward, simple mechanism.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_29">I will deal with a few points, most of which are contained in the section in our submission on compulsory purchase orders, rezoning and planning. One of the practical limitations to private property are compulsory purchase orders, which are overly used. In terms of infrastructure, we believe compulsory purchase orders can be used to facilitate social housing and local authorities who will ensure they can acquire land at a price below the market price, where necessary, for the common good. We outline some of the legal findings in respect of compulsory purchase orders. We believe that, where necessary, compensation should be based on the existing use value plus a percentage, as outlined 30 years ago in the Kenny report.</p>
          <p eId="para_30">In the four points at the end of that section we state that we support the use of compulsory purchase orders, in particular against speculators who are sitting on land banks and derelict properties. In such incidents, compensation might not be merited, and compulsory purchase orders should be used by the State or allowed to be used by the local authorities to regain possession of the land.</p>
          <p eId="para_31">On rezoning and planning, we believe the State is entitled to compensation if infrastructure changes were made and services put onto the land to increase its value. It is not morally acceptable that developers and speculators should make huge profits at the cost of the community, which is then unable to build houses which can be sold to the community.</p>
          <p eId="para_32">The State must have the ability to tackle the problem of landowners whose land has been rezoned but who are still sitting on that land. The amount of land which is zoned and available for residential housing could accommodate 327,784 houses. There is currently enough zoned land to tackle the housing crisis. The figures suggest that speculators are sitting on land; therefore, compulsory purchase orders or the repossession of the land should begin to ensure the common good. The theme in our submission is that the common good should enjoy a higher right than the right to private property.</p>
          <p eId="para_33">We believe there is an onus also on the Government to monitor the cost of building land, with specific reference to the gap between the cost of building houses and house prices. That is a function we believe could be taken on by a resurrected Land Commission, and there are other issues the Land Commission could also address. This joint committee should not restrict its view, as the Kenny report was restricted to dealing with the limitations of the Constitution. As this is a Joint Committee on the Constitution it can examine the possibility of changing the Constitution to allow us go further than the Kenny report and other reports, and ensure land which is available for building is not hoarded.</p>
          <p eId="para_34">The last item with which I wish to deal is the abolition of ground rents. Ground rent landlords should not be compensated. Ground rents should be abolished forthwith. There is no need for constitutional change for that but if it is required it should be done as a matter of urgency. The hangover from colonial days in Ireland should be got rid of. Those ground rent landlords, including some Irish companies which have resurrected the practice of ground rents in recent years - a facility for making money and putting many into dire circumstances because one-eighth of the value of a house in this city is a huge figure if one wished to buy it out - should not be compensated.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_35">There is much in that submission with which we would all agree but I do not know if many of its proposals are relevant to constitutional change. While we would all agree in principle with the part of the submission dealing with ground rents it is not a matter for this committee but rather for legislation. The legislators have been tickling at that problem for a long time without tackling it. There are many good aspirations in the Sinn Féin submissions but perhaps we could get guidance on whether it is relevant to a review of the Constitution.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_36">In regard to the guidelines we sent out, some of the points made on the question of property and rezoning of land are relevant but there is a question mark hanging over ground rents. Obviously some of the issues can be dealt with by legislation. Do members wish to comment on that point?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DanNeville" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy Neville</from>
          <p eId="para_37">Some of the submissions made to us have said, "if it is not broken do not fix it". In regard to the Sinn Féin laudable submission I would interpret that it is up to us, the Legislature, to deal with it and it is our duty to deal with it. If we support it we should deal with it as an Oireachtas. Putting it into the Constitution will involve Supreme Court tests and all kinds of delaying mechanisms whereas the Constitution, at present, will facilitate what has been proposed. I would like to hear your views on that issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_38">I welcome the submission and wish to dwell on the constitutional aspects. The submission is specific in terms of religious denominations and the deletion of Article 40.3.6° but does Sinn Féin have a suggested wording in terms of the right to housing as a fundamental right and having that included?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_39">We will take the first three questions, one of which is general and concerns whether there should be a constitutional change or legislation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DanNeville" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Deputy Neville</from>
          <p eId="para_40">Housing is a social issue, it is not a property issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_41">Most of it has to do with property. We believe some of our suggestions require legislation but the excuse given for not acting on them until now was that there was a constitutional problem. This committee should be able to say to the legislators there is no constitutional problem; we do not need to deal with it. That is the reason it was included in the submission. If a message comes from this committee to say ground rents can be dealt with by legislation, it should be dealt with.</p>
          <p eId="para_42">On the issue of private property and the right to housing, we do not have a specific wording. We are working on it and trying to look at other models in other countries to see if a wording can be found which allows for the right to private property and the right to housing. One of the problems with the 1937 Constitution is that the right to private property can sometimes be to the detriment of the common good, for example, the holding of land banks and property by speculators.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DanNeville" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Deputy Neville</from>
          <p eId="para_43">We are advised that can be dealt with under the present Constitution.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_44">If that is so and if that is the message from here, I still believe the Constitution should have contained explicitly in it the right to housing accommodation. We can deal with the standard of that housing through legislation. In other jurisdictions that is being looked at. Is it just a case of the people of Ireland having the right to housing? Will it be as simple as that or do we need to expand it? The Constitution should be as simple a document as possible. It might end up being that simple but we will come back to it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Deputy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_45">I welcome the submission. On the issue of land banks being held and the suggestion that compulsory purchase orders could be used and that those who hold on to land while its value increases should not be entitled to compensation, did Sinn Féin look into whether the matter could be dealt with under current legislation or did the party consider it was necessary to change the Constitution?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_46">We did consider it and we have stated in our submission that in most cases it can be dealt with through legislation. The problem is that the political will has not been there until now and the excuse given was that there were constitutional difficulties. The reason it was included in our submission was so that the committee could send out the message that there is no problem, that the committee does not need to deal with this matter again, that it is a legislative problem and that we can deal with other issues in the Constitution that need to be changed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBreen" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Deputy J. Breen</from>
          <p eId="para_47">In relation to entry onto property, a landowner should be exonerated from all blame and should not be held liable if a person has an accident on the land. That would require a legislative change not a constitutional change.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_48">It is clear from the submission that is what it desires.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCuffeGP" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Deputy Cuffe</from>
          <p eId="para_49">I welcome the submission. In page six of the submission Sinn Féin points out "that there are instances where compensation is not merited", presumably no compensation whatsoever. Will the Deputy give examples? I presume what he is looking at is a building which has been derelict for many years and where the owners did nothing about it. I am curious as to whether he has any other examples of where compensation is not merited.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_50">I do not have specific instances, but I am concerned with derelict sites or land which have been rezoned but have been purposely held to increase value.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_51">I thank the members of the delegation for their presentation. While the remit of the committee is narrowly focused, I hope that over the next four or five months we will be in a position to conclude if constitutional or legislative change is required.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">Sitting suspended at 11.22 a.m. and resumed at 11.25 a.m.</summary>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_52">The next item on the agenda is the presentation by the Dublin Transportation Office, represented by Mr. John Henry and Mr. James Muldowney. You are both welcome. I must again remind visitors that members of the committee have absolute privilege but the same privilege does not apply to witnesses appearing before the committee. I now invite you to make you presentation in six to eight minutes, which will be followed by questions. You have already made a detailed submission, which we have studied. In view of this, perhaps you would provide the committee with the salient points.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryHenry" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Mr. John Henry</from>
          <p eId="para_53">I thank you for inviting us to this important committee. My name is John Henry and I am director and chief executive of the Dublin Transportation Office. My colleague, James Muldowney, is a chartered surveyor, town planner and barrister.</p>
          <p eId="para_54">The DTO was established in 1995 by statutory instrument. Our principal function is to co-ordinate and monitor strategic land use and transportation planning in the greater Dublin area. We cover the four counties, Dublin, Meath, Kildare and Wicklow. It is also a requirement of our office to review and update our transportation strategies and policies at least once every five years. I am sure the committee is aware that in 2001, we published a strategy for Dublin, Platform for Change, which is not only a transportation strategy but also sets out land use policies and so on. It is a comprehensive policy for the region. We are also involved in the current review of the planning guidelines for the country, with specific reference to the Dublin area.</p>
          <p eId="para_55">The DTO is interested in removing barriers that prevent the timely delivery of infrastructure, especially transportation infrastructure, and the promotion of sustainable land use development policies within the region. I will now ask Mr. Muldowney to summarise our submission and focus on the key points.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Mr. James Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_56">I thank the committee for affording us the opportunity to make this submission to what is a very important issue. I will deal with the headings we consider appropriate to the DTO. Articles 43 and 40 of the Constitution deal with private property and the common good. In essence, Article 43 deals with the institution of property as such and is perhaps directed to the State and its attitude to the right to private property, which is counterbalanced, of course, by the interest of the common good. That is not the main focus of our submission which relates to Article 40, or perhaps in the context of the 1996 review, the possibility of amalgamating the two Articles.</p>
          <p eId="para_57">Article 40 deals with personal rights, for example, the right of a citizen to a piece of property. Article 40.3.1° states: "The State guarantees in its laws to respect, and, as far as is practicable, by its laws to defend and vindicate the personal rights of the citizen.". One of those personal rights is the right to private property. On the question of property, a balancing exercise runs through the Constitution in that it seeks to balance the right to property with the common good. A body of legislation and case law relates to that, to which I will return later. Article 40.3.1o states the State will respect, as far as practicable, the personal rights of the citizen.</p>
          <p eId="para_58">Article 40.3.2° states: "The State shall, in particular, by its laws protect as best it may from unjust attack and, in the case of injustice done, vindicate the life, person, good name and property rights of every citizen.". The Constitution here acknowledges that there is no absolute right to private property, but it will protect the personal right to private property against unjust attack. The key test here is whether there is an unjust attack on property rights if a law is introduced. The law must be tested as to whether it constitutes an unjust attack. A body of case law deals with these tests. I do not have time to elaborate, but I am sure members of the committee are familiar with it.</p>
          <p eId="para_59">The case law culminated in what some might consider to be a high point in connection with the Article 26 referral of Part V - the social housing provision - of the Planning and Development Act 2000. The provision gave local authorities the power to acquire land at less than the market value. An Article 26 judgment delivers one judgment; there is no minority judgment. Mr. Justice Keane basically stated that a planning permission is essentially an enhancement or enlargement of property rights which is conferred on the applicant or the owner of the land. Prior to this, the jurisprudential thought was that one had a right to develop one's land subject to the law of tort. However, in 2000, the Supreme Court said this was not the case and that a planning permission amounts to an enhancement of one's rights.</p>
          <p eId="para_60">This is a fundamental change. The Supreme Court basically also held that compensation at less than market value can be constitutional. It also stated that, in exceptional cases, compensation at nil value could even be constitutional. This was a landmark judgment. It held that the social housing scheme was rationally connected to an objective of sufficient importance to warrant interference with a constitutionally protected right and, given the serious policy and social problems which the scheme was designed to meet, it held that there was an undoubted relationship between these concerns, which in a free and democratic society should be regarded as pressing and substantial. In other words, what it was saying is that, yes, property rights are important, but they are not so important that they cannot in some way be attenuated in the interests of social good and of the common good, that land can be acquired at less than market value, and that market value is not necessarily the only test of a just compensation.</p>
          <p eId="para_61">The court was satisfied that the provisions of Part V impaired those rights, that is, property rights, as little as possible and that their effects on these rights are proportionate. One of the constitutional tests is the following, "Is the legislation which addresses a social problem and relates to the common good, proportionate?", and that test of proportionality runs through a great many constitutional issues, not just the constitutional issue of property rights.</p>
          <p eId="para_62">The court appeared to recognise the iniquity of having to pay compensation to a landowner for value enhancement which was created by Government fiat or action, in other words, where the Government carried out infrastructural works or where the Government was involved in rezonings, etc., which effectively enhanced the value of land. Why then should the Government, when it needs to acquire the land, have to pay for the land value enhancement which it has created?</p>
          <p eId="para_63">The key point I would make is that to reduce the prospect of repeated challenges to similar legislation in the future, this rebalancing of private property versus the common good should be made manifest in the Constitution. In other words, when you are introducing legislation in an area such as this, you are always asking yourself "Am I being second guessed by the Constitution? Can I introduce legislation which will not be constitutionally fragile?". This is one of the big problems. You can see from the body of case law and the constant challenges on these constitutional issues that this is something of which any drafter or proposer of legislation in the Dáil must be aware.</p>
          <p eId="para_64">To reduce this level of uncertainty it is necessary to be explicit in the Constitution on property as to what factors can be taken into consideration which would restrict property rights. The two I suggest here, which could be introduced in a manner consonant with the 1996 recommendations which are in the report at page 366, are that sustainable land use and transportation planning, and the protection of the environment, should be two checks on property rights essentially. That would give much more certainty to the legislators when they are introducing legislation they think is necessary in the interests of the common good.</p>
          <p eId="para_65">Having dealt with that issue, I want to move on to compulsory purchase. We are particularly concerned with the provision of transportation infrastructure. We are also concerned with the integration of land use and transportation planning. This is considered to be good transportation practice and it is something which has not really been embraced in this country but we hope in the future will be embraced more progressively, and which, if it is, will cut down some of the problems we have in our cities at present.</p>
          <p eId="para_66">If you put in a new metro line, for example, you may find that the new metro line leads to an enhanced value which is created around the stations and along the line. This is especially so in a city, for example, that suffers from chronic congestion. In such a situation the Government pays for the value created, or for some of the value created, by rezoning and by infrastructure provision. In addition, if you acquired land for the metro, some of the retained lands actually go up in value as a result of putting in the metro or the transportation infrastructure and, paradoxically, you end up paying a high market value just to acquire the land to facilitate the implementation of the infrastructural project. In addition, the landowner who retains land also gains a windfall because the value of his lands increase. Basically the point that has to be made is: why should the Government pay twice? The existing use value is not necessarily a disproportionate burden on the person who sells the land and if you look at the Kenny report you might, for example, decide that existing use value plus a percentage such as 25% or 15%, depending on what is deemed appropriate, could be a fair compensation for land which is acquired for such projects.</p>
          <p eId="para_67">The compensation rules could be changed. I realise that. There are two ways of handling this, in other words, you can change the legislation and assume that the body of case law built up will facilitate this and that the change in legislation will not be constitutionally fragile, but again I come back to the point. In order to introduce certainty, a change in the Constitution will give you much more flexibility and allow you to be more creative in the framing of the legislation with the certainty that the chances of it being successfully constitutionally challenged are significantly less.</p>
          <p eId="para_68">I will move on briefly to zoning. When we talk about sustainable and unsustainable development,——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_69">You should conclude in a few minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_70">In terms of zoning, some of the points I already made are appropriate. Zoning is an enhancement of land value - it is something that is created by the community - and if, in order to recover some of that, it is necessary to acquire land at less than market value, it is deemed that this is reasonable and in the interests of the common good. As a result of that, I again suggest that the same two provisos and checks be introduced into the Constitution to accommodate that kind of legislation.</p>
          <p eId="para_71">The price of development land is the next topic with which I will deal. Because of the enhanced price of development land over the past few years, there has been a tendency to hoard land and this has been easy to do because there are no rates on agricultural land and zoned agricultural land can be held without any real penalty. The costs of the acquisition of this land are so prohibitive that local authorities cannot acquire the land.</p>
          <p eId="para_72">The Kenny report made recommendations with which the committee will be familiar, and also looked at site value rating. Again the point is made that to cut down on the scope for challenge in terms of the acquisition of land below market value, it is posited that three legal restrictions on the right to private property should be introduced in the Constitution: the raising of taxation and revenue, and the other two I mentioned, sustainable land use and transportation planning, and the protection of the environment.</p>
          <p eId="para_73">I will skip through infrastucture because some of the points I have made already are repeated in that section and I will move on to the penultimate comments on house prices. Without going through the factors which have led to the increase in house prices, one of the major factors was the high cost of serviced sites and the high cost of building land. Again, in order to reduce house prices, it is necessary to reduce the costs of building land and to stop land being used as a commodity.</p>
          <p eId="para_74">Land being used as a commodity essentially can mean that some key lands on the edges of cities remain undeveloped in that they are held as an investment and then a leapfrog effect takes place. Lands are rezoned further out from the city and developed and then you have the consequent commuting and this almost slightly doughnut effect which occurs where the most appropriate lands which should be released are not released. To facilitate the timely release of these lands, it is recommended that the changes to which I have already referred should be implemented.</p>
          <p eId="para_75">I will deal with the conclusions very briefly. The high price of building land is effectively a barrier to the provision of transport infrastructure. It prevents and hinders land assembly at stations and comprehensive redevelopment. The land becomes a commodity and hoarding is almost encouraged. It causes unsustainable leapfrog development and increases car usage, congestion and pollution, and it threatens the economic viability of the city in so far as in a study we were doing last year it was remarked to us on occasions in the US that Dublin was "maxed out" as such, that the infrastructure does not match the economic development. Essentially this has been looked at by the Kenny report, the joint committee on building land in 1985 and the Article 26 reference to which I referred on Part V of the 2000 Act. The all reflect that there is a need for certainty in the Constitution. This can only be given by modifying the Constitution in the manner I outlined earlier and this should ensure that the legislation, which seeks to return the benefits created by the community to the community, can be enacted with a good prospect of surviving constitutional scrutiny.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_76">You mentioned two additional checks, sustainable land use and transportation planning, and the protection of the environment. Are they in addition to the checks already incorporated that refer to the common good?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_77">Yes. What often happens is that when cases which test the constitutionality of an Act are taken, there is a great debate as to what constitutes the common good and whether sustainable transportation and land use planning are consonant with the common good and whether the protection of the environment is consonant with the common good. It is not to say the arguments cannot be very subtle - they often are - but I feel that if it is explicitly pointed out in the Constitution, then the scope for challenge is significantly reduced and the scope for more creative legislation and the scope for the legislators to work without this almost potential nemesis on their shoulders is greatly enhanced.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_78">Is Mr. Muldowney saying that the Supreme Court decision on Part V of the Planning and Development Act 2000 does not go far enough but is a step in the right direction?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_79">Yes. It is a landmark change, but if one reads it one will see that there is a predisposition towards compensation at full market value. All other things being equal, that is the predisposition. One almost gets the impression that Part V is seen as exceptional and that might lead to other provisions consonant with Part V being challenged again to see if the courts would still make that leap. It should also be noted that Part V has been amended. While it was originally ringfenced from constitutional challenge, that has essentially been dismantled.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_80">You referred in your submission to the fact that there is evidence that there is hoarding of land and land banks, especially in and around Dublin. A previous grouping comprising people involved in the property market made a submission to us and said it had no evidence of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_81">It is an understanding. It is difficult to have explicit evidence because most of the land can be bought by placing an option on it. That does not necessarily have to be recorded in the Registry of Deeds or anywhere else. It might be said that the evidence is anecdotal but I have seen references to it from the highest authority in the land down. If the Chairman is inquiring whether I have empirical evidence which is explicit and incontrovertible, the answer is that I do not.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_82">What I gather from having read the submission is that the law or the Constitution impedes or strangles the development of Dublin, be that the Luas, metro, ring roads or whatever.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_83">Yes, it does to a certain extent because, to pick up on a point on which I did not have a chance to enlarge, if land is rezoned, that does not mean it will be developed. A builder or developer can wait until he believes it has reached maximum fruition. It is the timely release of the appropriate land and the development of the lands around the stations that concern us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ArthurMorganSF" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Deputy Morgan</from>
          <p eId="para_84">I thank Mr. Muldowney for making the presentation and attending the meeting to elaborate on it. We heard in an earlier presentation that a body of case law had been established around the issue of property rights and Articles 40.3 and 43 of the Constitution that clarified to a considerable extent the issue of the common good. There is an assumption around the issue Mr. Muldowney raised of compensation.</p>
          <p eId="para_85">Is constitutional change required and, if so, where? What are Mr. Muldowney's views on Articles 40.3 and 43? Does he think they need constitutional change and tidying up? What would he say in reply to the earlier submission that case law deals with it adequately?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_86">On the body of case law, it is not clear. If it were, the President would not have seen fit to refer Part V of the Bill to the Supreme Court for a four day hearing, which I attended, on the issue of acquiring land for social housing at less than full market value. This is the key point. The President is a lawyer.</p>
          <p eId="para_87">That said and having attended that hearing, cogent arguments were made on both sides regarding the Constitution as it stood then. To some extent, many of the eminent lawyers were surprised by the finding of the Supreme Court at the time. Some have criticised the final judgment. I contend that the argument that the case law is clear does not hold water.</p>
          <p eId="para_88">In terms of the test on Part V, it is an interesting judgment but it does not clarify these matters. Therefore, in the interests of certainty, it is necessary to make changes. I accept that a great debate has taken place regarding the 1996 committee's thinking on this subject and it debated whether to combine the two Articles or leave them as they were. I do not have a strong view on that. I would be prepared to go along with the line of combining the two Articles but it is necessary to place these checks on the antecedent status of the right to private property.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCuffeGP" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Deputy Cuffe</from>
          <p eId="para_89">The Chairman's point about hoarding land is interesting. There appear to be different views on it. Mr. Boland of the Institute of Chartered Surveyors yesterday said he felt there was evidence of hoarding in the greater Dublin area. There appears to be a variety of views among those in the property sector.</p>
          <p eId="para_90">Am I right in thinking that Mr. Muldowney believes the Part V protection has been removed by the passing of the Planning and Development (Amendment) Act 2002 which changed the Part V provision slightly?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_91">The changes to Part V have not been constitutionally tested, so they are not ringfenced anymore. The original Part V and the sections contained therein were ringfenced. When a small alteration is made, it opens it up to constitutional challenge again.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCuffeGP" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Deputy Cuffe</from>
          <p eId="para_92">On the issue of site value rating to which Mr. Muldowney referred on a number of occasions in his presentation, does he mean a site value tax that is applied, probably on an annual basis, to zoned undeveloped land?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_93">Yes, that is how it could be used. If one examines the international literature on the subject, that is what it suggests. It is a way of effectively ensuring that key lands located in relatively close proximity to the city are released. Otherwise there is what I describe as a slight doughnut effect in that development takes place ten miles down the road where land is released and houses are built, with the result that commuting begins to take place because of the lack of proper or adequate public transport and the lands held in between increase in value. This is contingent upon the lack of a comprehensive national development plan that has definite goals in terms of what is to be developed. The land retained nearer to the city of Dublin, for example, will increase in value.</p>
          <p eId="para_94">This must also be examined in the context of alternative investments. If one holds on to land, it is not subject to rates because it is normally still held as agricultural land. In the Brennan case, which was a constitutional challenge to rates, the State lost and rates for agricultural land were abolished. One can hold land without significant costs safe in the knowledge that it is usually going to appreciate, perhaps much more so than equities or putting the money in a bank. It is a good investment. I do not criticise the people involved in that business. I started out as a chartered surveyor who would have advised developers. I am looking on this in a dispassionate way.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCuffeGP" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Deputy Cuffe</from>
          <p eId="para_95">I appreciate that. I am thinking within my constituency of the possible Luas-metro connection out towards Cherrywood. Dún Laoghaire-Rathdown County Council is rezoning lands but would not be able to force developers to develop that land.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_96">No, it would not. That is true. That was the first section 49 scheme introduced. I should clarify this for other committee members. Section 49 of the Planning Act allows for the establishment of a contribution scheme for special projects such as the development of Luas or an extension to the metro. It is an extension to Luas that is at issue in the area to which the Deputy refers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCuffeGP" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Deputy Cuffe</from>
          <p eId="para_97">One will be hit either way. If it is developed, there will be the section 49 levy, and if it is not, there is the site value levy. Presumably the site value levy or tax is a way of kick-starting development.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_98">The site value levy is to push land towards development. We have conducted a survey of many developers and they are of the view that they would like to make contributions if the infrastructure were put in place because it makes their land of sufficiently greater value that they are only returning a fraction of that gain.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_99">Mr. Muldowney referred to the market value of land. Every deputation and presentation we have heard has referred to the market value of land. How will that eventually be defined? The market value of land is what it will sell for when it is offered for sale. How is the market value defined in such circumstances? If someone puts up for sale 30 acres of land beside Galway city, it will sell for between €40,000 and €70,000 and possibly €100,000 an acre. Is that the market value of land? How is it defined?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_100">The market value is defined as a willing seller and a willing buyer in an open and unfettered market.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_101">Your contention is that this is a chicken and egg situation as to whether we bring in legislation first and have it challenged or we have a constitutional amendment and have that challenged. Other delegations suggested there was greater scope for challenge if this were a constitutional amendment rather than if it were legislation. Should this be tackled from the point of view of legislation and then we could deal with a challenge to the legislation by constitutional amendment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_102">Should I answer?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_103">Other delegations suggested it would be far better to legislate and then deal with challenges to that constitutionally rather than have a constitutional change as that would encourage more challenges.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_104">I do not agree with that because the Constitution is the foundation of law in the State and provides the litmus test for all Acts to be challenged or not. If one looks at the hierarchy of legal rights, it starts at the top with the Constitution and then comes down to statute and moves down to statutory instruments, regulations and so on. If one is saying it is logical to litigate each piece of legislation, that leads to delays and uncertainty. If the Constitution is changed by plebiscite, how is that to be challenged? One cannot challenge the Constitution as such unless one goes to the European Court and I doubt the chances of success there. I fundamentally disagree with whoever made that suggestion but it might be someone interested in having more litigation, in which case I can see the point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_105">Mr. Muldowney seems to be against leaving pockets of land and developing outside those, but sometimes leaving those pockets can be a good idea. One then looks at the need for different services such as open space amenities and so on. It can often be very good not to develop. If anyone wants to see it, in my area a farmer in the middle of Renmore would not sell 30 or 40 acres but once McInerney built all round him the local authority was able to buy it and now it is a very well planned area, with open amenities and schools in the middle of the parish. Sometimes it is a good idea to leave pockets of land undeveloped and those can then be examined ten or 15 years down the line when communities have developed and there are different needs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ArthurMorganSF" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Morgan</from>
          <p eId="para_106">Could the whole committee go over to Deputy McCormack's place?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_107">Anytime.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_108">Mr. Muldowney made a point that is very important to a committee dealing with constitutional issues in suggesting that an amendment to the Constitution might be the right way to go, because in a plebiscite the people decide and that cannot be challenged. An eminent lawyer has told us the Law Society's view is similar to that and a typical example of this going wrong was the Eighth Amendment to the Constitution on the abortion issue in 1983. That created more referenda and court challenges. That is an example contrary to the view expressed by Mr. Muldowney.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_109">It is not related to uncertainty in how it should be interpreted.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_110">I am not saying the Law Society is right but its view is that one should not fix what is not broken. Doctors differ and patients die.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_111">The point is that the checks on the right to private property can be clearly and precisely framed and that would reduce the chance of challenge. The case referred to by the Chairman was fraught with great social division and was somewhat ambiguous, to say the least.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_112">I thank the deputation. I am not a lawyer and found it difficult to follow some of the legal implications. To clear my mind, is the delegation recommending a change to the Constitution?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_113">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_114">Does the delegation have a wording it could submit to us for consideration?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_115">I have mentioned the three checks which should be introduced. If the committee wants me to submit something at a later date, I do not have a specific article redrafted as I did not think that was my function as someone making representations. Regarding the right to private property, which now has antecedent status to positive law, it might be considered whether that phrase should be retained. In addition, it should be specified that the right to private property was qualified by the exigencies of the common good which include the raising of taxes and revenue, sustainable land use and transport planning and the protection of the environment. There may be other issues which other advocates could put forward. I do not see this as comprehensive but these are changes we feel the DTO would be interested in seeing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_116">That is what I understood from the submissions but it would be helpful if the delegation made a further submission outlining precisely the changes it would like. The Constitution is very succinct and that would be helpful.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnnOrmonde" eId="spk_67">
          <from>Senator Ormonde</from>
          <p eId="para_117">I welcome the deputation. The pendulum is swinging between the right to private property and the common good. The more I think of this the more confused I am. I do not know at this point what side I will come down on but there will have to be changes. I find it very difficult to accept that one evening one has agricultural land and the next evening one is a millionaire. I have difficulties with that and if the Constitution could handle that I would certainly go down that route.</p>
          <p eId="para_118">Regarding compensation and acquiring land at existing values, I do not know how that is possible. There were so many schools of thought on this issue, yesterday and today, that this will be a huge hurdle. I would welcome an amendment to the Constitution to give many people, not the few, the benefits of the boom. That is why I am anxious for a constitutional amendment, but I do not know if it will be possible to get a wording that will encompass what we have discussed today and yesterday. Delegations have had different views on whether a constitutional amendment or legislation should be pursued. There is a huge amount of work to be done but I appreciate this presentation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_119">Over the next few days we will get other views but that is a matter for the committee to decide.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_69">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_120">I thank Mr. Henry and Mr. Muldowney, whose delegation is one of the few to deal with the substance of what we are discussing here rather than peripheral legal matters though they may be germane to the argument. I want to focus on Deputy Devins's point about wording. It would be helpful if the delegation produced a wording, as in this and other areas where we are confronted by a universal wish for what is to be achieved, putting that into words is very difficult and fraught. We saw that in the example I quoted where there was a totally unintended side effect. People who wanted to achieve one thing ended up achieving something completely different. Producing a wording would be valuable to us.</p>
          <p eId="para_121">Regarding the existing use value of land and establishing that as a baseline, does the delegation accept that there are plenty of circumstances where development, particularly in infrastructure, has a negative effect on the value of land? I am thinking of agricultural land outside the greater Dublin area where a motorway goes through the land. That renders land difficult to farm, so that is another aspect of this. There would have to be compensation in that case.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_122">But it is compensated.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_123">I know it is but the inference of what Mr. Muldowney said was that apart from not enjoying the gain, one should not benefit——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_124">No, I agree. In England this is referred to as betterment and worsement, though worsement is a little maladroit.</p>
          <p eId="para_125">To take the Senator's point, severance, disturbance and injurious effection are all compensated for. A person should not lose if a road runs through their land and severs their farm if they receive compensation for severance. Injurious effections relates to the injurious effect it has on the business and disturbance relates to any disturbance such as moving hay sheds, house or whatever and you are compensated for that as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_126">I am speaking from personal experience. On the hoarding of land and a tax which would encourage the release of the land, one could argue that if the tax is imposed it will be ultimately reflected in the sale price of the land. In other words, it will not be the person who is paying the tax who will suffer the loss, it will be the person who is buying the house who will ultimately pay the price. How would Mr. Muldowney respond to the proposition "use it or lose it" and are there constitutional implications in this regard, in other words, that the local authority should dezone the land if it is not used?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_127">I think one can now dezone. Under the Planning Act 2000, one can dezone without compensation, but one must pay the compensation for any attendant works that might have been done. I agree with the "use it or lose it" philosophy but I have not studied in detail how it could be copperfastened or nailed down in legislation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_75">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_128">You do not believe there is a constitutional implication?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_129">I do not think so. I believe, however, that if the Constitution were changed in the manner I outlined, I would have a greater level of certainty that such legislation could be introduced without the risk of being constitutionally fragile.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_130">Do Mr. Muldowney believe that the 19th century compensation rules we have inherited are appropriate to the 21st century?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_131">They could probably do with some tweaking, particularly rule 2, which talks about the open market value. Rule 2, under the 1919 Act, is the most controversial. This could be tweaked to allow for acquisition at existing market value. The Kenny report addresses this aspect. I agree generally, not fully, with the provisions in the Kenny report in terms of the adjustment to rule 2. I am saying that rule 2 could be amended to allow for acquisition at less than market value.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_79">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_132">Does you feel the compulsory purchase mechanism is cumbersome and slow or is it efficient from the point of view of Dublin transportation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_133">The CPO provisions are currently being reviewed in England - I have been following this closely. The feeling there is that because of the high prices that must be paid, local authorities and other State bodies are reluctant to use them. The process is also somewhat cumbersome. The combination of these two aspects has led to a thrust to change the legislation in England and we are waiting for a Green Paper on this. The compulsory procedures could be changed and perhaps brought more into line with 2003 thinking rather than 1919. However, any changes one might wish to make in terms of the price paid for the acquisition of land would be better buttressed by a change in the Constitution.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_134">That is an interesting point. Someone else mentioned the situation which is currently evolving in England. Perhaps we should consider what is happening in Spain, Portugal and other European countries. England might not be the best example.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_135">I have looked at systems in these countries.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Deputy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_136">I support other members who requested the consideration of specific wording to encompass the three points made, even though perhaps there is a duty on us as a committee to do that.</p>
          <p eId="para_137">Mr. Muldowney suggested that it would be better to buttress these changes within the Constitution. Given what he said about the drafting of legislation, does he think this is often unnecessarily conservative and careful because of fear of constitutional challenge? The experience of the Opposition when dealing with legislation is that the Constitution is often thrown at us as the reason something cannot be done or an amendment cannot be incorporated. Does this aspect partly colour Mr. Muldowney's view that we should amend the Constitution?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_138">I certainly would not disagree with that point. In fact, I am dealing with aspects of section 49 of the contribution scheme in which some provisions have been included. Sections 48 and 49, which are inter-related, are very complicated sections to deal with. Effectively, to accommodate the antecedent status of property rights, some provisions have been included which are highly ambiguous and almost meaningless to some extent when one tries to analyse them and apply them in the field, so to speak. I can see that the intention was to protect existing property rights but it almost went overboard to do so. This has probably resulted in a great deal of uncertainty in the section which in future could lead to a constitutional challenge.</p>
          <p eId="para_139">The Constitution to some extent reflects a fundamental set of values that existed at the time it was drafted. As members know, a constitution is not set in stone. It evolves with society to some extent. We have a written constitution and the British do not. Ours must be changed, whereas they have parliamentary sovereignty. The Constitution can be changed as society changes? Property rights have not been revisited in the Constitution since the initial drafting. Many of these issues have been thrashed out previously, in the 1985 review of the committee on building land, the Kenny report and the various seminal Supreme Court cases on constitutional issues in relation to property rights, whether on the use of land bonds for compensation or rent restrictions. These examinations illustrate the uncertainty which exist since the Constitution was introduced. The committee is in a unique position to introduce more certainty, which can only be of benefit.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DanNeville" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Deputy Neville</from>
          <p eId="para_140">Could I put it to Mr. Muldowney that it is a failure of the Legislature to test the Constitution, if it had the will to make the changes? Some of the issues raised could have been dealt with under the present Constitution but the Legislature is not doing so. Therefore, it is our fault that we have not enacted laws to achieve many of the changes raised.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_141">The Deputy has made a reasonable point. I am saying that the changes will introduce greater certainty. The last time the Legislature tried to rebalance the balance between private property and the common good was in relation to Part V and the President saw fit to refer Part V to the Supreme Court to test its constitutionality.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DanNeville" eId="spk_87">
          <from>Deputy Neville</from>
          <p eId="para_142">Does Mr. Muldowney think his proposals will be carried by the people?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_143">That is a political question. I defer to the Deputy's expertise.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_89">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_144">I listened earlier to questions put by other members. Mr. Muldowney down played the significance of the decision of the Supreme Court under the Planning Act 2000 - perhaps down played are the wrong words. Does Mr.Muldowney envisage that this particular area will be revisited? Other submissions made the point that this was a landmark decision.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_145">Obviously I did not explain myself very well. I echo the sentiment that this was a landmark decision in so far as it stated that planning permission represented an enlargement or enhancement of one's property rights. Even though it did not state it explicitly, it referred to another American case, stating that it was conferred by the community. In other words, prior to the Supreme Court decision, the previous position of most eminent lawyers was that one had a right to develop one's land subject to the law of tort, which includes nuisance and so on, and the planning Acts. The planning Acts were just an infringement of one's fundamental prima facie right to develop one's land.</p>
          <p eId="para_146">The Supreme Court has ruled that a planning permission is an enhancement of one's rights. The corollary of that is that if it is an enhancement of one's rights which is conferred by the community, then surely the community is entitled to some percentage to be recycled back into infrastructural projects and other projects which effectively enhance these rights?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_91">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_147">Are you saying that may not go far enough and that a better balance in the Constitution is also required?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_92">
          <from>Mr. Muldowney</from>
          <p eId="para_148">Yes. If one reads Mr. Justice Keane's judgment in detail, it states that there must be a prima facie assumption that, generally speaking, compensation should be made at full market value. He was making an exception more or less for Part V. If the Constitution is not amended, any of these issues that needs to be addressed through legislation will consistently be tested. Those who promote and draft the legislation will be forced to watch over their shoulder for the potential nemesis which will undo their best plans.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">Sitting suspended at 12.10 p.m. and resumed at 12.15 p.m.</summary>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_93">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_149">The next item on the agenda is the presentation by the Irish Senior Citizens' Parliament, represented by Mr. Michael O'Halloran, Ms Sylvia Meehan and Mrs. Ina Broughan. I welcome the delegates to this meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_150">I remind visitors that members of this committee have absolute privilege but the same privilege does not apply to witnesses appearing before the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_151">I invite the delegation to make your submission and to confine your remarks to six to eight minutes. The committee has already received a written submission from the delegation which has been studied by the members. I suggest that the delegation delivers a synopsised version of the written submission and members may then wish to ask questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_94">
          <from>Mr. Michael O’Halloran</from>
          <p eId="para_152">I wish to formally introduce Ms Sylvia Meehan, president of the Senior Citizens' Parliament and Ms Ina Brougan, treasurer.</p>
          <p eId="para_153">We are an organisation of older people with 90,000 members. We tried to calculate that in terms of quotas but we have given up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_95">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_154">We can do that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_96">
          <from>Mr. O’Halloran</from>
          <p eId="para_155">We are a big organisation. Like all voluntary organisations, we have big aspirations and limited resources. We would like to have made a more detailed submission to the committee on this important issue. We are speaking not just for ourselves as older people but for our children and grandchildren who have suffered greatly because of the failure of our community through its legislators and its own failure to deal with these issues. We have failed young people in the sense that housing has become almost impossible for low income families and even for middle income families.</p>
          <p eId="para_156">I will give an example to put this into its human context. I started off as a baker and I worked in a bakery. There was hardly anyone in that bakery who was not able to afford a house. They struggled to save the deposit and they had high interest repayments but they could pay for a house. Today, people in a similar job and with both people in a couple working, could not afford a similar house for their family. Despite the great cycle of economic development which we older people welcome, because we and our children and grandchildren have been the beneficiaries, we have taken our eyes off the ball with regard to land. We need to turn our attention to that question and find a solution in the context of the Constitution and in how legislation is passed in the Dáil.</p>
          <p eId="para_157">This question has exercised the minds of men and women for a long time. There have been both micro and macro experiments in trying to deal with it. One of the micro-experiments was carried out by an Irishman, William Thompson of Cork. It was an interesting co-operative idea. He went broke and the experiment did not come to fruition. Robert Owen, the Utopian socialist in Wales, did the same thing. They were important people who thought about the organisation of society. The other people who tried to come to grips with this issue were the socialists. Karl Marx spent years in the British Museum and not months in a committee, working on his volumes of Das Kapital. We are all aware that the philosophy failed. The Catholic Church had the most radical views of all on the subject of property. It is amazing that it is not preached from pulpits except on very rare occasions. I recommend that the committee members read the Veritas publication, <i>Catechism of the Catholic Church</i>, part three, section two, page 513. It sets out the purpose of property. It does not use words such as “nationalisation” or “adequate compensation”. In some cases, it talks about the appropriation of property for the common good.</p>
          <p eId="para_158">There is a balance to be found between individual rights and the rights of a community. As a community, we need to reflect on this issue and to ask ourselves whether the Constitution that has served us well in many ways but was amended in the light of social and economic development, could now be an obstacle to further social development. As older people, we must not be afraid of the future and we must not be afraid of change. If we are to have a legal system that recognises and identifies the importance of social rights as against individual property rights, then we must have the courage to attempt to have a Constitution that facilitates this rather than forming an obstacle.</p>
          <p eId="para_159">I listened to the previous presentation. It is true that the Oireachtas must have courage and introduce legislation but it should not be the case where legislation could be challenged as being unconstitutional. The great thing about our Constitution is that it is the people's legislation and not the Dáil's or the Seanad's and this is what it must be seen as. The Dáil can and does facilitate the amendments to the Constitution as necessary through enacting the legislation to have the amendment, but the people enact it. The people will have to be given an opportunity of setting out values in relation to property rights and duties. That can only be done through referendum. However, I recognise as has been said by members of this committee that the framing of such an amendment to the Constitution will prove difficult but not necessarily impossible.</p>
          <p eId="para_160">If it can be achieved, we want to see serious consideration given to the type of legislation we now need in the housing area. There have been many attempts in the past to deal with this and I am thinking particularly of British ones. I believe the 1967 commission on land went as far as wanting to get rid of zoning completely. Members may ask what it would mean to get rid of zoning. It would mean pockets of land could not be held by a small number of people looking for enhanced value over the original owners. They wanted land to become more available for development purposes and the only criterion would be the grant of planning permission based on very strict planning criteria. The reason we have our tribunals is that not enough land was zoned. If enough land had been zoned there would have been no need for people to influence the outcome of political decisions. I say that simply by the way.</p>
          <p eId="para_161">The members of the committee have our submission setting out some of the areas we would like to see tackled by the legislators and not by the Constitution. The Constitution is only a facilitating law. We want to see the State more involved in creating land banks. We believe it is a stroke of the pen in granting planning permission by the local authority that enhances the value of the land and not somebody putting a spade in the ground. It is outrageous - I hope that is privileged in using that word - when a site today can cost more than it costs to build the house. When the architect, building contractor and the workers get less reward for their efforts than the owner of the site, there is something terribly wrong in that system and it has to be tackled in many different ways.</p>
          <p eId="para_162">The Constitution is a wonderful document. Probably the best part of it is the part about which one cannot go to the courts. I do not know whether the committee has been looking at this. Article 45 deals with the principles of social policy. These are directive principles and it is not possible to go to the courts to enforce them. We know who the architects of the Constitution were. They recognised there was a need for State intervention to protect the common good. Article 45.2.3° states that the State shall, in particular, direct its policy towards securing:</p>
          <p eId="para_163">That, especially, the operation of free competition shall not be allowed so to develop as to result in the concentration of the ownership or control of essential commodities in a few individuals to the common detriment.</p>
          <p eId="para_164">That was their aspiration. That is guidance to the Oireachtas. Unfortunately we cannot go to court on that and I wish we could. That is what I would like to see more solidly in our Constitution. However, it is there as policy guidance to the Oireachtas and is kept out of the courts. Even this problem of the concentration of ownership to the detriment of the common good was recognised by the original framers and architects of the Constitution. Unfortunately, as with many things in Ireland, we get to things late and out of breath. I hope the committee will get to this one and do something about it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_97">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_165">I note your view that the Constitution should be changed. At the outset I compliment you. I have great admiration for the enthusiasm of people such as you who still have a great interest in not alone your generation, but subsequent ones. This has been a very welcome intervention and you have made some very valid points.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrendanDaly" eId="spk_98">
          <from>Senator Daly</from>
          <p eId="para_166">I welcome the delegation. Mr. O'Halloran mentioned the duty of property and the need to change the Constitution. How would he define such a constitutional amendment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Mr. O’Halloran</from>
          <p eId="para_167">It is very interesting. The Constitution may not be as bad as we think. With all due respect, our problem may have been judge made law. Three groups enact law in our country. The Oireachtas can be considered as a combined House of the Seanad and the Dáil. If something is tested in the courts, the courts may interpret that law in a way that was never intended by the Oireachtas and hand down a new law. This happened in a famous case concerning a midwife in Limerick. When she lost her job with a health board she went to court to seek remedy. Her dismissal was held to be legal because the judge said that while the Oireachtas might have intended one thing, that was not what it did. He interpreted it and handed down a new definition of dismissal for redundancy. This was later put right by Mr. Brennan, a Minister from County Donegal. We have the problem that not only is there law but there are also interpretations of law.</p>
          <p eId="para_168">Our Constitution not only talks about the right to property; it also talks about the duties a great deal. In the sub-sections there is a lot about duty. The problem is that when one goes to court, the right of property seems to take precedence over its duties. I am not a constitutional expert and I do not claim to be an expert in anything. As my grandfather said "experts on tap are never on top", which is also an important consideration.</p>
          <p eId="para_169">However, we have to say what we want out of property. The first thing we want is good and adequate compensation for property owners, who are not speculators. I will give an example, if I may. Matthew Macken was the city manager here at one time. He was a tough man and was tough on councillors. I became a councillor the year after he retired. I was rather glad I came then and not before as he was a very tough man. He made a statement at the city council one night that was incorporated into the evidence given to the Kenny commission on land prices.</p>
          <p eId="para_170">When he left his office to look for land in north County Dublin or south County Dublin for housing purposes, he was followed by agents who parked outside his office waiting for him to make a move. If they thought he was interested in certain aspects of land they then moved in and bought it in advance of the corporation. The corporation could not acquire the land until it was rezoned at which time a compulsory purchase order was made. The compulsory purchase order always took into account market prices. The man or woman who sold the land originally might have got a good price for it, but nothing like what the speculator got. There are a lot of things happening there.</p>
          <p eId="para_171">As was said earlier, maybe legislation is the way forward. The problem is if the legislation is to be hampered by a narrow definition of the right of property with no emphasis on duties, that has to be strengthened. I heard the Chairman state we might study Spain and Portugal. If possible the committee should also look at the Japanese and German systems of land use. There the emphasis is totally different.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_100">
          <from>Deputy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_172">I welcome the delegation. Would I be right in interpreting Mr. O'Halloran as saying he wants more of an emphasis on the common good as opposed to the rights to private property? While there is already a proviso in the Constitution that the right to property is tempered by the common good, Mr. O'Halloran wants more of a swing in favour of the common good.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_101">
          <from>Mr. O’Halloran</from>
          <p eId="para_173">It is a very simple reason.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Deputy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_174">I know Mr. O'Halloran heard some of the discussion with members of the previous group who suggested specific areas that should be clarified in the Constitution as being qualifiers of the right to private property. They did not mention the right to housing, but mentioned sustainable land use, transportation, planning and protection of the environment. Is Mr. O'Halloran suggesting that other rights, such as housing, should be added? His submission indicates a particular interest in that area. In relation to the land bank issue, I fully support his suggestion that it should be possible for local authorities to establish land banks for good social purposes. Does he feel that can be done, under the Constitution without a requirement to pay substantial compensation to owners of land or does he consider that the Constitution needs to be changed in order to incorporate his proposals with regard to a land bank?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_103">
          <from>Mr. O’Halloran</from>
          <p eId="para_175">One has to be careful, even if given the freedom to write our Constitution - one cannot write everything into a constitution. A constitution has to be a protector of rights and an exponent of duties. It has to be so worded that it is not an obstacle to legislators doing what they have to do, not just today or tomorrow but over a long period. It is a matter of determining the right time to create land banks, which should be by majority vote in the Dáil, where the matter will go through various stages of refinement and lobbying by interest groups, resulting in the emergence of a package designed to achieve social good for the greater number. That is how the Catholic catechism describes the purpose of property - to do the greatest good for the greatest number, not just for the few. That process results in very detailed legislation.</p>
          <p eId="para_176">All one can do in a constitution is to provide certain guarantees for people. The original property owners would also have rights - I recognise that. My concern relates to the use of property rights to circumvent or, as it were, laugh in the face of society which is trying to provide the very basic requirement of shelter. That is very fundamental to human needs in any political system, regardless of one's ideology, in terms of decent human values. While there may be ideological arguments in terms of the political left, right or centre, there should be no argument as to people's fundamental rights. The right to shelter is as important as the right to property, but it is not recognised as such.</p>
          <p eId="para_177">I recognise the great difficulty of getting our Constitution right in that regard by removing the barrier to action by the Oireachtas, if it so wishes. In practice, it may never do so - that is not for me to say. However, it should not be hampered by the prospect of legislation being struck down by the Supreme Court, despite agonising hours of debate by the elected representatives of the people. We are also the servants of the people, albeit in a different way. Politics is a most noble calling which is liable to fall into grave disrepute, perhaps because of individual behaviour. The legislative process must be allowed to continue, unhampered by a constitution which prevents innovation.</p>
          <p eId="para_178">The people, in their sovereign capacity, should be asked once again to make their judgment on what is needed for the future. If they reject a proposal for change, so be it. If they accept it, thereby facilitating the Houses of the Oireachtas in doing better work for our communities, that would be a great accomplishment. That is simply our view of the matter; we do not claim to be experts.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_179">I welcome the delegation and compliment its presentation. I have three questions. First, what is the Senior Citizens' Parliament and whom does it represent? How does it relate to the Active Retirement Association?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_105">
          <from>Mr. O’Halloran</from>
          <p eId="para_180">I will deal with that in my reply to questions. I assume the Deputy is not suggesting its inclusion in the Constitution.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_181">I will move on to my second question. I note that Mr. O'Halloran quoted from the Catholic catechism. In yesterday's presentation by CORI, there was a suggestion that all lands should be purchased by the relevant local authority and the zoning should follow on accordingly. Third, I refer Mr. O'Halloran again to Senator Daly's question with regard to the specific duties of property. I find that a very interesting concept - perhaps Mr. O'Halloran will explain in more detail whether he defines duties as attaching to property, the individual or the common good.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_107">
          <from>Mr. O’Halloran</from>
          <p eId="para_182">I will try to do that very briefly, although, as a former politician, I have been noted for long winded speeches. The Irish Senior Citizens' Parliament is a democratic organisation which has 300 affiliated organisations, including the Active Retirement Association to which the Deputy referred. Our smaller organisations have the same status as the bigger ones. An organisation with 10,000 members has three votes in our parliament, the same as smaller organisations. That is designed to avoid disenfranchising any group - we do not wish to allow big groups to dominate. We like people to feel that, in joining us, they are truly respected and their views are as important as any others.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_108">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_183">Is the organisation somewhat like the United States Senate?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_109">
          <from>Mr. O’Halloran</from>
          <p eId="para_184">It is a little bit like that - not quite as powerful, but we are working on it. In our organisation, we have people from urban and rural areas. Our membership includes retired farmers, former business people, PROBIS clubs, the ICTU retired workers committee and SIPTU. We are a rather universal group in the sense of representing the whole community. We are non-party political, although we are very political in pursuing our objectives and issues with all political parties.</p>
          <p eId="para_185">In relation to the point raised by CORI with regard to local authorities, I regard that as an issue for the Dáil rather than a constitutional matter. However, if the Dáil regarded that as the way forward, the approach should be on the basis of facilitating appropriate constitutional change. I am not familiar with all the mechanisms involved; they should be debated and evaluated. We would favour the creation of new towns, with the necessary transport infrastructure and industrial development.</p>
          <p eId="para_186">The last question deals with the duties of property. As I understand it, property has many duties which I will deal with to the best of my ability - I can only analyse it by reference to the Catholic catechism. One of the mirror situations in life is that for every right there is a duty; that is a simple philosophical truth. Man should regard the external goods he legitimately owns not merely as exclusive to himself but common to others also in the sense that they can benefit others as well as himself. The ownership of any property makes its holder a steward of provenance, with the task of making it fruitful and communicating its benefits to others, first to his own family. In other words, one has a duty to oneself and others. For example, it would be totally unacceptable to society that a vital service such as the blood bank should be a private monopoly rather than a State service.</p>
          <p eId="para_187">Duties arise from the needs of other people. To understand those duties, one has to understand what land can do to enhance the needs of other people if it is available at a reasonable price - by which I do not mean an uneconomic price. We cannot have a law which would exploit farmers, for example; that would be socially unjust. Social justice must be for everybody, not just certain sections. In buying land, it would be our duty to ensure that there was adequate and fair compensation, based on appropriate criteria. If other people bought and retained the land to enhance its value through rezoning or the granting of planning permission, the duty to the rest of us - to make the land available at a reasonable price - could not be realised. I would like to reflect further on this important question before sending a further submission to the committee, giving details on the issue of duties. It is not true that I should have been better prepared for this meeting, as I was prepared for it. A great deal of work has been done in this area. Case studies in various countries have examined the different approaches. It will take me a few weeks to compile another submission but I would like to do so in response to the question I have been asked.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnnOrmonde" eId="spk_110">
          <from>Senator Ormonde</from>
          <p eId="para_188">I welcome the deputation. I was about to ask the same question. One could have a full school of thought on the terminology of duties, which also relates to responsibilities, community development and whether this area should be covered in the Constitution. As it is such a wide subject, I do not know if one could incorporate a definition of duties in the Constitution. That is my concern.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_111">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_189">Mr. O'Halloran has answered that question, in so far as he has said that he will make a further submission. I thank the delegation for contributing to this interesting debate. Mr. O'Halloran's partners were silent, but they are more than welcome. His point about the loss to society of the philosophy of the penny catechism is a very interesting one.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">Sitting suspended at 12.45 p.m. and resumed at 2.00 p.m.</summary>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_112">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_190">Representatives of Cunnane, Stratton, Reynolds, town planners, are here to make an oral submission. We have already been provided with a written submission. Mr. John Creane is very welcome. Before we begin, I remind visitors that members of this committee have absolute privilege but this same privilege does not apply to witnesses appearing before the committee. I take this opportunity to remind members returning from lunch to switch off their mobile phones if they have not already done so. I will allow Mr. Creane five or six minutes to elaborate on his submission after which time there will be questions from members. It would be helpful if Mr. Creane could synopsise rather than read over the written submission which we have all studied.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_113">
          <from>Mr. John Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_191">I thank the committee for the opportunity to make this submission. We have been retained by Colm Gaynor, the solicitor who has acted for a number of landowners and people with land interests who would like to see those lands developed but have been presented with problems in doing so. Mr. Gaynor asked us to look at this issue in the context of suggestions in the media that legal measures may be introduced to encourage the development of lands. It is important to inform the committee that there are practical issues to consider in terms of the development of land and that measures exist in legislation to facilitate that development which do not necessarily require amendments to the Constitution.</p>
          <p eId="para_192">Public infrastructure is required to facilitate development of land. Much land can only be developed with the provision of temporary infrastructure by the developer or permanent infrastructure by the local authority. Such infrastructure can be services, roads or access. There are many measures in the planning and development system as it stands which could be used more effectively to encourage developers to release lands for development once they have been zoned. For example, section 10(8) of the Planning and Development Act 2000 allows for the dezoning of lands without compensation. Section 15 of the Act obliges the county manager in all local authorities to review the performance of a development plan within two years of its adoption. This provision could be used as a means to advise developers whose lands have not come forward for development whether such lands will be dezoned at a further development plan review. Part VIII of the Planning and Development Regulations 2001 has been used by certain local authorities to facilitate development of lands where they have had problems with third party appeals.</p>
          <p eId="para_193">There are practical issues in the zoning and development process which it is important to identify. While there may be an appearance that lands are being withheld from development, it is often the case that local authorities zone lands in excess of what is required under a development plan or by projected population change. In the context of housing, it is not unusual to zone two or two and a half times the volume of land needed to provide for future population growth on the basis that some lands will not be developed. We have made such provision in development plans we have prepared for local authorities. Some lands which are zoned for development may be difficult and expensive to service or may only be capable of development on the provision of appropriate infrastructure. Very often, such provision is outside the control of landowners.</p>
          <p eId="para_194">Similarly, in terms of the development process, we had a concern, in that, we have had occasion to act for many people and an application can be in the planning process for an extensive period of time. An application may continue for up to three years before you can get a decision from the planning process. There are opportunities for public consultation and objections at the initial stages through to the appeals stage with An Bord Pleanála and subsequently, in very rare cases, with judicial reviews to the courts. As a result many developers spent years in pre-planning consultation and in the planning process itself. Ultimately they have a planning permission which is not to their liking or changes need to be made to it and consequently they seek further modifying permissions.</p>
          <p eId="para_195">There are a number of measures in the development system at the moment to try to encourage the development of land be they compulsory purchase orders, section 15 of the Planning and Development Act or even Part VIII of the planning regulations. Local authorities are also constrained by a lack of bodies on the ground, so to speak, to facilitate development and to allow more than just a development control process to be carried out on an effective basis within local authorities. That is a summary of what I have to say. I will be happy to answer any questions the committee may have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_114">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_196">I wish to clarify one point. Mr. Creane said he is acting on behalf of Cunnane, Stratton, Reynolds and Company; are they also landowners and developers?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_115">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_197">No, not that I am aware anyway.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_116">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_198">They are representing clients.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_117">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_199">They have a number of clients but, in any case, we would make the same comments because we act for a range of developers; private individuals with small sites, larger developers, community bodies and local authorities. We have had experience of the development process from both sides. We have tried to get applications through the planning system and we have also prepared development plans for local authorities.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_118">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_200">Most committee members have experience of local authority frustration. Mr. Creane said in his conclusion that the development of land will often require the provision of infrastructure by local authorities. Some of the submissions made to us advocated, somewhat along the lines of the Kenny report, that local authorities should be proactive in terms of acquiring tracts of land ahead of developers and speculators. They are in a position to see how towns or cities are expanding. Is there a case for more levies to be imposed on those who benefit substantially from the zoning of land? The DTO, which made a submission to the committee this morning, is encountering difficulties.</p>
          <p eId="para_201">Another group made the point that the taxpayer, through local authority funding from central Government, is ultimately giving added value to properties in certain areas through the provision of infrastructure, be it sewerage connections or transport links such as roads, Luas or a metro line. Can Mr. Creane suggest a way in which there could be some clawback to the taxpayer or to the local authority for the sake of the common good and social justice?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_119">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_202">I will first address the point about the local authorities being more proactive. Local authorities should be encouraged to be more proactive and they should be given the finance to acquire more lands. I would be concerned, however, that they may buy land that is not necessarily in the best location for development as they may not be in a position to compete financially for the best development land. This reminds me of a comment I heard from CORI that further land should be rezoned to try and facilitate the development of new properties for people. While I accept that land can be rezoned to facilitate development or that local authorities may purchase land, they should be conscious of good planning practice. We want to avoid the development of a new Tallaght by developing lands where the infrastructure may be separate from the transportation routes, sewerage, water or sanitary services or even schools. That lesson has been well learned in Ireland.</p>
          <p eId="para_203">In terms of levies on individuals who have benefited from the rezoning of lands, I agree that there is a windfall issue which needs to be addressed. In terms of the provision of infrastructure there is currently a section 48 development contribution scheme in the Planning and Development Act where local authorities have the right to charge development levies on the basis of the quantum of development that takes place on lands to pay for the public infrastructure that is put in place to service these developments. I do not really have a position on whether developers should be taxed or levied for having their lands rezoned principally because, as I set out in the submission, there are many ways in which lands can be rezoned. Individuals can have their lands rezoned against their will. For instance, they might be rezoned for residential purposes but the landowner might want to continue agricultural use. Individuals might have their lands rezoned by third parties who make observations on the public display of a development plan. I would be concerned about such a provision because it might put an unnecessary obligation on a private individual to either sell their land, develop it or pay a levy on lands that have been rezoned which may not have been at his or her behest.</p>
          <p eId="para_204">It also raises other minor issues such as whether you impose levies on people for not developing a garden area with development potential attached to a house. Under new planning Acts most local authorities are moving away from the system of having white lands and are trying to zone all lands for development. You may have an anomalous situation occurring in that instance where you might have lands zoned for residential use with the potential for the development of a second or third house on the basis of planning permissions already granted in the area. Are people to be liable for a windfall tax on the basis of the potential even if they have not developed their lands? Will people who have been levied get their money back if their land has been rezoned but they cannot get planning permission? This may result in a local authority being liable for compensation. It is a good idea which can work in certain circumstances, such as with greenfield sites on the edge of a town. On balance, it raises a lot of issues in my mind.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_120">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_205">Can I take it from Mr. Creane's submission that he is not advocating constitutional change on behalf of his clients?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_121">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_206">Generally, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnnOrmonde" eId="spk_122">
          <from>Senator Ormonde</from>
          <p eId="para_207">I thank Mr. Creane for his presentation to which I listened carefully. As the Chairman pointed out, it appears that Mr. Creane supports legislation rather than constitutional amendment. He also seems to think that landowners will have to make improvements to local services and infrastructure in order to get planning permission. Local action plans are continuously being revised within county development plans and I do not have any difficulty with the onus being on a developer to provide the necessary infrastructure on the basis that the land has been rezoned from agricultural use. Mr. Creane suggested that the developer may not be able to afford to do this but I do not understand his thinking in that regard. Most developers can afford to do what is required. Legislation could be used to address these issues rather than amending the Constitution. We have to take into account the balance between the two; the right to private property and also the right of the common good for those who cannot acquire a house. There is a great responsibility on the developer to make the system work. There needs to be a commitment to the community in which the developer operates. I would like to hear Mr.Creane's views on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_123">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_208">I wish to clarify a point raised by the Chairman. Is Mr. Creane representing Colm Gaynor and Company, or is he representing his own firm?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_124">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_209">Colm Gaynor and Company.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_125">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_210">If land is zoned and is not developed within the timescale of the development plan, does the landowner suffer a penalty?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_211">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_127">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_212">Are you arguing that you are against the imposition of levies on such a landowner?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_128">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_213">There is a perception that lands are not developed because people are hoarding them so their value will increase, which is fair enough. I am sure certain individuals choose to do so, but many developers I know have paid money for lands and want to have them developed as fast as possible. However, they have difficulties getting through the planning process, whether it is because the necessary public infrastructure is not in place or they have to negotiate land deals with third parties to try obtain access to their lands or access to main roads. The development is premature pending the provision of roads or infrastructural services. It is particularly challenging to get through the planning process and very often one could spend two to three years trying to process an application for a sizeable development.</p>
          <p eId="para_214">There are many applications for the development of large sites. The committee is probably very interested in what happens to large land banks, whether they are developed or how they are developed. I discovered that most local authorities do not approve of planning applications for large developments or land banks where they have not had a substantial degree of pre-planning consultation before the application is lodged. Very often it can be very difficult to engage in pre-planning consultation and hold meetings with local authorities. Therefore, there are many practical difficulties in the development of lands and I would question the value of penalising people for not developing the lands when the reasons for the failure to do so are outside their control.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_129">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_215">Following on from that, does Mr. Creane believe land is being hoarded, particularly in the larger cities?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_130">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_216">The potential exists but I do not know of any lands being hoarded. All the evidence seems to be anecdotal and I do not know of any studies that state that lands are being hoarded by particular developers.</p>
          <p eId="para_217">In Wicklow, for example, where one might encounter a landowner with 60 or 70 acres around a particular town, one would want to have those lands developed. Very often one would try to control the development of the lands rather than have them developed on a piecemeal basis. Because such lands are all under one person's control it is desirable that they be developed on an integrated basis. In cases like this, it works very well. One tries to work with the landowner, who wants to try get the lands developed. Ultimately, the process hinges on the availability of services to facilitate the development of those lands. It can often be very expensive and challenging to develop large parcels of land of, say, 70 to 90 acres in one go.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_131">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_218">Would the solution not be for the local authority, whether it be in Wicklow, Cork or Kerry, to buy the lands and, when required, either provide service sites or sell them off as required? It would have no axe to grind and would exist as an honest broker. Some groups have advocated this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_132">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_219">The local authorities would still have to provide the services.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_133">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_220">They generally do in any case.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_134">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_221">I accept that, but developers may not be willing to take on lands if they are not convinced the services are already in place to provide for development.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_135">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_222">In west Cork, the county manager has bought about €50 million worth of land around towns and villages. In my town of Bantry he bought about 60 acres. Most of these lands may not be built on but may be sold off for service sites. They may be sold to a local builder who might want to build 40 houses. Development would be mixed. The local authority would ensure that water and sewerage services are established in tandem with the development. That is an interesting point. Obviously this is more difficult to achieve in Dublin where one would not have the same——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_136">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_223">Obviously that issue would arise.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_137">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_224">I thank Mr. Creane. From his professional experience, does he know the typical timescale that would apply to a 100 to 200 house development from when the developer decides he will make an application to when the first houses are sold after being built?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_138">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_225">Without any problems?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_139">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_226">Take both ends of the spectrum. Let us assume that the development has to be considered by An Bord Pleanála and does not stop with the county council.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_140">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_227">If this occurs, one could frequently spend six months in pre-planning and design. If is a very large, complex scheme, especially if it triggers the need for an environmental impact statement. Assuming that the planning on the site is clean and that there are no access, service or infrastructural problems to be addressed, it could take considerable time. Once one enters the planning process, despite the changes in the Act, one could be involved for a lengthy period and might have to wait two months for a decision, which could be a decision asking for further information. One could have to prepare a response to this request for further information which could take another two months to prepare. The council might have to make its decision within two months if an environmental impact statement is required. Even on that basis, it could take at least six months for the local authority to deal with the application. Even within that six months, other scenarios could arise, such as the local authority requiring a material contravention procedure to process the application. This would further extend the timescale.</p>
          <p eId="para_228">Once the local authority has finished one has to wait four weeks for an appeal - either a first party or third party appeal. One might want to appeal oneself at that stage if one believes that there are conditions that will not work or are very onerous or if certain houses need to be in locations other than those proposed. If it is a first party or third party appeal one might have to wait six months before a decision is made by An Bord Pleanála, or even longer if some party requests an oral hearing. Ultimately the board might try to find a date or venue for such a hearing that suits all parties involved, which could delay the process by another couple of months - it is not specified. Even in the best of circumstances, one expects an appeal in respect of a development of 200 or 300 houses, and this could take at least a year and a half, and that is an optimistic estimate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_141">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_229">That is before a block is laid.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_142">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_230">That is before a block is laid and even before somebody might try to challenge the development in terms of judicial review, which would involve another eight weeks in addition to the decision period of An Bord Pleanála.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_143">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_231">Has Mr. Creane noticed any improvements as a result of the most recent Act?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_144">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_232">It has become more complex - extremely complex. I know the changes were introduced by the recent Act to make the planning system better for the local authorities and easier to handle but we found that there are so many ways for planning applications to be deemed invalid when lodged with the council that one is frequently at the whim of the council as to whether an application will be declared valid. If declared invalid, one might only discover this two, three or four weeks after the application has been lodged. This means that one is back at the beginning.</p>
          <p eId="para_233">I have had occasion to deal with applications which were subject to administrative problems on their being lodged, and subsequently people took judicial reviews on the basis of these problems. The new system is better because of the changes to the Act but it has not been used to its full potential in terms of trying to encourage people to develop land. In the past, we would have lodged planning applications under the old Act and if there were minor problems to be sorted or if the council required additional drawings, for example, these would have to be sent in and the council should deem this satisfactory. Then the application runs from the date on which it was lodged.</p>
          <p eId="para_234">Under the current system, if one submits an invalid application or if it has a minor problem, such as a window detail left out or minor problems with dimensions on the plans, some councils will send it back. One has to start again from the word "go" in such circumstances. While I accept the obligation on the applicant to make sure that everything is valid, it means that an extra month might be required to cross all the t's and dot all the i's to make sure there is no reason the application should be declared invalid before submitting it. Ultimately one could be scuppered in any case.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_145">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_235">Has Mr. Creane noticed differences between different local authorities in terms of how they approach the matter?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_146">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_236">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_147">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_237">A short answer to a short question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BarryAndrewsFF" eId="spk_148">
          <from>Deputy Andrews</from>
          <p eId="para_238">I welcome the delegation to the committee. My question refers to a point made on page 3 of your submission relating to the amount of land local authorities zone in their draft plans.</p>
          <p eId="para_239">Being from Dún Laoghaire-Rathdown, it breaks my heart that the local authority is zoning twice or two and a half times the area of land that is required. Dún Laoghaire-Rathdown and Cork County Councils are the only two authorities which have commenced their draft development plans under the new Act. If it is true that Dún Laoghaire-Rathdown has zoned twice or two and a half times more than is necessary, it undermines the whole process. In a city environment there is a natural conflict between the requirement for development and those who wish to preserve green areas. Perhaps Mr. Creane would comment on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_149">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_240">It is not something which is set down in law; rather it is a rule of thumb. Some local authorities opt for two times, others for two and a half times, the amount required. In general it is a way of ensuring that one has a sufficient volume of land available.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BarryAndrewsFF" eId="spk_150">
          <from>Deputy Andrews</from>
          <p eId="para_241">Does this occur mainly in urban areas?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_151">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_242">It occurs in expanding areas. The Dún Laoghaire-Rathdown development plan has gone on display with a qualifier on it stating that the authority has not zoned sufficient residential lands. I know Dún Laoghaire because I used to work there and it is a challenge because it is a constrained urban and county area. Therefore, the potential to meet one's population targets might be through higher densities rather than zoning more residential lands.</p>
          <p eId="para_243">I would not be overjoyed with zoning far in excess of the lands required for development. I know many local authorities do so. Some use a factor of one and a half times, others two times and others still two and a half times the volume of land which is necessary. However, it would not be prudent to zone the exact amount of land required for development because it may not get developed and if that is the case, one is not providing for the needs of the area. It is a balancing act.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_152">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_244">Since Mr. Creane is effectively representing developers, would it not be in his interest to have less rather than more land zoned?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_153">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_245">Yes, but I am also a planner. I would not recommend three or four times the volume of land be developed. In the past when I have had a chance to do development plans, one would recommend the phasing of development plans. One might zone for future use, but it is phased in order that it is a blind sequential test in retail planning. One provides for sites closest to the town centre to be developed first and those furthest from the town centre are developed last because they are hardest to service and provide with public amenities.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBreen" eId="spk_154">
          <from>Deputy J. Breen</from>
          <p eId="para_246">Is Mr. Creane representing one firm or a number of firms?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_155">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_247">I am representing a solicitor.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBreen" eId="spk_156">
          <from>Deputy J. Breen</from>
          <p eId="para_248">What does Mr. Creane feel about the role Dúchas and An Taisce have in planning? Do they have too much of a say?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_157">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_249">Yes, although Dúchas has an important role. However, there are certain local An Taisce bodies which cause significant problems and one is never sure whether they are objecting to an application. Some of the objections are not well written but are given a great deal of weight when an objection is received. Both organisations have an important role but they sometimes cause delays which could be sorted out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBreen" eId="spk_158">
          <from>Deputy J. Breen</from>
          <p eId="para_250">Does Mr. Creane think they have too much say? Should directly elected representatives not have more say?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_159">
          <from>Mr. Creane</from>
          <p eId="para_251">I think the system for assessing planning applications works slowly but well. Everyone gets his or her fair say. I am aware that planning applications come before members from time to time to comment on. The system works but it could be improved.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_160">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_252">I thank Mr. Creane for his contribution. We will now suspend the meeting to allow the next group to come before the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8">Sitting suspended at 2.35 p.m. and resumed at 2.38 p.m.</summary>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_161">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_253">The next item on the agenda is a presentation by Feasta, represented by Ms Emer Ó Siochrú and Mr. John Jopling.</p>
          <p eId="para_254">Before we begin I must remind visitors that members of this committee have absolute privilege which does not apply to witnesses appearing before the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_255">Although Feasta has provided a detailed submission, unfortunately due to time constraints, we can only allow you six to eight minutes to make your contribution. I would ask the representatives to synopsise their presentation rather than reading through it, and then we will then ask questions. I remind witnesses that we are a committee on the Constitution with a narrow remit dealing with property rights. Some people wanted us to expand but we are in something of a straitjacket.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_162">
          <from>Ms Emer Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_256">I represent Featsa, an Irish word which means the on-going future and comes from the poem Cill Cais: "Cad a dhéanfaimíd feasta gan adhmad, Tá deireadh na coillte ar lár". The poem was written at the time of the Gaelic lords and a change in the culture in Ireland. We feel we are at that point of change again and must make the transition into a world of sustainability. We are looking particularly at the economics of sustainability. We are a not for profit organisation set up about five years ago. Membership is open to anyone. We do not accept the current orthodoxy about the need for growth and how money matters more than anything else.</p>
          <p eId="para_257">Our presentation is obviously about private property. However, it is not really about the need to change the title or ownership of property in order to achieve common good or the benefit for future generations. Instead, it is about the need to change the nature of the ownership and title of property. It is also about redefining property ownership from a model of regarding property as a thing to a model of social relations which can be negotiated by different generations to suit the changing circumstances.</p>
          <p eId="para_258">In our submission, we have made recommendations about changes to the Constitution and have included changes to words here and there and short inclusions. An alternative, however, would be to put in an entirely new clause. What we would like to see is a clause that includes the following provisions. First, the State shall respect the distinction between natural and man made property. Natural property is that property which is God given. It is not created by man. If one does not believe in God, it pre-exists man. Man has not contributed anything to bringing it into existence. Man made property obviously uses natural property as an input, but man contributes energy, risk and investment in order to make of it his own. That property should be treated differently from property such as land, air, water, genetic codes, electromagnetic waves and so on, which are natural and part of the bounty of the earth. Second, the State shall respect the principle of common share in natural property and in value created by community investment. Common share is the community's share in all natural property. We feel there should be an element of community share in all natural property given by the earth. This is for two reasons. The first is what the representatives of CORI said: that this property is given as a gift to humanity. The other reason is that most of the value of land is created by community deed and investment. For the most part, it is not created by the individual who owns it. That element of the value of the land should be respected in the Constitution. It should be recognised that this property belongs by rights to the community. Third, the State shall respect the principle of sustainability. This extends the concept of the common good into the future to benefit future generations and to recognise humanity as part of the natural world.</p>
          <p eId="para_259">We tend to use the words "natural capital" instead of "property" but they are essentially interchangeable in the text. We do not believe that any changes in the Constitution are actually necessary. None of the legislative proposals or new programmes that we suggest requires a change in the Constitution. The common good should be defined broadly, as it was meant to be when the Constitution was written. Unfortunately, a very narrow understanding of the common good has prevailed whereas the rights of the private owner have expanded to include all possible rights pertaining to the land. We think that is unfortunate. We do not think the Constitution, when it was written, intended that. However, it might be useful, although not necessary, to change the Constitution to bring in this understanding of the common good which is broader and recognises community share. It also recognises the common good in terms of future generations, in other words, it deals with sustainability.</p>
          <p eId="para_260">It might be useful to cover the issue of housing land. From other submissions and from what I have read in the newspapers, I have found that much of the impetus for changing the Constitution arises from the problems we have with housing affordability and the need to implement good and proper planning. These problems are real and should be addressed. We advocate in our proposal that the way to recognise the common share is through an annual tax, particularly a tax on development land which would be predictable. It would be a small proportion, perhaps 5%, of the increased value of the land due to zoning and it should apply to all zoned land. That could be phased in, but those details could be left to local authorities. We see that tax going to the local authority, hypothecated for development in housing and investment in infrastructure. It would allow the local authorities to have a predictable stream of income which it could invest in sewerage, water and roads and it would bring development land onto the market.</p>
          <p eId="para_261">At the moment, the owners of land are in complete control of the housing market because they can release land as it suits them in such a manner that the price of land is kept high. This does not require a conspiracy; it is the natural effect of the market and the nature of land. An annual tax on development land would rebalance that equation in favour of the community without any other regulations or interference in the market - a simple, clean predictable tax would solve all our problems with the cost of land. The tax would be capitalised immediately into the cost of land, in other words, the price of land would drop. The surveyors explained this to the committee in detail earlier. It would also reduce the price of land by bringing more land onto the market.</p>
          <p eId="para_262">The tax would make planning far more effective because when land is zoned it will have to be developed within the five year timeframe. At the moment, far more land is zoned than is needed - in some cases, three or four times as much land is zoned as is required. That is partly to create a market, as the councillors would say, and partly to spread the benefit of zoning to as many people as possible. These are laudable sentiments. With a development land tax or a tax on zoning, some of that community benefit would go back to the community so there would be less need to zone widely in order to share benefits.</p>
          <p eId="para_263">It is not necessary to change the Constitution to do what we recommend. We are against CPOs, the Kenny report or any element of compulsion except in the case of necessary investment for infrastructure - roads, rail, etc. - and in a few other circumstances which should be outlined in great detail. If a CPO is necessary, the price paid for the land should be the existing zoned value, which would be far closer to the existing use value if we had a development land tax, in other words, it should not be based on some use that land may acquire in the future, and it should not take into account any shadow value or hope value which may have fallen on that land. Only the use for which the land is currently zoned should be taken into consideration.</p>
          <p eId="para_264">However, there should be an element of compensation for compulsion. An important right attaching to land is that of possession. CPOs and any mechanisms for compulsory acquisition of land can be an imposition on individual rights. The community's rights can be well taken care of through taxation mechanisms. This system would allow the owner to sell or develop and it would stop speculation. It would be good for developers and for builders because they would not have to hoard land. At present, very little land comes on the market so developers must buy in advance to ensure that land is in place for them to build when they are ready. That would be unnecessary with a development land tax.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_163">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_265">I must admit to some ignorance - I had not heard of Feasta before. Could Ms Ó Siochrú tell us about the organisation? Is it privately or publicly funded?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_164">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_266">Feasta is a charitable organisation which was set up about five years ago. Membership is open to anyone. We are funded by private donations for the most part, although we received a very small grant from the Government - a couple of thousand euro. Our remit is mainly educational and research based. We have done conferences on renewable energy and hope to have one on land and housing in October. We have included insertions, which I hope will be distributed later, to tell the members about that conference. Our interests are money systems, ultimately taxation measures, particularly tax shift - the development of environmental taxes, which are a tax on bads, not goods - and issues of renewable energy. We are neither left wing nor right wing; we are somewhere strange in the middle.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_165">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_267">The job we have been charged with is to look at the Constitution but this submission implies there is no need for change. Am I correct in that interpretation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_166">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_268">If we look closely at the Constitution, the common good is there, it defines the right to private property. It is a question of political will but misunderstandings have built up over time and it might be useful to insert some changes to the Constitution to clarify matters and to guide legislators.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_167">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_269">It could be argued that the Constitution recognises personal property over the common good. That is the dilemma we face. To be absolutely clear, should this be dealt with through legislation and not through a constitutional amendment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_168">
          <from>Mr. John Jopling</from>
          <p eId="para_270">We are suggesting that the job of the Constitution is to spell out the underlying principles on which the Legislature would then be bound to act. Depending on how the Constitution is interpreted, it may or may not spell out those principles clearly. We think it would be helpful to spell out those principles through the amendments we have set out on the sheet we have presented to the committee. These put in slightly different words the amendments that were spelt out by way of amendment of the particular sections. The Constitution should draw the attention of the Legislature and the people to this distinction between natural and man made capital, which is fundamental for social justicein this situation. It would help for it to bringout the principle of the common share in natural capital.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_169">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_271">I found this a most interesting and novel approach to the concept of ownership - that there is personal ownership and community ownership of the God given aspects of land. It is an idea we can consider. Amendments were suggested to Articles 40:3 and 45 of the Constitution. This is the first group to put in writing what they should be like so we will be able to look at this when we are deliberating on the presentations. The rest of the submission deals with ways to do things other than amending the Constitution. If the group has any further suggestions relevant to a constitutional amendment, it could brief us again.</p>
          <p eId="para_272">In the submission, where planning permission or zoning is granted, the value should be recouped on behalf of the community by an annual value tax on the designated permission. Would that be a reintroduction of rates on houses?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_170">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_273">The tax is not on houses, it is on land. Undeveloped land that is zoned and ripe for development which the community needs for housing imposes a cost on the community if, having provided the services such as roads, sewerage and water, the land is not developed. It is a way to recoup the cost the community puts into the infrastructure and part of the value. It is easier, more effective and fairer to take a percentage of the value created in the land rather than increasing development levies having achieved permission.</p>
          <p eId="para_274">It is not another form of rates because that tax would stop when the houses are developed. There is, however, a case for a local land tax further along and we have made the case for that. For the purpose of providing affordable land and proper planning, all that is necessary is an annual tax on zoned and ripe development land.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_171">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_275">If that is the group's interpretation, that is fine, but I read the situation differently. The value should be recouped on behalf of the community that created it by an annual site value tax on the designated permission. Is that before the houses are built?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_172">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_276">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_173">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_277">Then the community loses all rights to get anything back as soon as the houses are built; there is no further contribution to the community once the houses are built.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_174">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_278">There are many problems with development levies at present. They are levied inconsistently between counties and are almost impossible to assess. How much of the cost of the infrastructure is due to the site? How much could be recouped from future development that we do not even know will take place? We are saying that we should get the money up front for the local authority when the land is zoned and not rely on the development. There would then be no need to levy fees later, the funds are already coming in.</p>
          <p eId="para_279">A tax of 5% on all development zoned land for housing would bring in €1 billion a year to local authorities, allowing them to invest. I have interviewed local authorities recently and many of them are unwilling to invest in sewerage schemes, particularly in rural areas, when they are not sure development will take place. They have no way to make it happen at present.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_175">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_280">How would 5% on zoned land be assessed? What is it 5% of?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_176">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_281">It is 5% of the increased value of the land due to the zoning and it is easy to calculate. I am an architect but I am also a valuer and a chartered surveyor in development and planning. Working out the residual value of land and then taking that percentage is very straightforward. Whole departments in most local authorities are looking at valuation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_177">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_282">Are we talking about the market value of land? What is its base price?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_178">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_283">It would be based on market value - on what people would pay for a house, less construction costs, profits and fees. The price of land is the residual and, from that take the price of the agricultural use of land, which would be insignificant. A percentage of around 5% of that increased value should be levied. It could be phased in over two years to allow people to get their act together. There are different ways to introduce it so that people can be given fair warning because it should be allowed to impact on the price of land. The price of land will go down by the capitalised amount of that levy immediately.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_179">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_284">What happens in towns where the original farm owner has the land rezoned for residential development because of urban expansion? Where does the base value of his land come from and how is the added value worked out when the property is not yet sold? Is the land owner penalised by 5% per year as long as his land remains undeveloped?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_180">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_285">It is very easy to find out the price of agricultural land by comparing it with land in the area that is not in the shadow of development. It is easy then to work out how much land is worth once it is zoned. Any auctioneer in the local area will say that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_181">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_286">What does the group think agricultural land is worth?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_182">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_287">Agricultural land can vary between €3,000 per acre for poor land up to €10,000 per acre. Agricultural land is generally overvalued but that is the market value.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_183">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_288">The market value of any property is what it will make if offered for sale on the open market. Agricultural land in County Galway can fetch anything from €10,000 to €150,000 per acre.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_184">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_289">That is land that was previously used for agriculture and is in agricultural use now but hopes for development. It is the shadow of development value that is falling on that land. That is not the value of land in agricultural use. One would have to compare it——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_185">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_290">We could have an argument about the value of land all over Ireland, so I think——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_186">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_291">I was a valuer and I am merely pointing out the difficulties that would be involved. I am not condemning what is being proposed, merely pointing out that it would involve great difficulties.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_187">
          <from>Deputy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_292">I welcome our guests. Deputy McCormack has teased out some of the issues I was unsure about in the recommendation for an annual development site tax. Is Ms Ó Siochrú simply talking about land that has already been zoned for development?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_188">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_293">I am talking about land that is already zoned or will be zoned. As it is zoned the tax becomes due, more or less, but local authorities may decide to give two years' grace for newly zoned land. That would be up to the local authorities.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_189">
          <from>Deputy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_294">Would the money then be ringfenced specifically for social good? Would Ms Ó Siochrú see the money being used for particular purposes? The local authority I have just left, for example, does not have any land. It is a city authority circled by developing authorities so it would not gain any benefit from such a tax. Would Ms Ó Siochrú recommend that the money go specifically to the local authority and be ringfenced for particular purposes within that local authority? How would she see the levy being used?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_190">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_295">I would see it going to the local authority and contributing towards Part V and towards infrastructural provision. The Deputy made a good point about a local authority in a developed area with very little undeveloped land. That is why we go on to say in our submission that land taxes should ultimately be attached to all land on its appropriate use, as decided democratically by the councillors and the planners. That tax would more or less substitute for the Derelict Sites Act 1990, for instance, and would substitute for rates, which are an unfair tax.</p>
          <p eId="para_296">As regards rates tax initiative and investment, somebody who has put in effort and invested in a property pays quite a lot in rates unfortunately, whereas a nearby derelict, poorly developed or neglected property pays very little in rates, or nothing at all. That is not fair. We suggest at the next stage a change to the American system of a dual rate local tax. It is very similar in essence to the development land tax but it would deal with local authorities in urban areas where most of the land is developed. It would consistently apply the principle throughout, which would bring considerable revenue into that local authority.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_191">
          <from>Deputy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_297">I am interested in applying the concept of sustainability to these issues because it has not particularly been done up to now. Ms Ó Siochrú's ideas certainly merit a lot of examination. I am not sure how, in terms of the practical application of our work, we can take these ideas on board but things should be sustainability proofed, if that is the right terminology.</p>
          <p eId="para_298">I was interested also in a piece circulated about a conference, which referred to the idea of using land value levies to pay for infrastructure in London as one of the issues to be looked at. Is that an example of what Feasta is proposing in practice?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_192">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_299">Yes. We would argue for that where a major piece of infrastructure is going in. If, for instance, the people of the west want a railway, this is an excellent idea. The question has arisen as to how to pay for it, and so far the idea has not been considered of paying for it out of a land tax or levy on benefiting land owners. Every landowner at every station where that train would stop would see his land go up significantly in value.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BarryAndrewsFF" eId="spk_193">
          <from>Deputy Andrews</from>
          <p eId="para_300">Is this possible for the local authority to do?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_194">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_301">As far as I know it is possible to do that. The local authority can do it in partnership. That is how I suggest——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_195">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_302">Land could drop in value if an estate was separated by the railway or the new road.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_196">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_303">In that case the land tax would go down or even be remitted. It is a wonderful system that can deal with any eventuality. The railway could actually be paid for out of the increased value of the land. I think the owners would be happy to do so and they should be canvassed to see if that is the case.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_197">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_304">It would be very unfair to the poor farmers of the west to put a land tax on them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_198">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_305">We do not want to go into taxation as it is not within our remit. We are dealing with the Constitution.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCuffeGP" eId="spk_199">
          <from>Deputy Cuffe</from>
          <p eId="para_306">I apologise for missing the start of the presentation. Many of the issues we are discussing now were discussed in great detail earlier with the Dublin Transportation Office, which is also in favour of a site value tax. We were just discussing over here section 49 of the Planning and Development Act 2000, which allows for a levy and which is being used in Dún Laoghaire-Rathdown at the moment. The difference appears to be that the section 49 levy only kicks in once a person seeks planning permission whereas this proposal kicks in once the land has been zoned.</p>
          <p eId="para_307">Leading on from that, I ask whether this tax would substitute for stamp duty and whether it would vary depending on the actual zoning of the land. I presume that the tax stems from what the best and maximum available use of that land would be.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_200">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_308">That is the case. We would like to see a reduction in transaction taxes such as stamp duty because they inhibit the market. We need more land sales, not less. We need people to find a better fit for their own family circumstances. The Government would have the possibility of reducing transaction taxes if it had a reliable income stream from development land taxes. This is the only tax one could levy that will not affect development. It will actually stimulate development.</p>
          <p eId="para_309">Taxing labour or even capital puts a brake on development which is not what we want as we enter a phase of natural decline. Land tax has the wonderful benefit of stimulating development and we should look at it even more closely now as we come into an uncertain period. Effectively, either the Government takes part of that increase in the value of the land or the landowner does. At this point, the money is better off in the hands of the Government, and particularly local authorities, because they need it more than landowners.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCuffeGP" eId="spk_201">
          <from>Deputy Cuffe</from>
          <p eId="para_310">One final supplementary on that. I presume the derelict sites levy is like a very small approximation of a site value tax in so far as it is a get up or shut up tax that prompts people to either make use of the land or sell it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_202">
          <from>Ms Ó Siochrú</from>
          <p eId="para_311">It is very similar.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_203">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_312">I thank Ms Ó Siochrú very much for her submission.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_9">Sitting suspended at 3.05 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</summary>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_204">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_313">The next item is the presentation by the Office of the Ombudsman represented by Mr. Patrick Whelan, Mr. Willie O'Doherty and Ms Maureen Beehan. They are very welcome. Before we begin, I remind visitors that while members of the committee have absolute privilege, that same privilege does not apply to witnesses appearing before it. We have all studied the written submission the Office has made to the committee. I ask that the submission be synopsised rather than read through in a period of six to eight minutes after which members will ask questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_205">
          <from>Mr. Patrick Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_314">I am very pleased to accept the committee's invitation to expand on the Office's submission of 30 May regarding property rights. I do not propose to read through that submission again though I will summarise some of its main points. The issues raised in our submission predate the appointment as Ombudsman of Ms Emily O'Reilly. She has asked me to address the committee on her behalf and on behalf of the Office. Our submission covers two issues, the first of which is the right to private property in the context of which we deal particularly with the question of public rights of way. The second is the question of private property and the common good in terms of which we address the difficulties faced by planning authorities in attempting to protect the common good from a planning perspective.</p>
          <p eId="para_315">The Office of the Ombudsman is a complaint driven organisation. We have looked at the subject of property rights in the context of our examination of complaints from members of the public about local authorities. In particular, our comments are informed by our experience of dealing with complaints about the alleged failure of local authorities to take enforcement action under the planning laws. On a point of clarification, the Ombudsman does not have jurisdiction to examine complaints about decisions to grant or refuse planning permission which are issues for An Bord Pleanála. However, the Ombudsman has the power to examine complaints about the general administration of the planning process, complaints alleging failure by local authorities to enforce the conditions attaching to individual decisions to grant planning permission or, where no planning permission exists, complaints about the pursuit of unauthorised development. When I refer to the general administration of the planning system, at issue are the obligations on planning authorities to inform applicants and objectors of decisions on planning within statutory time limits. We have examined cases in which there has been a failure to so inform within the time limit.</p>
          <p eId="para_316">Of all the complaints examined by the Ombudsman, complaints about the planning enforcement process are among the most difficult to deal with. They are time consuming, protracted and often involve voluminous documentation. Among the historical reasons for this is cumbersome planning legislation which contains a multiplicity of enforcement mechanisms though this has been streamlined with the enactment of the Planning and Development Act 2000. Also involved are local issues which influence local authorities in the exercise of their discretion in terms of whether they will take enforcement action. The resources may not be available to local authorities to take enforcement action through the courts and the attitude of the courts to enforcement issues, as advised to us by local authorities, is also a factor. There is an emerging view that development has been impeded by objectors and there have been calls for limitations on the right to object to development. To a greater or lesser extent, each of the above factors has an influence on the issues covered in bothour submissions on the protection of publicrights of way and the enforcement of the planning code.</p>
          <p eId="para_317">In the context of public rights of way, the Office of the Ombudsman suggests that the committee considers whether a person should have recourse within our constitutional and legislative framework to a legal process as of right where the State is unwilling or unable to act in their place. A relevant example is section 108 of the Environmental Protection Agency Act 1992 which provides a person with a legal right to complain about noise levels to the District Court irrespective of the view of a local authority on the matter. At present, the local authority has the responsibility through the Planning and Roads Act to protect rights of way. Such legislation does not provide for the right of an individual to take action in the courts and if the local authority does not act to protect an individual's rights, the individual concerned is virtually powerless to act.</p>
          <p eId="para_318">In the context of private property and the common good, the traditional view has been to regard the requirement to obtain planning permission as an interference with and a restriction of a person's property rights. It is doubtful that anyone living in modern Ireland accepts or believes that the requirements to obtain planning permission and to abide by planning conditions infringe on property rights. Where permission is granted there is often the potential for significant or other gain for the applicant and in these circumstances such permission represents an enhancement of property rights. Such enhancement should arguably carry an obligation to adhere to the terms of the permission in the interests of the common good. As property rights are dealt with in Articles 40 and 43 of the Constitution, perhaps these can be examined to establish if a greater balance between a person's property rights and the common good can be achieved to ensure that property is developed by reference to a planning code which is enforced consistently by all appropriate arms of the State.</p>
          <p eId="para_319">My final point is of importance to the committee in the carrying out of its review. It is our experience that the confidence of many complainants in the planning process has been seriously undermined by the manner in which they have been treated by planning authorities. Indeed, many have expressed their disillusionment to the Office in respect of the way in which local government administers and enforces the planning code. There is a need for greater balance in the manner in which the views of all parties to the process are considered and taken into account in dealing with individual planning issues. It is in the long-term interest of our democratic process that the rights of all parties are properly balanced and considered in an open, fair and accountable manner.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_206">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_320">A couple of points arise from Mr. Whelan's submission according to which the Office favours, on balance, an updating, streamlining or amendment of Articles 40 and 43 rather than legislative change. Some groups that have come here advocate that we do this through current or new legislation. However, I garner from that paragraph that you feel a need for greater balance since the argument for our committee is whether the exigencies of the common good and the principles of social justice are being served as laid down by the Constitution. I get the impression that the balance is not correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_207">
          <from>Mr. Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_321">I am very sensitive to the committee's brief and that it wishes to look primarily at the Constitution and not simply at legislative proposals for change. It is obviously much easier to consider the latter. My point is that the operation of legislation up to now has not been entirely satisfactory in striking a balance between the right to property and the common good in the Constitution. If one examines Article 40, one sees that there may be something of a contradiction between it and Article 43. The latter quite clearly lays out the balance between those two objectives, but Article 40 seems to be very dogmatic in what it says about protecting the right to private property. The issue is that there is very little by way of scrutiny by the Supreme Court of where the balance lies between those two somewhat opposing objectives. Based on our experience of what people say to us, be they complainants or local authorities doing their best to enforce legislation, we feel that, when they see what goes before the courts, they have occasion to question whether that balance is properly and fairly reflected.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_208">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_322">If the following is not a fair question to put to you, you may refuse to answer. I am not putting a gun to your head. Do you feel that the interpretation by the Supreme Court to date, apart from the recent decision on the Planning and Development Act 2000, has been narrowly construed in favour of the property owner rather than the common good?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_209">
          <from>Mr. Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_323">I would answer that by saying that we have, as I said in our submission, difficulties in dealing with complaints about the planning process. To some extent some of those problems arose out of the Local Government (Planning and Development) Act 1963. That has been modernised and updated in the Planning and Development Act 2000. It is much more streamlined and, one hopes, more effective legislation. Ultimately, local authorities say to us that the jury is still out on the new Act. It is obviously early days yet. However, some of them have said that they are not confident they will be able to operate the legislation to secure adequate planning enforcement. We are talking about three mechanisms - warning notices, enforcement and, most importantly, court action. Some of them have said they are not confident that court action will produce the kind of results the local authority might wish to see in a planning enforcement situation, which is essentially the protection or balancing of the common good against the rights of individual developers who are, of course, sometimes acting without any planning permission whatsoever. The jury is out, but the councils are not confident that the balance is reflected in how the courts handle such situations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBreen" eId="spk_210">
          <from>Deputy Breen</from>
          <p eId="para_324">You speak of local authorities and enforcement notices. When the local authority issues such notices, are they not pursued vigorously enough? If they are not pursued vigorously enough and are passed to the Ombudsman for adjudication, what is the time scale? You could have a man moving in destroying the landscape, and by the time the Ombudsman had dealt with that case, the landscape would have been completely and irreparably destroyed. What is the time scale? Where a right of way is extinguished and the local authority does not appear to be acting, has the Ombudsman a role?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_211">
          <from>Mr. Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_325">On the first question, that of time scales, the Deputy has described the situation with which we were faced under the old regime of the Local Government (Planning and Development) Act 1963. However, things have improved a great deal under the Planning and Development Act 2000 since there are now specific time limits placed on local authorities by which they must take action. If they do not do so, there is a whole series of other measures that click into place. At the moment we are monitoring the manner in which local authorities are implementing those enforcement provisions. Ultimately, what we must do is investigate why a local authority is not taking enforcement action. They have the discretion not to do so, but our brief is to ensure that if they decide not to take such action, that is a reasonable decision, perhaps because the breach or transgression was minor, in which case it would not be reasonable to expect a local authority to take action. Perhaps the developer is acting in good faith and has made promises to make good whatever transgression he or she has committed.</p>
          <p eId="para_326">The issues are not black and white. They are difficult and require a great deal of probing on our part. Ultimately, the Ombudsman makes recommendations, so we depend to some extent on the goodwill of the local authority to pursue our recommendations. However, I must say in their defence that they might see the only solution as court action, and they have not had a happy record in the past with the courts' views in enforcement proceedings that we have taken. It is quite a complex jigsaw and difficult to pin down where the blame lies in any specific case. It involves the developer, the local authority, and it may ultimately involve the courts.</p>
          <p eId="para_327">On the second issue of rights of way, essentially the same kinds of issues come into play. There is provision in the Planning and Development Act 2000 for the local authority to take action where rights of way are wrongly being extinguished by a landowner. We have documented some cases in our 1999 annual report on that issue. We wrote about cases involving Mayo County Council and Bray Urban District Council. Ultimately, in the Mayo case, the local authority entered into discussions with the landowner to try to reach an agreement that will accommodate the interests of all parties. It is a slow process, and that is why we suggest to the committee that an individual, as under other legislation, should also have the right to pursue that issue through the courts.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_212">
          <from>Deputy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_328">I welcome the fact that your Office has made a submission to us. I interpret what you are saying as that the courts are essentially not implementing the law. Obviously they have some discretion, but in effect they are not implementing the intention of the legislation with regard to developers who have clearly breached the planning legislation. Is it necessary to amend the Constitution to address that or could we reduce the level of discretion, limiting it or defining what the courts would have regarding the legislation? It seems that the law itself is fairly clear. If a person builds or develops something for which he or she does not have planning permission that person is in breach of the law and should have to take the appropriate action, be it taking down a structure or anything else. The courts are feeling sympathetic to the developer and in effect feel the local authority is being heavy handed. It seems to me that the courts are not implementing the letter of the legislation. Would you see any scope for limiting the discretion of the courts through legislative amendment or do you feel it is necessary to change the Constitution to address this issue?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_213">
          <from>Mr. Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_329">What I have outlined is the position as relayed to us by local authorities. One might look at what the role of the courts is, as documented by Professor Yvonne Scannell from the Centre of Environment Law and Policy in Trinity College Dublin. She indicated seven criteria that the courts, in her opinion, have taken on board in looking at cases. These are the technicality or triviality of the breach; the impact of the unauthorised development on the applicant; the hardship to the developer or the landowner; the conduct of the applicant; the conduct of the developer or landowner; the public interest; and, finally, the attitude of the planning authority. Of course the public interest, which was equated with the common good, is in there. The enactment of the Planning and Development Act 2000, I think, was intended to streamline many of these procedures and to put more power into the hands of the local authorities. That has happened. It was enacted in March 2002, so it is still a little too early to judge, but what we are getting clearly from some local authorities is that the final link in the chain is the courts. Unless the courts have due regard to the public interest not much will have changed.</p>
          <p eId="para_330">I could go into detail about some of the technical issues that have arisen. For example, the Act says that where someone is applying for a retention and goes before the courts, the proceedings should not be stayed on the basis of such an application. Nevertheless, some justices have adjourned proceedings to allow a developer to apply for retention, notwithstanding the fact that the local authority has said it will not grant retention under any circumstances - and they have made that clear in their submissions to the court. To reflect the court's position fairly, what the courts have said is that an adjournment is not the same as a stay. If the legislation provides for a stay, and if somebody seeks an adjournment, that is a separate issue. Already some local authorities are talking about what appears to be a need to amend the recently enacted legislation, to make the distinction between a stay and an adjournment.</p>
          <p eId="para_331">It is their feeling that the bias - or balance - is still very much in favour of the developer and less in favour of the common good. Finally, they face ancillary difficulties also, such as costs, for example, whether they will be successful in an application for costs in cases like this. In some cases their experience has not been a happy one. There are resources issues as well, of course. Everybody is strapped for cash.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_214">
          <from>Deputy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_332">Is it more clearly a constitutional issue?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_215">
          <from>Mr. Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_333">That is the point I am coming to. I just wonder whether legislation alone would be effective, particularly since we now have the Planning and Development Act 2000. If we were talking about this here, two years ago, we might have said, "Let us see how things go with the new Planning and Development Act". The early indications, however, are not very encouraging.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_216">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_334">First, it is very much to be welcomed that the Office of the Ombudsman contributed to this debate. It would have been quite easy for it not to have contributed. I think it is also good we have somebody with plenty of experience in these issues who can offer an independent view. That is beneficial from our point of view. I should like to develop a little more the point raised by Deputy O'Sullivan. In your submission of 29 May there is a reference, "It seems to us that arising from the provisions of Article 43 and its interpretation by the courts as evidence by local authorities that the public does not enjoy that comfort, and therefore, local authorities may, despite their increased powers under the Planning and Development Act 2000, continue to hesitate pursue planning infringements through the courts for the reasons explained above", which is what you have just developed.</p>
          <p eId="para_335">The inference or explicit statement is that their reason for not proceeding is due to the deficiencies in Article 43. In other words, it would appear from what Mr. Whelan contends that the reason they do not proceed is because of Article 43 and the fact that they would be likely to lose - or not succeed - in those circumstances. Those of us who are members of local authorities might suggest it has more to do with inertia within the system, that they do not proceed rather than any inherent deficiency in Article 43 as it stands. I would be interested in Mr. Whelan's observations on that. Are there any examples he is aware of from the cases that come before him, where in his view the development should have stopped and the local authority decided not to act because it did not believe it would succeed - and in any event it did not think it should act? That is the point I am trying to get across. It is what I believe Deputy O'Sullivan was getting at as well.</p>
          <p eId="para_336">On the issue of enforcement, it would be the experience of local authorities that there have been cases where <i>prima facie </i>there was a breach but there was no evidence of the council being prepared to proceed in a vigorous way to remedy this. Sometimes that has to do with resources and lack of manpower, etc. In my own local authority, Kildare County Council, for example, where there is a great deal of development ongoing and few staff to deal with enforcement, that would be our experience. I would agree with Mr. Whelan’s point. We have had experience as well where the courts have said they will adjourn in response to the question: “Is this the subject of a planning application, even though it may be two or three years down the line?” Where the answer was, “Yes, it is”, the courts have decided to adjourn the case until the local authority adjudicated on the planning issue. That seems to give rise to some sort of limbo.</p>
          <p eId="para_337">The other aspect I would refer to is rights of way. In the presentation to us this afternoon, the point is made that a local authority does not act to protect an individual's rights. If the local authority does not act, then the individual concerned is virtually powerless to act. In what way does Mr. Whelan think that could be rectified and that the individual would have recourse rather than the local authority having to act on behalf of the individual or group? If we look at the Mayo incident, that goes back to 1989. It seems extraordinary that it would take that length of time to resolve the issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_217">
          <from>Mr. Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_338">I will start with the Senator's first point about Article 40 versus Article 43. I do not think when the local authority is considering a planning issue it is thinking about the Constitution. It is looking at the legislation and trying to operate that to the best of its ability. When one goes to court, however, the scene is a bit different because one would expect judges to have a better sense of balance between competing rights. Notwithstanding that, they must, of course, enforce the law as they see it. If the Constitution was more explicit on this point, it would, in turn, be more explicit in the legislation as well so that the rules of the game are more clearly evident and there is more of a level playing field.</p>
          <p eId="para_339">On the second point, enforcement, it is true that local authorities sometimes have to be prodded and cajoled into taking enforcement action. Sometimes when we get a complaint and go to them they will say, "No, it is not warranted here at all". Then we begin to probe and find that the local authority is simply unable to justify this response. At this point may begin to think in terms of taking enforcement action and to introduce warning notices and take court action. We often have to do that. Take the number of cases with which we had to deal last year, for example. We dealt with 184 cases involving planning enforcement and we were successful in resolving 48 or 29%. We were also able to provide some form of assistance to a further 82 complainants. That is approximately 180 cases we have been able to progress to some extent out of a total of 184. Two arguments can be made from that. If the Office was not there, would anything happen? The fact that the Office exists, even within the current legislative constraints, means we have been reasonably successful in moving forward some of these issues.</p>
          <p eId="para_340">On the rights of way, I have forgotten what the——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_218">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_341">The individual's recourse.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_219">
          <from>Mr. Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_342">Yes. In terms of how that would change matters, local authorities can decide not to take action in relation to a right of way for all sorts of reasons but an individual will be much more focused on the wrongdoing, so to speak. A member of a hill walking club or whatever will be extremely focused on that aspect but a local authority might be more inclined to take a broad view and decide that, on balance, it is not worth doing. It may be aware of other future plans which might make it unwise, in its view, to take action in that regard. I am not suggesting that the granting of the right to an individual is a panacea for all the ills in this area. I do not believe that is the case. I mention it because it exists in other forms of legislation where——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_220">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_343">Could it be rectified by a simple legislative measure?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_221">
          <from>Mr. Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_344">The legislative process could give more power to individuals in terms of processing but it will not necessarily deal with the common good issue because again we are talking about what happens when one gets into court. We are looking at the traditional view, which was that the rights of the landowner, for whatever reason, appear to take precedence over any other rights, including the common good.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCuffeGP" eId="spk_222">
          <from>Deputy Cuffe</from>
          <p eId="para_345">I had intended asking Mr. Whelan how to pronounce the name of that beach in Mayo.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_223">
          <from>Mr. Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_346">White Strand.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCuffeGP" eId="spk_224">
          <from>Deputy Cuffe</from>
          <p eId="para_347">I was tempted to suggest that the alternative name for it might become a verb or a noun over time, in the same way Captain Boycott added his name to the English language. The timeframe for what is happening there is incredible.</p>
          <p eId="para_348">There is a crisis in planning enforcement within local authorities, based on my own experience of the largest local authority in the State. On receipt of a complaint about, say, a coffee shop becoming a late night take-away overnight, we have to wait for an inspector to go out. We then have to wait for the report to come back. The report then has to go to the law agent and we then have to wait for the law agent to take action. Years can pass in that process. That is my own experience.</p>
          <p eId="para_349">We can suggest that the local authority is either unable or unwilling to enforce the law. We discussed earlier whether this is a resources issue, but I wonder whether it is a more deep seated problem. Mr. Whelan suggests that persons should have independent access to the law as of right. Is it not the case under the Planning and Development Act 2000 that one can go straight to the courts with a planning complaint and that there is more direct access to the courts under the planning Acts? Following on from that, are there examples abroad where this right is recognised in more detail than it is here? If my memory is correct, in the United States there appears to be much more direct access by an individual to the law when it comes to planning enforcement. Is Mr. Whelan looking abroad when he makes the suggestion that access to the legal process, as of right, should be available?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_225">
          <from>Mr. Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_350">To go back to the remarks about Uggool beach, we found that a very frustrating case to deal with and we are not happy with the length of time it is taking to get a resolution. Again, this underlines some of the issues we have spoken about already. We can make a recommendation that something should happen there but the local authority does not have to accept our recommendation. We could make a special report to the Oireachtas if they were to do that but, fundamentally, it would be far more satisfactory if solutions of this type could be found by agreement rather than by the imposition of a position because we are talking about property and I am not sure that moving by diktat, under the current constitutional and legislative regime, is the way to get the best results. To be fair to the local authority, it could have moved earlier under the existing legislation to recoup the right of way but the issue is whether that would have solved the problem. What it is trying to do now is come at the problem in a slower way but in a way, in its view, which will be longer lasting in terms of getting an agreed solution to the problem. If the landowner does not like the solution, he or she may choose not to operate it. That is a problem.</p>
          <p eId="para_351">In terms of individuals going to court on planning issues, An Bord Pleanála is the Planning Appeals Board and if an individual wishes to object to a planning development, in the first instance they appeal to the planning authority and if they are not happy with that, they can appeal to An Bord Pleanála. The area where the courts might come in is in relation to a judicial review of a decision by An Bord Pleanála but I believe that is the full range of measures that are available to an individual.</p>
          <p eId="para_352">On the point about the position abroad, we have not looked at that very much. We did examine a situation in the United Kingdom where the Countryside and Rights of Way Act 2000 makes provision that will extinguish in the year 2026 all footpaths and bridle ways in existence before 1949 where they are not recorded in a definitive map for public rights of way, but we have not studied that in any detail.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimmyDevinsFF" eId="spk_226">
          <from>Deputy Devins</from>
          <p eId="para_353">I thank the representatives for coming in today. I want to make two comments, the first of which relates to the enforcement by local authorities. I am a member of Sligo County Council. A year and a half ago the council set up a dedicated enforcement unit, as a result of which many of the potential cases were dealt with. Now that the word has got out to the general public that the council is prepared to deal with cases of unauthorised structures by going through the whole rigmarole, right up to court, there has been a decrease in the number of complaints made. The mindset is slowly changing in that regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_354">On the issue in question today, the last paragraph on page 1 of the two page presentation suggests that greater balance might be achieved between a person's property rights and the interests of the common good. That neatly encapsulates what the committee is trying to address. Can I take it from the comments made earlier that Mr. Whelan would suggest that the interests of the common good are not sufficiently protected under the Constitution and that he would like to see those strengthened? If that is the case, would he be prepared to put in writing suggestions for proposed changes to the Constitution?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_227">
          <from>Mr. Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_355">That is a difficult issue for us as we are not constitutional lawyers on this side of the table. The joint committee can take it that we feel there is a deficiency there and this is reflected in some of the general comments I made. There has been a big push during the past couple of years towards development with the Celtic tiger and so on and many local authorities have been stretched for resources, all of which have gone into development and not into enforcement. That is understandable and it is interesting to hear the comments about what has been happening in Sligo. Certainly we would welcome more of that happening.</p>
          <p eId="para_356">We deal with individual complaints and I am at pains to emphasise that to the joint committee. In regard to the debate about building things quicker, that we have to be like Madrid and get the metro built in a year and that it should take ten years to have it done here, I can well understand the frustration with all of that. However, the bottom line is that if we are to do things more efficiently and more quickly - and there is a need for that - it is important not to lose sight of the rights of individual people in that process. Their rights still need to be protected. We have to find a way of striking a balance between those who object for the sake of objecting and those who are genuinely and seriously affected by development. There must be a right to be heard and a right for their views to be considered. That is where the common good comes into play.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoannaTuffy" eId="spk_228">
          <from>Senator Tuffy</from>
          <p eId="para_357">I thank the delegation from the Office of the Ombudsman for its presentation. I am sorry I was not present for the presentation but I have read a summary. On the issue of whether a person would have legal recourse, is there not an injunction procedure in relation to planning? So far as I know it was provided for in section 27 of the old planning Act but I am not sure what section it is now. If we provide for the right to go to court, that is not necessarily the solution because it involves costs, time and so on and, in fact, it is one of the deterrents. One of the reasons the Office of the Ombudsman is so attractive is that it does not involve those things. If there were to be many court cases on this type of issue it would not necessarily be a good thing. That is one of the reservations I would have with it. As a member of a local council I am aware of a lack of enforcement particularly in relation to developers of housing estates. Even if the council had more powers it would not have the resources if it involved going to court constantly. What would the delegation think of legislation whereby a developer, or other types of people, who got planning permission for one thing but did not comply, would have some restriction imposed on him in respect of future planning permissions? Perhaps that would be one way of helping to deal with the enforcement needs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_229">
          <from>Mr. Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_358">I do not disagree with the Senator's comments in respect of individuals going to court. The courts are getting clogged up with many things. We should always avoid having to go to court. I said earlier I did not see this as a complete solution to the problem; it is something that might operate in tandem with the local authority deciding whether to take court action. At least it gives some degree of satisfaction to the individual that they are not just in the hands of the local authority when it comes to it and that they can take an individual decision on it. I take the Senator's point about clogging up the courts.</p>
          <p eId="para_359">On the issue of planning permissions, the issue raised by the Senator is provided for in the Planning and Development Act. There is a restriction on future planning permissions if one has not abided by the existing one.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoannaTuffy" eId="spk_230">
          <from>Senator Tuffy</from>
          <p eId="para_360">It is a weak provision and could be much stronger. Many developers do not finish housing estates but go off and build several others and, perhaps, years down the line they come back and finish off. They should not get planning permission for the next estate if they have a bad record and have not finished a couple of estates. Perhaps they should be excluded from getting planning permission.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_231">
          <from>Mr. Whelan</from>
          <p eId="para_361">I agree with the Senator that keeping cases out of court is well worth considering. Years ago before the introduction of the bonding system, estates were built, builders fled the scene and the local authority was left holding the baby in terms of finishing footpaths, sewerage systems and so on. At least the bonding system helped to some extent but it still did not get over the problem of enforcing that through the courts. That was obviously the final say.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_232">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_362">In one sense I find it intriguing but in another sense understandable that the local authorities are reluctant to go before the courts. It is a case of once bitten, twice shy, that they have had unhappy experiences. As a local authority member for 18 years the impression in the court is that the local authority is a big body and has a good deal of money. Whatever about the developer there is much sympathy by the lower court towards the individual who has not complied with the rules and regulations. Even if the local authority succeeds there is the danger that it will be lumbered with the costs, as mentioned. This is an interesting aspect but it is also a worrying feature because local authorities, even though as members we may have our differences, are not always wrong. I commend Mr. Whelan on the excellent work being done by his Office and wish the new Ombudsman, Ms Emily O'Reilly, the very best. I am sure I speak for all members. In many instances, not only in the area of property, the Ombudsman's office has saved many citizens the hassle and trauma of going to court. Overall the office does a wonderful job. The worrying feature is the lack of trust by local authorities that even if they win they still lose because they have to pay the fees. That is a problem.</p>
          <p eId="para_363">I acknowledge the sincere view that there is a need for a better balance in the Constitution. We will certainly take that on board during our deliberations. I thank the delegation for coming before the joint committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_10">Sitting suspended at 16.16 p.m. and resumed at 16.19 p.m.</summary>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_233">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_364">The next item on the agenda is the presentation by the Mountaineering Council of Ireland represented by Ms Helen Lawless, Mr. Milo Kane, Mr. Frank Nugent and Mr. Seán Quinn, all of whom are welcome. I must remind visitors that members of the committee have absolute privilege, but this same privilege does not apply to witnesses appearing before the committee. I acknowledge you have made a submission to us which we have studied and in view of this, I suggest you outline the salient points following which there will be a questions and answers session.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_234">
          <from>Ms Helen Lawless</from>
          <p eId="para_365">Thank you, Chairman, and I thank the committee for giving us the opportunity to make an oral presentation on the question of access to the countryside and the related issue of private property and the common good. Each of our delegates will speak briefly. I will begin with a brief outline of the Mountaineering Council of Ireland. Frank Nugent will speak about access issues generally, Seán Quinn will speak about the access situation in countries abroad and the constitutional position while Milo Kane will refer to the committee's terms of reference.</p>
          <p eId="para_366">The Mountaineering Council of Ireland is the national representative body for the sport of mountaineering. That means we encompass activities as diverse as hill walking in which the majority of our members engage, rock climbing and more leisurely rambling. We have over 8,000 members and are a 32 county body. Approximately 90% of our members live in the Republic of Ireland. We have over 100 affiliated clubs and have clubs in every county in the country. We also have 900 individual members.</p>
          <p eId="para_367">Research conducted by the Waterford Institute of Technology in 1997 suggests that our 8,000 members perhaps represent only 5% of the hill walking population in Ireland. We conservatively estimate that there are approximately 100,000 active hill walkers in the country. Bord Fáilte research on the subject indicates that 250,000 visitors to the country each year engage in hiking or hill walking, a figure that has been consistently achieved every year since 1996. Bord Fáilte statistics also show that hill walking is more popular and valuable to the Irish economy than cycling, angling or touring.</p>
          <p eId="para_368">Our organisation exists to promote the enjoyment, protection, wise and safe use of the Irish uplands. We define the uplands as constituting that 5% of Ireland that is above 300 metres in elevation. Our main aim with regard to access is that we seek to gain reasonable access to the countryside for responsible users. I ask Mr. Nugent to continue on the general issues.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_235">
          <from>Mr. Frank Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_369">Access has increasingly become an issue for mountaineers and hill walkers. We recently undertook a membership survey and got over 1,000 respondents. It revealed that 48% of them had experienced specific access difficulties. These mostly occurred in the west and south-west. These problems are not unique to Ireland but they have been addressed in most other developed countries, most recently in Scotland with the Land Reform Act 2002. These countries have formally defined access rights, something citizens and visitors here do not enjoy.</p>
          <p eId="para_370">However, it is important to note that mountaineers and walkers have, and continue to enjoy, a lot of access to our uplands. We are seeking to reach a satisfactory access rights agreement for responsible users. We hope that the agreement will cover landowners and the tourism industry in the interests of the common good.</p>
          <p eId="para_371">We essentially aspire to two types of access. At lower levels, where farming is in general field based, we seek agreed routes on which responsible walkers may proceed from public roads and car parks to reach traditionally unfenced mountain and moorland areas where they should have the freedom to select routes with varied destinations. We are not looking for something we have not already enjoyed, but it is not legally defined. Mountaineers and walkers have enjoyed great access in the country, but there appears to be an increasing need for a legal definition of the issue. I will ask Mr. Quinn to speak at this point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_236">
          <from>Mr. Seán Quinn</from>
          <p eId="para_372">Our submission, in particular the additional information we submitted today, deals with the position in Britain and Scotland because we consider these to be the most relevant comparisons to Ireland. We believe that the lack of definition in Ireland places us at a unique disadvantage relative to all other European Union countries. It also disadvantages EU citizens.</p>
          <p eId="para_373">The problem is not only related to tourism, although we know that agri-tourism is very important, even if we are not achieving our full potential in this area. Ireland faces serious disadvantages in the present situation. We also have information on other jurisdictions which show how out of step is Ireland. It is making a serious impact on tourism, especially agri-tourism, which the Government has been trying to develop. We believe there is huge potential here, not only with regard to overseas but Irish visitors. Irish walkers and mountaineers are now tending to travel to destinations abroad where their rights are clear. In Ireland there is a lack of definition which is very unsatisfactory. It must be addressed and we welcome this opportunity to present our submission and answer questions.</p>
          <p eId="para_374">The relevant law in England is the Countryside Right of Way Act 2000 while the Scottish Bill was passed by a large majority in the Scottish Parliament, with 100 MSPs voting in favour and 19 against. Both jurisdictions were already way ahead of us and we have now fallen further behind. It is, therefore, time to address the matter.</p>
          <p eId="para_375">We suggest that Article 40.6 of the Constitution be expanded to cover the rights of reasonable access to Ireland's uplands for responsible users, while the committee may wish to examine the case for strengthening the provisions for delimiting property rights set out in Article 43.1 and 43.2 in the interest of the public good. We are concerned here with the majority of the people, the masses as against the classes, as Gladstone once put it when he supported the masses against the landowners. Both Articles provide scope for amendment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_237">
          <from>Mr. Milo Kane</from>
          <p eId="para_376">I wish to revert to the task for the committee as it has been outlined to us and to comment on the relevance of our submission in terms of what the committee considers to be its task, especially its concern to analyse and determine whether legislative provision in regard to the matters with which we are dealing has been constrained by the Constitution and, if so, to make recommendations. To date, there has not been to our knowledge an attempt to make legislative provision towards access rights. However, in our view, some legal definition is increasingly required for reasons we have made clear in our submission.</p>
          <p eId="para_377">We think that if the committee so feels, the Constitution should be reviewed to allow scope for the drafting of such legislation without it being overshadowed by a perceived constitutional problem or without it being subject to challenge. Our feeling is that there is balance within the present Constitution but there is rather less balance in how the Judiciary has interpreted the Constitution. In general the interpretations that we have seen, perhaps most recently with the Supreme Court decision on Kinsale but also in various other instances, have considerably favoured the propertied side. We are not saying that this necessarily has to be so but it has been hitherto so. If the committee should see fit to recommend a constitutional modification, we would certainly hope to see this.</p>
          <p eId="para_378">In conclusion, we would not wish to be seen as being anti-landowner. Yesterday a member from Kerry pointed out to me that to a very large extent those Irish people who are city bound are frequently largely descended from the younger siblings of landowners who, because of the system of land tenure, particularly after the Famine, left their rural roots and came to live in the city. We feel it would be equitable that the interest and roots of such people should be recognised in their being legally entitled, to a greater extent than they currently are, to recreational use of the open countryside.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_238">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_379">We already had the group called Keep Ireland Open before us and next week the Uplands Forum group will come before us. To get my thought process clear on this, are both groups aligned and affiliated to you?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_239">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_380">The Mountaineering Council would be a membership body of mountaineers whereas I think Keep Ireland Open would have other members. We would be primarily concerned with uplands dealing with mountaineering and hill walking as such whereas they would be interested in access in general.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_240">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_381">What about the newly formed Uplands Forum?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_241">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_382">The Uplands Forum is really a body which is concerned with trying to develop co-operation between owners and users within the communities of uplands. It is very much based around a co-operative type approach to dealing with the economy of uplands and we would be participants in those fora.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_242">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_383">I understand that Bord Fáilte and the IFA are also involved in the Uplands Forum.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_243">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_384">We would be very supportive of the objectives of the Irish Uplands Forum. We would be less associated with Keep Ireland Open.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_244">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_385">I suppose in one sense I must confess a particular interest because I am involved in the Sheep's Head Way and Slí Muintir Beara. I am one of the people who originally, over three years, developed that particular route.</p>
          <p eId="para_386">Returning to some practical issues, unfortunately we are confined here to the constitutional parameters in which the committee finds itself, but the big worry that comes across from the public at large and people in Ireland who are very sensitive to their property and their little commonage or whatever, is insurance. You touched on the Supreme Court decisions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_245">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_387">There was an issue. We worked in tandem with IFA and with other farming bodies in the introduction of the Occupiers' Liability Act 1995. We very much support the idea that farmers are not responsible for people going on their land. We would support that position. In fact, we were quite surprised with some of the findings in some of the courts where judges appear to be unaware of the most recent legislation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_246">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_388">In fairness, some of those proceedings may have been initiated before the new Act came into being and obviously legislation is not generally retrospective. I would be interested in your views on this. I would see that the kernel to solving all of this is co-operation, primarily with the IFA. This arose at one of the meetings I had recently with the Minister, Deputy Ó Cuív, on this general issue and on compensation of farmers, the REP scheme and the Beara Way in my constituency in west Cork which is currently closed, etc. There are 12,000 or maybe 14,000 commonage holders in Ireland and unless there is co-operation and consensus between the various groups and even if we change the Constitution, you cannot ram something down their throats. That approach might be the one that should be explored.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_247">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_389">We would very much support that whole approach of sitting down with landowners and other economic interests in the uplands and trying to forge practical solutions to these matters. One cannot force a way. We would not be interested in bullying people into anything.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_248">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_390">I accept that. On a few occasions, at least twice, the Kinsale Head model was suggested to us. I would urge caution on that because, apart from the local difficulties - I would be <i>au fait </i>with some of them - some of the tactics of people who were supposed to be representing hill walkers and mountaineers at local level were found to be less than appropriate. I will caution myself in using those words.</p>
          <p eId="para_391">The main difficulty you have is that you want us to perhaps come in line with Great Britain and Scotland and that is something on which we obviously cannot embark. Are you telling the committee that within the Constitution as it currently stands, the common good and the principles of social justice are too constrained and restricted for the benefit of your association?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_249">
          <from>Mr. Kane</from>
          <p eId="para_392">There is that danger. We could not give an absolute opinion, not being constitutional lawyers, but while we have a considerable record of co-operation with the IFA, and, in fact, no MCI input as such occurred in the Kinsale instance - I can be quite definite on that - what we are concerned about is that we can go a long way down the road with an awful lot of people and the next day somebody different in another area may decide that he is shutting his land. This may come out of the blue to people who have essentially, as things now stand, no right in that situation. This appears to be an instance where an imbalance might be addressed between the very reasonable rights and concerns of landowners and other reasonable concerns that other people may have. There should be a defined legal code which may be appropriate to Ireland and may differ from what applies to Scotland and England, but which is at the end of the day a defined code.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_250">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_393">I welcome the submission from the mountaineering council. I am very much in awe of anybody who has climbed Everest and I note from Mr. Nugent's CV that he has been there, and I congratulate him on that achievement. The liability issue is one which I was also wondering about and I note that there was not a particular reference to it in the document. Does the council carry insurance for its members? Angling clubs and game or shooting clubs do.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_251">
          <from>Ms Lawless</from>
          <p eId="para_394">Yes, we do. We have cover of up to £5 million sterling for civil liability, which is a very wide wording that includes public liability, and we also have personal accident cover for permanent injury.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_252">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_395">Has the council found that this cover is a reassurance in your dealings with landowners?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_253">
          <from>Ms Lawless</from>
          <p eId="para_396">It is, but it is very difficult for a farmer to tell from the farm gate whether the people who are approaching are insured. Our members carry cards stating they are insured and in discussions with landowners it has helped. It gives our members peace of mind and landowners protection.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_254">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_397">I accept what Ms Lawless says about the most recent legislation, but would she be prepared to accept that it should be a requirement and a responsibility to carry insurance if one enters land?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_255">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_398">The law is very clear that a farmer does not have liability for someone who has entered his land.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_256">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_399">This is in a slightly different category.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_257">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_400">The law as I understand it is that anyone who enters open land does so in the knowledge that he or she must accept full responsibility for his or her well being.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_258">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_401">I have examined the Scottish legislation which appears to place strong emphasis on rights of access. Is there much of a difference between current practice in Northern Ireland and the Republic?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_259">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_402">In Northern Ireland they are conducting research with a view to bringing out a new Bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_260">
          <from>Mr. Kane</from>
          <p eId="para_403">It is at an earlier stage than pertains in the United Kingdom. A consultation paper was issued approximately 18 months ago but no legislation has been drafted yet.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_261">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_404">If one were to go to Northern Ireland would one notice any practical difference between climbing a mountain there and in the Republic?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_262">
          <from>Mr. Kane</from>
          <p eId="para_405">I think the same exceptions are liable to occur. There are differences between areas, North and South, but I cannot say there is a de facto difference between the North and the South to the same extent as there will be shortly between the Republic and Scotland and England.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_263">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_406">Would the witnesses be happy enough with the legislative response now and a possible enhancement of the Constitution from their point of view later?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_264">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_407">We would like to have the law defined in the context of access. Were that to happen constitutionally as a support, that would be desirable. If the law were defined clearly for all and to our satisfaction, we would be very happy with that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_265">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_408">I would not disagree with what the witnesses said about fencing. Much of it has been imposed on farmers by REP schemes. There were grants for sheep farmers to fence the commonages so that sheep would not go over the top of the hill. I would not disagree with the witnesses on this issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_266">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_409">Thankfully many of those REP schemes have been revised and are moving away from that approach.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_267">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_410">It does seem pretty crazy, as I have seen in a few places near Croagh Patrick where there is a nice stream with a wire on either side because that is the requirement of the REP scheme. It does not make much sense, even from an environmental point of view.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_268">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_411">Does the delegation have any suggestion how constitutional adjustments, as they refer to them, would help the case they make? Where do they feel that a review of any aspect of the Constitution would help their case?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_269">
          <from>Mr. Quinn</from>
          <p eId="para_412">We referred in our submission to both Article 40.3.2° and Article 43.2.1°. These would be the relevant Articles and it is a great opportunity to move this issue forward and deal with it. Senator Dardis queried whether legislation would come first. This committee has identified access to the countryside and the right to private property as specific issues. It would be a pity if it were not tackled now because reviews of the Constitution do not take place very often. Regarding the Constitution, we pointed out that the balance between property rights and the common good is at present weighed substantially in favour of property owners. We feel that Article 43.2.1° appears capable of coping with it. We would certainly support regulation of or delimiting the property rights for the public good. The committee may have had submissions yesterday on Article 40.6 under which certain rights are guaranteed subject to public order and morality. It would be helpful if reasonable and responsible access was added on to Article 40.6.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraicMcCormack" eId="spk_270">
          <from>Deputy McCormack</from>
          <p eId="para_413">I strongly agree with Mr. Kane that everyone is only one or two generations removed from the countryside. I was astonished recently when my nephew from Dublin who is not even one generation away from the countryside, his mother having been reared on a farm, said he thought potatoes came out on stalks. I could not believe it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoannaTuffy" eId="spk_271">
          <from>Senator Tuffy</from>
          <p eId="para_414">I thank the witnesses for their presentation which is very helpful. They refer in their submission under the heading of "Access and the Constitution" to the fact that it should be possible to support a more balanced approach and to draw up legislation which need not conflict with the provisions of the Constitution. They go on to say that, if we were to amend the Constitution, they would support that. If it is not necessary to amend the Constitution, would it be better not to amend it and introduce legislation instead? Would an improved wording be achieved?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_272">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_415">Sometimes defence of property rights would come through a constitutional defence and a court would tend to be influenced by that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoannaTuffy" eId="spk_273">
          <from>Senator Tuffy</from>
          <p eId="para_416">There have been previous proposals to amend it and the wording is similar but slightly different. Is it necessarily going to be any better?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_274">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_417">If there were a process which involved a dialogue between landowners and our interests, I am sure it could be possible to find an appropriate wording that people would not feel was an attack on their rights.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoannaTuffy" eId="spk_275">
          <from>Senator Tuffy</from>
          <p eId="para_418">I see a contradiction in that the witnesses say it would be possible to draw up legislation. If it were possible to do so within the Constitution as currently framed, that would be the way to go.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_276">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_419">We believe that the Constitution as drafted has that latitude, but from what we have seen from High and Supreme Court decisions, it does not appear to be so. They appear to favour property rights highly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_277">
          <from>Mr. Quinn</from>
          <p eId="para_420">It has not happened so far which means there is a problem in this regard. This is why we believe it would be better to tackle it now. Britain does not have a written constitution. We do and, for better or worse, we must accept that and deal with it. It is better to tackle it now.</p>
          <p eId="para_421">Regarding the position abroad and in neighbouring countries, their access has improved over the years whereas ours has deteriorated. We have always been famous for being Ireland of the welcomes. None of us wants to see that becoming Ireland of the unwelcomes. It is not just for visitors from abroad; it is also for our own citizens from the point of view of health and well being. The Minister for Health and Children is trying to promote greater activity for health purposes and has launched a new campaign in this respect. Walking appeals to everyone of all ages and classes in every part of the country. It is not an urban or rural phenomenon. Everyone is beginning to appreciate that they must have proper exercise.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_278">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_422">Who would have thought public access to the Old Head of Kinsale would have been denied?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDardis" eId="spk_279">
          <from>Senator Dardis</from>
          <p eId="para_423">Did that more than anything else cause the alarm bells to ring?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_280">
          <from>Mr. Nugent</from>
          <p eId="para_424">It shows what can happen. There is a sign pointing towards the head and people go there every day only to find they cannot gain access to an area where there used to be a lighthouse.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_281">
          <from>Mr. Quinn</from>
          <p eId="para_425">Tourist literature highlights the point. Tourist literature from Scotland states that the country has a long standing tradition of access to open country and that the Scottish Parliament has incorporated this in law giving individuals the right of responsible access to open country. It is the same in England which has the Countryside and Rights of Way Act 2000.</p>
          <p eId="para_426">These matters take time and there is a lead-in in Britain because the management of this issue is very important. We know there are problems. In England and Wales this is being tackled methodically and it will be another couple of years before the Act comes into force. There are mapping processes and local fora are being set up. We are falling behind all the time. Northern Ireland will take on board what is happening in other parts of the UK.</p>
          <p eId="para_427">This is not just a matter for other parts of these islands. We can provide information from New Zealand, America and the continent if it helps the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_282">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_428">Thank you. The concept is probably accepted on health grounds. The Irish people are probably seen as not walking enough. Lest the wrong message goes out, from my experience in west Cork 95% of farmers were co-operative and those who were not may have had undue fears. Most small farmers in the Beara Peninsula, Sheep's Head Bay, Mizen Head and west Mayo are unable to derive a full-time living from the land and they depend on subsidies and headage payments. The IFA recognises the importance of tourism in these areas and that this area should be nurtured. If the IFA comes on board it may have to be done region by region. There are open dedicated routes signposted all over the country, which I notice in places like Kerry and Clare, but I am not sure what we can do as a committee. We will look at the submission and deliberate on it. It may be our conclusion in six months that constitutional change is not as appropriate as legislative change. I wish the delegation well in its work and thank it for this submission.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_11">The joint committee adjourned at 4.55 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 17 July 2003.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
