<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_affairs/2006-09-12/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_affairs/2006-09-12/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2006-09-12" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/29/joint_committee_on_european_affairs"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_affairs/2006-09-12/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_affairs/2006-09-12/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2006-09-12" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_affairs/2006-09-12/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_affairs/2006-09-12/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None" showAs="Vol. None" eId="#vol_None"/>
          <oir:numberReference href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None/no/182" showAs="No. 182" eId="#no_182"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AengusOSnodaighSF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aengus-Ó-Snodaigh.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Aengus Ó Snodaigh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AnnOrmonde" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ann-Ormonde.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Ann Ormonde"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BarryAndrewsFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Barry-Andrews.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Barry Andrews"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CamillusGlynn" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Camillus-Glynn.S.1997-09-17" showAs="Camillus Glynn"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DanWallace" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Dan-Wallace.D.1982-12-14" showAs="Dan Wallace"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DermotAhern" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Dermot-Ahern.D.1987-03-10" showAs="Dermot Ahern"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FergalQuinn" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Feargal-Quinn.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Feargal Quinn"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FrankFeighan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Frank-Feighan.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Frank Feighan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeCostelloLAB" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Costello.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Joe Costello"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeWalsh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Walsh.D.1977-07-05" showAs="Joe Walsh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnDeasyFG" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Deasy.D.2002-06-06" showAs="John Deasy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaeSextonPD" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mae-Sexton.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Mae Sexton"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NedOKeeffe" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ned-O'Keeffe.S.1982-05-13" showAs="Ned O'Keeffe"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RuairiQuinn" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ruairí-Quinn.S.1976-07-01" showAs="Ruairí Quinn"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeamusKirk" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seamus-Kirk.D.1982-12-14" showAs="Seamus Kirk"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chair" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chair" showAs="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chairman" showAs="Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_for_Foreign_Affairs" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister/foreign_affairs" showAs="Minister for Foreign Affairs"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>COMHCHOISTE UM GHNÓTHAÍ EORPACHA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>JOINT COMMITTEE ON EUROPEAN AFFAIRS</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2006-09-12">Dé Máirt, 12 Mean Fómhair 2006</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2006-09-12">Tuesday, 12 September 2006</docDate>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 11 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#DermotAhern">Deputy D. Ahern <i>(Minister for</i>
                                    </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#MaeSextonPD">Deputy M. Sexton,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#DermotAhern"><i>Foreign Affairs)</i>,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#DanWallace">Deputy D. Wallace,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#BarryAndrewsFF">Deputy B. Andrews,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeWalsh">Deputy J. Walsh,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeCostelloLAB">Deputy J. Costello,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#FrankFeighan">Senator F. Feighan,*</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#SeamusKirk">Deputy S. Kirk,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#CamillusGlynn">Senator C. Glynn,*</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#AengusOSnodaighSF">Deputy A. Ó Snodaigh,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#AnnOrmonde">Senator A. Ormonde,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_13">
                  <person refersTo="#NedOKeeffe">Deputy N. O’Keeffe,*</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_14">
                  <person refersTo="#FergalQuinn">Senator F. Quinn.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">*In the absence of Deputy M. Mulcahy and Senators P. Bradford and D. Lydon, respectively.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#JohnDeasyFG">
   DEPUTY J. DEASY IN THE CHAIR.
  </person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>EU-Israel Association Agreement: Motion.</heading>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_15">Apologies have been received from Deputies Allen, Connolly and Mulcahy and Senators Dardis, Lydon and McDowell.</p>
          <p eId="para_16">I invite Deputy Ó Snodaigh to move the motion on the EU-Israel Association Agreement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p title="motionProposal" eId="para_17">I move:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_18">That this committee requests that the Government uses its position within the European Union to:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_19">— express its grave concern at the illegal invasion of Lebanon by Israel in recent weeks, the slaughter of innocents, the confiscation of lands, the destruction of towns and property and the indiscriminate aerial bombardment of Beirut and other towns by Israeli armed forces and the indiscriminate rocket attacks by Hizbollah on northern Israeli towns and settlements;</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_20">— deplore all human rights violations and other violations of international law perpetrated during the course of this conflict, and calls for their immediate end;</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_21">— consider that the European Union has a moral obligation to use all diplomatic means at its disposal to bring an end to these violations and to promote an immediate withdrawal from Lebanon of Israel's invading army and call for a peaceful and negotiated settlement between Palestine and Israel;</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_22">— note with regret that grave and systematic human rights violations by the Israeli defence forces against the Palestinian people and in particular the collective punishment being carried out against the people of the Gaza Strip continue despite the repeated calls on the Government of Israel by the European Union to end these violations;</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_23">— note that the Euro-Mediterranean Association Agreement between the European Communities and Israel includes in its Article 2 a provision stating that the agreement is based on respect for human rights and democratic principles, thus providing a mechanism to bring the EU's influence to bear in cases of non-respect for human rights;</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_24">— note that parliamentarians throughout the EU have called for the use of Article 2 of the association agreement as a mechanism to bring about the end of these violations of human rights and international law by Israel;</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_25">— consider that the value of the inclusion of a human rights clause in the European Union's association agreements with third countries will be brought into disrepute if no action is taken on foot thereof given the lack of progress in addressing Israel's human rights violations through other mechanisms; and</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_26">— therefore request that the Government ensure that the Minister and Minister of State for Foreign Affairs propose to the General Affairs and External Relations Council the suspension of the EU-Israel Association Agreement under Articles 2 and 79, until such time as there has been a significant and measurable improvement in compliance with international human rights standards.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">Some might feel that the context of this motion has changed since I had first hoped to have it discussed in July or early August at the height of the conflict in Lebanon but the motion is still valid. It is similar to the amendment to a motion proposed by Deputy Mulcahy last year, during Ireland's Presidency of the EU.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">A clause in the trade agreement between the EU and Israel allows the suspension of the agreement in the case of major human rights abuses by either side. The trade agreement should be suspended to demonstrate the outrage of the EU at the activities of Israel in July and August in particular but also the ongoing activities of the Israeli forces in the Gaza Strip. The conflict is in a period of cessation but Israeli forces are occupying parts of southern Lebanon.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">Cluster bombs and other weapons contrary to UN regulations and international agreements were used in this conflict. The people who must foot the bill for clearing the southern Lebanese territories of such weaponry, which targets civilians, are the Lebanese or the UN but not the Israelis. The motion calls on our Minister and the EU to forcibly put the point to the Israelis by withdrawing the preferential trade agreement until they agree to fully respect commitments given when they signed up to the preferential trade agreement with the EU.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DanWallace" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Deputy D. Wallace</from>
          <p eId="para_30">A previous motion was unanimously agreed by the committee. Events have overtaken the need for this motion. The Taoiseach, the Government and the Minister for Foreign Affairs have clearly outlined the Irish position on the situation in Lebanon and the attitude of the Israelis. The determination to deal with the issue and have it resolved is clear. In my opinion, it is not necessary to proceed with this motion because much progress has been made. The Minister should observe the situation on an ongoing basis on our behalf.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_31">Deputy Ó Snodaigh tabled a valuable motion. It is a pity the motion was not before us much earlier, which would have been the time to debate it and take a position. Since the motion was tabled, much water has passed under the bridge and many developments have taken place. A ceasefire was declared in Lebanon and United Nations troops are in place, with more on the way. Arrangements have been made by all sides in the conflict.</p>
          <p eId="para_32">In recent days, we heard a coalition government will be formed in Palestine between Hamas and Mr. Abbas of the PLO and Fatah and much progress has been made on that matter. I expect funds to Palestine which were not directed through the Hamas government will be channelled through the new coalition government. Will the Minister for Foreign Affairs comment on that? A breach of human rights occurred and the manner in which the Israeli Government invaded the sovereign state of Lebanon in retaliation for the abduction of two soldiers was completely unacceptable. Nevertheless, it would be best to note this motion and move on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RuairiQuinn" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Senator Quinn</from>
          <p eId="para_33">I understand why Deputy Ó Snodaigh tabled this motion a month or two ago but it will not help the situation to introduce it at this stage. I remember being asked in the United States to explain in a few minutes the situation in Northern Ireland. That occurred after the Good Friday Agreement was signed approximately five years ago and it was not easy to do. A number of people approached me afterwards to state they did not understand why the British were there and did not leave. I fear we are in danger of taking a similarly simplistic attitude to what happens in an extremely difficult situation in the Middle East.</p>
          <p eId="para_34">I am concerned the motion does not touch on the two kidnapped Israeli soldiers nor the fact that Hizbollah was supported by Iran and Syria. It does not refer to the fact that Israel left Lebanon of its own accord some years ago and that this attack came from Lebanon. A solution, namely the roadmap which includes the two-state solution, is on the table. That solution will not be easy to achieve, no more than it was easy to achieve a solution in Northern Ireland. A motion such as this, which is one-sided and does not bear any relationship to the balance which must be taken into account, was worthy of debate a month or two ago. However, it does not serve any useful purpose to debate it now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_35">I understand the points made by members on the motion. The motion accords with the statement made by the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs, which recommended that Ireland should raise the implementation of sanctions on Israel under the terms of Article 2 of the Euro-Med trade agreement at the next meeting of the Council of Ministers on the grounds of human rights abuse. As I noted in my introduction, this issue does not pertain only to Lebanon. Although progress has been made in that regard since the motion was first submitted in July and the situation has improved in Lebanon due to the ceasefire and the deployment of UNIFIL troops, I remind members of the ongoing abuses of human rights and the targeting of civilians and civilian infrastructure taking place in Palestine and, in particular, the Gaza Strip. In the past two and a half months, 47 children have been killed and 196 injured, along with four journalists who were injured during the same period. Ambulances travelling to help the injured have been obstructed during the course of this one-sided conflict. The motion before us deplores the abuses of human rights and other violations of international law committed by all sides. We hope to see success in the efforts to form a new coalition government in Palestine but such a government will not survive unless the seven Cabinet members and 41 Members of Parliament captured by the Israelis are released. Some of the activities of the Israeli forces in south Lebanon and the Palestinian State are aimed at perpetuating rather than addressing the conflict.</p>
          <p eId="para_36">We could consider a suspension of this motion but a similar suggestion was made when I made my original proposal during Ireland's EU Presidency because it was said that the motion would not be passed. In the meantime, however, the conflict has continued and anybody who examines the figures with regard to death and destruction will understand how one-sided it has been.</p>
          <p eId="para_37">Senator Quinn is correct that I did not address specific violations of human rights or the events leading up to the capture of the soldiers. Similarly, however, I did not rehearse the entire history of the Palestinian conflict because my motion pertains to the situation at hand. I did not mention the US or other international players, even though these countries are intertwined in the events taking place in the region. I want to ensure that Israel, which is party to an agreement with the European Union, is held to account for targeting civilians and killing UN soldiers because it seems that the Israelis are not being sanctioned for their actions.</p>
          <p eId="para_38">This matter will be discussed in the Dáil when we are asked to agree to the deployment of Irish soldiers to the region. Will Irish soldiers also be targeted by the Israelis in the event of a renewed outbreak of hostilities? That is the reason for my motion. I am not trying to simplify or solve the conflict but to ensure that the Israeli Government and others in the region understand that the EU will not stand idly by but has some clout in this region, in terms of the preferential trade agreement, and is willing to use it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_39">It is up to the Deputy as to how we proceed. As he is aware, the Minister will appear before the committee after this discussion and he can ask him these questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_40">I do not seem to have the backing of the committee, which is regrettable. I will not labour the point but will raise it with the Minister again. I would like the motion noted so it is on the record. If the conflict is sparked again on the scale witnessed in July and August, I will revisit it. I hope the committee will back me at that stage.</p>
          <p eId="para_41">If anybody is interested, there is a list of actions by the Israelis in Palestine on the website of the Palestinian Centre for Human Rights which has been acknowledged by the UN. It lists what is happening there which has been forgotten because the media focus was on Lebanon. The focus is now elsewhere and people seem to have forgotten about the potential for these conflicts to explode again in this region. Unless the world is willing to give as much help as possible and to be firm, we will have to revisit this motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_42">Is it agreed to note the motion? Agreed. We have been in discussion with the Embassy of Israel and the new ambassador to Ireland has agreed to appear before the committee in the near future to answer questions put by members. We will let the committee know about that.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">Sitting suspended at 11.22 a.m. and resumed at 11.24 a.m.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>General Affairs and External Relations Council: Ministerial Presentation.</heading>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_43">Item No. 2 on the agenda is a discussion with the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Dermot Ahern, on the forthcoming General Affairs and External Relations Council meeting. On behalf of the committee, I welcome the Minister and his officials from the Department of Foreign Affairs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DermotAhern" as="#Minister_for_Foreign_Affairs" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Minister for Foreign Affairs (Deputy D. Ahern)</from>
          <p eId="para_44">I thank the committee for giving me the opportunity to say a few words about the forthcoming meeting of the General Affairs and External Relations Council, GAERC.</p>
          <p eId="para_45">It has been a fairly busy summer break. There are major issues ahead of us on the agenda, even in the next couple of months. Between now and the German Presidency there will be some major issues including increased focus on the constitutional treaty, the question of enlargement as well as some of the issues that address us, particularly from a European-wide point of view, and also the energy issue. We look forward to working with the Finnish and German Presidencies in taking forward the debate on the future of Europe and in delivering to the people of Europe the benefits of concerted action at EU level.</p>
          <p eId="para_46">Friday's meeting in Brussels will be the second regular meeting of the Finnish Presidency. As the committee will be aware, it was necessary to meet in extraordinary session twice during August to take account of the events in the Middle East. We also had an opportunity to meet at Lappeenranta in Finland in formal session at the beginning of September and I pay tribute to the Finnish Presidency in that respect.</p>
          <p eId="para_47">The comprehensive external relations agenda begins with the western Balkans which will focus on Bosnia-Herzegovina, in view of the elections which will take place on 1 October, and on Montenegro where the elections took place on 10 September.</p>
          <p eId="para_48">Bosnia-Herzegovina has come a long way since the signature of the Dayton Agreement in 1995. The progress it has made was recognised by the EU last November when the Council authorised the Commission to open negotiations on the stabilisation and association agreement. Further progress will depend on how quickly it can adopt the necessary reforms to enable it to become a fully functioning and viable state. We are increasingly concerned within the Union that many of the key reforms in this regard have been delayed in 2006 and I expect that the Council will take the opportunity to urge the new parliament that they should take forward the reform process once it assembles following the October elections.</p>
          <p eId="para_49">On Montenegro, we await the report of the international election monitoring mission, which I hope will be in a position to pronounce the elections as free and fair. On that basis, I welcome the intention of the Commission to open a stabilisation and association agreement with Montenegro.</p>
          <p eId="para_50">The Council will also discuss recent developments in Sudan and Darfur. Our conclusions are expected to express strong concern about the recent severe deterioration of the security and humanitarian situation in Darfur, condemn reported attacks by the Sudanese Government and rebel groups, and stress that any attempt to take renewed military action will have a devastating humanitarian consequence and remove any prospect of achieving peace through implementation of the Darfur peace agreement.</p>
          <p eId="para_51">The Council is also expected to welcome the adoption on 31 August 2006 of the UN Security Council resolution, which authorised a UN peacekeeping operation in Darfur in principle and urged the Sudanese Government to consent to its deployment. The Government remains gravely concerned about the continuing humanitarian and political crisis in Darfur and welcomes the Security Council's decision to send a UN peacekeeping force to Darfur with a strong mandate to protect civilians and provision of security of the delivery of humanitarian assistance, but the consent of the government of Sudan remains vital if deployment is to proceed as planned. So far, despite some encouraging signs that I received on my visit to the region in July, it remains opposed. We will do all that we can in co-operation with our partners in the international community to exert pressure on the Sudanese Government.</p>
          <p eId="para_52">There is obviously a particular onus on Sudan's neighbours, on the African Union and on the permanent members of the Security Council. We fully support the rapid and full implementation of the Darfur peace agreement of May 2006, which provides a constructive basis for peace and reconciliation and urges non-signatories to adhere to it and to commit to its implementation. Blame for the situation rests with all of those who are reluctant to take the path of peace.</p>
          <p eId="para_53">At the Council I will again lay particular emphasis on the need for NGOs to be properly protected and facilitated in their vital work, something I did at the last meeting when we discussed the Darfur situation immediately after my return from the region. It is appalling and unacceptable and I saw for myself that the situation has become even more dangerous for them in recent times.</p>
          <p eId="para_54">The DRC will review the position following the presidential and parliamentary election of 30 July, which passed off relatively peacefully in an open and fair manner. That represents an important step in its democratic development, but it is regrettable that the progress has been marred by violent incidents. The EU and the international community need to maintain pressure on all parties in the DRC to avoid further recourse to violence. The EUFOR mission deployed in the DRC played an important role in stabilising the situation following the incidents in August. The Government also supports an extension of the UN MONUC peacekeeping mission when its mandate expires at the end of November.</p>
          <p eId="para_55">Most of the Council's time will be taken up by the Middle East situation, building on the meetings to which I referred earlier. The attempted attack on the American Embassy in Damascus earlier provides further evidence of the precarious situation across the region and of the determination of certain elements to destroy any prospect of a revival of the peace process. Over recent months, the Government has been very clear that there can be no military solutions to the crises in Lebanon and in the Occupied Palestinian Territories or to their underlying causes. The only way to provide for lasting peace and security for all the people of the region is through a comprehensive settlement, with a negotiated two-state solution to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict at its core.</p>
          <p eId="para_56">The tragic and unnecessary violence and destruction visited on the Lebanese, Palestinian and Israeli people provides clear evidence of the emptiness of unilateralism. At our detailed policy discussions during the informal Foreign Ministers meeting, it was clear that there is a strong consensus on this point among member states. I expect the Council to issue conclusions on the determination of the EU to play a leading role, with its international partners, in working to revive the Middle East peace process.</p>
          <p eId="para_57">The Union played a vital role in the achievement of a ceasefire in Lebanon. The nature of the conflict — the cynical initial attack on Israel by Hezbollah and the largely disproportionate Israeli military response — underlines the challenges facing the democratically elected government of Lebanon. The EU will be visible and consistent in its support for Prime Minister Siniora and his government as they work to rebuild their country after yet another war, to assert their authority and to protect Lebanon's territorial integrity.</p>
          <p eId="para_58">The Council will emphasise our commitment to the full implementation of Security Council Resolution 1701 and its strong support for the ongoing efforts of Secretary General Kofi Annan. We welcome the progress made in the deployment of the Lebanese army in southern Lebanon and the leading role being played by European troops in the new UNIFIL mission. A total of 3,500 UN troops are on the ground while it is expected that 5,000 international peacekeepers will be on the ground in the coming weeks and that the Israeli withdrawal should be complete at that point.</p>
          <p eId="para_59">The Government had an initial consideration of the situation in Lebanon at its meeting on 30 August. We are continuing to review the question of possible participation in the new UNIFIL mission. After initial uncertainty, greater clarity was achieved in regard to UNIFIL's rules of engagement and the objectives of the force, with Secretary General Annan making it clear a proactive role in disarmament is not envisaged. The commitment of significant numbers of troops by France, Italy and Spain, in particular, has created a framework within which an Irish contribution could be made. Against this background, the Defence Forces are consulting potential partners to see how Ireland might contribute in a meaningful way to UNIFIL II. The Defence Forces remain engaged in the detailed technical assessment and planning required for the Government to make a decision in due course. Key criteria will be the situation on the ground as it continues to develop and our capacity to play a useful role within the overall structure of the force. Under the triple lock, Dáil approval will be required for a deployment.</p>
          <p eId="para_60">Ireland has responded effectively and swiftly in response to the humanitarian crises in both Lebanon and Gaza and has committed a total of €4 million in additional funding. I welcome the lifting by Israel in recent days of the air and sea blockade on Lebanon. This is an important first step in facilitating the delivery of humanitarian aid and starting the process of economic recovery, but all sides must meet their obligations in the period ahead.</p>
          <p eId="para_61">One issue which has caused particular concern is the extensive use of cluster bombs in southern Lebanon, about which I spoke strongly previously. These pose a serious threat to the civilian population returning to their homes. It is essential that all parties co-operate fully with the UN to ensure that southern Lebanon is cleared of this danger. There is a serious moral responsibility on Israel now to do everything possible to ensure this happens without delay.</p>
          <p eId="para_62">Ireland has been to the fore internationally in expressing concern at the potentially indiscriminate nature of these weapons. Apart from the danger posed by unexploded cluster bombs after conflicts have ended, we believe that the international community also needs to address their use during conflicts, and in particular the dangers posed to civilians. Last week at discussions in Geneva under the framework of the Convention on Certain Conventional Weapons, on my instruction Ireland joined with five other delegations in calling for a specific mandate for negotiations to lead to "a legally binding instrument that addresses the humanitarian concerns posed by cluster munitions". We will pursue this initiative in the months ahead in co-operation with the other sponsors and with international civil society organisations.</p>
          <p eId="para_63">I expect that our discussions on the region on Friday will focus on the unresolved crisis in the Palestinian Territories and on developments in the formation of a Palestinian government of national unity. The situation in Gaza is now unsustainable. More than 200 people have been killed since the end of June, the humanitarian and economic crisis continues to deepen and there is virtually no freedom of movement in and out of the area for people or for goods. The first priority must be to end all violence from whatever source, achieve the release of the Israeli soldier captured over two months ago and ensure the reopening of border crossings.</p>
          <p eId="para_64">The EU is continuing to take the lead in the provision of assistance to the Palestinians. The temporary international mechanism to channel aid directly to the people is now in operation and the Council will extend its remit for a further three months to December. The level of Community assistance is now higher than in any of the past five years. Ireland's bilateral assistance will be higher in 2006 than it was last year but the humanitarian and financial crisis in the occupied territories will not be effectively addressed until Israel restores its transfers of tax and customs duties, which have been withheld since April, and until there is again a credible political process between the parties. The EU has a vital role to play in this regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_65">It is of course clear to all that the Quartet roadmap is now in abeyance but it is important to emphasise that the principles which it sets out are those on which a settlement must be based. In the weeks and months ahead the EU will work with the Israeli Government, with the Palestinians and with its regional and international partners to inject new momentum into the stalled political process. We will continue to emphasise very clearly the obligations on both sides under the roadmap and under international law. We want to see an early and substantive meeting between Prime Minister Olmert and President Abbas, as a first step towards the resumption of a credible process based on the essentials of the roadmap.</p>
          <p eId="para_66">The EU has strongly supported President Abbas in his negotiations with Hamas and the other parties for the formation of a national unity government. I warmly welcome his announcement yesterday that agreement has been reached, and that a new government will be formed in the coming days. This is potentially a hugely significant development. The EU and the Quartet have set out very clearly the principles on which we can work with any Palestinian government. However, we need to be pragmatic and imaginative in encouraging progress as it happens. I have already stated that if it is clear that the violence has stopped and if the government is committed to the negotiation of a two state solution I will argue very strongly for an appropriately positive EU response.</p>
          <p eId="para_67">The situation with Iran has entered a very delicate phase following its failure to abide by the Security Council's demand, that it suspend enrichment-related activities by 31 August. The five Permanent Members of the Security Council together with Germany are currently discussing next steps in light of Iran's failure to comply with the terms of Resolution 1696. High Representative Solana is engaged in discussions with Iranian officials regarding the reply from Iran on 22 August to the wide-ranging package of incentives presented last June. These discussions have reportedly been constructive and are expected to continue later this week. We will have an opportunity for a detailed briefing at the Council. I would continue to urge Iran to suspend enrichment-related activities as a confidence building measure so that detailed negotiations can begin. We all want to see a successful diplomatic solution to the current impasse, a solution which will respect the rights and interests of Iran while countering the threat of further nuclear proliferation. We believe that the package of incentives, which Europe took the lead in developing, has the potential to offer just such a solution but Iran has to be prepared to move also.</p>
          <p eId="para_68">The Council will also review developments in Iraq where the daily toll of death and destruction has reached horrific proportions. The European Union remains determined to give its full support to the national unity government which was approved by the Iraqi Parliament in May. Nobody underestimates the severity of the challenge it faces in securing the unity and prosperity of the country. For the EU the focus in the period ahead will be on working with the government to develop urgently its initial proposals for an international compact for Iraq. The idea of a compact, which the EU strongly supports, would involve greater international co-ordination in the provision of assistance for the reconstruction of the country in accordance with the government's own policy priorities.</p>
          <p eId="para_69">Under the heading "Any Other Business" Greece is expected to speak on the European Union's relationship with the Black Sea Economic Council, BSEC. It believes the EU should adopt a regional approach to the Black Sea states and favours closer EU co-operation with the BSEC to this end. Ireland would welcome such enhanced co-operation if it adds value to the activity already under way in the region.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_70">On the possible involvement of the Defence Forces in UNIFIL II in Lebanon, I assume from the Minister's comments that the chances of participation in the mission have improved. When does the Minister expect a decision to be announced? Potentially how many troops would be involved? On what criteria will a decision on participation in the mission be made?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DermotAhern" eId="spk_13" as="#Minister_for_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy D. Ahern</from>
          <p eId="para_71">As I indicated, the detailed assessment is being carried out by the Defence Forces. The position is now much clearer than it was when the United Nations made its initial call for a force for Lebanon. France, Italy and Spain have the core of a force in place and this will be built up over a short period. I indicated that, having considered the matter in conjunction with the advice it received from the Defence Forces, the Government believes an Irish force, if it fits in anywhere, would be relatively small. While I cannot indicate what numbers are being considered, in the context of our size and the fact that Ireland is already close to the limit of Defence Forces participation in overseas missions, with substantial forces already in place in the Balkans and Liberia, we would only consider participation in the second or third wave. The second wave will, it is hoped, be concluded by the end of October with the final phase completed at the end of November.</p>
          <p eId="para_72">What determines our consideration? Ultimately, the key issue is the safety of our troops. One of the reasons we are somewhat hopeful is that all our contacts on the ground indicate a desire on both sides to maintain the ceasefire. Obviously the fact that the ceasefire has held for so long will be another element in our decision on whether to participate in the mission.</p>
          <p eId="para_73">As members will be aware, Irish troops served in Lebanon for 23 years and it took a long time to get them out. We also suffered significant fatalities, among the highest of participating countries in proportion to size. The Government will have to weigh up all these issues and take into account whether a relatively small Irish force would validly fit within the requirement of the overall force. We must work with our partners and I understand from my colleague, the Minister for Defence, Deputy O'Dea, that discussions are taking place with some potential partners on how an Irish contribution, if required, could fit in. These discussions are ongoing. While I expect the Government will arrive at a clear view before November, I cannot give a precise date.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_74">When will the international election observers in Montenegro pronounce on whether the elections held recently in that country were free and fair?</p>
          <p eId="para_75">Before the Minister arrived, we were discussing the suspension of the Euro-Med association agreements, which is something I have raised in the past. This has been discussed because of Israel's violation of international law in Lebanon and in Palestine. Has that been considered? Would it be considered and will the Minister comment on it? There has been a huge amount of disruption in Lebanon and I welcome the aid announced recently, as well as the response of the EU. Israel is not being made to pay for the environmental damage caused due to its targeting of oil refineries. It is not being made to pay for the clean-up of unexploded ordnance. It is not being brought to account for the targeting of UN personnel or civilians. Even though the situation is calm at the moment, there is a major need to address the heightened tensions in the region. What does the Minister think the Council will do about the manoeuvrings of other states which have used this crisis to forward their own agenda, such as Israel, Syria or Iran?</p>
          <p eId="para_76">Given the announcement of a unity government in Palestine, does the Minister think that Israel should release Palestinian MPs and Ministers who have been held since the most recent outbreak of conflict? What steps are necessary to ensure that a Palestinian state becomes viable? It cannot continue to survive on hand-outs from the EU. It needs to be made economically viable if it is to have any chance in the future. Will the EU repeat its calls for the ports and the airports to be opened in Gaza? The EU should ask that the electricity supply be provided again.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DermotAhern" eId="spk_15" as="#Minister_for_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy D. Ahern</from>
          <p eId="para_77">The report on the elections in Montenegro should be available in the next couple of days.</p>
          <p eId="para_78">I saw the Deputy's proposed all-party motion, which is a regurgitation of a motion that was tabled during the conflict. The motion has been overtaken by recent events as we now have a ceasefire, albeit a very precarious ceasefire. As it is maintained, we will become more confident that it will be retained.</p>
          <p eId="para_79">I have heard the call that we should isolate Israel and not enter into continued dialogue with its government. That would be counterproductive in my view. Given the history of the Deputy's party, he should know that isolation is not the way to sort out difficult issues. I urge that we treat motions such as that proposed by the Deputy with some caution. We must consider whether it has a chance of getting past the EU. I suggest it does not have a snowball's chance in hell. Moreover, it would have a negative practical effect for the people of Palestine, whom most of us would try to protect, in particular from a humanitarian perspective. As the Deputy noted, if Palestine is ever to become a fully recognised state it must be viable, and the way in which the goods that enter Palestine will be correlated and dealt with will be through the Israel-EU trade agreement. There would be a negative impact on ordinary people in Palestine if we were to pass a motion which seeks to cut off EU trade links with Israel. It would be an empty gesture.</p>
          <p eId="para_80">I strongly agree with the Deputy's comment on the release of the imprisoned and captured Hamas leaders, members of parliament and members of government. As I have stated at EU meetings — this is the strong view of the broad brush of the EU — if we are to make any progress, this must happen. Equally, the captured Israeli prisoners should be released forthwith. We very much welcome the moves towards a national unity Government. I am on the record of this committee earlier this summer as stating that it was no coincidence the conflict in Lebanon began just as Hamas and President Abbas were coming to an understanding on a national unity government. That was derailed and put on the back-burner until very recently. I strongly welcome that it seems the national unity government will now be put in place.</p>
          <p eId="para_81">We will have to tread warily with regard to whether this is the type of government the international community can deal with in the normal way, and whether it is a government that fully recognises international rules and laws on human rights issues, the recognition of Israel and so on. However, it is an important step, which we welcome and have encouraged.</p>
          <p eId="para_82">There have been some misconceptions in this regard. I sometimes read newspaper reports which suggest it is terrible that the EU has turned off the tap to the Palestinian people. That is not the case. The EU has this year dramatically increased its aid, even given the difficulty of recognition and the difficult political situation in Palestine. The level of EU aid which was supposed to be dedicated to Palestine was in the region of €250 million but to date it is in the region of €330 million. It is not for want of assistance from the EU that the Palestinian people are suffering but because of the continued blockade by Israel and the withholding of tax and customs revenues by Israel, in regard to which the EU and I have called strongly on Israel to deliver what is due to the people of Palestine.</p>
          <p eId="para_83">The committee can take it that while we adopt a strong position on the need for Israel to move on these issues, at the same time we must be conscious that we can only deal with a government in Palestine on the basis that it recognises the principles set down in the roadmap. That must be a prerequisite because there will not be peace in that part of the world unless and until there is an acceptance of the two-state solution between Palestine and Israel.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DanWallace" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy D. Wallace</from>
          <p eId="para_84">I thank the Minister for appearing before the committee and making a presentation to it. While any single area of conflict could dominate the Minister's time at the Council meeting, I wish to refer to Darfur in Sudan, which the Minister has mentioned. Since the conflict erupted in 2003, the United Nations has estimated that more than 200,000 people have lost their lives, 2 million people have been displaced and more than 3 million people are in need of humanitarian aid. At present, a total of 1.6 million people cannot be reached owing to the fighting and direct targeting of humanitarian workers. Moreover, there is an estimated shortfall of almost $300 million in the sum needed by the United Nations to meet the ongoing needs in Darfur. If this money is not forthcoming within the next two to three months, a new emergency will arise in northern Darfur.</p>
          <p eId="para_85">I wish to refer to a number of reports that appeared during the weekend to the effect that the Sudanese Government is mobilising 25,000 troops to enter Darfur and to deal with the rebels. While that may be good, I note the camps will also be dealt with, which will be devastating for the people involved. Hence, I repeat my request to the Minister to keep Darfur to the fore at his meetings. Any topic from around the world could dominate and undoubtedly some of the other points raised earlier will do so. However, I make a strong appeal to the Minister. These people are helpless and it is terrible that humanitarian aid workers are not permitted to carry out their work, for which we have made provisions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DermotAhern" eId="spk_17" as="#Minister_for_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy D. Ahern</from>
          <p eId="para_86">I thank the Deputy for raising this issue, which is one of the greatest disasters facing the world. Unless the international community does something fairly quickly, the situation will deteriorate even further. While that was my view before I visited the region, it was copperfastened during my visit. I welcome the passing by the UN of a resolution in principle to set up a substantial force in Darfur. I visited the troops of the African Union mission in Sudan, AMIS, and spoke to its leading military personnel. It was clear they had been given an impossible task. While they stated their troop numbers came to approximately 7,500, I understand the figure is closer to less than 7,000. Darfur is 1.5 times the size of France, which puts the ability of 7,000 troops to do anything into perspective.</p>
          <p eId="para_87">I visited the largest camp in Darfur, which contains more than 50,000 people, and events there constitute a crime against humanity. Thankfully there is a substantial engagement by the UN and by non-governmental organisations. However, as I noted, the position of non-governmental organisations is becoming more precarious as time passes. While there, I met the Sudanese Foreign Minister, who is part of the more moderate wing of its government. He gave a fairly optimistic view as to whether the Sudanese Government would allow UN troops to enter.</p>
          <p eId="para_88">When I visited Ethiopia, I also met the chairman of the African Union in Addis Ababa and raised this issue with him. He had just come from a meeting of the African Union at which, he stated, considerable pressure had been placed on the Sudanese Government to allow a United Nations force to enter. However, as I noted on my return home, it would take some time for a UN force to be deployed. As a result of the pledging conference at which Ireland dedicated more resources, substantial financial resources will be made available to AMIS to beef up its troop numbers. The difficulty lies in the short term. In a number of months time, a UN force might go in if allowed by the Sudanese Government, but the critical period for the people of Sudan, particularly those in the camps, is the next six months to one year.</p>
          <p eId="para_89">I will raise this issue with the Sudanese Foreign Minister in New York when I attend the United Nations meeting. I will also raise it with the Chinese vice premier, whom I hope to meet in late September. The Deputy can rest assured that we are active in respect of this issue, given our history, the focus of our NGOs in this area and our visit to that area, which informed my thinking on the matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnnOrmonde" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Senator Ormonde</from>
          <p eId="para_90">I welcome the Minister and thank him for keeping the committee up to date regarding ongoing issues in the Middle East. I am concerned by the remaining cluster bombs in southern Lebanon. The Minister stated that he is entering negotiations to seek a mandate to remove the danger, but the timescale must be considered, as the disruption suffered by the civilian population trying to return home is a serious issue. I hope Ireland will play a considerable role in pressing the Israelis to remove this danger. The Minister has taken this matter on board and I would like to hear his comments in that regard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DermotAhern" eId="spk_19" as="#Minister_for_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy D. Ahern</from>
          <p eId="para_91">I welcome the Senator's comments and condemn the use by Israel of cluster bombs because their nature is to have an indiscriminate effect, particularly on civilians. Now that the ceasefire is in place and the Israelis have withdrawn, this is one of the sizable issues that must be dealt with by the Lebanese army, supported by UNIFIL and others. When we make our assessment of whether to send Irish troops, this issue will be to the fore.</p>
          <p eId="para_92">Last week in Geneva, we joined with five other delegations — Austria, the Holy See, Mexico, New Zealand and Sweden — in urging a specific mandate for negotiations under the framework of the Convention on Certain Conventional Weapons to have a legally binding instrument to address the humanitarian concerns posed by cluster bombs. This matter will be reviewed at the next review conference in November and, in conjunction with our co-sponsors, the International Committee of the Red Cross and the Cluster Munitions Coalition, the NGOs dealing with these matters, we hope to press the issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_93">I thank the Minister for appearing before the committee and speaking so candidly. The situation seems to have improved somewhat since our last meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_94">I will refer to a number of questions asked in the context of the General Affairs and External Relations Council. The conflict in Lebanon was sparked by the abduction of two Israeli soldiers. Will the Minister ask about the reasons behind a conflict of that magnitude whereby a sovereign state was invaded, civilians were indiscriminately bombed and cluster bombs were left behind? Why this disproportionate response? Is there any acknowledgement by the Israeli Government of ways of doing things without all-out war as a response to something that should not have happened? I welcome the lifting of the blockade, that UN troops are on the way and that Ireland has donated €4 million to the international community, which raised €1 billion.</p>
          <p eId="para_95">The Lebanese Prime Minister, Mr. Siniora, specifically stated that he would like to see an Irish element in the force. Owing to our other commitments, Ireland could send only a small number of troops, if it sends any. To some extent it would be symbolic but Ireland has expertise and experience because of our past decades of involvement. Does the Minister think it likely that an Irish force will be sent?</p>
          <p eId="para_96">Funding from the EU and the international community has not been channelled through the Palestine Government since the election of Hamas. In recognition of the Palestinian government of national unity, will the Minister raise the matter of channelling EU and other international funds directly through the government rather than bypassing the government, thereby undermining it?</p>
          <p eId="para_97">Does the Minister have an idea of the result of the elections that took place two days ago in Montenegro as distinct from the validity of the elections?</p>
          <p eId="para_98">More information has emerged about Guantanamo Bay and there have been admissions by the US authorities regarding prisons in EU countries. Countries identified as having been used for the imprisonment of people from Iraq on the way to the US are Bulgaria and Romania, two accession countries that will join the EU in January 2007. Can the Minister throw any light on this?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DermotAhern" eId="spk_21" as="#Minister_for_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy D. Ahern</from>
          <p eId="para_99">The Government would not send troops for symbolic reasons. It would send troops if they were required by the UN. Having been there for so many years Ireland has expertise such as geographic knowledge. Previously Ireland had a relatively large cohort within a small force in the area but this force will be much larger. The key question is whether a small number of Irish troops could fit into such a force. We are considering a number of options in conjunction with partners. We wish to be helpful and to assist. People such as the Lebanese Prime Minister would want us to be there. There is and always has been much goodwill towards the Irish in Lebanon because of our involvement for 23 years. We will make our decision in a calm and measured way with the full facts available to both the Government and the Oireachtas. Therefore, if our troops are killed at least we will have sent them in with full knowledge of what might happen.</p>
          <p eId="para_100">The channelling of money to the government of national unity will be one of the key issues to be discussed during the coming weeks. The temporary measure in place to channel money is not ideal. However, it is designed to provide EU money to assist the ordinary people of Palestine. No one in the Oireachtas or any other parliament in western Europe would be happy if European taxpayers' money was channelled into a government or state where strong suspicions existed that the money would be used for violence.</p>
          <p eId="para_101">We must be careful to ensure the money goes to the ordinary people of Palestine. On my first visit to meet the former Israeli Foreign Minister, he handed me a copy of the charter of Hamas, which clearly shows that the duty of anyone involved in Hamas is the destruction of Israel. From that perspective, one must not only understand Israel's point of view but also understand that if we assist people in Palestine it must be for humanitarian reasons only.</p>
          <p eId="para_102">I have no information on Guantanamo Bay other than press reports. These matters must be considered not only in the context of the countries mentioned but also the ongoing investigations into so-called "black sites". As we have stated on many occasions, we will not allow this country to be used in connection with either "black sites" or extraordinary rendition.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RuairiQuinn" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Senator Quinn</from>
          <p eId="para_103">I thank the Minister for his articulate explanation of what is happening in the Middle East. He touched on the tasks facing the EU during the coming year, particularly under the Finnish and German Presidencies. Is the treaty establishing a constitution for Europe up for discussion during the next six months? Will the matter be raised at the upcoming meeting? Is it confirmed that Romania and Bulgaria will join the EU on 1 January 2007? What is the position regarding Croatia and Turkey?</p>
          <p eId="para_104">During the past two months, the European Parliament passed a resolution on fair trade. One of the objectives is to make Africa more wealthy in order to avoid conflict there. That will not happen by giving alms but through providing an opportunity to participate in the world market. The recent WTO talks failed. Will the Minister give an insight on what is happening on that matter? The European Parliament made an interesting proposal that fair trade products should get preferential treatment in terms of import duties or VAT in the European market. Is this matter likely to be discussed at the upcoming meeting? Will it be high on the agenda during the coming months?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DermotAhern" eId="spk_23" as="#Minister_for_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy D. Ahern</from>
          <p eId="para_105">Our position on the constitution is clear. A draft constitution was agreed which was a compromise. I have seen reports of the proposals made by various EU leaders but I do not think they are feasible. The constitution has to be treated as an agreement which was hammered out after very detailed negotiations and cherrypicking it will result in grave difficulties. However, the matter will be discussed over the coming months and a strong push will be made during the German Presidency.</p>
          <p eId="para_106">No decision has been made on Romania and Bulgaria but we are assessing the situation in conjunction with our EU partners. To date, only Finland has indicated its willingness to permit citizens of the two states to immigrate without restrictions from day one. We have to consider the issue in terms of the dramatic figures on immigration to Ireland. There was surprise in the UK, where 500,000 people immigrated from the ten accession countries, yet at least 300,000 have come to Ireland. In Sweden, the only other country which allowed free access, the numbers of immigrants were in the region of 5,000. That indicates we have done more than any other member state for the new accession states. I have advised my colleagues at one of our informal meetings that it is up to other member states to break down their restrictions and they will have to do so anyway within a relatively short period of time.</p>
          <p eId="para_107">With regard to Turkey, progress on negotiations is slow and it is envisaged that the country will not be ready to join the EU for a considerable time to come. Due to the difficulties arising in respect of General Gotovina, Croatia's timeframe for accession has slipped somewhat. However, the issue will be the subject of further negotiation between Croatia and the EU.</p>
          <p eId="para_108">We are disappointed with the lack of movement by other blocs on the Doha Round of the WTO negotiations. I understand Senator Quinn's comments with regard to developing countries. We were insistent that the WTO negotiations had to be conducted in such a way that developing countries, and African countries in particular, should be given a fair deal on trade. At the same time, we must also look after the interests of Ireland and the developed world, in that some of the changes being pushed on us would have the effect of assisting large countries rather than the sub-Saharan countries we would like to target. Due to the impasse, we do not envisage much progress before the end of the year, which is unfortunate for the continent of Africa. However, we will continue to push as much we can for progress on the issue of fair trade for Africa.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusKirk" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Deputy Kirk</from>
          <p eId="para_109">I ask the Minister to enlarge upon the situation pertaining to Iran. It goes without saying that there are concerns with regard to the nuclear enrichment programme being pursued by the Iranians. As regards progress on the diplomatic front, obviously the UN Security Council is seriously concerned about it. At a European level, in terms of who is taking the lead role in this area, who has the best prospect of getting to the decision-makers in Iran? Perhaps the Minister will give us a brief outline of the position.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DermotAhern" eId="spk_25" as="#Minister_for_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy D. Ahern</from>
          <p eId="para_110">At the informal meeting in Lappeenranta last week, Javier Solana gave a full briefing to EU Foreign Ministers, including myself. There was some discussion. By and large, the member states were all in favour of the continuance of the EU three initiative in conjunction with other partners on the UN Security Council. The EU three comprise France, Germany and the UK.</p>
          <p eId="para_111">As members will know, a very substantial package of measures across a broad spectrum — economic, nuclear, etc. — was put to the Iranians in exchange for understandings that while we respect their right under the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty, NPT, to prosecute nuclear energy for civilian use, they would not use it for military purposes. As requested by the Iranians, that package of measures is secret. They gave an initial response on 22 August and have said there are still some issues to be dealt with.</p>
          <p eId="para_112">Javier Solana was delegated on behalf of the EU to meet the Iranians and he did so last week. I understand both sides said those meetings were productive and further meetings will be held next week. There is a view among a number of EU member states and outside the EU that Iran has been given more than enough time, that all it is doing is, in effect, playing cat and mouse with the international community and that it is dragging out negotiations while at the same time continuing to develop its nuclear capability for military purposes.</p>
          <p eId="para_113">We should continue with the diplomatic initiatives. I will meet Hans Blix when I leave this meeting in a couple of minutes and he is strongly of the view, which I share as somebody who represents a country with a very strong adherence to the NPT, that while we criticise some states for the proliferation of nuclear weapons, some of the countries which demand non-proliferation by other states do not disarm under the other side of the NPT. That is a point countries such as Ireland and others, including the country from which Hans Blix comes, Sweden, have articulated over the years and will continue to do so.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_114">I thank the Minister.</p>
          <p eId="para_115">The joint committee went into private session at 12.25 p.m. and adjourned at 12.35 p.m. until 2 p.m. on Wednesday, 27 September 2006.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
