<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2006-02-28/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2006-02-28/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2006-02-28" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/29/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2006-02-28/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2006-02-28/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2006-02-28" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2006-02-28/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2006-02-28/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None" showAs="Vol. None" eId="#vol_None"/>
          <oir:numberReference href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None/no/115" showAs="No. 115" eId="#no_115"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AengusOSnodaighSF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aengus-Ó-Snodaigh.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Aengus Ó Snodaigh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CharlieOConnorFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Charlie-O'Connor.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Charlie O'Connor"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FinianMcGrath" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Finian-McGrath.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Finian McGrath"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FrankFahey" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Frank-Fahey.D.1982-03-09" showAs="Frank Fahey"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="GeraldineFeeney" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Geraldine-Feeney.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Geraldine Feeney"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JimOKeeffe" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jim-O'Keeffe.D.1977-07-05" showAs="Jim O'Keeffe"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JimWalsh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jim-Walsh.S.1997-09-17" showAs="Jim Walsh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeCostelloLAB" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Costello.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Joe Costello"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MauriceCummins" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Maurice-Cummins.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Maurice Cummins"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="OllieWilkinsonFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ollie-Wilkinson.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Ollie Wilkinson"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanArdagh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Ardagh.D.1997-06-26" showAs="Seán Ardagh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanOFearghaillFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Ó-Fearghaíl.S.2000-06-09" showAs="Seán Ó Fearghaíl"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chair" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chair" showAs="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chairman" showAs="Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/justice__equality__law_reform" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM DHLÍ AGUS CEART, COMHIONANNAS, COSAINT AGUS CEARTA NA mBAN</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>JOINT COMMITTEE ON JUSTICE, EQUALITY, DEFENCE AND WOMEN’S RIGHTS</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2006-02-28">Dé Máirt, 28 Feabhra 2006</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2006-02-28">Tuesday, 28 February 2006</docDate>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 2.30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeCostelloLAB">
                Deputy J. Costello,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#OllieWilkinsonFF">
                Deputy O. Wilkinson,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#FinianMcGrath">
                Deputy F. McGrath,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#MauriceCummins">
                Senator M. Cummins,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#SeanOFearghaillFF">
                Deputy C. O'Connor,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#GeraldineFeeney">
                Senator G. Feeney,*
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#CharlieOConnorFF">
                Deputy S. Ó Fearghaíl,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#JimWalsh">
                Senator J. Walsh.
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#JimOKeeffe">
                Deputy J. O’Keeffe,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">*In the absence of Senator T. Kett.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#SeanArdagh">
   DEPUTY S. ARDAGH IN THE CHAIR.
  </person>
          </summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">The joint committee met in private session until 2.40 p.m.</summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>EU Council Decisions and Regulations: Motions.</heading>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_10">I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform, Deputy Fahey, and his officials to the meeting, the purpose of which is to consider four EU proposals which the two Houses have referred to the committee. It is proposed, with members' agreement, to consider the four motions together. Is that agreed? Agreed. After an initial presentation by the Minister of State, members may make opening statements and ask questions. Copies of the briefing notes supplied have been distributed to members. The speaking note has also been circulated.</p>
          <p eId="para_11">I invite the Minister of State to make his presentation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FrankFahey" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Deputy Fahey)</from>
          <p eId="para_12">I thank the joint committee for making the necessary time available to debate these important instruments in the context of the Oireachtas scrutiny mandated by Article 29.4.6° of Bunreacht na hÉireann. Although the committee has dealt with 20 instruments in the civil law area, I wish to recall that under Article 3 of the Fourth Protocol of the Treaty of Amsterdam, we have three months from the date a measure is presented pursuant to Title IV of the treaty establishing the European Community to notify the President of the Council of our wish to take part in the adoption and application of any proposed measure.</p>
          <p eId="para_13">The positive and timely exercise of the opt-in option is critical to our ability to influence the shape of future negotiations. It is seldom that everything in a Commission proposal accords fully with our aspirations and ideas but vigorous and effective participation in the negotiating process is the best way to secure the desired outcome. This frequently involves making common cause with other like-minded member states to maximise support for particular policy positions. Contacts of this nature are an essential aspect of the negotiation dynamic. By exercising our opt-in rights we make it clear that we are active and committed players in the EU legislative process.</p>
          <p eId="para_14">All of the substantive instruments before the committee are provided for in the Hague programme on strengthening freedom, security and justice in the European Union, which was endorsed by the European Council in 2004. A timetable for the presentation of these instruments was set down in the subsequent action plan which is intended to translate the Hague programme into specific and concrete measures. That timetable has been adhered to. Both the Hague programme and the action plan emphasise the importance that should attach to the broad area of civil law in light of its potential to impact on the daily lives of ordinary citizens. Emphasis is also placed on practical aspects of co-operation which aim to simplify the procedures for obtaining court judgments in other member states and to ensure that such judgments, once obtained, can be recognised and enforced throughout the EU with a minimum of formality and cost.</p>
          <p eId="para_15">Members will undoubtedly have noticed that the proposals under discussion are somewhat diverse in nature. In order to assist discussion, I will briefly outline the background to each of them in turn.</p>
          <p eId="para_16">The first proposal concerns the accession of the European Community to the Hague Conference on Private International Law. The Hague Conference has been a permanent intergovernmental organisation since 1955, although it first met in 1893. Its key objective is the progressive unification of the rules of private international law. In essence, this is that part of the law which comes into operation when a court is called upon to determine a case that involves a foreign element. Typically, this will arise where the parties to a case are resident in different countries. It will also arise where a case involves property which is located in another country. The conference works towards its objective by facilitating the drafting and negotiation of international conventions and also by monitoring the practical operation of such conventions. To date, some 37 conventions have been adopted and these range across a wide variety of subject matter such as child abduction, the service of documents, financial securities and choice of court agreements. A total of 65 states are members of the conference and this includes all member states of the European Union.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">It is not surprising that in recent years there has been an increasing overlap between the work of the conference and that which is ongoing within the EU in a variety of fields. Consequently, the Union, albeit in an observer capacity, has been playing an active role in the conference. There is a general consensus, on the part of both the Union and the Hague Conference members, that the interests of the conference would be best served if its relationship with the Union were to be placed on a more formal footing. This consensus has resulted in changes being proposed to the statute of the conference which will, in the event of those changes being approved, enable the Union to accede to the conference. Hitherto, only individual states have been able to become members of the conference.</p>
          <p eId="para_18">This willingness to modify the statute, which has remained unchanged since 1955, is seen as an important acknowledgement of the role which the Union, via its member states, has in respect of the work of the conference. For the changes in the statute to be effective, it is necessary that they be approved by two thirds of the Hague member states. A voting process is under way and it is envisaged that the outcome of this will be known by the end of March. Assuming a favourable outcome to the vote, a formal decision to admit the Union to the conference could well be taken in July.</p>
          <p eId="para_19">The accession decision before the committee was presented towards the end of last year in order to ensure that in the event of the statute being amended, the Union's instrument of accession can be deposited as soon as is practicable. That decision requires the assent of the European Parliament and will be adopted within the framework of the Justice and Home Affairs Council. There are no reasons that we should decline to participate in the decision which has been presented. Furthermore, in its role as a member of the Hague Conference, Ireland is, in any event, being called upon to vote in respect of the statute changes being proposed in order to facilitate Union accession. The second item for consideration by the committee concerns a proposal for a regulation on the law applicable to contractual obligations, more commonly referred to as Rome 1. This proposed regulation arises in the context of a general programme of measures in the field of judicial co-operation in civil matters having cross-border implications and which are necessary for the proper functioning of the internal market. Its essential purpose is to modernise certain aspects of the current Rome Convention, which is an intergovernmental agreement, and, in the context of that modernisation, to transform it into a Community instrument.</p>
          <p eId="para_20">Like the convention from which it takes its inspiration, the proposed regulation sets out rules that aim to determine which country's substantive law is to be applied by a court to contractual obligations in any situation involving a choice between the laws of different countries. Its presentation is a further step in developing a more coherent body of private international law rules within the Community on civil and commercial matters. That process is already well advanced with the adoption of the Brussels 1 regulation in 2000 which deals with jurisdiction matters and the pending adoption of the proposed Rome 2 regulation, which concerns the law applicable to non-contractual obligations.</p>
          <p eId="para_21">As regards the Rome Convention which is the precursor to this proposal, its ratification by Ireland was facilitated by the Contractual Obligations (Applicable Law) Act 1991. That Act also enabled Ireland to ratify a 1984 convention which provided for the accession of Greece to the Rome Convention. Ireland has signed but has not yet ratified the accession conventions of subsequent member states, including those of the ten new member states during our EU Presidency in April 2004. Should the proposed new regulation be adopted, it would of course be directly applicable and would not require primary legislation. From contacts with other Departments and legal sources, my Department is not aware of any particular impacts or difficulties since the 1991 Act came into force.</p>
          <p eId="para_22">The purpose of the Rome Convention was to have uniform choice-of-law rules on contracts, which would govern both the member states' relations <i>inter se</i> and relations with non-Community countries. The main benefit of the convention was that it raised the level of legal certainty in contractual cases involving an international element by making it easier to predict the law which would be applied to a case, thereby reducing the level of forum shopping in such cases.</p>
          <p eId="para_23">The basic rule of the proposed regulation is to be found in Article 3 and is in similar terms to that contained in the convention. It is that, subject to certain qualifications, parties are free to select the applicable law to govern a contract. In the absence of an express or implied choice, Article 4 of the proposed regulation provides that the contract shall be governed by the law of the country with which it is most closely connected.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">This proposal has been preceded by extensive consultations undertaken by the Commission involving government, business, consumer and other interests. Those consultations suggest there is significant support for the conversion of the Rome Convention into a regulation. The revised provisions modernising some of the rules will provide for improved clarity and precision, thus boosting certainty as to the law without introducing new elements which would substantially change the existing legal situation.</p>
          <p eId="para_25">No change in substantive Irish law in the area of contractual obligations will be effected through this draft regulation. We should be clear that it deals only with the choice of applicable law where a contractual dispute has arisen between parties, and both domestic and foreign elements are involved. Furthermore, given that the proposed regulation touches upon a broad range of business, consumer and employment issues, my Department will remain in close contact with the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment during the future negotiations on this instrument. The proposed regulation is subject to qualified majority voting. It is also subject to co-decision with the European Parliament.</p>
          <p eId="para_26">The third item for consideration is a proposed regulation on family maintenance matters which have a cross-member state dimension. The proposed regulation contains common rules on jurisdiction, applicable law, recognition and enforcement of decisions, and co-operation in matters relating to maintenance obligations. The purpose of the regulation is to eliminate obstacles which prevent the recovery of maintenance across member state borders within the European Union. It does not alter the way in which our courts deal with purely domestic Irish maintenance obligations. The entitlement of the Irish courts to make orders regarding the maintenance rights of dependent spouses and children protected under Irish law would not be affected in any way by the new proposals.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">The growing frequency of couples separating, combined with greater mobility of people within the EU, has resulted in more cross-border maintenance claims and disputes. Common minimum standards are proposed to apply to procedures relating to maintenance which will build confidence between the member states and allow for mutual recognition and enforcement of maintenance orders.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">The regulation aims to enable an individual seeking maintenance to obtain easily, quickly and generally free of charge, an enforcement order capable of circulation without obstacles in the European Union. It builds on and replaces the common rules for the recovery of maintenance already in place in the Brussels 1 regulation on jurisdiction and the recognition and enforcement of judgments in civil and commercial matters to which I referred earlier. The key jurisdiction rule in that regulation is that a case is usually brought in the member state where a person is domiciled. However, there are exceptions to this rule and in matters concerning maintenance obligations, there is a special rule whereby the case can be brought in the member state where the maintenance creditor is domiciled or habitually resident. This protection for the weaker party is continued in the proposed regulation.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">In Ireland, we already have in place mechanisms to deal with the enforcement of maintenance obligations which have an international dimension. The 1994 Maintenance Act provided for the establishment of a central authority to process maintenance orders received from abroad and to assist in the enforcement of Irish maintenance orders in other jurisdictions. This Act gives effect to the 1990 Rome and 1956 New York conventions on maintenance recovery. Both of these conventions require the establishment of a central transmitting and receiving agency to process requests for the enforcement of foreign maintenance orders. My Department's central authority for maintenance recovery acts as this central transmitting and receiving agency. However, it does not currently, nor will it, play a role in domestic maintenance cases.</p>
          <p eId="para_30">The proposed regulation contains a number of provisions providing for a range of co-operation activities among designated central authorities in all of the member states and I am sure that the experience gained hitherto by the Irish central authority under existing conventions will be very useful in terms of the future activity now being proposed. One final aspect of this proposal to which I should make reference concerns the fact, apparent from the somewhat unwieldy title of the instrument, that it does contain provisions dealing with applicable law. This is an aspect of the proposal to which particular attention will be paid during the negotiation process.</p>
          <p eId="para_31">The fourth proposal is a communication from the European Commission which calls on the Council to decide that measures relating to maintenance obligations, which would include the specific proposal just outlined, be adopted by the procedure laid down in Article 251 of the treaty establishing the European Community. Where measures are adopted on foot of that article, the co-decision procedure with the European Parliament applies as does qualified majority voting. This is the procedure which generally applies to measures within the field of judicial co-operation in civil matters. However, by way of exception, measures relating to family law are adopted unanimously by Council in consultation with Parliament.</p>
          <p eId="para_32">The Commission's view is that maintenance obligations are hybrid by nature, in that they are a family matter in origin but a pecuniary matter in implementation. For this reason the Commission considers that maintenance debts should be viewed like any other civil claim and its proposal to alter the legal basis for adoption of EU maintenance measures reflects this view. In this jurisdiction, maintenance is very much a family law matter and very often is dealt with in the context of divorce or separation proceedings. Under the Constitution and our family law, it is not possible for a court to grant a decree of divorce unless proper provision is made between the spouses. Maintenance cannot be viewed simply as a debt collecting issue but comes within the area of general family law. This is the position I propose taking at Council and know that other member states share this view.</p>
          <p eId="para_33">From the brief outline I have given on the proposals before us, the committee will appreciate the significant amount of activity in the civil law area within the Community. The growth of activity reflects a perception that the needs of civil society warrant increasing attention in order that the day-to-day problems which individuals confront in a cross-border context can be addressed fully. These problems arise in business and personal contexts.</p>
          <p eId="para_34">Against the background of the instruments with which we are dealing, I reiterate my view that it is important that Ireland respond positively by exercising our right to opt into all of the negotiations from an early stage to be in a position to influence the eventual outcome. I hope the committee will support this approach. I need hardly add that any points raised by members on the draft proposals will be noted and taken into account during the negotiating process. I look forward to comments and questions from members.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_35">I thank the Minister of State.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_36">I thank the Minister of State for his explanation and elaboration. I do not think anybody could object to any provision in the Hague programme that would strengthen freedom, security and justice in the European Union. An extension of co-operation in various areas of law would be welcome.</p>
          <p eId="para_37">In the context of the first proposal which concerns the accession of the European Community to the Hague Conference on Private International Law, will the Minister of State give some examples of how this will operate in practice where the persons involved are resident in a number of countries, move between countries or have businesses or family homes in different countries? Is it practical? Will there be sufficient central authority to take care of all of this? Is there a database? Where are the mechanisms to implement the proposal on a Europe-wide basis and with non-European countries?</p>
          <p eId="para_38">The second proposal concerns contractual obligations, the Rome 1 aspects of judicial co-operation in civil matters having cross-border application where it is necessary for the proper function of the Internal Market. This involves similar matters of a civil and commercial nature. The Minister of State gave some examples:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_39">We should be clear that it deals only with the choice of applicable law where a contractual dispute has arisen between parties and both domestic and foreign elements are involved. Furthermore, given that the proposed regulation touches upon a broad range of business, consumer and employment issues, my Department will remain in close contact with the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment during the future negotiations on this instrument.</p>
          <p eId="para_40">To what extent does this have nuances of the EU social directive? How will it operate in terms of cross-border activity between member states? What will be the impact on employment issues, in particular?</p>
          <p eId="para_41">I am not clear on how there can be family maintenance while not playing a role in domestic maintenance cases. Does the Minister of State suggest a separation between domestic maintenance and family maintenance issues? Obviously, there are divorce and separation. However, there are also matters of support in terms of domestic maintenance. They all come under the broad heading of family matters. How will the measure operate in general and in terms of maintenance, considering that the laws of each member state can be so varied? The supports available and the law regarding family matters must be an absolute minefield, given the variations from one member state to the next. Implementing a maintenance system would be extremely problematic. It is difficult enough to implement such a system in this jurisdiction. While it is a desirable proposition, it appears that it would be extremely difficult to implement it, other than in high profile cases.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_42">I have a number of questions and concerns regarding two of the proposals. While some of the cases might be desirable, I do not understand why we should create an additional vote that might be used against us in the future. We are encouraging the conference to take on board the Union as another voting partner in the Hague Conference. Ireland is already a member of the conference. What would happen in the event that we opposed a measure after encouraging another group, which might take a different view, to join? This group might strengthen the measure to which we were opposed, particularly in light of the fact that Ireland is a small country.</p>
          <p eId="para_43">The Union has been in attendance at the Hague Conference, although I am not sure whether this has been in the capacity of an adviser or observer. I do not see the point of rushing to make the entire Union another voting partner or participant in the conference unless it is part of a move towards eventually allowing it to be the singular voice, which is increasingly the case. This is in terms of the changes that would be brought about by allowing the Union to join the conference.</p>
          <p eId="para_44">The second proposal is fairly reasonable. The Minister of State indicated that Ireland signed but did not ratify the accession conventions of subsequent member states, including the ten new EU member states, during the EU Presidency. Will he explain why Ireland has not ratified these conventions? When will they be ratified? If they are ratified after 1 January 2007, will Ireland attempt to ensure that the two states which will have joined the EU by then are included in the conventions we must sign? I am concerned about what will happen if we do not ratify the conventions as soon as possible.</p>
          <p eId="para_45">The third proposal is also reasonable. The recovery of maintenance payments for children should be made as easy as possible. The Minister of State mentioned that the regulation aims to enable individuals seeking maintenance to obtain an enforceable order easily, quickly and, in general, free of charge. What countries do not allow individuals to obtain enforceable orders free of charge? Has there been any move to make such orders free of charge?</p>
          <p eId="para_46">The Minister of State mentioned that maintenance is generally free of charge. Member states obviously have different ways of dealing with such matters. Is there any move to ensure all member states will have access to individuals to ensure they are not charged when making maintenance orders?</p>
          <p eId="para_47">I am opposed to the last proposal, which is part of a wider trend involving a shift in the decision-making process within the EU. This was evident among the Dutch delegation when discussions on the EU constitution were taking place in France. It was one of the reasons the proposal was defeated. In this case, the shift involves decisions in more and more areas being made unanimously by the Council, in consultation with the European Parliament. There is a shift towards qualified majority voting by the Council and the European Parliament. Our preference in the area of justice and home affairs, in particular, is that the Council should act in unison rather than in opposition to it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldineFeeney" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Senator Feeney</from>
          <p eId="para_48">I welcome the Minister of State and thank him for outlining an intricate legal piece of information. I would like to ask for his views on a broader issue. I am aware of several Irish people who are married to people who come from countries that have not signed up to the Hague agreement, mainly from the USA. Even though the marriages have broken down and Irish spouses have come back to this jurisdiction with their children, they have been ordered to return to the US because we are signatories to the Hague agreement to which we must adhere. These people have fought very expensive legal battles in this country with no aid from the Irish Government. They had to fund the cost of the legal cases themselves, while their American spouses got free legal aid of the highest standard.</p>
          <p eId="para_49">I am referring to just one case, even though I know of several such cases. The woman involved went back to America, as she was obliged to do under the Hague agreement. When she did so, she had to fund a court case in America to get a barring order against her spouse in order to keep him away from the home and her two young children. This person feels very aggrieved. As an Irish citizen, she would like to come back to this country where she has family and where she would have support to rear her two children. However, her husband, who has no contact with her at this stage, will not allow her to do so for some sinister reason.</p>
          <p eId="para_50">I would like the Minister's view on the issue. Will this always be the case and will Irish citizens always feel victimised? While the matter is not related to what we are discussing today, perhaps the Minister will reply.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Senator Cummins</from>
          <p eId="para_51">On the Hague Conference, why did the Community have just observer status up to now? Was there a reason for this and why has it changed? While it is agreed that we have no reason to decline the position, why did the Community have just observer status up to now?</p>
          <p eId="para_52">In regard to Rome 1, the Minister of State said there was extensive consultation and broad agreement from the parties involved. Who was involved in the consultation process? Did it include some who did not believe we should go along with it, or was there total agreement? I agree with the Minister of State's comments on family law and maintenance that the two are inextricably linked.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimWalsh" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Senator J. Walsh</from>
          <p eId="para_53">The Minister of State informs us that the contractual obligations will set out the situation in regard to the laws of the different countries. However, most contracts of this nature now stipulate clearly which state's laws will apply in the event of a dispute. Contracts drawn up in this State, for example, generally specify that the laws of the Republic apply. The second paragraph on page 6 states that "subject to certain qualifications, parties are free to select the applicable law". Does this qualification impinge in any way on a contract which clearly specifies which state's laws will apply in the event of a dispute, or does it apply only where there is no such condition within the contract?</p>
          <p eId="para_54">Is there an attempt within the European Union to harmonise property laws, particularly those governing ownership and contracts of sale? Many interjurisdictional purchases are made by Irish people and those of other nationalities in various states within the European Union. We should try to move in the direction of having a reasonably uniform provision for issues of property ownership and sale.</p>
          <p eId="para_55">The Minister of State has mentioned that emphasis will be placed on practical aspects of co-operation for the purposes of simplifying procedures and that any such judgments will be recognised with a minimum of formality and cost. In some jurisdictions — Ireland being a prime example — legal costs are prohibitive. This serves to exclude large sections of the population from the civil law process simply because they cannot afford the risk of undertaking cases. We have heard much recently about the services directive, eastern European immigrants and job displacement. Is an attempt being made within the Department to get lawyers from other jurisdictions to practise here in order that we might inject competition into the legal system? This would allow us to achieve what should be an objective of any republic, equal opportunity of access before the law.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_56">I have one question in regard to foreign adoptions. In the recent judgment in the case of Tristan Dowse, the judge insisted that maintenance should be paid by adoptive parents in the circumstances of the case. Will the issues under discussion today bring us closer to full implementation and acceptance of the Hague Convention on Intercountry Adoptions in the State?</p>
          <p eId="para_57">Many questions have been put to the Minister of State and I do not expect him to respond to each individually. The committee will appreciate it if he deals with the generality of the issues raised.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FrankFahey" eId="spk_10" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Fahey</from>
          <p eId="para_58">I did not have much time to prepare for this meeting but will deal with the questions as well as I can.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_59">We understand.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FrankFahey" eId="spk_12" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Fahey</from>
          <p eId="para_60">Deputy Costello asked what would be achieved by member states as a result of the proposed regulation. Some of the rules are being modernised to provide greater clarity and precision and enhance the certainty of the law without introducing new elements that would substantially change existing law. The essence of the regulation is contained in Article 3, which is similar to the rule in the convention that, subject to certain qualifications, parties are free to select the applicable law to govern a contract. In the absence of an express or implied choice, Article 4 of the proposed regulation provides that the contract should be governed by the law of the country to which it is most closely connected.</p>
          <p eId="para_61">Deputy Costello also asked about the impact on cross-border property matters. The accession will not have any impact on such matters because the EU has no competence at present over property ownership, which will continue to be a matter for the member states. There will be no impact on the services directive, which is an entirely separate issue. There will be no impact on the domestic situation pertaining to family maintenance or cross-border recovery because national rules will continue to prevail. The new directive will, however, afford much greater clarity and ease of operation for people attempting to claim maintenance in the international arena and the convention will certainly help Irish people in this regard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_62">Is there a clearing house system in place?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FrankFahey" eId="spk_14" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Fahey</from>
          <p eId="para_63">Yes, and it will be further enhanced as a result of this regulation. Our clearing house supports people who are seeking maintenance. The convention will apply in both directions and will improve the ability of people to claim maintenance in foreign countries.</p>
          <p eId="para_64">Deputy Ó Snodaigh asked if it would create an additional vote that may be used against us and whether the EU was developing a single voice. That is essentially what will happen as part of this process of modernisation.</p>
          <p eId="para_65">Senators Jim Walsh and Cummins asked about the membership of the conference. For the first time it will be open to regional economic integration organisations. Until now and other than individual countries, the United States was the only participant. This development means other regional economic organisations such as the European Union can be the voice of their member states. This will lead to greater clarity on issues of international law. There may be a misunderstanding on the issue raised by Senator Feeney. A reciprocal agreement between Ireland and the United States on maintenance issues has been in place since 1996. In other areas such as child abduction a similar agreement may not be in place. This may be to what the Senator refers. I understand that while the maintenance agreement between the United States and Ireland works well, the issue of child abduction is not covered in it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldineFeeney" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Senator Feeney</from>
          <p eId="para_66">Perhaps the woman concerned did not believe she was abducting her children in bringing them home. I will take up this point with the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FrankFahey" eId="spk_16" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Fahey</from>
          <p eId="para_67">The issue of foreign lawyers practising here, raised by Senator Walsh, may be addressed by the services directive being developed in Brussels and on which the Council of Ministers will have discussions in the coming months. This issue is the responsibility of the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, not one for this debate.</p>
          <p eId="para_68">On the Chairman's question about foreign adoptions and the application of the Hague Convention, the Minister of State with responsibility for children, Deputy Brian Lenihan, is preparing legislation in order that foreign adoptions can be ratified under the convention.</p>
          <p eId="para_69">Deputy Ó Snodaigh raised the matter of voting. Increasingly, the Hague Convention is striving to work on the basis of consensus. Therefore, the question of who casts a vote is unlikely to arise. In the extremely unlikely event that a vote was required, the Community or the member state in question would have voting responsibilities, depending on where the balance of competence lay. Given that Community competence is usually shared with member states, practical arrangements for voting are likely to be dealt with on a case by case basis. Our domestic arrangements on maintenance issues are not affected by this development.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_70">That concludes our discussion. I thank the Minister of State and his officials for attending. Is it agreed that there will be no further debate by Dáil Éireann and Seanad Éireann on the matter? Agreed. Is the draft report agreed, subject to inserting details regarding attendance and contributions to the debate? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Messages to Dáil and Seanad.</heading>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_71">Under Standing Order 85, the following message will be sent to the Dáil:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_72">The Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women's Rights has completed its consideration of the following motions:</p>
          <p class="indent_3" eId="para_73">That Dáil Éireann approve, in accordance with Article 29.4.6° of Bunreacht na hÉireann, the exercise by the State of the option, provided by Article 3 of the Fourth Protocol set out in the Treaty of Amsterdam, to notify the President of the Council of the European Union that it wishes to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:</p>
          <p class="indent_4" eId="para_74">a proposal for a Council decision on the accession of the European Community to the Hague Conference on Private International Law,</p>
          <p class="indent_3" eId="para_75">a copy of which proposed measure was laid before Dáil Éireann on 5 January 2006.</p>
          <p class="indent_3" eId="para_76">That Dáil Éireann approve, in accordance with Article 29.4.6° Bunreacht na hÉireann, the exercise by the State of the option, provided by Article 3 of the Fourth Protocol set out in the Treaty of Amsterdam, to notify the President of the Council of the European Union that it wishes to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measures:</p>
          <p class="indent_4" eId="para_77">(i) a proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and the Council on the law applicable to contractual obligations (Rome 1),</p>
          <p class="indent_4" eId="para_78">(ii) a proposal for a Council regulation on jurisdiction, applicable law, recognition and enforcement of decisions and co-operation in matters relating to maintenance obligations,</p>
          <p class="indent_3" eId="para_79">copies of which proposed measures were laid before Dáil Éireann on 12 January 2006; and</p>
          <p class="indent_4" eId="para_80">(iii) a proposal for a Council decision annexed to the communication from the commission to the Council calling on the Council to provide for measures relating to maintenance obligations taken under Article 65 of the treaty establishing the European Community to be governed by the procedure laid down in Article 251 of that treaty,</p>
          <p class="indent_3" eId="para_81">a copy of which proposed measure was laid before Dáil Éireann on 24 January 2006.</p>
          <p eId="para_82">Under Standing Order 67, the following message will be sent to the Seanad:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_83">The Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women's Rights has completed its consideration of the following motions:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_84">That Seanad Éireann approve, in accordance with Article 29.4.6° of Bunreacht na hÉireann, the exercise by the State of the option, provided by Article 3 of the Fourth Protocol set out in the Treaty of Amsterdam, to notify the President of the Council of the European Union that it wishes to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:</p>
          <p class="indent_3" eId="para_85">a proposal for a Council decision on the accession of the European Community to the Hague Conference on Private International Law,</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_86">a copy of which proposed measure was laid before Seanad Éireann on 5 January 2006.</p>
          <p class="indent_3" eId="para_87">That Seanad Éireann approve, in accordance with Article 29.4.6° Bunreacht na hÉireann, the exercise by the State of the option, provided by Article 3 of the Fourth Protocol set out in the Treaty of Amsterdam, to notify the President of the Council of the European Union that it wishes to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measures:</p>
          <p class="indent_4" eId="para_88">(i) a proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and the Council on the law applicable to contractual obligations (Rome 1),</p>
          <p class="indent_4" eId="para_89">(ii) a proposal for a Council regulation on jurisdiction, applicable law, recognition and enforcement of decisions and co-operation in matters relating to maintenance obligations,</p>
          <p class="indent_3" eId="para_90">copies of which proposed measures were laid before Seanad Éireann on 12 January 2006; and</p>
          <p class="indent_4" eId="para_91">(iii) a proposal for a Council decision annexed to the communication from the commission to the Council calling on the Council to provide for measures relating to maintenance obligations taken under Article 65 of the treaty establishing the European Community to be governed by the procedure laid down in Article 251 of that treaty,</p>
          <p class="indent_3" eId="para_92">a copy of which proposed measure was laid before Seanad Éireann on 24 January 2006.</p>
          <p eId="para_93">The joint committee adjourned at 3.25 p.m. <i>sine die.</i>
                    </p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
