<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2003-11-11/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2003-11-11/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2003-11-11" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/29/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2003-11-11/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2003-11-11/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2003-11-11" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2003-11-11/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2003-11-11/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference showAs="Vol. 1" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/1" eId="#vol_1"/>
          <oir:numberReference showAs="No. 38" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/1/no/38" eId="#no_38"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AengusOSnodaighSF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aengus-Ó-Snodaigh.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Aengus Ó Snodaigh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BreedaMoynihanCronin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Breeda-Moynihan-Cronin.D.1992-12-14" showAs="Breeda Moynihan-Cronin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CharlieOConnorFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Charlie-O'Connor.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Charlie O'Connor"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FinianMcGrath" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Finian-McGrath.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Finian McGrath"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeCostelloLAB" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Costello.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Joe Costello"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnDeasyFG" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Deasy.D.2002-06-06" showAs="John Deasy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MarianHarkinIND" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Marian-Harkin.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Marian Harkin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MarieHoctorFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Máire-Hoctor.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Máire Hoctor"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelMcDowellPD" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-McDowell.D.1987-03-10" showAs="Michael McDowell"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="OlwynEnrightFG" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Olwyn-Enright.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Olwyn Enright"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PeterPowerFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Peter-Power.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Peter Power"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanArdagh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Ardagh.D.1997-06-26" showAs="Seán Ardagh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SheilaTerry" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Sheila-Terry.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Sheila Terry"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TonyKett" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Tony-Kett.S.1997-09-17" showAs="Tony Kett"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chair" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chair" showAs="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chairman" showAs="Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister/justice__equality__law_reform" showAs="Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>COMHCHOISTE UM DHLÍ AGUS CEART, COMHIONANNAS, COSAINT AGUS CEARTA NA mBAN</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>JOINT COMMITTEE ON JUSTICE, EQUALITY, DEFENCE AND WOMEN’S RIGHTS</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2003-11-11">Dé Máirt, 11 Samhain 2003</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2003-11-11">Tuesday, 11 November 2003</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="volume">
        <docNumber refersTo="#vol_1">Vol. 1</docNumber>
      </block>
      <block name="number">
        <docNumber refersTo="#no_38">No. 38</docNumber>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 3 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">Members Present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeCostelloLAB">Deputy J. Costello,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#CharlieOConnorFF">Deputy C. O’Connor,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#MarieHoctorFF">Deputy M. Hoctor,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#PeterPowerFF">Deputy P. Power,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#FinianMcGrath">Deputy F. McGrath,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#TonyKett">Senator T. Kett,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#BreedaMoynihanCronin">Deputy B. Moynihan-Cronin,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#SheilaTerry">Senator S. Terry.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">In attendance: Deputies J. Deasy, O. Enright, M. Harkin and A. Ó Snodaigh.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#SeanArdagh">
   DEPUTY S. ARDAGH in the chair.
  </person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>CEDAW Convention: Presentation.</heading>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_9">I welcome members to the meeting. We will be discussing with representatives of the Women's Human Rights Project the report of the Irish Government to the United Nations on the CEDAW convention.</p>
          <p eId="para_10">I welcome Ms Noirín Clancy, the project co-ordinator of the Women's Human Rights Project, Dr. Joanna McMinn and Ms Maeve Taylor of the Women's Human Rights Project. The purpose of this meeting is to discuss the concerns of the Women's Human Rights Project about the official Government report to the CEDAW committee on the elimination of all forms of discrimination against women. Members have been circulated with background material and the presentation document. I invite Dr. McMinn to make the presentation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Dr. Joanna McMinn</from>
          <p eId="para_11">Good afternoon. My name is Joanna McMinn. I am the director of the National Women's Council which is one of the members of the Women's Human Rights Project. The Women's Human Rights Project is made up of 13 organisations which have come together on a common platform to promote and fulfil women's human rights.</p>
          <p eId="para_12">We have distributed background information and our presentation will highlight the main points in that information. On my left is Maeve Taylor, who is a training and development officer in Banulacht. She will give a brief background on women's human rights and an overview of the convention on the elimination of all forms of discrimination against women, CEDAW. Noirín Clancy, on my right, who is co-ordinator of the Women's Human Rights Project, will outline the shadow report and highlight our concerns about the Government's fourth and fifth report to the CEDAW committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Ms Maeve Taylor</from>
          <p eId="para_13">Good afternoon. I thank the members for the opportunity to address the committee. I will begin by reading a quote from the Vienna declaration on human rights.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_14">Can we release the submission to the committee to the press?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Ms Taylor</from>
          <p eId="para_15">Yes. I will begin by quoting from the Vienna declaration on human rights which was signed by the international community in 1993. It states:</p>
          <p eId="para_16">The human rights of women and the girl child are an alienable, integral and indivisible part of universal human rights. The full and equal participation of women in political, civil, economic, social and cultural life at the national, regional and international level, and the eradication of all forms of discrimination on grounds of sex, are priority objectives of the international community.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">Women's human rights are of paramount importance since there is no country where women enjoy human rights equally with men.</p>
          <p eId="para_18">The Women's Human Rights Project has come together out of a recognition of the systemic and systematic discrimination against women which has resulted in deep patterns of inequality and disadvantage for women, with women disproportionately affected by poverty and social marginalisation. Women also face a range of additional barriers, such as the disproportionate burden of reproductive and care-giving work; segregated employment practices; discriminatory, traditional and cultural laws and practices; lack of information and services in the areas of family planning and reproductive health, the unequal representation of women in political and other decision making structures at all levels and widespread violence against women in all societies.</p>
          <p eId="para_19">In addition, many women experience multiple barriers in gaining access to rights to employment, housing, land, food and social security. The Women's Human Rights Project, as Dr. Joanna McMinn said, is a platform of 13 organisations which have recognised the need to form an independent organisation in Ireland, an independent voice for women's human rights to promote recognition of women's rights as human rights and to lobby for the implementation and fulfilment of women's human rights in Ireland.</p>
          <p eId="para_20">The Women's Human Rights Project which is funded under the equality for women measure through the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform focuses on the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women. This convention, known as CEDAW, was ratified by Ireland in 1985. Since then Ireland has had an obligation to report to the UN Committee on the Elimination of all Forms of Discrimination against Women and to report on Ireland's progress in the implementation of women's human rights. To avoid confusion the acronym CEDAW refers to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women, which is the international treaty drafted in 1979 and ratified by Ireland in 1985, and to the Committee on the Elimination of all Forms of Discrimination against Women, which is a United Nations committee of 23 experts elected by the United Nations at a special sitting of the General Assembly. The role of this committee is to oversee and monitor implementation worldwide of the CEDAW convention, to receive reports from countries, which are signatories to the convention, and to comment on them and make their own progress reports. The CEDAW committee makes general recommendations, which elaborate and elucidate on the principles in the CEDAW convention.</p>
          <p eId="para_21">The CEDAW convention is unique in international human rights law. It is the central and most comprehensive international law document on women's rights. It does not add to the list of rights in other treaties but it aims to change and challenge the system within which women's rights are violated. It is intended to be transformative. It contains a wide ranging definition of discrimination and forbids intentional and unintentional discrimination based on sex and recognises the role of structural discrimination, in other words, the kinds of discrimination which are embedded in the systems and structures and cultures of states. It recognises the role of structural discrimination in preventing women from fully enjoying their human rights.</p>
          <p eId="para_22">The convention obliges states to pro-actively adopt policies and measures to remove obstacles to women's enjoyment of their human rights. There is a strong recognition in the CEDAW convention that removal of legal barriers is not enough to bring about equality for women. While an equal opportunities approach is necessary to begin to create the conditions for equality, specific measures are required to remove the barriers and obstacles to women's full enjoyment of their human rights. For example, article 3 of the convention places a duty on states in all fields to take all appropriate measures to ensure the full development and advancement of women for the purpose of guaranteeing them human rights on a basis of equality with men.</p>
          <p eId="para_23">CEDAW recognises the importance of culture and tradition in shaping the thinking and behaviour of men and women and the significant part they play in restricting the exercise of basic rights by women. Article 5 of the convention addresses the way in which sex role stereotypes and traditional customs and practices can contribute to discriminate against women and prevent them from achieving equality.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">Under article 1 of the convention, the United Nations CEDAW committee has the power to make general recommendations. Since 1990 it has issued four recommendations on violence against women, equality in marriage and family life, political and public life and health. The recommendations strongly suggest the need for special measures to be taken by states governments to advance equality and that in reporting to the committee it is necessary for states to include the targets they are trying to achieve in their national policies, the resources directed to bring about equality for women and the indicators used to measure the impact of those policies.</p>
          <p eId="para_25">The Government will present its report at the next meeting of the CEDAW committee at the United Nations. The Women's Human Rights Project has been co-ordinating the production of a shadow report which challenges the Government's official report. My colleague, Ms Clancy, will give an outline of the shadow report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Ms Noirín Clancy</from>
          <p eId="para_26">I shall outline the process involved in drawing up the alternative or shadow report to the CEDAW committee and highlight some of our concerns on the content of the Government's report to the CEDAW committee. We carried out a survey among women's groups throughout the country to ascertain what they saw as the priority issues that should be included in the shadow report. Four key areas emerged - political representation, violence against women, health and the barriers to education and employment. When the Government's report was published we organised regional workshops around the country in Limerick, Athlone, Sligo, Galway and Dublin, at which women were given an opportunity to comment on what the report was saying on the above four key areas. These workshops gave women's groups an opportunity to feed into the shadow report, ensuring their voices would be heard at UN level. We have also conducted consultations with key organisations. The process is ongoing. By the end of December we hope to complete the shadow report and in the new year to submit it to the UN CEDAW committee in New York.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">We welcome the report and the positive measures which have been undertaken by the Government in regard to combating discrimination against women, one of which is the equality for women programme administered by the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform and which funds our own project as well as over 70 projects throughout the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">For the purposes of this meeting I shall highlight some of the key issues in regard to the four areas mentioned. In regard to political representation, I am disappointed that in the Government's report there is no examination of the barriers prohibiting women from entering politics, whether at local or national levels, such as the inhibitive male culture, the extremely family unfriendly working practices, lack of supports, such as training and child care, and no cre×che in the Dáil. Women's groups ask where is the political will or leadership to address these obstacles given that they do not merit any discussion in the report.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">In the Government's report the issue of violence against women is entitled "Domestic Violence". The Government needs to get the definition right. Violence against women is not just about domestic violence; it is about rape, sexual assault in the workplace and trafficking in prostitution. Apart from the need for more public awareness of the problem and increased resources, a key problem highlighted over and over again at our workshops throughout the country is that of the Judiciary and the complete lack of consistency in how judges approach violence against women. Less than 6% of domestic violence perpetrators receive a prison sentence. When the Government was last interviewed by the CEDAW committee it emphasised the need for gender sensitive training for the Judiciary. Women ask why such training is not a condition of employment for judges and legal professionals at all levels.</p>
          <p eId="para_30">On the issue of health, a huge concern among women throughout the country is the lack of progress in cancer screening programmes. The rolling out of these programmes has been very slow and women's groups want to see them nationwide. Women ask when there will be an expansion of these essential screening programmes. Reproductive rights are also highlighted as major concerns. The fact that the abortion issue has not yet been resolved continues to have significant consequences for women's health. The Irish Family Planning Association estimates that over 6,000 women travel to the United Kingdom each year to seek abortions. The rate of late abortions is higher among Irish women. There is unequal access to abortion, depending on women's socio-economic circumstances.</p>
          <p eId="para_31">The CEDAW committee urged the Government to facilitate a national dialogue on reproductive rights, including this country's restrictive abortion laws. The Government has never put a proposal to the people to vote for a liberalisation of the abortion laws. This issue cannot be separated from the need for increased resources for information and education about family planning services, particularly for young women and people in rural areas.</p>
          <p eId="para_32">The lack of affordable and sufficient child care places remains one of the principal barriers to education and employment. Recent cuts in FÁS training courses affect the most marginalised women who do not know whether they will be able to complete such courses. Given that almost 30 years have passed since the introduction of the Anti-Discrimination (Pay) Act 1974, it is hard to believe that women's earnings in industry remain almost 30% less than those of men and the gap is widening. When women discuss this matter at the workshops they realise that it has become the norm. It is no longer debated but accepted as the status quo in the same manner as political under-representation. Many people have highlighted the need for legislation to enable women to challenge unequal pay structures.</p>
          <p eId="para_33">Women are asking when the national women's strategy will be produced. It is over eight years since the Government committed to publishing a national action plan for women, but the plan has not yet materialised. The Government report states that the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform has decided to consider the development of a national women's strategy in consultation with other Departments. Women's groups are keen to know where the strategy is.</p>
          <p eId="para_34">I would like to conclude by quoting from the general recommendations of the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women. The committee has highlighted the fact that Ireland is not a democratic society because "societies in which women are excluded from public life and decision making cannot be described as democratic".</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_35">I thank Ms Clancy who has mentioned a number of issues which will be discussed by members of the committee. Members are also free to ask questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarianHarkinIND" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Harkin</from>
          <p eId="para_36">I welcome the ladies from the Women's Human Rights Project. We have been given an outline of the work of the delegation in respect of the recognition of women's rights as human rights. I would like to make some observations and to ask some questions.</p>
          <p eId="para_37">What are the barriers, according to the delegation, to the increased representation of women in politics? There seems to be a belief that women should get on with it by joining political parties or doing what they have to do, but it is not happening. It is not the case that women are not interested in this area. The project's survey indicated that political representation is one of the four key issues. Over 3,000 women in the north-west participated in a recent major survey of women's health issues. The need for women to be involved at the decision making level was found to be the top priority, ranking higher than child care, rural transport and access. Women are aware of the need for increased political representation. What does the project consider to be the barriers to such an increase?</p>
          <p eId="para_38">What are the specific measures that could be taken by political parties to address this problem? I believe some funding is available to political parties, but I am not quite sure what they do with it. It is worth noting that a number of female Deputies, Senators and other political representatives are Independent. It is probable that the percentage of Independent Deputies who are female, which I accept is small, is higher than the equivalent percentage for any of the political parties. I would like to hear the delegation's thoughts on this issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_39">I was shocked to read in the delegation's report that although 300,000 was made available to the Minister for gender training for the Judiciary, no information is available on the nature or extent of the training that has been accessed. I was shocked when I read that neither the Minister nor the Department is in a position to encourage participation by judges on such courses. As far as I am concerned, the Judiciary should lead the way in this regard. The Minister should ensure, as the project has stated, that gender training should be a condition of office of all judges and legal professionals.</p>
          <p eId="para_40">I would like to conclude by commenting on an issue that is very important to many women in County Leitrim. I remember reading a submission made by Leitrim Women's Network some time ago. One of the major arguments made in the submission was that the social welfare system discriminates against farm wives. Such people have no entitlement to PRSI, for example. Although over 40% of farm wives work on the farm, only 3% of them have access to their entitlements in their own right. I would like to hear the Women's Human Rights Project's ideas about what could be done in respect of this issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BreedaMoynihanCronin" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Deputy B. Moynihan-Cronin</from>
          <p eId="para_41">I also welcome the representatives of the Women's Human Rights Project. I am delighted we are debating these issues which have been under discussion for many years.</p>
          <p eId="para_42">We seem to be making slow progress, but proof of the fact that progress is being made is the number of women who are here today. One-third of my party's Deputies and 40% of my party's Senators are women. As the political parties prepare for the local elections, the difficulties faced by young women who are interested in putting their names forward are evident. I left home to drive to Dublin at 6.45 a.m. today. That is the reality if one does not live in Dublin. It may be different if one lives within driving distance of the Dáil. The provision of child care facilities is a huge issue. Female Deputies of all parties who live far from Dublin deserve great credit. They could not do what they do without the support of their families. If we are serious about attracting women into the political arena, we have to provide the resources. I know we will all be criticised if money is spent on certain things, but I think we have to put our money where our mouth is in respect of child care, for example. The necessary services should be provided.</p>
          <p eId="para_43">Being a member of a local authority is almost a full-time job. Perhaps it would be easier for local authorities to arrange their meetings at more humane times than is the case at present. I made such a proposal when I was a member of Kerry County Council, which had just two female members, both of whom represented the Labour Party. What I am saying applies to all political parties. Women parliamentarians on all sides of the political divide agree that they have a very difficult task because of the lack of child care facilities and the lack of support at home.</p>
          <p eId="para_44">I would like to discuss the barriers to access to further education. Women who are returning to education do not receive child care funding in respect of their children over five years of age as a result of the cuts in the VTOS programmes this year. Some of the women to whom I refer were preparing to sit the leaving certificate examination. The State entered into a contract with these women when they started a two-year programme of education, but they are unable to complete the courses because the State cut the funding in respect of their children this year. It is unreal that there should be such a lack of planning.</p>
          <p eId="para_45">It seems that the Government is deciding to impose certain arbitrary cuts. If we are to be serious about encouraging women to return to education, we have to have a plan that we can fund at all stages. There is no point in funding a plan in the first year, before deciding that it will be funded in part only in the second year. Such practical issues have to be nailed down. I hope they will be dealt with in the budget so that women who are prepared to return to education, many of whom find it very difficult because they have children, do not suffer in this manner again. The decision to which I referred was a serious blow to women trying to return to education.</p>
          <p eId="para_46">The issue of female carers is a huge one. We all know that such people are not recognised by society. If they apply for the carer's allowance they are means tested against their spouse's income. They have no independence even though they do all the work. They often have to look after two or three people.</p>
          <p eId="para_47">Our hospitals are in a chronic state. It was stated in reports last night that many elderly people in hospital should be cared for in the community. It is women who do all that work but they are no longer prepared to do it unless they are recognised, and I do not blame them. That is another issue; we must be prepared to give recognition to those women who look after the elderly and those in need in our society. That would be one way of relieving the difficulties being experienced in our hospitals. I could talk for another hour on this issue but I will conclude on that point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FinianMcGrath" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy F. McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_48">I welcome the representatives from the Women's Human Rights Project and commend their work which is an essential part of the education agenda for men and women. I particularly welcome the major role they play in terms of educating the broader public because many people believe the equality agenda debate is over. In middle income areas in particular the view is that the battle has been won and the war is over whereas the reality for many poor families, particularly poor women, is that there is a long way to go in terms of equality. Education is the key to equality and liberation.</p>
          <p eId="para_49">There is a perception among the broader public, and particularly in political areas, that there is not a sufficient number of women from disadvantaged areas involved in groups like the National Women's Council, the Women's Human Rights Project or other groups. Is that perception correct?</p>
          <p eId="para_50">Some 70,000 children in Ireland are living in poverty and many of the women involved in those situations are living in violent, dysfunctional families. For them there is no real hope of equality unless groups like the group here push legislators to do something about it. We have a major crisis in terms of that question. Do the representatives have concerns about those women and their right to safety before we even begin to talk about health care or other such issues? I am talking about the right to safety. That should be the first item on the agenda.</p>
          <p eId="para_51">I strongly agree with the comments that we are not a democratic society unless everybody is treated equally, particularly women. I have outlined the reasons we are not a democratic society, given the exclusion of the 70,000 women connected with families living in poverty in this State. Do the representatives have any strategies to assist us as legislators to deal with these issues?</p>
          <p eId="para_52">I commend the work of the representatives. They make a massive contribution. The reality is that many people are not aware of the position. For example, 97% of city managers in local authorities are men, 91% of TDs are men and women earn 73% of the average male industrial wage. Many people might not necessarily be aware of these figures, but the figure I would zoom in on is that 42% of women have experienced some form of sexual abuse during their lifetime. This is not acceptable and the public must be made aware that is not acceptable and that it is going on. The genuine feeling among the public on this equality issue is that the war is over.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_53">With regard to political representation, the representatives suggested that there is an inhibited male culture. Many of the members have been members of local authorities and they are now Members of the Oireachtas. I note from the report that the success rate of women candidates in the European elections was far greater than their participation rate. Some 33% of successful candidates were women whereas only 19% of candidates were women. That shows that the people who go forward have a good deal of grit and determination. There may be an inhibited male culture in the local organisations but those local organisations in every party are diminishing and they are very small. The numbers involved in Labour, Fine Gael or Fianna Fáil in the 1950s and the 1960s were far greater than the numbers involved in those parties today. There should be an opportunity for women who would organise themselves to become involved in political parties because they are not that many people involved.</p>
          <p eId="para_54">It is necessary to address the question of family friendly policies. We are talking about it a good deal but we must do something about it. There is something wrong when fewer than 6% of domestic violence offenders receive a prison sentence. Do the representatives believe that changes are necessary in the criminal justice system to address this problem, aside from the training of judges on gender issues?</p>
          <p eId="para_55">The representatives mention that there has not been a referendum on abortion. This has been an emotive issue. We had a number of referendums and they split society to a great extent. By stating this issue is a very important one of the four issues put forward, I wonder whether the representatives are weakening the other three issues in terms of the amount of gunpower they would have to use to do something about those three issues which are vital. I also wonder whether they would alienate a large section of society, women and men, by the attitude that has been expressed towards abortion.</p>
          <p eId="para_56">Women's wages are, on average, 30% less than those of men and the gap is widening. Is the gap widening in term of the percentage figure increasing to 31%, 32% or 33% or does that figure represent the absolute amount because increases in pay generally are widening?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Dr. McMinn</from>
          <p eId="para_57">I will start by answering the political representation questions. In terms of the barriers to women's representation there are structural and cultural barriers. Specific measures are necessary to redress those within parties such as some mechanisms which would achieve greater equality in both women standing for election and being placed in seats where they are not necessarily bound to fail, and there should be support for women within parties. There are structural and support measures that could be taken.</p>
          <p eId="para_58">There has been a voluntary recommendation in Government programmes for a 40:60 gender balance on State bodies that has not been met. It has been a voluntary recommendation and the argument put forward has been that there have not been women to put forward. It has been clearly shown that where there is a political will to do that it can be achieved. We recommend that such gender balance representation be made mandatory. We would also be considering legislation to introduce parity democracy which exists in other countries, particularly in France, to achieve an equal representation of men and women in political parties.</p>
          <p eId="para_59">In terms of other issues concerning political representation, young women have difficulties participating in the local elections. We agree with what the Chairman said about unfriendly family practices and that resources are needed for child care. This is something for which we will be lobbying and which we will be highlighting, although there are none so deaf as those who do not want to hear.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Ms Clancy</from>
          <p eId="para_60">On the caring issue, one of the disappointments we have with the report is that it makes no reference to the contribution or value of the unpaid work women do in the economy and in the community. In some of the workshops many of the farm women were very angry that they are not recognised and called for reforms in this particular area. They said that they should be entitled to pensions in their own right and that is certainly one of the recommendations we would be calling for in our own shadow report.</p>
          <p eId="para_61">When we did our survey, poverty was one of the key issues which came up but we see it as a cross-cutting issue because it affects health and it affects violence against women.</p>
          <p eId="para_62">Deputy Finian McGrath raised the issue of connecting with disadvantaged groups. We would see that as crucial. When we were doing our regional workshops around the country there were very few Traveller women and asylum seeker and refuge women represented, and we organised two specific workshops for minority ethnic groups, which are increasingly not only asylum seekers or refugees but also migrant women, who are becoming increasingly marginalised. We would work closely with organisations like Pavee Point, the National Traveller Women's Forum, the Irish Refugee Council and local community development projects on the ground, and feed into the issues emerging at local level.</p>
          <p eId="para_63">We need to look at other countries on the issue of gender training. In other countries judges are obliged to undergo different levels of training before they take office and there is nothing to prevent a similar requirement being introduced here. I refer here not only to training around gender sensitivity but also to training on all forms of violence against women and also on anti-racism. That is another recommendation which we will be making to the UN CEDAW committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_64">The whole civil and criminal justice system needs to be reformed and the organisations, Women's Aid and the Rape Crisis Centre, have conducted several excellent studies and recommendations have been made on this particular area.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Dr. McMinn</from>
          <p eId="para_65">I want to say more about violence against women and the point Deputy McGrath made about the perception that women from disadvantaged backgrounds find things even more difficult. Certainly research shows that 88% of women who do not leave, do so because they have nowhere to go as they are economically dependent. We are keen to promote the indivisibility of human rights in terms of women's economy and social rights as well, obviously, as political and civil rights. Both the Women's Human Rights Project and the National Women's Council of Ireland have prioritised women who are at the margins, and we also have another equality for women measure called In From the Margins which addresses poverty, health and anti-racism for women in very disadvantaged communities, and asylum seekers, refugees and migrant workers are the priority groups with whom we would work.</p>
          <p eId="para_66">On right to safety, clearly there is a need for more refuges, but part of a problem is that where there is a lack of housing, women are reluctant to go into refuges if they have nowhere to which they may move on to - if there is no social housing - and that is one of the problems. Not investing in social housing has the knock-on effect of impacting on the lives of women who would be the ones who could not afford to do otherwise than go to a refuge.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Ms. Taylor</from>
          <p eId="para_67">To pick up on the question on abortion and reproductive choice, a decision the Women's Human Rights Project has made is that an organisation focusing on women's human rights cannot shy away from the area of reproductive health/reproductive choice and specifically abortion.</p>
          <p eId="para_68">In Ireland, an estimated 6,000 to 7,000 women travel to Britain annually for abortion. The only thing stopping this country from having a huge problem of maternal mortality through clandestine abortion is the proximity of abortion available in Britain. That is the position. The cliché has been repeated over and over again, the Irish solution to an Irish problem, but it is certainly not something on which one can say it is a difficult topic and therefore we cannot look at it. It is something very real in the lives of Irish women. The fact that access to abortion in Britain requires the economic resources to travel, puts additional burdens and additional discriminations on economically disadvantaged women.</p>
          <p eId="para_69">In terms of debate and discussion around abortion, what we have seen is that since 1983, when Article 40.3.3° was inserted in the Constitution, there have been a number of situations which have arisen which have reintroduced the debate on abortion into Irish politics and discussions in Irish society - the X case, the various referenda on information and travel, the C case and last year's referendum. What is notable is that every time a referendum has put a proposal which seeks to restrict abortion further, in other words, to remove probability of suicide from the category of life threatening situations for which abortion is permitted, the Irish people voted against those further restrictions. In the 2002 referendum the Irish people voted against a series of measures which would have been inserted into the Constitution, the kinds of restrictions on women's reproductive choices and reproductive health which the CEDAW committee has repeatedly said are part of the overall structural discriminations against women.</p>
          <p eId="para_70">The CEDAW committee has repeatedly called on countries to remove the criminalisation of abortion for women. It has repeated called on countries, at a minimum, to recognise that threat to the life of a woman is a ground for legal abortion. The referendum last year attempted to restrict those grounds by removing suicide. It is interesting to note that in the report to CEDAW, in the section on article 12 on health, this referendum was described in the following way - it would have introduced legislation intended to ensure that a pregnant woman who was suffering from a life threatening medical condition, could receive whatever treatment she might need. That shows - given the numerous negative impacts that the Human Life and Pregnancy Act would have had on women in crisis pregnancy, and the fact that there is no sign that crisis pregnancies are reducing in number, quite the opposite - there is a need for continuing debate and dialogue in a real and meaningful way. That involves looking at the issue of crisis pregnancy, what is required in terms of education programmes and supports for family planning and supports around crisis pregnancies and what legal measures are needed to ensure 6,000-7,000 Irish women do not travel to Britain for abortion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_71">Some of the members will ask questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#OlwynEnrightFG" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Deputy Enright</from>
          <p eId="para_72">I will expand on some of the questions asked already. My first question is on the lack of consistency among judges in approach and treatment. Can the delegates elaborate a little on what they mean by "approach and treatment"? Is it inconsistency in terms of sentences being handed down or is that included in the term? Does the proportion of between one and six of domestic violence perpetrators, to which they referred, relate to those convicted or to complaints made, or do they know the proportion going to court and the proportion convicted?</p>
          <p eId="para_73">Many people mention the issue of child care. A few months ago we were discussing the cost of the cre×che being provided in Leinster House and one Minister of State commented that if one wanted women in politics, one must have a cre×che - which can be a token response. There were six people under 30 elected to the 28th Dáil and I was the only female among them. To the best of my knowledge, none of them has any children or such commitments. The question "why are there not more people of that generation who are not affected by issues of child care?" is one which we need answered because it is easy to state in response that it is a child care issue. Obviously it is far broader than that.</p>
          <p eId="para_74">Deputy Moynihan-Cronin mentioned the VTOS programme. I agree that the impact of that programme is already evident. It is hitting home everywhere but from a rural perspective there are obviously additional issues such as transport. The type of isolation being experience in rural areas is probably far different to that being experienced in cities, but obviously there is isolation in urban areas too. Have they studied that area - the participation of women in the context of the urban-rural divide? I think we would find there is quite a difference. On Dáil reform, I wish to discuss the issue of child care. There has been a great deal of discussion about the advent of a five day working week in the Houses. I would like to hear our guests' comments and observations on that because if there is already a barrier for women, aspects of which would include distance, child care, etc., the advent of a five day week may have more negative consequences.</p>
          <p eId="para_75">Does the pay gap apply at all levels or is it more apparent at the levels at which people are paid much higher salaries? Certain jobs have definite pay scales and I presume difficulties do not exist in such circumstances. Does the gap apply more at the higher level or is it across the board?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SheilaTerry" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Senator Terry</from>
          <p eId="para_76">I welcome our guests to this important debate. I will not repeat much of what has already been said. Poverty is the greatest threat to women's participation in political life or life outside the home. I have stated previously that as soon as a child is born, one can almost determine whether he or she is going to be able to progress through life and be given the various advantages on offer. One of the major issues we need to tackle is that of young single mothers who, in most cases, are struggling to survive and to give their children the best that is available. Unless we tackle the poverty in which single mothers are living, their children, male and female, will also be impoverished and will not be able to participate fully in life in the way we would want. The provision of child care for single mothers, whether they be in full-time education or full-time employment, is a must, but it is not available at present. Child care facilities must be made available to every mother who needs them. The cost of child care is prohibiting many women from going out to work.</p>
          <p eId="para_77">We must also consider the issue of part-time work and the institutions that provide it. This type of work is generally taken up by women who are providing cheap labour. The major banks are availing of the use of such labour and that is a matter at which we must look.</p>
          <p eId="para_78">I am particularly interested in parental leave. Comparisons between Ireland and other EU countries show that the amount of such leave of which women here can avail is much smaller than elsewhere. While the period of parental leave that may be taken was extended recently, it remains short.</p>
          <p eId="para_79">What are our guests' views on mothers in the home, namely, those women who decide to give up their jobs and income in order to remain at home and rear their children for how ever long is necessary? How are such women treated by society? I am aware of the obstacles such women face in terms of trying to return to the workforce. In my opinion, the work done by such women in the home is not recognised. Women are encouraged, perhaps too strongly in some cases, to go out to work at a time when many of them would like to remain at home for a few years to rear their children. How supportive would our guests be of those women?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_80">Others have mentioned child care. Many of the child care projects were dependent, perhaps wrongly, on CE schemes. Government policy and the way FÁS has interpreted it has decimated child care and caused a crisis in that area. The fact that an organisation or part of a service is in crisis means that it is not going to attract women. In my area it is difficult to find available spaces in any of the services offered by child care providers. There are a number of new crèches, etc., planned, but difficulties have been caused for mothers, particularly those who are trying to get into the workplace or those who want to return to education. Do our guests believe that the Government is committed to its child care programme?</p>
          <p eId="para_81">Reference was made to the Dáil cre×che, which will not even be operational within a year. It might be open for a week next June before being closed again. The cre×che is not aimed at Deputies in general; it is aimed at the huge number of staff who will be working here when the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission takes over the running of the Houses. It is a very small cre×che, involving small numbers. If the Government cannot get it right in its own backyard, how can we expect it to get it right elsewhere?</p>
          <p eId="para_82">I wish to provide an example of CE cuts. There was a women's programme in my area for Traveller women who are returning to education. Each of these women has gained some type of certificate in the past year. To give an indication of how marginalised these women are, last year one of them was the first ever from Labre Park to obtain a junior certificate. Each year, those who run the programme have to seek funding or the decision is held over for the entire summer so they do not know whether the programme will proceed. It is difficult for women to have any confidence if every good project that is going well is put on hold for months on end or has no guaranteed future.</p>
          <p eId="para_83">Our guests mentioned the 60:40 split on State boards. In my view, this should be reflective of society and should be at least 50-50 in order to make up for many years of under-representation.</p>
          <p eId="para_84">I have not had an opportunity to consider the issue of health in detail. I am aware, however, that smear testing is mentioned. I am also aware that when people manage to get smear tests, there are inordinate delays in the results being returned to them. Funding is not being put in place to alleviate the difficulties these people are experiencing. Anyone who has such a test carried out will be worried until the results, positive or otherwise, are returned. It is not acceptable that people are obliged to wait a month for results which should be returned within a day or two.</p>
          <p eId="para_85">One of the points made in the document relates to the national women's strategy. Will our guests indicate what is the current position regarding the strategy because we are eight years down the road and there is no plan in place? Who should be involved in developing this strategy and how should it be rolled out to outside interests rather than just being concentrated around the Department? I accept that the answer to my final question is probably how long is a piece of string, nevertheless I will ask it. With regard to our guests' budget, what additional supports do they need? Every group who appears before the committee is seeking such supports but the work this group has carried out to date and the material presented to us is to be commended. I see, however, that there is only one project co-ordinator. Are there any more working for the organisation or how many more are needed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_86">I welcome the Women's Human Rights Project. Many important issues have already been dealt with. However, there are a number of matters to which I wish to refer.</p>
          <p eId="para_87">To what extent have the reservations that have been expressed by the Government in a number of areas been dealt with over the years? There were five reservations in 1999 regarding our ability to fulfil the terms of the convention and these were to be kept under review. A specific commitment was made at that time to having a minimum of 40% female representation on each State board. What is the current position in that regard? Is there any forum in which pressure can be put on the Government to adhere to that commitment, which obviously is only honoured in the breach? Not so long ago we were debating the Private Security Services Bill and we tried to get the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform to accept an amendment committing to 40% representation of both genders on the board. The Minister would not consider or tolerate it at all and it was ruled out. The old argument came up again, that it would be difficult to get enough women in the security business. To what extent has this commitment been honoured as it is not operating across the board?</p>
          <p eId="para_88">The two areas of greatest discrimination against women are in caring for the young and caring for the old. Has the delegation considered a radical approach in those areas? People have indicated the problems that arise. For example, CE schemes were wonderful as stepping stones for lone parents getting into the workforce and many child care services are operated through CE schemes and funded by FÁS but there is an absence of paid parental leave in Ireland, despite European directives to that effect. We have a rather artificial level of primary education, which is funded by the State, for children of four years, but the service for children between two and four is completely inadequate. It is a hand to mouth education service. There are some private Montessori schools but other services exist on the basis of funding becoming available from time to time. Many of the problems associated with child care would be dealt with in one fell swoop if this were addressed.</p>
          <p eId="para_89">Tens of thousands of carers, and women in particular, look after the elderly and disabled and often they get very little for that work, apart from the stunting of their own lives and careers. Has abolition of the means test for the carer's allowance been considered? If that were done anyone presenting as available and willing to become a carer, irrespective of whether they are paupers or millionaires, would be welcomed and paid by the State. The current payment is minimal. There is substantial discrimination against women in these two areas.</p>
          <p eId="para_90">The delegation's view on the lack of consistency in the Judiciary is correct. Our judicial system is very adversarial in terms of those who are appointed as judges. Barristers and solicitors are suddenly supposed to work in a judicial capacity with no training or induction course, let alone any understanding of the complexity of the issues they will face on the bench. We need a substantial induction procedure for all judges when they are appointed and there should be a monitoring procedure to deal with the lack of consistency and sensitivity. This applies to interaction with women, ethnic groups and so on.</p>
          <p eId="para_91">I direct the delegation's attention to legislation mentioned earlier, the Criminal Justice Act 1993, which provided a model in giving statutory rights to the homosexual community. However, at the same time it set women back when it came to soliciting and prostitution. It strengthened the law against women but not against men involved in the same activity; the legislation is good on one side and retrograde on the other, so it could do with examination. Social housing and poverty have also been addressed.</p>
          <p eId="para_92">Is the delegation satisfied that the Convention on the Elimination of all Forms of Discrimination has been covered adequately in the terms of reference of the Human Rights Commission?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_93">Some of the Deputy's comments were self-explanatory, so the delegation should just address the questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Ms Clancy</from>
          <p eId="para_94">The statistic of 6% mentioned earlier relates to those who are convicted, according to my research. As Deputy Costello said about treatment, this goes back to training and the need for understanding the issues. It is also linked to the insufficient resources for programmes to deal with sexual offenders. There are some very good programmes but there are not enough of them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#OlwynEnrightFG" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Deputy Enright</from>
          <p eId="para_95">Are treatment of the victims and the fact that these people are not trained influencing the sentences being handed down?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Ms Clancy</from>
          <p eId="para_96">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Dr. McMinn</from>
          <p eId="para_97">Poverty and child poverty are issues linked to women's access to education and employment and obviously child care plays a huge part here. We were asked if the gender pay gap exists at all levels. That is quite complex; there have been some studies done of graduates and so on but we also need to look at part-time workers and the fact that women make up the majority of part-time workers, which means lower paid work and different conditions. Also, the majority of those receiving the minimum wage are women, so there are many factors related to the gender pay gap.</p>
          <p eId="para_98">We were asked about mothers in the home and those women who choose to stay at home to rear their children. It is important to point out that there is a great diversity of women who choose to stay at home. We are looking at supports for women who do unpaid work in the home, such as caring for children and the elderly. That would require reform of the social welfare system and we are concerned that women do not have economic independence. They are defined within the social welfare system as dependants, based on the model of a male breadwinner, which is unequal. We are looking for a whole range of payments based around social insurance credits and pensions as there are women who had to give up their jobs on marriage years ago who are now suffering poverty as older women. There is a raft of supports there but women who are doing unpaid caring work in the home should be recognised and paid.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Ms Taylor</from>
          <p eId="para_99">The National Women's Strategy is an obligation that came out of the Beijing Platform for Action, which was signed in 1995. The Beijing Platform for Action is an international document which takes forward the principles laid out in the Convention of the Elimination of Discrimination Against Women and recognises and identifies the strategies and objectives that are necessary in order to bring forward women's rights and equality in 12 areas. Those areas are linked and they include all the issues we have discussed - women in poverty, female representation, women in health, women in education, violence against women and so on. The Government undertook in 1995 in Beijing to produce a national plan for women but there was no consultation nationally to develop a national plan for women until last year. What was produced was a gathering of ideas towards a national plan for women but there was no strategy that took the actions identified in the Beijing Platform for Action. The platform for action requires resources, recommendations and timeframes on all those actions.</p>
          <p eId="para_100">Rather than a piecemeal approach to various programmes and policies that address different aspects of the kind of discrimination barriers that we have looked at, there is a need for a national strategy that pulls all the issues that women face together and looks at concrete measures that will bring forward equality for women. CEDAW, the Convention on the Elimination of all Forms of Discrimination Against Women, acknowledges that there is a need for special temporary measures, on occasion, to accelerate the equality of women in certain areas. There is a need for Government to take actions that will boost the capacity of women to move into certain areas such as political representation. The CEDAW committee recognises that there is a necessity for 30% representation for women, at a minimum, to have some kind of critical mass. This would give women a large enough presence in politics and representation and challenge the idea, perception, image and stereotype of politics as a male sphere. Political parties must take action and identify, train and support women candidates. There is a need for Government to implement specific measures, such as quotas and targets, to enhance and bring forward women's representation.</p>
          <p eId="para_101">We were asked if we were satisfied that CEDAW had been adequately reflected in the Human Rights Commission's terms of reference. As far as we are aware, the commission will make a report to CEDAW and will report on the UN convention. While this is a very positive move we would like the commission to do more. It has the power to make recommendations to Government, to change laws and to introduce legislation that will implement the various human rights agreements and treaties that Ireland has signed up to. While we, as a women's human rights project, can lobby, attend meetings like this and make recommendations, the commission, as an independent body established by statute, can bring greater weight to those recommendations. We would like the commission to take on this task in terms of women's rights.</p>
          <p eId="para_102">Deputy Ó Snodaigh asked about the Women's Human Rights Project and its resources. At present we have a co-ordinator and funding is provided under the equality measure for women. We also have the resources of the 13 organisations who were involved. For the project to continue its work we need additional resources. We are currently looking at a range of different funding opportunities. We would be very happy to have this committee's support and representations during this process and in the future.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_103">That is a good note to finish on. I thank Ms Noirín Clancy, Dr. Joanna McMinn and Ms Maeve Taylor for coming here today to represent the Women's Human Rights Project and for giving their response to the Government's report on the CEDAW convention. This committee will raise the points outlined by the organisation and our own views with the Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform at a meeting that will be arranged very shortly. Representatives from the Women's Human Rights Project are more than welcome to attend the meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_104">We shall now suspend the meeting until after the Order of Business. When we resume we shall consider two motions on Council decisions and an EU scrutiny matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">Sitting suspended at 4.15 p.m. and resumed at 5.55 p.m.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Scrutiny of EU Proposals.</heading>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_105">We will now discuss COM (2003) 483 concerning the European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia. Mr. Niall McCutcheon has come in and I will just give him a moment to get himself organised. COM (2003) 483 proposes to recast Council regulation EC 1035/97 on the European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia. This proposes to amend the regulation that governs the centre which is based in Vienna. Essentially, the proposal widens the scope of the data-information collection work of the centre and proposes some changes to the management structure. I welcome Mr. Niall McCutcheon of the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform and invite him to make a presentation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Mr. Niall McCutcheon</from>
          <p eId="para_106">I am principal officer in the equal status division of the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform. I am also the national liaison officer for the European Union Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia. I understand that the Irish member of the management board of the centre, Ms Anastasia Crickley, has already spoken to the committee and given a very clear background picture of the work of the centre.</p>
          <p eId="para_107">Before discussing the principal features of the commission's proposals to amend and recast the regulation governing the centre, I emphasise just how small an operation the centre is. It has fewer than 30 staff and an annual budget of about €6 million. After the accession of ten new member states in May 2004, the management board will grow to 28 members, and unless the working methods of the board are to change the Commission is of the view that it will become unwieldy. It is in that context that the Commission has come forward with its proposals.</p>
          <p eId="para_108">As the Chairman said, the EUMC was established by regulation in 1997 and its primary objective is to provide the European Union and member states with objective, reliable and comparable data at European level on the phenomena of racism, xenophobia and anti-Semitism. The Commission submitted to Council its proposal to amend the regulation on 5 August 2003. The stated aim of the proposal is to sharpen the focus of the work and means of operation of the centre in the light of enlargement. The proposal was circulated by the Council secretariat on 1 September 2003.</p>
          <p eId="para_109">The Government's position, in short, is to welcome the proposals in general. It particularly welcomes the aim of increasing the effectiveness of the centre and of emphasising its responsibility for data collection. The Government has some concern about the proposal to require member states to appoint to the management board of the centre the person in each country responsible for the running of the equal treatment bodies or of an equivalent independent public body. It is the view of a majority of member states that this proposal is over-prescriptive. However, the Commission has indicated a willingness to compromise on this issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_110">Of the articles in the Commission's proposal, only six show any significant change. These concern the objectives of the centre, its tasks, working methods and areas of activity, the management, the executive board and the director. Article 2 emphasises that the primary recipients of the information collected by the centre should be relevant institutions and authorities of the community and the member states responsible for combating racism and xenophobia and that the scope of the phenomenon of racism-xenophobia should be interpreted broadly to encompass related intolerance.</p>
          <p eId="para_111">The proposed changes in terminology recognise the increasing importance of phenomena such as Islamophobia or religious hatred, particularly since 11 September 2001, and in the context of the current political situation in the Middle East, and they mirror the responsibilities of the Council of Europe, notably the European Commission on Racism and Intolerance, thus promoting greater synergies. The purpose of the centre is to support the work of the member states and the general public regarding racism/xenophobia. The primacy of data collection and information gathering is because this is essential to measure any progress made in combating these phenomena.</p>
          <p eId="para_112">Regarding the changes in tasks, there has been some concern that the work of the centre has been somewhat unfocused and that, like a lot of newly established organisations, it has taken some time to bed down and focus on its main activities. The main activities in terms of data collection are extremely difficult, which is recognised in the Commission document.</p>
          <p eId="para_113">In Article 4, the Commission broadens the range of phenomena which can be covered by the centre, recognising the significant development in the role of the EU in combating racism since 1997. Prior to the Treaty of Amsterdam, the EU had no competence, legislative or otherwise, in combating racism/xenophobia. That was when the centre was established. Since then, the EU has had the power under Article 13 of the treaty to bring forward legislation outlawing discrimination, and it did so in 2000 in the race equality directive. Also, under the amendments to the European Union treaty under the Treaty of Amsterdam, areas such as asylum, immigration and combating crime have become EU competences.</p>
          <p eId="para_114">It is important then that data collection be carried out by the centre to reinforce the work of the EU in these areas. The areas of competence of the centre have been widened in line with these legislative developments. The Commission proposes that the centre be able to look into data around racism in respect of immigration and asylum. Free movement of persons was already an EU responsibility but in areas around the supply of goods and services employment. These areas are significant and are covered by the race directive.</p>
          <p eId="para_115">The main area of concern, as I already mentioned, regards the structure of the management board. The Commission proposes to require member states to nominate to the management board the person responsible for the running of the equal treatment bodies designated under the race directive. The Commission sees two useful factors in this. First, it will mean that all the people represented would have experience in the area of combating discrimination and, second, the same people would have experience in management.</p>
          <p eId="para_116">The evaluation report which was carried out for the Commission found certain deficiencies in the management of the centre which, from the point of view of the Commission, were due to the nature of the experience of the board members. However, as I have already indicated, the Government and other member states feel that there is a downside to these proposals in that it would mean a certain uniformity among the membership and that the range of experience would be quite narrow and limited to anti-discrimination. Other areas of concern, such as racist crime, incitement to hatred, migration, integration and social exclusion are typically not the responsibility of specialised anti-discrimination bodies. Moreover, academic or non-governmental organisation experience, which can be extremely relevant, would be excluded from the board of the European Union Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia. The Commission has indicated that it is prepared to compromise on the proposals in this regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_117">As I said at the beginning, with enlargement, the size of the management board is likely to grow to 28 members. For an organisation which employs about that number of people, this is a severe imbalance. Thus, the Commission proposes that the day-to-day management would be delegated to an executive board of no more than ten persons. The question then is the relative responsibilities of the management board itself and the executive board. The detail of that has not yet been discussed by the member states, and views on the micro-issue of which powers would be reserved to the management board and which delegated to the executive board have yet to be discussed in full. The social Europe working group has already had one meeting to discuss the proposal. We hope that there will be a second meeting before Christmas and that proposal will be considered a priority for the Irish Presidency, which begins on 1 January. We hope, subject to the co-operation of the member states and the Commission, that it will be considered on the agenda for the meeting of the Social Affairs Council to be held in March.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_118">Thank you very much, Mr. McCutcheon. As you are aware, the other day we had Ms Anastasia Crickley. She mentioned the body's data collection function. She felt that it should be widened to include more awareness raising of racism issues so that some form of policy analysis could be conducted and it could have an advisory role regarding racism. How does that tie in with the current proposal?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Mr. McCutcheon</from>
          <p eId="para_119">There is a certain amount of room for manoeuvre when one focuses on data collection and information so that analysis can lead to policy proposals or to the consideration of policy issues. However, the Commission is anxious to get the centre to focus on its primary data collection purpose since there are huge gaps in our knowledge of racism in Europe. Data collection is very uneven between countries. There are serious problems over definitions and comparability. Those problems must be faced if we are to know whether we are making progress in combating discrimination and racism at European and national levels. It is very important that the centre not be distracted from its primary role.</p>
          <p eId="para_120">Another issue that must be considered is that there are other international agencies with a policy advisory role in this area. There is the European Commission against Racism and Intolerance, a Council of Europe body which carries out a country by country analysis of the member states of the Council of Europe on combating racism. There is also the United Nations Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination, which carries out a country by country analysis on a global basis. It is built into the original regulation that there be complementarity between the role of the Council of Europe and that of the European Union monitoring centre in the area. Therefore, the policy review role, which is being carried out at Council of Europe level, is not duplicated by the European Union monitoring centre. That said, in analysis and information, policy issues are frequently raised. That has happened at the level of the European Union monitoring centre.</p>
          <p eId="para_121">Perhaps I might give just one example of where it has carried out excellent work, namely, its timely response to Islamophobic tendencies which emerged in the aftermath of the attacks of 11 September 2001. It quickly carried out a survey of the situation in each member state and was able to put together a useful and timely report highlighting incidents in member states.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_122">I thank Mr. McCutcheon. As the Chairman said, we had Anastasia Crickley from the National Consultative Committee on Racism and Interculturalism here the other day. Another concern that mentioned was that we had still not incorporated into legislation the racism directive from the European Union nor had we done anything about the employment directive which is due to come into operation in December. I understand that the racism directive was due to be implemented by all member states by June 2003, but it is still outstanding. If we are to have a European Union monitoring committee, we should at least ensure that member states adhere to statutory requirements as early as possible, and certainly within the designated timescale. Article 2 says that the primary recipients of the information collected by the centre should be the relevant institutions and authorities of the Community and the member states responsible for combating racism and xenophobia. That is the first step towards ensuring that the relevant directives are incorporated into domestic legislation. Perhaps Mr. McCutcheon might comment on that and the timescale for it.</p>
          <p eId="para_123">This is the first time that I have seen the word "Islamophobia".</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_124">The member saw it when Ms Crickley was here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_125">I meant in the context of these discussions. I presume it is a new piece of terminology but it certainly seems relevant in the present context, and I am glad to see it agreed there. It seems incredible that Mr. McCutcheon is saying that the comparability of data remains the most important factor for the added value of the centre. It has not proved possible so far to provide truly comparable data, and to do so seems simple. It will require strong co-operation between the centre and the authorities of the member states and, in particular, their national statistics offices. That is a purely logistical matter. With the centre in place for seven years, why should it not be possible to get the national statistics offices of the member states to connect with each other and provide the data? I cannot see the reason for any problem in that regard, especially since it is one of the most important aspects of added value.</p>
          <p eId="para_126">This is the European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia and its main function is to collect data. There is obviously a problem collecting that data in a comparable format. Until we have that, we do not know where we stand regarding the other member states. Is there any procedure for delegations to visit the member states and collect data at source rather than simply relying on whatever data are provided on racism and xenophobia by the various governments and state institutions to ensure that one is getting a proper selection of data? For example, the European Committee for the Prevention of Torture goes around various European countries visiting prisons and compiling data. Afterwards, a report is written on the various countries. Might we not have a similar sub-committee from the European Union monitoring centre whose function would be to visit the countries in question and see the situation at first hand, meeting the relevant organisations and agencies?</p>
          <p eId="para_127">I am happy with the extension to the field of employment and social inclusion. Article 8 deals with the size of the management board and the voting structure. If under article 9 one establishes a new structure with an executive board composed of ten persons, how will the individual countries participate in it if we take responsibility from the 28 states, each of which has a management board which will be hands-on, and we then pass authority to an executive board to make the day-to-day decisions? How advisable is that? The figure of 28 may be a little wieldy for a centre that will meet on a regular basis but how often does the board of management meet? Is it not desirable for small countries like Ireland to ensure - it is a little like the argument about the commissioners - it has somebody at the table all the time? It is important we have such a person there to deal with our concerns. I do not see 28 people as being too many around the table when making decisions. Is it desirable to do that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_128">If this is merely a statistical data collection, why is more than one person required to do the job? Many of the matters raised may be policy issues and we understand, Mr. McCutcheon, if you are not in a position to answer them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Mr. McCutcheon</from>
          <p eId="para_129">On implementation and transposition of the race directive, it is true that the deadline for transposition was July 2003. As I understand it, none of the member states has fully complied with that transposition date to the satisfaction of the Commission. Ireland is already substantially compliant because the Employment (Equality) Act 1998 outlaws discrimination on the ground of race in the area of employment and training and the Equal Status Act 2000 outlaws discrimination on the grounds of race in the supply of goods and services, housing and education and on eight other grounds.</p>
          <p eId="para_130">The amendments required to give effect to the race directive in Ireland are of a relatively minor, technical nature and will deal with issues such as the definition of indirect discrimination which applies to this directive and which differs from that which exists in our current legislation. The reason it is taking time to transpose is that Ireland has a unified system of law on equality - we apply more or less the same rules in nine areas rather than having separate rules for different areas. To maintain that unity, we have to consider to what extent it was possible to apply the provisions of the race directive not just on the grounds of race but also on the grounds of gender, sexual orientation, age, disability and so on. Those issues are of concern to us and that has made our transposition more complex than would otherwise be the case.</p>
          <p eId="para_131">Other countries have been able to transpose the directive by means of secondary legislation but we did not go down that route because, on legal advice, to do so would mean we could not apply the changes inherent in a race directive to any other grounds. We would have the anomalous situation whereby we would have one set of rules where somebody is discriminated against on grounds of race and another set on grounds of religion. The Government hopes to be in a position to publish in December 2003 the Bill implementing three directives dealing with race, employment and gender. It is also hoped the directive will be transposed early in 2004.</p>
          <p eId="para_132">Deputy Costello referred to our problems regarding data. Serious legal problems subsist in certain countries. As a result of their experience of abuse of data on ethnicity during the Nazi area, Germany and others outlawed the collection of data on an ethnic basis, except in the area of criminal activity. While in England one can get good data on the number of children of ethnic minorities expelled from school as compared with white children, that kind of useful analysis is not available in countries where this type of collection is not permitted by law. There are different definitions of what constitutes a racist crime. In the Garda statistics collected here, we have followed the experience of Britain and the recommendations of the Lawrence Inquiry which stated that a crime is considered racist if it is seen as so by the victim, a garda or a witness. It is a somewhat subjective definition which many other countries do not have. Therefore, the countries which have a wider definition of what constitutes a racist crime would have a higher incidence of racism than those which have a narrower one. Countries tend to be rather sensitive if portrayed as being more racist than another. Those countries with good statistics in this area, in particular the Netherlands and the UK, apparently have a higher incidence of racism.</p>
          <p eId="para_133">There are serious data comparability problems in trying to harmonise existing data sets. Other ways of dealing with this have proven successful. For example, the euro barometer survey, an ongoing survey of attitudes in the European Community, has been used to measure levels of intolerance. Such surveys are carried out in member states on a standardised basis by questionnaires and opinion poll systems. The same question is asked in various member states and a comparable set of data emerges.</p>
          <p eId="para_134">The EUMC operates by appointing as contractors in each member state what is called a national vocal point. This is an independent agency, academic body or research institution depending on the skills and ability of each country to extract the data. In Ireland, the national vocal point comprises two agencies, the National Consultative Committee on Racism and Inter-culturalism, of which Anastasia Crickley is chairperson, and the Equality Authority. They have experience and knowledge of the situation here to extract such data. A similar analogous agency or institution in each country collects data locally.</p>
          <p eId="para_135">On the matter of visiting countries, two issues arise. The original regulation placed a requirement on the centre to hold what are termed national round tables which would facilitate a meeting with non-governmental organisations and other activists in each member state to discuss the centre's functions and to provide an input into its activities. These have varied between countries. Some have been extremely successful. Certain member states are anxious to see the practice continue. The Commission proposes to remove the obligation on the centre to carry out such national round tables. The matter is currently under discussion at Council level.</p>
          <p eId="para_136">Countries are already visited by two institutions to which I referred earlier. The European Commission on Racism and Intolerance carries out a country by country analysis of the situation by way of study visit. That organisation, which published a report some years ago on the situation here, has produced two reports on Ireland so far. The United Nations committee for the elimination of all forms of racial discrimination carries out a review of each country's report on its compliance with provisions of the United Nations convention on the elimination of racism and discrimination.</p>
          <p eId="para_137">The involvement of the EUMC should be complementary to other agencies. It is essential there is some form of national link with the work of the centre. They should be given every encouragement to visit each member state and to liaise with the people on the ground both at governmental and non-governmental level.</p>
          <p eId="para_138">The matter of the appropriate delegation from the management board to the executive board has not been discussed at Council level. I hear the point being made by the Deputy and the Chairman on this matter and it will require negotiation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_139">I thank Mr. McCutcheon for his attendance. The committee will report to the Sub-Committee on EU Scrutiny that it has completed its consideration of the proposal.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Joint Flights and Land Transit: Motions.</heading>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_140">The next item is the consideration of two motions concerning initiatives by the Italian Republic with a view to adopting a Council decision on the organisation of joint flights for removal from the territory of two or more member states of third country nationals who are subjects of individual removal orders and a Council directive on assistance in cases of transit through the territory of one or more member states in the context of removal orders by member states against third country nationals. I welcome the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform and his officials.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Deputy McDowell)</from>
          <p eId="para_141">I thank the committee for the invitation to give a briefing on two initiatives proposed by the Italian Republic - one with a view to adopting a Council decision on the shared organisation of joint flights for removals of third country nationals illegally present on the territory of two or more member states, and the other with a view to adopting a Council directive on assistance in cases of transit through the national territory of one or more member states.</p>
          <p eId="para_142">Members may wonder why these initiatives are coming from the Italian Republic. Under a pillar of the European treaties, member states, as opposed to the Commission, may come forward with initiatives which do not get far unless they have unanimous support. It is still an area in which member states have a power of initiative and that is why these proposals have been made by the Italians.</p>
          <p eId="para_143">I will begin with an overview of both proposals and I hope to explain the current state of negotiations, what will be involved if agreement is reached on the proposals and where they fit into overall EU policy development in this area. I will then gladly respond to questions members may have on the proposals.</p>
          <p eId="para_144">I understand that members of the committee have been given a copy of the Council Documents COM 12025/03, on the proposed joint flights decision, and COM 12026/03, on the assistance during land transit directive, both dated 9 September 2003. Both of these initiatives were proposed by one member state, Italy, and not by the European Commission. Such proposals are processed in the same manner and have the same validity as if they had been initiated by the Commission. However, the right of individual member states to initiate such proposals in the asylum and immigration area will end in May 2004. This is likely to be one of the final national proposals to come before us.</p>
          <p eId="para_145">Both draft instruments presented to the Council include recitals to the effect that Ireland is not taking part in the adoption of the directive and decision and, therefore, without prejudice to Article 4 of the protocol, is not bound by them or subject to their application. These recitals will be amended to reflect Ireland's decision to opt in under Article 3 of the protocol, assuming the approval of the Oireachtas has been given. This is one of the cases provided for in the Constitution. The Oireachtas must give its say so if the Government chooses to exercise an option or discretion under that aspect of the European treaties.</p>
          <p eId="para_146">I propose to first examine the proposal for a Council decision on the shared organisation of joint flights. The purpose of this decision is to improve co-operation between member states in implementing measures for the removal and return of third country nationals illegally residing in the state. If adopted, the decision will oblige participating states to advise each other whenever joint flights for the removal of illegally resident third country nationals are organised, indicating the number of seats available on board and inviting the participation of other member states.</p>
          <p eId="para_147">The organising member state will appoint a leader for the operation, select a suitable air carrier, arrange the necessary contract and then ensure the carrier obtains a flight plan, necessary fly-over permits and landing authorisation at the destinations and intermediate places. It will be up to the participating member states to ensure enough escort personnel are provided for each third country national removed. This decision has been under discussion at EU level for several months and was discussed last week at the Justice and Home Affairs Council in Brussels, which I attended. The Council intends to adopt this decision once the European Parliament has delivered its opinion and when the scrutiny parliamentary reservations entered by France and the Netherlands have been lifted. The implementation date is May 2004.</p>
          <p eId="para_148">From Ireland's point of view, joint charters are a more efficient and effective means of removing increased numbers of third country nationals who are the subject of deportation orders. Charters are used extensively by the UK and other member states acting on their own initiative or in conjunction with other neighbouring states. Until now, Ireland has used commercial flights to effect the majority of its removal orders. There have only been three occasions where deportees could not be removed using commercial flights and, at the request of the Garda national immigration bureau, charter flights have been used. The first chartered flight took place in January 2002 to Algiers, the second in March 2002 to Lagos and the third, also to Lagos, in November 2002. Ireland intends to make effective use of the proposed joint charter decision as it offers a more effective and cost saving way of removing persons with deportation decisions.</p>
          <p eId="para_149">The second proposal, if adopted, will oblige participating states to provide each other with the necessary support and assistance when travelling through the territory of one or more member states for the purposes of carrying out removal orders of third country nationals. It also includes sea crossings between two points within the same country. This directive complements an earlier proposal put forward by Germany which offers assistance to member states carrying out removal orders by air. The land transit directive provides for a range of assistance measures, including accommodation and subsistence needs. The assistance on offer would involve, for example, meeting expellees and their escorts on arrival at border crossings and making sure the transit operation is carried out effectively. Importantly, the proposed directive provides that escorting personnel shall not carry weapons during a transit operation, shall wear civilian clothes and shall only use reasonable and proportionate action to deal with any serious and immediate risks which may arise in accordance with national legislation.</p>
          <p eId="para_150">This proposal is still under discussion at the EU migration and expulsion working group. The implementation date for this initiative is also May 2004. These initiatives come under title IV of the treaty establishing the European Community. This means they do not automatically apply to Ireland or the UK. However, under Article 3 of the fourth protocol to the Treaty of Amsterdam, to which the UK is also a party, Ireland has three months from the date a proposal or initiative is presented to the Council to notify the president of the Council in writing of its wish to take part in the adoption and application of any such proposed measure.</p>
          <p eId="para_151">The approval of both Houses of the Oireachtas is required before such a notification can be made. Members will be familiar with this process in the exercise of previous opt ins. Ireland has exercised the option in respect of a number of other proposals for EU instruments, mainly in regard to asylum and judicial co-operation matters. With the proposed joint flights decision and the land transit directive, the three month notification deadline is 26 November 2003.</p>
          <p eId="para_152">Ireland should respond positively to both these instruments. Ireland has issued a declaration that it intends to take part in the adoption of measures pursuant to title IV of the treaty establishing the European Community to the maximum extent compatible with the maintenance of the common travel arrangements with the UK. As there are no freedom of movement provisions in the proposed directive or decision, it is unlikely to have an impact on the common travel arrangements. I expect the UK will also opt in.</p>
          <p eId="para_153">Both initiatives were presented by Italy to the Council on 27 August 2003 and have their legal basis in Article 63(3)(b) of the treaty establishing the European Communities. This article deals with the obligation of the Council to adopt measures in the area of illegal immigration and illegal residents, including the repatriation of illegal residents. The current proposals should be considered in the context of other important Community measures in the area of expulsion that have been adopted or are under discussion under the same article. First is Council Directive 2001/40/EC on the mutual recognition of the expulsion decision. This was adopted by the Council on 28 May 2001 and makes it possible for member states to recognise the expulsion decisions made in another member state. Ireland has opted into this directive following earlier Oireachtas approval.</p>
          <p eId="para_154">Related to this is the proposed Council directive to compensate member states for financial imbalances arising from the application of the mutual recognition directive. This decision was agreed at last week's Justice and Home Affairs Council and, on behalf of Ireland, I indicated our intention to participate under Article 4 of the fourth Protocol of the Amsterdam treaty, which allows Ireland and the UK to opt in any time after the adoption of a measure. In Ireland's case, this is subject to Government and Oireachtas approval beforehand.</p>
          <p eId="para_155">Another measure relevant in this area is the proposed German Council directive on providing mutual assistance during transit for removal by air. This is similar to the land transit under discussion today and effectively means that the member states will provide each other with a range of assistance measures in cases of transit for the purpose of expelling by air illegally resident third country nationals who are the subject of expulsion orders in member states. This is valuable to us since, if we are moving someone via London to Lagos, the British have power under European law to help us keep that person in custody while he or she is moved from one aircraft to another.</p>
          <p eId="para_156">The Council has given the European Commission a mandate to negotiate readmission agreements with 11 countries or entities on behalf of the member states. These are at various stages of negotiation and when finally concluded will greatly facilitate the removal and return of illegally resident third country nationals from the territory of member states. In that regard, if the European Commission has greater clout and leverage with third countries of origin, it gives us a huge advantage if it negotiates an agreement on our behalf.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Deputy Deasy</from>
          <p eId="para_157">Does the Minister have a list of those countries?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_41" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_158">I do not have a list of the countries but I can arrange for them to be provided. I do not want to be inaccurate because I know the list only from a verbal briefing by Commissioner Antonio Vitorino. I will come up with as many as I can and will notify the committee in writing of the full list.</p>
          <p eId="para_159">All those Community measures are in accordance with a comprehensive plan to combat illegal immigration and trafficking in human beings in the EU, which was approved by the Council on 28 February 2002 as well as the plan for the management of the external borders of the EU, approved by the Council on 13 June 2002, which was confirmed by the return action programme, approved by the Council on 28 November 2002.</p>
          <p eId="para_160">As I have already mentioned, the proposals have their legal basis in Article 63 of the treaty establishing the European Communities. The proposed decision and directive are also considered to the building on the Schengen Convention. In essence, the Schengen system involves the abolition of border controls between participating states, together with a series of measures designed to strengthen external EU borders and address participants' security concerns. All EU member states, with the exception of the UK and Ireland, are full participants in the Schengen system, as are Iceland and Norway. The system forms and <i>acquis communautaire </i>- an annex to the Maastricht treaty and the treaty establishing the European Community.</p>
          <p eId="para_161">A Council decision of 28 February 2002 approved Ireland's application to participate in certain aspects of the Schengen <i>aquis </i>in regard to police and judicial co-operation, certain immigration measures and the Schengen information system and data protection.</p>
          <p eId="para_162">I hope my contribution gives a broad contextual understanding of the two measures and the context in which they are being discussed and I am pleased to take members questions. Having noticed the discussion on the Order of Business, many people said this was a vitally important matter and seemed to have views to express but they have not turned up here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Deputy Deasy</from>
          <p eId="para_163">I will not take too long since I support these proposals as recognisable and common sense measures. We constantly refer to the cost of the immigration system to the country, which is close to €350 million. In that context, how much has the Minister calculated we will save through these measures? I have asked such questions and raised concerns about the amount of money we are spending on the chartering of aircraft and commercial flights, as well as the cost which adds up in regard to the Garda escorts.</p>
          <p eId="para_164">I presume that, in some cases, these third countries have more aircraft than us. As I understand it, these measures could bring a benefit to Ireland in regard to the financial cost. However, I do not want this to be a good reason or attraction for deporting more people. If it is executed properly, this is a common sense measure which could save us a lot of money. How much does the Minister expect to save on air travel?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_43" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_165">I cannot answer that because it depends on how effective the measure is. The Deputy might ask if anything similar to this in operation. I am constantly mystified why European directives have to issue in respect of issues which are common sense. However, the advantage of such directives is that they give a legal basis for custody and so on which would otherwise require primary legislation and perhaps an international convention to back it up.</p>
          <p eId="para_166">The UK immigration service currently offers a facility to the Garda national immigration bureau. It has a weekly charter flight from Stansted Airport to Kosovo and Albania for the purpose of deporting persons to those countries. That co-operation began in 2002 and according to the Garda works well. In total, 13 Kosovars and four Albanians have been removed from Ireland using that charter facility and there has been only one report of a disruptive passenger.</p>
          <p eId="para_167">Deputy Deasy asked how much is saved by such and arrangement. We would have to decide whether it is reasonable to detain groups of non-nationals long enough to accumulate a sufficient group and, if one was to do that, what kind of aircraft one would charter. I do not know the exact costs of what are effectively air taxis because we are dealing with such small numbers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_168">Where would we keep them?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_45" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_169">They would have to be lodged in Mountjoy or Wheatfield prisons pending their deportation, which is not a happy situation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Deputy Deasy</from>
          <p eId="para_170">Have we co-operated with countries in this regard before?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_47" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_171">We have co-operated with the UK in regard to the Kosovars and are in negotiations with Dutch authorities to set up a similar scheme. We hope to have a joint flight with the Netherlands authorities to Romania at the end of the month. That is the kind of practical co-operation we are talking about. The amount of money this saves depends on how many people one sends on any particular flight. It is difficult to put a figure on it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Deputy Deasy</from>
          <p eId="para_172">How much are we spending on this currently?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_49" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_173">For the year 2003, the figure is €1 million. Last year, the figure was €1.8 million and the year before that, €900,000. In 2000, it was €300,00 and in 1999, €21,000. The average <i>per capita </i>cost has declined from €3,589 to €2,698 over that period because we are doing more of it.</p>
          <p eId="para_174">I will tell anyone who will listen that, when one thinks of the decisions one must take for which €1 million would come in handy, these are significant sums of money. In 2003, we deported 398 people so far for just more than €1 million, which is a small fraction of the number of deportation orders which I have signed during the year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Deputy Deasy</from>
          <p eId="para_175">Do those figures relate to the cost of the flights only or do they include Garda resources and time?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_51" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_176">I imagine they relate to the cost of the flights and do not include the escort costs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_177">Does Deputy Costello wish to commence a line of questioning?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_178">I wish to raise a few points. Does the Minister agree that this is a fairly substantial and serious matter and that we will have to amend the original draft instrument from which we dissented? We indicated that we were not going to be part and parcel of this procedure. We were entitled to opt out under the Schengen acquis but now we are indicating that we wish to opt in. We have a substantial new decision on the matter which not only requires an amendment for Ireland in respect of the protocol but also, as the Minister indicates, may well require secondary legislation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_54" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_179">Although the draft document before the committee recites the fact that we had opted out or, to put it more accurately, were not opting in, that is not the case. That is just standard drafting. Unless they had a clear signal from us that we were in, we were recited as not being in. We never actually came to a conclusion one way or another on this issue——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_180">Is it the case that we had not opted in but are now doing so?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_56" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_181">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_182">Can I take it that the draft document is inaccurate? It says that the initial instrument includes the recital at paragraph 9 to the effect that Ireland is not taking part.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_58" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_183">The point is that the Italian State composes its own draft. It does not consult us to the point where we can ask it to change this or that. It is an automatic default situation. If Britain and Ireland are not in, the recitation is stuck in the draft. If France, Germany or anyone else tenders one of these documents, they stick a sentence in the recitals to the effect that the United Kingdom and Ireland are not opting in, unless they get a clear signal that we are.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_184">Does it mean we are opting out if we are not opting in?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_60" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_185">We have to opt in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_186">We have to opt in otherwise they will say we have opted out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_62" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_187">They will say that we are not exercising our options and recite that in their recitals. It is almost like something that is on the word processor. It comes out unless we——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_188">Then we did not really say no.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_64" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_189">No, and we are not changing our minds either.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_190">We just did not say yes. Now we are saying yes and are opting in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_66" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_191">That is correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_67">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_192">Will secondary legislation be required to give effect to our opt in? The draft document says secondary legislation by way of a statutory instrument may be required.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_68" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_193">It depends.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_69">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_194">Yes or no?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_195">We are not at a tribunal now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_71" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_196">Our arrangement with Britain does not require any secondary legislation at the moment. We simply bring people to Britain in custody - handcuffs may or may not be used - and they are put on the flights to Nigeria or wherever. That is how it happens now. It is debatable whether it would be desirable to have a statutory instrument under the European Communities Act providing for this or if we should just proceed with the directive providing a legal base.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_197">These matters should be sorted out before it is presented to us here. I do not see any reason——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_73" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_198">The answer is I do not——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_199">It does, at least, require approval by the Oireachtas and this is what the Minister is looking for now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_75" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_200">All I am looking for now is approval by both Houses of the Oireachtas for us to opt in. The directive, if it becomes binding and is adopted by other member states, will bind us when we opt in. When it binds us, it becomes a matter of the Attorney General's legal opinion whether it is sufficient that it exists as a directive or whether we need further primary or secondary elaborating legislation. These issues will follow from our decision to opt in.</p>
          <p eId="para_201">The clock is ticking against us at this stage. We have until 26 November to opt in. We can sort out the ramifications of how we will live up to our obligations at a later stage. The question is whether we agree to opt in or not. Ireland is one of the few countries in Europe where a Minister is not merely bound by statute but by the Constitution to come and ask for permission to do something like this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_202">Can we have clarity on this? Is there a 26 November deadline? Can we not make our decision at a future date when we have got this properly organised and know whether we need secondary legislation or if the United Kingdom is opting in? The Minister is not able to tell us whether the United Kingdom will join. What are the implications for us if it does not? Most of the other countries are not bound by the Schengen agreement anyway. It seems to me that we are coming at this half cocked. The whole purpose of the Schengen <i>acquis </i>was to allow us the freedom to opt in or out of the various protocols without facing a deadline demanding our decision.</p>
          <p eId="para_203">I would just like to mention a few other points.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_204">We can just go with one point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_78" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_205">May I just deal with that point? I cannot oblige Britain or pre-empt its decision. I have indicated that it is my understanding that the British will opt in on the first of these measures. They may not opt in on the second on the basis that they have so many direct flights to London that the idea of sending people across land for deportation is unattractive.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_79">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_206">Will the Irish not be able to cross over the United Kingdom by land?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_80" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_207">We will have to see whether that is one of the things affected. It might help us if the British joined on this but I cannot force their hand on it. They have a free choice to opt in or out.</p>
          <p eId="para_208">I would put a second point to Deputy Costello. Once a directive is made, it is a done deal. One of the advantages of opting in is that we can participate in the wording of the directive. When attending the Justice and Home Affairs Council Ireland and the United Kingdom are in a kind of neutral or semi-detached position. Unless they exercise an option, they cannot just chip in and say they do not like clause 3 of a directive and want it amended. If they did they would be quickly reminded by the Chair that they had not opted in on this and it was none of their business. They would be told that the other member states were in on it and that if they wanted to come in to negotiate the text of the directive and how it should apply, they would have to come on board and say that they were getting involved in the process. Essentially we have to put up or shut up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_209">Could we explore that? If we are going to get involved in the process we have to opt in by 26 November or whatever. The process was initiated by the Italian Government which has in a sense run it and is now presenting it to the other members with this deadline. To what extent will negotiations continue from that point or do the beginning of negotiations on the text of the document begin once we reach the deadline of the opt in or opt out clause?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_82" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_210">No, once the opt-ins take place, negotiation and amendment can take place in the process which brings it forward. This raises an interesting and tricky constitutional question for us. If I go there with the committee's say-so and opt in and then the directive turns into a wholly different one and the sense of it is totally changed, do I have, effectively, a blank cheque to sign up? When I was Attorney General the answer to that was if something was substantially different at the end of the process than when the right to negotiate was given, we would have to come back and get another licence to agree. I do not believe there will be much more apart from drafting changes on this.</p>
          <p eId="para_211">One of the difficulties is that it is perfectly reasonable for our European partners to say we cannot get involved in negotiations if we are completely neutral as to whether this will affect us. In a body where it is difficult enough to get a consensus there are people who are both negotiating and keeping their exit clause open. The short answer to the question Deputy Costello is posing is that I cannot assist him in a clinical way. There is a point at which, if we opted into negotiations and the thing became a cow rather than a horse, I would feel obliged to come back and get a second authorisation for a final vote.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_212">I will let Deputy Costello ask this question and then we will return to Deputy Deasy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_213">Does that mean we are buying a pig in a poke?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_214">A cow and a horse.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_215">It depends to what degree it will be changed. If there is, what the Minister would consider a minor amendment, or a more substantial amendment, he will have the discretion, if we give him the go-ahead, to opt into the negotiations as distinct from opting into the finished product or opting out. With our go-ahead, the Minister will have full discretion to determine whether to come back to us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_87" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_216">I feel like a dentist approaching Deputy Costello with a syringe, saying trust me, trust me.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_217">The Schengen agreement, as I understand it, would mostly mean not opting in to negotiations; it would be opting in to a finished product. When we see the finished product we decide whether we want to go in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_89">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_218">Is the Minister going to report back to this committee?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_90" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_219">I always do; I keep reporting back to the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_91">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_220">Could you refer this back to the committee after the meeting?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_92" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_221">I am asking for the committee's authority to become involved in the discussions and negotiations. I will take it as a licence to proceed to full adoption unless what I hear is radically different.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" eId="spk_93">
          <from>Deputy Deasy</from>
          <p eId="para_222">Perhaps the Minister can explain the practical side of the sharing of costs. We are talking about another country with individuals from a particular country. Who shares the cost in this case? How does that structure work? How is it set up?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_94" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_223">If Ireland was preparing a flight to Romania we would be obliged, under the first of these two measures, to notify other member states that we were preparing a flight to Romania, leaving Dublin on a certain date. It would then be open to the Dutch to say that they have four Romanian people they want to bring and that they will fly them to Dublin. It is a matter of agreement. We are not obliged to allow the Dutch to wade on board the plane at a fixed price. It is a matter for agreement between the two governments, but I cannot imagine the circumstances in which either the Dutch or Ireland would agree to anything other than an average percentage of the cost. If it is costing Ireland, €500,000 or €100,000 to fly 12 people home, the normal course would be that if the Dutch turn up with 10% of the potential passenger load they would be billed for 10% of the cost. There could be exceptional circumstances in which it would vary, but I presume that the Dutch would be intelligent people and would not pay more than their fair share of the operation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" eId="spk_95">
          <from>Deputy Deasy</from>
          <p eId="para_224">Presumably the Minister can negotiate with any member state?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_96" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_225">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_97">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_226">I have a question about escorts. Article 9 says that in the absence of law enforcement officers from the requested member state, escort personnel may take reasonable and proportionate action to deal with a serious and immediate risk, etc. Whereas I can see that the escorts the Minister would employ as Minister for Justice and Law Reform would use reasonable methods, is there a possibility that other countries could use methods like sedation by intravenous methods, such as injection?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_98" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_227">As far as I know sedation is never used. The Taoiseach said today that nation states retain their sovereignty in respect of these matters. If I or the gardaí saw some third country national being abused or improperly treated, the Irish Constitution and Irish criminal law apply to such a person. The term "reasonable and proportionate action" would be subject to Irish criminal law. One could not have somebody doing something which an Irish policeman in similar circumstances could not do. It is very hard to put in a formula what that may amount to. For instance, is it absolutely essential to handcuff people? That is one question. If one is dealing with a family of husband, wife and children, it is probably unnecessary to handcuff anybody. One could have difficult people, which we have had, when they went berserk and bit and kicked people. In the courts recently a person was released on a technicality and rearrested. The immigration officer's arm was broken in the Four Courts when the arrest took place. People behave very violently on occasion. Proportionate and reasonable force is effectively what is necessary to ensure that people cannot frustrate the deportation. It does not go to terrible extremes. It does not go to sedation or gagging, to my knowledge.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_228">I suppose it would be a reasonable presumption that Ireland would not be party to assisting other countries in the transit of people, either by land or sea, unless they were going to the United States, as everything would be heading in an easterly or south-westerly direction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_100" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_229">It could happen theoretically. If one examines the situation where a person from Northern Ireland was to be deported from Shannon to somewhere else, one can imagine that it would be by land transit. It could happen.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_101">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_230">Yes. Given that this is operating in the context of 25 countries, to what extent does it make Ireland party to the decisions and rules of those countries in respect of asylum seekers and the people expelled? We are going to be facing a situation caused by the Supreme Court decision, which was made last Christmas, on the expulsion of thousands of Irish-born children. This is in the context of 11,000 people who will effectively face mass deportation. That would be peculiar to Ireland in terms of asylum applications, etc. There was a mention today in the Dáil of the policies of Silvio Berlusconi towards refugees around the coasts of Italy and the fact that this is an Italian initiative not coming from the Council of Ministers or the Commission. This is an initiative of an individual state. Do we know what sort of briefing document was produced by the Italians to indicate that they wanted this particular approach on this issue?</p>
          <p eId="para_231">Major issues are raised by this. The Minister stated that people would be held in prisons, or could be if awaiting deportation, or in transit. It was stated that the various other jurisdictions would come into play and the sovereignty of each jurisdiction would apply. No doubt the general rules on detention and armed police and the distinctive operations of each country would be issues that would arise if this particular procedure goes ahead. Perhaps the Minister might indicate his position?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_102" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_232">I think I have the drift of the Deputy's questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_103">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_233">Are there any other questions? I want Deputy Costello to put together——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_234">We could easily have armed escorts coming into this country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_105" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_235">Under this arrangement, an explicit exclusion is made in terms of anybody being armed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_236">That is specific.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_107">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_237">Is the Minister referring to batons, firearms and all weapons?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_108" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_238">Firearms.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_109">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_239">So, irrespective of how they are armed, members of a police force in a particular jurisdiction cannot enter another jurisdiction while——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_110" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_240">They cannot carry firearms into another jurisdiction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_111">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_241">They can just carry handcuffs and batons.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_112" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_242">They have to be allowed to use handcuffs otherwise the entire system would be unworkable.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_113">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_243">Will the Deputy conclude his questions on this matter?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_114">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_244">That is all I have to offer in terms of what happens——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_115" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_245">May I deal with the question at which I believe the Deputy was driving?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_116">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_246">The Minister may do so.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_117" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_247">Across the European Union, measures are about to be agreed - we hope during the Italian Presidency but definitely during our Presidency - under which there will be common criteria for recognising and dealing with asylum seekers. These measures will not be entirely uniform because different member states will have their own ways of dealing with matters of this nature. However, the fundamental structure will be one under which everyone will be obliged to observe the same minimum rules.</p>
          <p eId="para_248">Sweden is regarded as being far more liberal than many other member states. Ireland, because of its high <i>per capita </i>rate of asylum seekers, must be liberal. The latter is the only explanation why people travel so far to get here.</p>
          <p eId="para_249">People have been asking about particular matters and it is important to place the following information on record, In 1999, 126 deportation orders were made and six people were actually deported; in 2000, 930 orders were made and 187 were actually carried out; in 2001, 1,985 orders were made and 365 were carried out; in 2002, 2,464 orders were made and 521 were carried out and, to date in 2003, 1,955 orders have been made and 472 have been carried out. I must also point out that in 1999, 37 people left the country through assisted voluntary passages; in 2000, 248 left in this way; in 2001, there were 356 such departures; in 2002, there were 506; and, to date in 2003, 648 have left the country voluntarily. If one added together the deportation orders effected this year and the number of voluntary returns, one would arrive at a figure of over 1,000 out of 1,955. These orders and returns do not necessarily involve the same people, because they are people in arrears. However, if one considers the trend, the picture is not as appalling as a man on a bar stool might claim - none of them is ever sent home. It is now approaching 50% to 60%.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_118">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_250">There are other bars where people would say the picture is even more appalling.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_119" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_251">I apologise, I gave the figure. It is not that high. The 648 would not be part of the 1,955. I was wrong, I retract what I said.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_120">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_252">There is no direct correlation between the two figures.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_121" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_253">If someone says that they intend to return home in any event, we will assist them in doing so and the deportation order is not then made. The figure is not as good as I indicated. It is running at approximately 20%, not 60%.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_122">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_254">Twenty per cent——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_123" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_255">That percentage of deportations are effected. However, there are a number of people who leave before the deportation orders are made. It would be wrong for me to express these as a percentage of the total because they are, in effect, in addition to that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_124">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_256">Are there some people among the 1,955 who are appealing against their deportation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_125" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_257">I suppose there are some who would. For example, some decisions are made in cases where there is a humanitarian need to remain after the deportation order has been made. Some people are challenging the orders in the courts.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_258">We are talking about 700 or 800 people. Is there another category?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_127" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_259">As already mentioned, 648 people already returned home voluntarily this year when it was pointed out to them that they did not have a leg to stand on. Deportation orders did not have to be made in respect of these people.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_128">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_260">Out of the 1,955?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_129" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_261">No. The 648 are in addition to that figure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_130">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_262">How many of the 1,955 have ignored their deportation orders?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_131" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_263">It appears that approximately 80% of them have not been caught. In that regard, however, approximately 50% of those who apply for asylum disappear on the day after they make their application. We never hear from these individuals again. Deportation orders are eventually made against them because they would have entered the country, applied for asylum and their application would be deemed to be refused. The files eventually come to my office and I sign the deportation orders.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_132">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_264">That is fine.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_133">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_265">There would then be a vast discrepancy between each of those figures and the number of applicants.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_134">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_266">It would be extremely difficult for us to sort through those figures. There is a great deal of obfuscation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_135" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_267">The number of asylum seekers is decreasing at present.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" eId="spk_136">
          <from>Deputy Deasy</from>
          <p eId="para_268">I wish to follow up on one of Deputy Costello's comments. I presume that, in some cases, people who are going to be deported are languishing in Mountjoy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_137">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_269">Is the Deputy moving on to prisons now?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" eId="spk_138">
          <from>Deputy Deasy</from>
          <p eId="para_270">No, I am just wondering about the period.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_139" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_271">The maximum period is eight weeks. It would not frequently be the case that someone would be there for eight weeks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnDeasyFG" eId="spk_140">
          <from>Deputy Deasy</from>
          <p eId="para_272">However, some people would be there for a few weeks before transportation could be arranged. I presume this measure would expedite matters.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_141" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_273">It must be remembered that virtually all of the people in those cases would effectively be given the option of returning home. Someone whose situation is pointed out to them as being groundless is given the option of going home. We do not put people in prison out of some sense of retribution. Our aim is that everyone would go home as soon as their situation——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_142">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_274">Are any arrangements made for the children of people who may be in Mountjoy? We visited Mountjoy recently and there was——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_143" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_275">It does not have to be Mountjoy; it could be Wheatfield.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_144">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_276">——a child, who was not in the prison, involved in one particular case.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_145" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_277">If somebody is the subject of a deportation order they are, in the first instance, invited to attend at a Garda station and they will only be arrested if they evade the deportation order. Members will recognise - from the point of view of the Garda this is common sense - that we want people to co-operate with the procedure and we do not want to have to execute orders or make them the subject of unnecessary legal procedures.</p>
          <p eId="para_278">With regard to deportations that have been effected, the top five countries since 1999 are: Romania, with 425 - this is probably explained by the fact that it is a European country with which we have a return agreement; the Czech Republic with 223; Poland with 203; China with 80 and Nigeria, from which 30% to 40% immigrants to this country come, with 78. There is obviously much greater difficulty involved in effecting deportations to Nigeria because we do not have direct flights. We have a return agreement with Nigeria but its operation is causing much more difficulty with other states.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_146">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_279">I presume that this particular measure would facilitate deportations to Nigeria.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_147">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_280">I thank the Minister and his officials for their attendance and for the work they have done on the various motions. Can I take it the committee recommends there should not be further debate on the motion in the Dáil or the Seanad?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_148">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_281">I am not sure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_149">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_282">Unfortunately, the wording of such motions has been amended following agreement between various Whips and every committee chairman will be obliged to put this question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_150">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_283">The Chair is asking to us make a recommendation contrary to the division in the Dáil an hour ago. The Dáil divided on this issue. Those presenting for the division felt the motion should be debated by both Houses because it is a major issue. If the committee recommends that both Houses should not debate it further, it means the minority is recommending the majority should behave in a certain way. Generally, it is the other way around.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_151">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_284">The question must be put to a vote similar to an amendment to a Bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_152" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_285">All Deputies and Senators are entitled to attend the committee, not merely to make a speech but also to interrogate the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_153">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_286">I thank the Minister and his officials for their attendance and look forward to meeting them again in the near future.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_5">
        <heading>Messages to the Dáil and Seanad.</heading>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_154">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_287">In accordance with Standing Order 85, the following message will be send to the Dáil:</p>
          <p eId="para_288">The Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women's Rights has completed its consideration of the Joint Flights and Land Transit motion.</p>
          <p eId="para_289">In accordance with Standing Order 67 the following message will be sent to the Seanad:</p>
          <p eId="para_290">The Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women's Rights has completed its consideration of the Joint Flights and Land Transit motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">The joint committee adjourned at 7.45 p.m. until 3.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 19 November 2003.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
