<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2018-11-15/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2018-11-15/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2018-11-15" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/32/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2018-11-15/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2018-11-15/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2018-11-15" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2018-11-15/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2018-11-15/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-02-20" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="CatherineMartin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Catherine-Martin.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Catherine Martin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FionaOLoughlin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Fiona-O'Loughlin.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Fiona O'Loughlin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JanOSullivan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jan-O'Sullivan.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Jan O'Sullivan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="KathleenFunchion" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Kathleen-Funchion.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Kathleen Funchion"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LynnRuane" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Lynn-Ruane.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Lynn Ruane"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MariaByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Maria-Byrne.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Maria Byrne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulGavan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Gavan.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Paul Gavan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RobbieGallagher" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Robbie-Gallagher.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Robbie Gallagher"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ThomasByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Thomas-Byrne.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Thomas Byrne"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Acting_Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/office/acting_chairman" showAs="Acting Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM OIDEACHUS AGUS SCILEANNA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Education and Skills</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2018-11-15">Déardaoin, 15 Samhain 2018</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2018-11-15">Thursday, 15 November 2018</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 10:30 a.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 10:30 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#ThomasByrne">Thomas Byrne</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#MariaByrne">Maria Byrne</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#KathleenFunchion">Kathleen Funchion</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#RobbieGallagher">Robbie Gallagher</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#CatherineMartin">Catherine Martin</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulGavan">Paul Gavan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#HildegardeNaughton">Hildegarde Naughton</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#LynnRuane">Lynn Ruane.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#JanOSullivan">Jan O'Sullivan.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#FionaOLoughlin">Teachta / Deputy Fiona O'Loughlin sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Business of Joint Committee<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:30:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_1">
          <from> Clerk to the Committee<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_12">In the unavoidable absence of the Chair, I seek nominations for temporary Chairperson.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_13">I propose Deputy Catherine Martin.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_14">I second that proposal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_4">
          <from> Clerk to the Committee<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_15">As there are no other nominations, I ask Deputy Catherine Martin to take the Chair.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">
          <i>Deputy Catherine Martin took the Chair. </i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Acting Chairman (Deputy Catherine Martin)<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_16">I remind members to turn their mobile phones off when attending committee meetings. It is proposed to defer the private session until the end of the meeting. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i> Sitting suspended at 10.37 a.m. and resumed at 10.40 a.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Uptake of Apprenticeships and Traineeships: Discussion<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:40:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Acting Chairman (Deputy Catherine Martin)<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_17">I remind members and witnesses to turn off their mobile phones or switch them to flight mode because they interfere with the sound system and make it difficult for parliamentary reporters to report the meeting. Television coverage and web-streaming can also be adversely affected.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> The purpose of this part of the meeting is to have an engagement with a number of stakeholders on the uptake of apprenticeships and traineeships. On behalf of the committee, I welcome Dr. Jim Murray, director of academic affairs and deputy CEO of the Technological Higher Education Association, THEA, Mr. Brendan McGinty, chairperson of Skillnet Ireland, Dr. Mary-Liz Trant, executive director of SOLAS and Mr. Phil O'Flaherty, principal officer, further education and training section of the Department of Education and Skills.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> I will invite witnesses to make a brief opening statement, a maximum of three minutes each, which will be followed by engagement with members of the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_20"> I draw the attention of witnesses to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee. However, if they are directed by the Chairman to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence. They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable. </p>
          <p eId="para_21"> Any opening statements made to the committee will be published on the committee website after the meeting. </p>
          <p eId="para_22"> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> I call on Dr. Jim Murray to make his opening statement. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_24">Before the witnesses begin, I will have to leave for a few minutes at a certain point. The Chairman, Deputy O'Loughlin, is on her way but we will both have to leave to do a press conference. We will be back. I do not mean to show disrespect.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_8">
          <from> Dr. Jim Murray<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_25">On behalf of the Technological Higher Education Association, THEA, and its members, the 14 institutes of technology, I thank the committee for the invitation to its meeting to discuss the uptake of apprenticeships and traineeships.</p>
          <p eId="para_26"> The technological higher education sector is a strong supporter of apprenticeship and it will remain a key element of its provision into the future. The first technological university, TU Dublin, will be the largest educational facilitator of apprenticeship programmes in the country when it is designated in January 2019. Of THEA's fourteen members, 12 contribute to the provision of the off-the-job elements of some 23 of the designated craft apprenticeships. Of the nine new apprenticeships launched since 2016, seven are led by THEA members, as co-ordinating providers, in areas as diverse as polymer processing technology and insurance practice. In addition, institutes of technology are the proposed co-ordinating providers for a further ten new apprenticeships under development. </p>
          <p eId="para_27"> Apprenticeship, in the Irish context, is a statutory national programme that enables the apprentice to earn and learn at the same time and is traditionally associated with the construction, electrical, automotive and engineering industries. The great advantage of this approach is that it not only provides the opportunity to the apprentice to learn on the job but also to participate fully as an employee in a real-world work environment. The new apprenticeships aim to extend this approach more broadly into sectors that have not traditionally been associated with apprenticeships. It is a fresh, ambitious and innovative undertaking which THEA believes has the potential to bring about very significant enhancements to the apprenticeship system as a whole and to employment sectors that identify and choose it as the optimal model for educating and training their staff in particular occupations. </p>
          <p eId="para_28"> THEA views statutory national apprenticeships as one key element in a broad family of education and training programmes that are based on a learn and work model. This model also includes traineeships and non-apprenticeship programmes provided by the further education and higher education sectors that have varying levels of non-paid, work-based learning embedded within them. These include work placements integrated into regular degree programmes and bespoke programmes developed for individual companies. It is important to offer this mixed portfolio of work-based learning to enhance the employability of all graduates and it is equally important that employment sectors give consideration to which model is most suited to their recruitment needs. </p>
          <p eId="para_29"> Employers are primarily responsible for recruiting apprentices, not the education providers. Employers are best placed to comment on why there have been difficulties in recruiting apprentices in certain sectors. Our members are closer to the recruitment process of the new apprenticeships and their experience to date suggests recruitment tends to be more successful when an employment sector is well organised and has a strong professional association behind it that can determine whether apprenticeship is an appropriate work-based learning model for that sector. A strong professional association also helps to mobilise individual companies in recruiting apprentices and can support that recruitment directly. </p>
          <p eId="para_30"> There are significant challenges for all stakeholders in increasing the uptake of apprenticeships and, specifically, in meeting the targets enunciated in the 2016 action plan. Arguably, the greatest challenge relates to enhancing awareness of apprenticeship among the populace at large. Although awareness of apprenticeship has increased in recent years at policy level, it is a far greater communications challenge to raise public awareness of apprenticeship as a valid and valued option for school leavers. The magnitude of the task is reflected in the stark fact that the total apprenticeship population at the end of the 2017-2018 academic year was 14,871, while the total enrolments in public higher education were 235,644. </p>
          <p eId="para_31"> It is also arguable that there is a need to simplify the regulatory environment in which the apprenticeship system operates. It remains subject to the Industrial Training Act 1967, legislation that is 50 years old. While this legislation is sturdy and has stood the test of time, it is not easily reconciled with subsequent education and training legislation, particularly that relating to the national quality assurance system. It has led to a very complex, at times overly bureaucratic system within which to develop the new apprenticeship model. While all the stakeholders have worked collaboratively to make the system work, it has undoubtedly hindered the agility and responsiveness of the system, delaying the throughput of programmes and making it very difficult to predict and deliver registration targets. </p>
          <p eId="para_32"> As national supporters of the apprenticeship model, THEA's view is that apprenticeship is an integral hub in the overall provision of education and training. Our members are significant providers and supporters of the model. We believe that with streamlined employer support, a focus on simplifying the interpretation of the regulations, a re-visit of the recruitment targets in collaboration with the consortia and other stakeholders and a targeted public awareness campaign, the model can be enhanced to reach its full potential.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_9">
          <from> Mr. Brendan McGinty<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_33">I thank the committee for the opportunity to meet it. The primary focus is on discussing issues of apprenticeships and traineeships which for the most part is about points of entry into a career. Our focus in Skillnet Ireland in working with enterprise is about developing employability skills over the work-life cycle when people have taken up employment.</p>
          <p eId="para_34"> In that context, human capital is the single greatest asset any nation can possess. Workers, whether they were born in Ireland or attracted from abroad, are the muscle, brainpower, creative force and energy that drives our economy. </p>
          <p eId="para_35"> In an international context, the IMD’s competitiveness yearbook 2018 ranks Ireland fifth for attracting and retaining talent. The collective talent of our nation is not just the bedrock of our economy today; a well-educated, well-skilled and adaptable workforce has been a core pillar of Ireland’s economic and industrial policy since the 1960s. It is an advantage we must never cede. If we are going to keep that advantage and the promise of opportunity to future generations, we have some work to do. </p>
          <p eId="para_36"> Our economy is being rapidly reshaped by technology, automation, globalisation, geopolitical shifts, including Brexit, and several other forces. The manifestation of changes being discussed in the debate on the future of work are already with us today and are influencing the way companies operate and how work is organised. This affects job content, skill needs and quality requirements. This transformation is creating opportunity but it is also creating disruption and, with it, insecurity for many businesses and workers. Some of this insecurity can be attributed to two gaps that are preventing our nation from leveraging its talent and our people from realising their full potential. The first is a skills gap. Too many people lack the skills they need to compete for 21st century jobs. The second is a people gap. Too many businesses cannot find the workers with the right skills when and where they need them. Closing both gaps is imperative to our competitiveness. </p>
          <p eId="para_37"> It is a multifaceted challenge as skills supply is met in various parts through outputs from our higher and further education system, including apprenticeships and traineeships, from employment activation and supports to jobseekers, and from immigration.</p>
          <p eId="para_38">However, for the greatest part, the skills that power Ireland’s economy are derived from within employment. For this reason, it is crucial that both businesses and workers are placed at the heart of the response.</p>
          <p eId="para_39"> Skillnet Ireland is the national agency responsible for the promotion and facilitation of in-employment training. We have deep roots with enterprise in Ireland and we are contracted with more than 50 employer and sectoral groups, regional representative bodies and industry associations. In 2017, approximately 15,000 private firms participated in Skillnet learning networks and more than 50,000 workers were supported by Skillnet-funded training. We are funded from the National Training Fund and as a demand side agency in that we stimulate and support enterprise-led responses through 65 learning networks across a range of sectors and regions. We operate a cost-sharing model where State grants are combined with investments by businesses. As well as offering a subsidy to encourage upskilling, cost-sharing drives firm employer commitment to the training process. In 2017, employers made a total contribution towards training of €15.91 million through Skillnet.</p>
          <p eId="para_40"> The Skillnet cost-sharing model is also creating significant funding leverage in that every €1 of State investment is matched with €1.14 from employer contributions. This represents a highly efficient use of public moneys and an effective vehicle for State investment in the skills of our workers. For 2019, the annual budget allocation for Skillnet Ireland has been increased to €28 million, equating to approximately 4.5% of total National Training Fund expenditure net of other employer contributions.</p>
          <p eId="para_41"> Through successive independent evaluations both domestic and international, including the OECD, the European Union and the International Labour Organization, the Skillnet model has consistently been highlighted as an efficient means of addressing skills challenges.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Acting Chairman (Deputy Catherine Martin)<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">I ask Mr. McGinty to conclude as he has exceeded his time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_11">
          <from> Mr. Brendan McGinty<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_43">There are particular recommendations I should mention. The Government should maintain a rigorous focus on the skills of those in employment, directing supports at close to labour market skill requirements in targeting interventions that support effective enterprise-led training and preparing more people to take up employment opportunities. It should implement in full the recommendations arising from the independent evaluation of the National Training Fund undertaken by Indecon, including a greater priority being placed on supporting in-employment training and giving enterprise a bigger voice in how this is determined. The Government should also provide greater incentives to firms to increase investment at enterprise level in staff training. Such responses will serve to increase the productivity, innovation and competitiveness of firms and boost the skills and career mobility of workers and the value of jobs. The final recommendation is to continue to expand demonstrably effective Government and enterprise upskilling mechanisms such as Skillnet Ireland to allow us to accelerate our work and penetration, particularly with small and medium enterprises, which employ approximately 70% of our workforce.</p>
          <p eId="para_44"> At this moment of rapid change and massive transition, we must put the talent agenda foremost in our minds. That requires us to bridge the gaps that exist between students and workers and the jobs that will provide them opportunity, security and prosperity. It requires us to bridge the skills and people gaps that exist between the needs of employers and workers, where businesses seek to expand their businesses, serve their communities and grow the economy. Skillnet Ireland provides strong leadership in shaping the future of workforce development by working with enterprise to meet their skill requirements and helping those in work to progress, develop and upskill for the future. We are a strong example of how the State and enterprise can work together to meet identified challenges. With our deep roots in every region and sector, we are determined that these issues are addressed, and with the active support of the Government, all our stakeholders and through collaboration between agencies, we are working hard to play our part in addressing these issues.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Acting Chairman (Deputy Catherine Martin)<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">There will be an opportunity to engage further with members.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_13">
          <from> Mr. Brendan McGinty<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">We appreciate that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_14">
          <from> Dr. Mary-Liz Trant<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">On behalf of SOLAS, I am very pleased to make this statement to the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Education and Skills on the uptake of apprenticeships and traineeships. SOLAS funds and oversees further education and training in Ireland, which includes traineeships, and has statutory responsibility for the national apprenticeship system. The organisation has been closely involved in the national policy to expand apprenticeship and traineeship, supporting the Department of Education and Skills and working with education and training boards, higher education institutions, the Higher Education Authority, Quality and Qualifications Ireland, the enterprise community, apprentices and trainees.</p>
          <p eId="para_48"> Work has been under way since late 2014 on the expansion of apprenticeship in Ireland. It draws on a strong track record, evidence that apprenticeship is an effective way to build the pipeline of talent within industry and a vision of its potential to become a major route to skills development in Ireland. A national Apprenticeship Council appointed by the Minister for Education and Skills is steering the expansion of apprenticeships into new areas of industry and leading to awards from level 5 to level 10 on the national framework of qualifications. SOLAS is represented on the council and acts as the council secretariat.</p>
          <p eId="para_49"> As of this month, November 2018, the number of national apprenticeship programmes stands at 42, up from 27 in 2016. A further 35 programmes are in development. Apprentice registrations have more than doubled from just under 2,000 in 2013 to more than 4,500 as of the end of October 2018. Registrations on craft apprenticeships are exceeding forecasts and although registrations on the 17 newer programmes have been lower than originally envisaged, registrations are rising as the programmes become more established. The new apprenticeships are developed and overseen by industry-led consortia. During 2018 the Apprenticeship Council began engaging with these consortia to discuss progress, employer support for the new programmes and the ambition regarding targets for each apprenticeship by 2020.</p>
          <p eId="para_50"> A review of pathways to participation in apprenticeship was completed this year. As the apprenticeship system expands, it is essential that skills development becomes a realistic, valued option for the widest possible cohort of young and older citizens in Ireland. The review sets out five steps to tackle under-representation and exclusion in the apprenticeship system. A national promotional campaign, Generation Apprenticeship, has been under way since May 2017. It is designed to engage and influence employers, parents, teachers and potential apprentices on the opportunities arising from apprenticeship programmes.</p>
          <p eId="para_51"> The number of traineeships available via education and training boards, ETBs, has increased from 24 in 2016 to 51 as of November 2018. ETBs have been working with employer partners on expansion of traineeship offerings over the past 12 months, in particular since publication by SOLAS, in partnership with ETBs, of the five-step guide to traineeship in Ireland<i>. </i>While the target enrolments for traineeship in 2016 and 2017 were not achieved, enrolments have started to increase in 2018 and there are positive forecasts on traineeship enrolments for 2018 to 2020. The introduction in 2018 of Skills to Advance, a new policy to support upskilling of lower-skilled employees, is also enabling ETBs to adapt traineeship provision so that people at work can access this route to skills development.</p>
          <p eId="para_52"> We ask the committee to note that overall, apprentice registrations are increasing year-on-year, as are the number of participating employers. There are 17 new apprenticeship programmes available, with 35 more in the pipeline. Apprentice registrations on new programmes are, however, in effect one year behind target. Buy-in by employers to the new and expanded apprenticeship offerings will be a key success factor. Regarding traineeship, enrolment targets have so far not been fully met but as of 2018, the trend in enrolments is upwards and there is a strong pipeline of 51 traineeship programmes now available, with positive forecasting on numbers for 2019 and 2020. Similar to apprenticeship, employer buy-in to traineeships will be a key success factor over the next two years.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_15">
          <from> Mr. Phil O'Flaherty<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T10:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_53">I thank the joint committee for the opportunity to discuss the important area of apprenticeship and traineeship. The expansion of apprenticeship and traineeship is a key priority for the Government. The programme for Government and the Action Plan for Education contain a commitment to having a cumulative 50,000 enrolments on apprenticeship and traineeship programmes between 2016 and 2020. This represents more than a doubling of activity over the period. Details of how this overall target would be reached through increased enrolments each year were set out in the Action Plan to Expand Apprenticeship and Traineeship 2016-2020, along with information on a range of supporting initiatives.</p>
          <p eId="para_54"> Apprenticeship and traineeship are an important part of wider efforts to engage employers more closely in the education and training system and to ensure that education and training is meeting current and future skills needs. The programme to expand apprenticeship and traineeship was starting from a difficult position. Apprenticeship suffered enormously during the recession with a fall in registrations of more than 80%.</p>
          <p eId="para_55">This closed an important avenue for young people. As well as giving access to valued careers for learners, apprenticeships and traineeships deliver talented and work-ready people for employers. Rebuilding these pathways to rewarding careers and increasing the pipeline of talent for employers have required significant work and new thinking. </p>
          <p eId="para_56"> It was recognised that apprenticeships and traineeships needed to grow beyond the sectors of the economy that had traditionally engaged with the programmes and that this would need an entirely new approach. Informed by an independent review of the apprenticeship system, the then Minister appointed the Apprenticeship Council in late 2014. The remit of the council was to oversee the development of a range of new apprenticeships, initially through a call for proposals, and examine the issues associated with creating a more flexible and accessible model of apprenticeship that could meet the needs of a diverse range of employers. Alongside this work, the curricula of existing craft apprenticeships were remodelled to keep pace with new methods and technologies in the workplace and ensure apprentices would have the broader range of literacy, numeracy, ICT and team working skills they needed to be successful. Work was also undertaken by SOLAS with the education and training boards to engage with employers to develop a range of new traineeships in growing areas of employment.</p>
          <p eId="para_57"> Really good progress has been made. There has been strong growth in apprenticeship registrations in recent years. Seventeen new programmes have been developed through two open calls for proposals issued by the Apprenticeship Council and a strong pipeline of further programmes is in development. A completely new model of flexible industry-led apprenticeships has been created, with a diverse range of programmes at levels 5 to 9 of the national framework of qualifications now in place. Craft apprenticeships are growing strongly, with industry re-engaging with apprenticeship recruitment. Nonetheless there are challenges. Apprenticeship programmes have taken longer to get off the ground than originally envisaged and registrations of new apprenticeships are approximately a year behind the targets set in the action plan. Female participation in apprenticeships remains low and the recovery in numbers in craft apprenticeships has not been evenly spread across all trades. Traineeships which in the past were primarily for unemployed persons saw some falls in enrolment as unemployment reduced significantly. However, there are plans in place to address these issues and the Department is confident about the future of these important programmes.</p>
          <p eId="para_58"> We are in a new phase of development of apprenticeships and traineeships. All of the key building blocks are in place and there is an excellent base of new programmes. The focus is now on employers and learners. Through the Apprenticeship Council and other partners, we are working hard with employers to ensure they will fully exploit the new opportunities to develop the talent in their workforce. It is only through real partnership and employer support that these important pathways into employment for the first time or career advancement can be opened up. The Government is also working to address the visibility of apprenticeship and traineeship opportunities, promote these pathways to women and other under-represented groups and engage with the career guidance community. The generation apprenticeship campaign is in full swing and the campaign has a lot to promote. Only in the past two weeks, we have seen the first graduates from new apprenticeship programmes, hundreds of craft apprentices receiving their qualifications, the publication of a review of pathways to apprenticeship and the launch of a number of a number of new apprenticeship and traineeship programmes. The Government, assisted by additional contributions from employers to the national training fund, has put significant additional resources into this area. An additional €27 million has been allocated in budget 2019, a tangible commitment to the programmes at a time when there are many competing demands for investment in education and training.</p>
          <p eId="para_59"> I look forward to hearing the contributions of the other bodies involved - I have already heard some of them - and discussing with committee members the progress made and the opportunities and challenges to come.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Acting Chairman (Deputy Catherine Martin)<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_60">I thank Mr. O'Flaherty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LynnRuane" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Senator Lynn Ruane<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_61">While I am a great supporter of apprenticeships, obviously I have major issues with their class dynamic. When Mr. O'Flaherty referred to under-represented groups, I was wondering whether those who were under-represented in the uptake of apprenticeships were from the middle and upper classes. I work with schools in Dublin and teachers of middle class pupils have come to us to ask how they can make apprenticeships attractive to pupils in their schools. They are struggling to get them on board in considering the idea of taking up an apprenticeship. When I think about apprenticeships, I look at them through the lens of my school days when the only option for the majority of my friends and class mates was an apprenticeship. For me, it is about equality of access. It should be about choosing to take up an apprenticeship, rather than being told that it is the only thing available to the student because of who he or she is and from where they come.</p>
          <p eId="para_62"> Many of the delegates have mentioned the growth in registrations for apprenticeships. Part of me thinks it is good to have people working, but I view it in terms of social mobility. The evidence is that parents who only have a second level education and who take up an apprenticeship will keep going straight, while their children's social mobility will continue to spiral downwards. It is about being able to fill the gap; apprenticeships are not only about maintaining a certain number of people in a certain sector of employment, they are also about adding to the future progression and social mobility of young people as they become parents themselves and in terms of what their profession will mean for their children. </p>
          <p eId="para_63"> Since I was at school, there has been a widening of the apprenticeship programmes and sectors involved. Do the delegates have the demographics? Dr. Murray mentioned a figure of 14,871 registrations; SOLAS mentioned a figure of 4,500 by the end of October; while the Department of Education and Skills talks about strong growth, but I would like to nail down the social backgrounds of the parents of the children taking up apprenticeships and the schools from which they are coming. If the uptake of apprenticeships is highly concentrated among pupils from DEIS schools and more working class communities, what can we do to level the playing field in order that it will be more attractive across the board because college is not for everyone? Whether one is from a DEIS school or a really good school, taking up an apprenticeship needs to be a viable option for more pupils other than those in a particular social class. If the figures were available, it would be amazing to gain an understanding in that regard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">I thank the delegates for their presentations. I recently saw a European league table on which we in Ireland were very much in the bottom half when it came to the scale and diversity of the apprenticeships on offer. If we were to put the scale of the problem in perspective, the figures Dr. Jim Murray outlined are worth repeating. In the 2017-18 academic year the total apprentice population was 14,871. When one compares that figure to the 235,644 student enrolled in the same academic year in higher education, it nails down the scale of the problem in front of us. For years, as Senator Ruane outlined, the sexy option was to proceed to higher education, while the lesser option was to take up an apprenticeship. How do we tackle the statistics in a positive way? A few of the delegates mentioned public awareness. That is the key. We need to do a substantial amount of work to increase public awareness to try to attract people to apprenticeships. I come from County Monaghan. If I was to mention the name Combilift, most people in this room would be familiar with it. If I was to mention the name Martin McVicar, most people would associate it with Combilift. If we were looking for an ambassador for apprenticeships, Mr. McVicar would fit the role very well. He is managing director of a company that exports to more than 100 countries. He took the route of an apprenticeship as opposed to attending third level. If one were looking to find an ambassador for apprenticeships, one could pick up the telephone and call him.</p>
          <p eId="para_65"> I wonder about the level of consultation with employers. Having listened to the presentations, it seems that, in terms of apprenticeships, the journey is only beginning. It is admirable that we have made a start, but we have so much more to do. There should be more consultation with employers.</p>
          <p eId="para_66"> The other statistic in figures I saw recently that strikes me is where apparently the level of female participation in apprenticeships in this country is 2% and that in our closest neighbour, the UK, is 50%. Clearly, there is much to be done in that regard as well. What can we do to increase that figure?</p>
          <p eId="para_67"> We need to incentivise employers to go down that road. We need to incentivise those who are participating and show them a clear picture of what the endgame will look like. Do the witnesses have anything in mind that could incentivise employers to go down this road? For the unemployed who see an apprenticeship, initially at any rate, as leaving them not much better off financially than they would be if they were remain on social welfare, is there anything we can do to incentivise them as well?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Acting Chairman (Deputy Catherine Martin)<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">I propose to take one more set of questions from Deputy Funchion, go back to the panel of witnesses and then come back for another group of three.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KathleenFunchion" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy Kathleen Funchion<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">First, apologies for being late for the presentations. I have read the opening statements.</p>
          <p eId="para_70"> I agree with much of what Senators Gallagher and Ruane have said. It seems like there are many great ideas and there is a lot of good work going on to a certain extent, but my difficulty is that I do not think that information is filtering down to those at local level who might have an interest in apprenticeships. It seems to be difficult for such people to get information. For many, their first point of contact will be a local social welfare office, and those I deal with are pointed more in the direction of Turas Nua than towards any other option. Whether it be some sort of training scheme through SOLAS or an apprenticeship, that information does not seem to be forthcoming.</p>
          <p eId="para_71"> Touching on what Senator Gallagher said about employers, I would know of a number of people who cannot find apprentices. There are a bunch of people who are looking for information on how to get into an apprenticeship and there are many good points being said here today. Somewhere along that spectrum, there is a piece missing or the information is not being funnelled down. I do not know whether any of the witnesses are in a position to answer this, but when people go into their social welfare office, what is this obsession with Turas Nua and funnelling people towards that only? That is where many of the difficulties lie. I know of people who have been offered training schemes with SOLAS who have been told by Turas Nua that it cannot release them for that. This is really stupid carry-on that makes no sense. There needs to be something done to join up all those dots.</p>
          <p eId="para_72"> For some apprenticeships, such as a barbering apprenticeship to which there is a fee attached, the apprentices themselves must fund it. Is there any option for them? Someone coming from school who has been unemployed for less than a year will not qualify for the back to education allowance. He or she will not qualify for a SUSI grant. Where does such a person get that money? Must such people source it themselves? That can be a deterrent to them. I would like to get some answers to that.</p>
          <p eId="para_73"> There is an <i>ad hoc</i> approach. It is great if a person meets somebody locally who is good and will give that person the information, but what if that person does not? It depends on where a person is in the country and who he or she meets on a particular day. There does not seem to be any kind of uniformity in getting the information. There was a debate last week on a Private Members' motion on apprenticeships during which the Minister stated that there is some financial incentive for employers to take on apprentices. If there is, that information needs to be disseminated.</p>
          <p eId="para_74"> Mr. O'Flaherty explained how government is working to address the problems women have in finding pathways to apprenticeships. What practical steps is the Department taking in that regard and is it looking at the issue of quality and affordable childcare, which is always a difficulty? This comes back to different areas in different Departments not talking to each other. To qualify for certain schemes, a person needs to be unemployed for a year or meet other criteria and he or she might qualify for something, but it means the person will not qualify for the affordable childcare. What sort of joined-up thinking or interdepartmental dialogue occurs in that regard? Those are the barriers for many. It is a minefield when a person tries to get the information.</p>
          <p eId="para_75"> Perhaps Mr. O'Flaherty would be the most appropriate person to answer a question on the funding struggle of community education and the introduction of fees for those trying to get back on their feet, either through back to education or, as somebody I met yesterday said wisely, where this could be their first opportunity because the education system failed them in the first instance. What if they are forced to pay fees? Already, so much community education struggles for funding. They do not like to have to ask the students who are coming to them for fees. I would appreciate the opinions of the witnesses on such matters.</p>
          <p eId="para_76"> Some good measures were suggested. Much of this came up last week as well. For me, the information does not seem to be funnelling down to those on the ground, whether it be those who have left school early or those who have done the leaving certificate but want to do an apprenticeship rather than go on to higher education. There does not seem to be the same funding stream for the latter. For example, they do not qualify for SUSI grants and yet, financially, they would. It is such issues that we need to look at. It is not practical for many to pay those kinds of fees because while in an apprenticeship, they are on very low wages. It would not be viable for them to pay those fees.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_21">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">I ask witnesses to indicate if they wish to respond to any of the comments or questions posed by members.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_22">
          <from> Mr. Phil O'Flaherty<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">I am sure other panel members here will have perspectives on these matters as well.</p>
          <p eId="para_79"> It is important to note that one of the big achievements of the review of apprenticeships in 2013-14 was to conceive of apprenticeship more as a mode of learning as opposed to a particular skill that operates in a particular sector. For a long number of years, there were no new apprenticeships developed. They were essentially within the construction and engineering sectors, and that goes to some of the issues with recruitment.</p>
          <p eId="para_80"> The intention in implementing the recommendations of the review was that apprenticeship would offer a much broader range of opportunities for participants, both in terms of educational progression, so that the qualifications they would receive would be a pathway into higher education, and career progression of various types. It was also the intention that it would involve the participation of a wide range of education and training providers so that a person could be an apprentice in a higher education institution. We have a couple of universities, for example, getting involved in apprenticeship. To some extent, the dichotomy between apprenticeship on the one hand and higher education on the other is something we are working to break down.</p>
          <p eId="para_81"> The broadening out of apprenticeship into new sectors should also offer opportunities to get involved in the apprenticeship system to those who do a range of different subjects in school and have a range of different interests. I have spoken to young apprentices. Female apprentices say of the opportunities for them to go into apprenticeships that, apart from cultural issues and issues with employer attitudes, they went to all-girls schools and it was not only a matter of access to careers information, guidance, etc., but also that, in practical terms, the subjects they could take did not give them access to apprenticeship opportunities.</p>
          <p eId="para_82"> The social mix around apprenticeship is interesting. In many countries, apprenticeship is something that operates at upper secondary level within schools where a student gets to the equivalent of the junior certificate here and decides to go either the academic or vocational route. In Ireland, it is different. Even in the craft apprenticeships, over 70% of entrants have completed the leaving certificate. It is not a choice that people tend to make midway through their second level schooling. In response to Senator Ruane, I do not have figures.</p>
          <p eId="para_83">I think it would be a useful exercise. We have lots of markers around educational achievement before people enter an apprenticeship from which, unfortunately, certain inferences around social background could be made. The broadening out of the range of apprenticeship opportunities is intended to give those who enter apprenticeship a broader range of opportunities to move onwards but also to make apprenticeship available to a much broader range of people. That is not to say that we just deal with an issue such as female participation in apprenticeship by saying we will have apprenticeships in areas that have much higher rates of female employment. There is a job to be done in respect of the craft apprenticeships as well and around young women seeing themselves as having roles in the construction industry, engineering and motor mechanics. The generation apprenticeship campaign tries to push those female role models. I often think that where a female apprentice is in motor mechanics or engineering, the system leans quite heavily on her as a role model to speak about her experience and to give advice and direction to others.</p>
          <p eId="para_84"> Apprenticeship is complex in terms of growing the numbers. There are no apprenticeships without employers taking people on. There is a two-pronged issue in terms of generating interest for people to enter apprenticeships but also getting employers to engage. Some of the incentive issues for employers are relevant. Different apprenticeships bring about different experiences. Many people are interested in getting involved in some of the newer apprenticeships in particular, but the struggle is to get enough places with employers. There are other apprenticeships where there is a lot of employer interest and less interest from potential apprentices and learners. The situation varies across apprenticeships. Places in higher education must be funded. The number of places can grow with the significant efforts that have been made by higher education institutions, but it is more complex to grow places in apprenticeship because employers must be recruited.</p>
          <p eId="para_85"> Deputy Funchion made a very good point about the visibility of opportunities. Regrettably, a lot of apprenticeship recruitment is never seen by potential learners. Employers take people on in the same way as they employ people more generally. Some of it happens through word of mouth. Social capital and other such issues become important in that regard in terms of the people who are aware of what is happening.</p>
          <p eId="para_86"> The pathways to apprenticeship approach proposes a number of ways to deal with that, including having an apprenticeship marketplace where those opportunities are more clearly visible. SOLAS is working on that now. That would also help give the Intreo offices and the social welfare service better visibility of apprenticeship opportunities than is the case at present.</p>
          <p eId="para_87"> The Department of Education and Skills meets the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection on a range of issues in terms of the participation of people in education and training, those who are unemployed or those who are on a range of other payments, for example, single parents or those with disabilities and various other groups. We advocate strongly for longer-term interventions for apprenticeship that would make real differences in people's lives, but other people who have significant skills and shorter interventions may be more appropriate in that regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_88"> In terms of apprenticeship and the intersection between it and some of the supports that were mentioned, apprentices are paid and they are employees. I recognise that they are not always paid a lot but they are in a slightly different position than perhaps somebody who comes straight from school who has no income. Apprentices are paid by their employers. Nonetheless, there are very practical issues and there are probably broader issues around the taking up of employment by people in particular situations. Reference was made to childcare. The affordable childcare scheme is intended to enable women with caring responsibilities who want to become involved in the labour market to be supported into employment, and one of the types of employment we are talking about is apprenticeship.</p>
          <p eId="para_89"> Community education is an important means of bringing people into all sorts of education and training opportunities, through full-time programmes and certified learning into full-time further education and training programmes, and onwards into higher education and apprenticeship. I am more than willing to engage separately on the issue but, typically, people on community education would not be in a position where they would need to pay fees. However, I am more than happy to engage with Deputy Funchion on the issue. There is sometimes an issue around the providers themselves who raise the cost of accessing certification given the fees that are involved in them registering with Quality and Qualifications Ireland, QQI, for example.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Acting Chairman (Deputy Catherine Martin)<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">I thank Mr. O'Flaherty. He can send any additional information to the other witnesses through the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_24">
          <from> Mr. Brendan McGinty<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">A number of the issues that have been raised to my mind amount to asking where the opportunities are to make further progress. I do not think that can be answered without getting into some of the granularity because there are different issues in different sectors and different regions. I will raise it up one level to say the following, namely, that we really must get on top of the challenge that lies immediately ahead. As I said in my opening statement, the future of jobs agenda is not an issue for the future, it is for today. Thankfully, we are heading for full employment. We know that we are only going to be able to add somewhere between 15,000 and 20,000 at working age in terms of the population. That means employers will be under a lot of pressure to find new skills and talent. We can do what we can around net immigration, and that is happening already, but the real issue is how we improve the productivity of the economy to contribute to economic growth and to sustain jobs and lifestyle for people. A key instrument of that is boosting the skill set we have in the working population.</p>
          <p eId="para_92"> Below that, we are seeing a lot of innovation happening. One of the things to which we in Skillnet Ireland are very committed is working with enterprise. A key question was asked about how we get enterprise engaged. One of the key issues is working with it very strongly on workforce planning, development and bringing innovation to help people solve some of those talent problems and creating opportunities for workers to develop.</p>
          <p eId="para_93"> Senator Gallagher asked about female participation. I will give one very simple example. In the ICT sector, companies are crying out for skilled people to come and work in them. The level of female participation has been an issue, with women, understandably, stepping out of their career, for example, to raise a family for a few years or to do other things. For example, through Technology Ireland a programme has been put in place called Women ReBOOT, which is about reconnecting with women who were working in the sector, had taken time out and, because of the pace of change in the sector, had lost touch with what was happening in terms of skills.</p>
          <p eId="para_94">We now have 20 of the largest technology companies in Ireland participating in the programme, which is getting women back into the sector and re-equipping and reskilling them and building their confidence. This has been a great success. That is granular and only one small example but it is the kind of thing that has to be done to build these sorts of responses.</p>
          <p eId="para_95"> Senator Gallagher asked a question about incentivisation. There is an issue with regard to how we get enterprise more involved. This is a major challenge for small and medium enterprises, SMEs, on which we are primarily focused. The reason that is important at a macro level is that we recognise there is a major productivity deficit challenge, which is being masked by what is happening in the multinational sector. At a superficial level, our productivity numbers are looking pretty good. If we strip out the performance of the multinational sector, however, what we see is that productivity is relatively low, particularly in the SME sector. The issue tends to arise in harder to reach areas such as parts of the construction sector, domestic services, hospitality, etc. These sectors require a greater level of incentivisation to increase the commitment of employers to the types of tasks we are discussing in respect of participation in workforce training. That extends across all levels. This is about saying that we need a number of key things to happen at the same time, in particular lifelong learning must be incentivised and sold to companies. Generally speaking, levels of participation currently stand at approximately 8.5%. The policy commitment is to double that figure to about 15%. While that commitment is welcome, we need to accelerate the process.</p>
          <p eId="para_96"> At all levels of the education and training system, we need to inculcate a culture of agile learning on the part of workers. The systems we bring, including policy delivery and service support, have to be about preparing for the repurposing of skills and training. I ask the committee to remember, as the World Economic Forum has pointed out, that by 2022, which is only a short number of years away, 54% of all workers will need some level of reskilling or upskilling. That is one hell of a challenge and we need to be ahead of that in the competition for inward investment and to ensure job sustainability and in sustaining our regions. The regions are where many of our SMEs are located and they are sustaining jobs outside of the major urban centres. We have a significant role to play in that regard owing to our strong reach into every region and every sector. However, we have more to do. </p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">
          <i>Deputy Fiona O'Loughlin took the Chair.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_25">
          <from> Dr. Jim Murray<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">I would like to touch on one of the issues Senators Ruane and Kelleher both raised in different ways. One way of referring to it is the "Cinderella" status of apprenticeships. This is not an easy issue to address. The status of an education and training programme and how it is perceived socially is deeply embedded within the psyche. It is a real cultural challenge that we have to take on and we should approach it in two ways. First, we have to neutralise the term "apprenticeship". Mr. O'Flaherty touched on this to a degree. Apprenticeship has to be perceived more as a mode of provision, rather than as something that has a whole set of social values attached to it, notwithstanding whether they are right or wrong. Second, we need to mainstream apprenticeships as a mode of provision. That means they need to be much more visible within what I will describe, for want of a better term, as the regular system. That is particularly the case in higher education. The new apprenticeships have begun that task by putting apprenticeship right in at the heart of higher education. This is a small beginning but degree programmes are now available which are in the apprenticeship mode of provision. We have to keep working on that and make apprenticeships much more visible. Over time, an attitudinal change will hopefully occur. It is, however, a substantial challenge. As Senator Gallagher mentioned, the numbers are stark. There are reasons for that but with the new apprenticeships, we have opened up the discussion in a way that has never been done previously. We have to sustain this discussion in the long term to make that change.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_26">
          <from> Dr. Mary-Liz Trant<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">I will make up a couple of points on the contributions thus far. We talked about employers and the role of employers comes through very clearly. The Apprenticeship Council has been engaging with employers involved in the new apprenticeships to discuss how things are going and the roll-out. One of the issues that has emerged is that in apprenticeship programmes where a large number of employers went through the apprenticeship route, these employers are great champions of the programmes. Mr. Martin McVicar was mentioned as an example. He went through the apprenticeship route, understands it and is very committed to it as a way of learning and also of having a pipeline of talent.</p>
          <p eId="para_99"> In the newer apprenticeships in finance and even in the area of ICT, many employers have never engaged with an apprenticeship before. We are doing a major piece of work to engage employers and get their buy-in because it is very influential. The voices and experiences of the apprentices are the other issue. The first graduates have come through from these new apprenticeship programmes and we will have more next year. That social spread of people who are buying into and want apprenticeship opportunities is starting to shift but there is much more to do. Part of the generation apprenticeship campaign is about changing that narrative. At the heart of the messaging is that apprenticeship is a mode of learning and a choice. We have to promote that. </p>
          <p eId="para_100"> To return briefly to Senator Ruane's point, through the pathways review, we gathered as much information as we could on the social background and profile of apprentices. We know that 85% are men under 25 years, 2.8% declared a disability and just 2% are women. Interestingly, one of the new apprenticeships has more women than men but the majority of the traditional apprenticeships have a tiny number of women and, in some cases, none. We have some of that information but in the pathways review we commit to getting more information in that area and to building that picture and understanding. That is really important.</p>
          <p eId="para_101"> Deputy Funchion raised a point about apprenticeships in barbering and hairdressing. We have an apprenticeship in development in that area. It is planned to roll that out next year and it will include hairdressing and barbering. We know the industry is really enthused and excited about this and view it as a structured way of getting opportunities for people who want to get into the industry. It is also a way apprentices to earn and learn as they go through the programme.</p>
          <p eId="para_102"> To address a point Mr. O'Flaherty raised regarding the overall picture of awareness, we are working on what we are calling a jobs market where employers will be able to advertise vacancies. It will be available on <i>www.apprenticeship.ie</i>. The Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, schools, guidance counsellors and employers will be able to provide this level of visibility of apprenticeship opportunities. Where employers are finding it difficult to find apprentices or apprentices are not hearing about opportunities, we will be able to improve that. We are working on that now and we hope to pilot it by the end of the year with a number of employers and then roll it out in 2019. We believe it will be significant as part of that awareness-raising work. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_27">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">It is good to see that some more women are getting involved. The committee was concerned by the statistics from last year showing that only 2% of apprenticeships were taken up by women. We certainly hope this positive change will continue. I thank Deputy Catherine Martin for standing in for me while I was on other Dáil business. I appreciate it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_28" as="#Acting_Chairman">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">I thank the witnesses for the presentations. I note that Waterford and Wexford Education and Training Board, WWETB, is developing a nearly zero energy building, NZEB, centre of excellence and Limerick Institute of Technology is working with it to develop the training content for the programme. This will upskill electricians, plumbers, blocklayers and others. It is terrible that WWETB has to fight for money despite the work that it is doing. This is the wave of the future and funding will be necessary if we are to address fuel poverty and improve our energy security.</p>
          <p eId="para_105">While SOLAS has started new apprenticeships in auctioneering and property services, what actions is it taking to create them in services that improve the quality of the houses being auctioned, rented or sold? Building standards are still under-regulated and inspected, although there is self-certification, while there is a severe lack of trained professionals to do the work required. I know that many of the people who work in the areas of renovation, retrofitting and energy efficiency - the new green areas of the economy - have not been trained in Ireland and must travel elsewhere to acquire that expertise. What is SOLAS doing at regional level to upskill in and support the retrofit sector? What is its policy in that area? Has it started to build on the pioneering work of Waterford and Wexford ETB in the area of retrofitting, especially considering the requirement to meet current and incoming EU energy efficiency and NZ targets? I note that the action plan to expand apprenticeship and traineeship in Ireland 2016 to 2020 includes a target to have 67 apprenticeship programmes in place by the end of 2020 in new industry areas. There is a clear upward trend, but are we preparing the apprentices for the reality of our changing economy and where we need to go? Regarding the €120 million allocated for apprenticeships in 2018 and the €34.6 million allocated for traineeships to 2020, what is the breakdown in terms of how much has been invested in climate mitigation or adaptation measures, including energy efficiency measures, as compared to the level of investment in fossil fuel employment? I believe there is talk of the European Social Fund which funds the new apprenticeship and traineeship fund being used to upskill fossil fuel workers in Germany and the Czech Republic. Has the Department approached anyone at EU level or prepared any draft plan for the midlands to avail of such funding opportunities?</p>
          <p eId="para_106"> I am glad to see moves in the right direction towards gender balance, but SOLAS's submission does state the proportion of apprentices who are women is still 1%. I am glad to hear that there is a move to encourage them to move beyond certain areas such as beauty therapy and hairdressing which quite clearly are saturated markets that are vulnerable to cyclical dips in the economy. Care work is also an industry in which there are very poor pay levels and conditions. Is there, for example, an Athena SWAN award equivalent for institutions and businesses in this area? In addition, what departmental actions are being taken in the light of the fact that just 2.75% of apprentices declare a disability? Furthermore, is there an apprenticeship expo? Could this become a compulsory part of the transition year school programme?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MariaByrne" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Senator Maria Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">As I had to go the Seanad Chamber to attend to quorum duties, I apologise if I ask any question that has been asked already. </p>
          <p eId="para_108"> I thank the four delegates for their very informative presentations. To follow up on what Deputy Catherine Martin said about an apprenticeship expo, I know that in the mid-west there was recently an apprenticeship day. Free buses were provided which collected students from schools and brought them to the expo. It was a really successful day. Parents turned up with students to find out about the various apprenticeships on offer, which was good. I educated myself about some of the apprenticeships that I did not even realise were available. For example, I did not realise there were apprenticeships in the area of refrigeration and so on. I would not have thought about it before. It is welcome that apprenticeships are growing because I am a big fan of them, especially given that third level education is not for everyone. Many apprenticeships have been awarded. I am aware of QQI, but some of the apprenticeships are being tied with the institutes of technology and the universities such that apprentices can be awarded, say, a certificate, a diploma or a degree. Are they all being accredited or is it just some of them? Given the fact that the expo was such a success, will it be repeated in other areas? It was the second or third year it was run in the mid-west. I pay tribute to Mr. Joe Leddin, the regional skills manager, who put the project together. It was great to bring employers and apprentices together. </p>
          <p eId="para_109"> This ties in with a question that was asked earlier. Is there a lot of collaboration between employers and apprentices? I spoke to some hairdressers recently. They take on many apprentices and must pay the various fees, but they receive no incentive or tax relief or anything else. Could this be considered? Could employers be incentivised to take on apprentices in such a way that they would receive something at the other end for investing in the employee of the future? Some employers take on many employees or apprentices and train them. It is important that a balance be struck in that regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_110"> I think the delegates mentioned 35 other programmes in development. Could we be given a broad outline of what else has been proposed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Deputy Jan O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">I welcome all of the delegates. I apologise for being late. I had a conflicting meeting to attend. </p>
          <p eId="para_112"> I am delighted to see so much progress being made in developing the new apprenticeships, in particular. I worked with some of the delegates in the establishment of the Apprenticeship Council. It is most welcome that, I think, 67 apprenticeships are due to be created by 2020. Really good work has been done. The challenge now is to get the message out as broadly as possible because we need employers and apprentices to fish the opportunities that are available.</p>
          <p eId="para_113"> I join Senator Byrne in congratulating the regional skills organiser in Limerick, Mr. Joe Leddin, on organising the apprenticeship forum. I think he is one of eight regional skills organisers throughout the country. The forum is a model that should be followed in other places. The delegates might let me know whether that is the plan.</p>
          <p eId="para_114"> I will focus mainly on getting the message out. Someone mentioned the Generation Apprenticeship campaign. I would like to receive an update on how widespread is the campaign. Social media are crucial in getting young people interested. Is there a need for a reinvigoration of the presence on social media to ensure young people know about the campaign? I refer also to the local media, particularly in the case of parents.</p>
          <p eId="para_115"> I do not know whether anyone can do anything about the way in which league tables are published in newspapers, but the inclusion of apprenticeships, as well as higher education options, would make a difference in terms of perception. I find it disgusting to read that such and such a school is the best in the country because 100% of its pupils go on to attend higher education when there are other, equally valid, opportunities that reflect the excellence of schools and which are completely brushed under the carpet. Perhaps it might be worth contacting the media, specifically the newspapers that publish the league tables, to say apprenticeships should be included. I do not know what the views of the delegates are or whether they would have a role in doing this. Perhaps we might as a committee and it is something we could do.</p>
          <p eId="para_116"> The next issue I wish to raise follows on what members, particularly Deputy Catherine Martin, said about green building, the European Social Fund and the midlands. The Youth Guarantee is another European concept that should capture young people who end up going to the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection instead of the people about whom Deputy Funchion talked who should really be guided towards the opportunities which are meant to be covered under the Youth Guarantee scheme.</p>
          <p eId="para_117"> Regarding the midlands, I was struck by the reference to the displacement of peat and so on. I think Mr. O'Flaherty might have some knowledge of the globalisation fund. Is funding available to direct people who may have been involved in the use of fossil fuels, etc., towards alternative opportunities?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_31">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">I have a few questions to ask. I apologise that I did not get to hear all of the presentations, but I will have an opportunity to look back at the transcript. I also had the opportunity to read the submissions made prior to the meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_119">I will have the opportunity to look back at the transcript, and I read the submissions prior to the meeting. The witnesses mentioned that the 1967 legislation is now over 50 years old. Is it necessary to examine the legislation and consolidate the Acts to make the process more efficient? The committee could look at that.</p>
          <p eId="para_120"> Engagement with career guidance teachers is very important. Are there sufficient numbers of career guidance teachers to enable such engagement? It would appear that apprenticeships suffer from a lack of parity of esteem, which is an issue we have to address for our younger people who are getting ready to leave school. The career guidance teacher has a big role to play on that. </p>
          <p eId="para_121"> Will the witnesses provide more information about the promotion of traineeships, as opposed to apprenticeships? That is another important area. </p>
          <p eId="para_122"> The Government has proposed increasing the National Training Fund between now and 2020. The witnesses are liaising with industry. Is industry supportive of that proposal? </p>
          <p eId="para_123"> On the issue of women taking up apprenticeships, women tend to avail of flexible working arrangements. Are there training courses that are offered on those terms? </p>
          <p eId="para_124"> In its submission, the Department stated that traineeships in the past were associated primarily with unemployed people, but as unemployment levels have dropped this has obviously impacted on uptake. Has this resulted in a drive towards attracting second level students to traineeships? Are different courses available to people in their late 40s or early 50s who are unemployed, including those who have taken redundancy? I am thinking of the employees of Bord na Móna. We must be able to attract these people to different types of classes to ensure they remain employable. They are only halfway through their working lives. </p>
          <p eId="para_125"> Do the witnesses believe that some form of positive discrimination could be applied to apprenticeships and traineeships to encourage a greater uptake? By that I mean possible tax breaks for employers or employees, perhaps by allowing people who have been on benefits to retain a medical card. Would that help?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_32">
          <from> Mr. Phil O'Flaherty<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T11:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">I thank the members of the committee for their contributions. They have provided us with plenty of food for thought. SOLAS might comment on the promotion agenda and the expos we have engaged in. A major event will occur in the spring of next year. Members may have heard of WorldSkills, which is akin to the skills olympics. The national version of that event, which will determine the participants at the WorldSkills event, is being brought together with a major expo in the RDS in March so as to anchor the work we have done on apprenticeships and promote excellence. There is more to be said about promotion, but I will leave it to Dr. Trant to provide more details.</p>
          <p eId="para_127"> The idea of using the European Social Fund, ESF, is interesting. Without being too technical in the short time available, the total amount of ESF funding is determined at the outset of the programming period at EU level and is set for the various member states. This essentially makes it part of overall budgetary planning. It is not that additional resources can be acquired from the EU for specific things. It must all come from the overall ESF budget. The question of what is included within our operational programmes is important, and further education and training is a major part of ESF supported opportunities. As Deputy Jan O'Sullivan said, there are opportunities for specific additional interventions through the European Globalisation Adjustment Fund, EGF. I do not know if it is being deployed in the case of the Bord na Móna workers or for the decarbonisation agenda more generally or what impact it has on the economy, but I will certainly check with colleagues as to whether that is a part of it. People are aware of various major interventions facilitated by the EGF, and it is not always for one particular company. For example, it was used during the downturn in the construction industry on a broader basis, but I will check the position on that and come back to the committee with the information it requires.</p>
          <p eId="para_128"> The question of new building techniques and retrofitting was raised. The content of apprenticeship programmes is being changed at the moment. Members will be aware of the 27 craft apprenticeships. The curricula of those apprenticeships have been reviewed to look at new building techniques and regulations and how they impact on the various trades. A fairly significant part of those updated curricula involves ensuring that those different types of techniques are included. There are also a range of non-apprenticeship programmes which provide education and training in the areas of retrofitting. I do not have details of how much of the overall further education and training budget is going towards those programmes, but they exist and we can provide additional information on that. I am aware of the specific provision that is being put together in that area by the Waterford and Wexford Education and Training Board, WWETB. Hopefully that will provide an example for other parts of the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_129"> Perhaps this goes to Deputy Funchion's point about barbering earlier, but in terms of incentives, there are some things that in the common parlance are called apprenticeships but which are not necessarily statutory apprenticeships. The flow of State funding and resourcing for those sorts of programmes is not the same. We have people who are being called apprentice bar persons or apprentice barbers, but they are not State funded and they do not form part of the statutory programme. As Dr. Trant said, barbering and hairdressing are coming into the fold through a specific proposal and a programme is being developed, but where programmes are not on a statutory basis, not only do they not receive the same State supports, but the employees are not getting the same levels of protection available to apprentices under the statutory system. That may have something to do with the difficulty people have in engaging with some of those programmes.</p>
          <p eId="para_130"> On league tables, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan will be aware that this is a very contentious issue. League tables are not supplied by the Department but are collated by media organisations through information supplied by the CAO and other sources.</p>
          <p eId="para_131">However, I am aware that SOLAS has made a conscious effort broadly in further education and training but also in the specific area of how apprenticeship features as a mark of success.</p>
          <p eId="para_132"> Going back to Dr. Jim Murray's point, there is a danger that high levels of conversion into apprenticeships, because of some public perceptions, are not necessarily seen as a positive development. While I do not agree with it, it all plays into the picture. We are looking at some positive discrimination. The review of pathways to apprenticeship discusses this point. There is a bursary for recruiting female apprentices in the craft sectors. We are looking to extend this into other sectors. We need to engage with some of our other Government colleagues in the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform to get agreement around that. We are looking to extend that into new areas as well as to people with disabilities.</p>
          <p eId="para_133"> On the 1967 legislation and the statutory framework for apprenticeship as a whole, we are gathering information from employers about their experiences of engaging with apprenticeship programmes. We will consider areas and specific issues which may need some attention from a statutory perspective. There is not a formal proposal at this stage to change the legislative framework and it is a complex area. Some may argue the system is bureaucratic. However, this offers protection to apprentices in terms of the quality of the education and training they receive. It is important that agenda is fully protected.</p>
          <p eId="para_134"> On industry and the increase in the national training fund, obviously there was a formal consultation process around that. Employers said they are in a time of uncertainty, such as Brexit and various other issues, and they do not need additional costs regarding employment. We have walked a journey with employers around this. There was a review of the national training fund which came up with 14 recommendations around greater employer say in the allocation of funding and what the priorities should be. An implementation plan for those was published alongside budget 2019. An advisory group will be set up involving employers as well. There is recognition that greater funding is coming from employers, and with that comes some obligations around influence.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_33">
          <from> Mr. Brendan McGinty<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">On the issue of promotion, I accept the point made by Deputy Jan O'Sullivan about the importance of connecting locally. In our experience in Skillnet Ireland, the capacity to engage locally through social media and all the various other channels such as local media is important. Again, we have had some valuable experience around what works and does not. I would be happy to share that with the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_136"> Women being offered flexibility of options in training is important. To be fair, our experience is that employers are much more sensitive to that, not least because they have a challenge trying to attract people into their businesses. Obviously, people are testing employers to see the career mobility options available. Part of that is how the training approach is done. There is a much greater willingness to look at more flexible, modular, part-time evening programmes of one form or another. Back in the day, parts of retailing might have been described as just a job in a shop. It is not just a job in the shop and employers have grasped that issue. Through the work done with ourselves, there is now an active presentation of a full career in retailing, whereby people, predominantly women, are having prior learning recognised. We are working with the qualification bodies to ensure, in a systematic way, that people who may not have a leaving certificate but have worked in a retail environment for five or ten years can have that experience recognised as a stepping stone towards career progression. People can have their skill sets properly recognised and certified up to allowing for career progression whereby they can now have a degree in retail management practice at level 7 in the qualifications framework. That is significantly powerful and impactful. From a business perspective, it is important because it is attracting somebody into the sector, giving them an opportunity to see ahead and retaining them within the sector.</p>
          <p eId="para_137"> What is happening to the cohort of people in their 40s and 50s? That is an important issue. We have had that experience when the construction sector collapsed and the challenges presented in terms of cross-skilling and getting people retrained in new sectors such as green energy and sustainability. Even around the unfortunate experience of closures, we have been heavily involved in supporting workers who have been impacted by closures such as Coty in Tipperary, Hewlett-Packard in Kildare, TalkTalk in Waterford, Cameron in Longford and so on. One has to have a response to cater for those particular requirements. That has worked but it is about tailoring the response, the agility of the response and working collaboratively with other agencies. We have been able to bring that very much to the focus of the task in hand.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_34">
          <from> Dr. Jim Murray<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">Senator Byrne had a query around accreditation of apprenticeships in the higher education institutions. There are statutory quality assurance guidelines to which all providers of apprenticeships have to adhere. They then would be operated through the awarding bodies and the higher education institutions for apprenticeships at levels 6 to 10. They would be the accrediting bodies in those instances but operating under national guidelines.</p>
          <p eId="para_139"> In terms of legislation, the issue is around the policies and processes that flow out of multiple sets of legislation. That is where work among the agencies and providers can, over time, work on streamlining those processes. It is necessary because it helps to break the logjam in terms of the throughput of programmes coming through the system.</p>
          <p eId="para_140"> Deputy Catherine Martin had an interesting idea about having the Athena SWAN Charter for apprenticeships. We may be able to look at that in due course.</p>
          <p eId="para_141"> On the gender issue and access more broadly, as well as the system level activities, which Mr. Phil O'Flaherty and Dr. Mary-Liz Trant have articulated, there are also institutional on the ground efforts. I know DIT has a new programme called access to apprenticeship. It is run in three cycles over 12 weeks. It would bring in many young kids from socially and economically deprived areas to sample the different types of apprenticeship. That is the successful way of bringing people into the system. DIT has also had an open day specifically targeted towards women. There are many local initiatives complementing the central efforts.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_35">
          <from> Dr. Mary-Liz Trant<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">The local and regional element of all of what we are doing is important. We have 16 education and training boards, 14 institutes of technology, as well as more universities, and all of the employers. A big part of the generation apprenticeship competition has been about co-opting everybody in that.</p>
          <p eId="para_143">We have that local and regional reach.</p>
          <p eId="para_144"> Senator Byrne asked about what was happening in the mid-west. We now have these structures in place throughout he country which are very powerful and effective and making a very big contribution. The <i>apprenticeship.ie </i>website which receives approximately 25,000 visitors per month plays a big role in supporting, facilitating and generating apprenticeships. We are working to make it a one-stop shop, with a profile and a link with the jobs market. We are expanding our significant social media presence and have profiles on LinkedIn, Twitter and Facebook. We are examining how to reach men in their mid 20s, school leavers and transition year students, while not forgetting the role played by employers.</p>
          <p eId="para_145"> Members may be aware that the ESB recently received an award as part of European Vocational Skills Week for its work on apprenticeships and in attracting women into electrical apprenticeships, which traditionally were predominantly filled by men. It has done a significant amount of work in promoting opportunities and now has approximately 16 female apprentices, whereas two or three years ago there were only one or two. It is showing the way in terms of what can be done by an employer.</p>
          <p eId="para_146"> The Chairman asked how we were promoting traineeships. We are working closely with education and training boards across the country in that regard and have a very exciting pipeline of 51 traineeships on offer. We provide national support in branding, availing of opportunities to organise workshops, engaging with employers and working with the regional skills forums hand in hand with the education and training boards and their connections with employers.</p>
          <p eId="para_147"> Senator Byrne asked what was in the pipeline. The detailed list is available and includes apprenticeships in sales, retail, ICT, farming, horiticulture and engineering. Four chef apprenticeships will be available by the middle of next year, doubling our current offering. There will be apprenticeships in supply chain logistics, which is of great importance in the context of Brexit. There is a wide range of offerings. Part of what the council is doing is looking at how to ensure our apprenticeship offering is responsive in what we have and what we will need.</p>
          <p eId="para_148"> Deputy Catherine Martin asked what was being done on the issue of climate change. We are working closely with the Construction Industry Federation and other partners on an ongoing basis to ensure the existing apprenticeship courses have the content required to ensure we are responding to these imperatives and regulations and so on, to identify new areas in which apprenticeships are needed or need to be adapted and to ensure we can do so. The council is piloting an engagement with employers and other bodies to ensure it has its finger on the pulse in that regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_149"> The Chairman asked about life-long learning and opportunities for employees, including those at risk of losing their jobs. Apprenticeship is increasingly an opportunity for people in employment. Up to half of those in the first intake in insurance and engineering apprenticeships were employees who might have been working for five or ten years, did not have a formal qualification and were being facilitated by their employer to undertake the apprenticeship and potentially take up more senior positions in their company. Obviously, apprenticeship is increasingly a very important route for young people, but it is also for learners of all ages and backgrounds, as evidenced by the surge in new apprenticeships, of which it is to be hoped we will see more as time passes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_36" as="#Acting_Chairman">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">I asked for a breakdown to see how much of the €120 million allocated for apprenticeships and the €34.6 million allocated for traineeships in 2018 has been invested in climate mitigation or adaptation measures to achieve energy efficiency. What is the exact policy on the retrofit sector? I refer to the work done by Waterford Wexford ETB in that regard. Is it something that will be addressed many years into the future? That is not where we need to be; rather, we need to deal with it in the here and now. Is there a timeframe for building on the pioneering work done by Waterford Wexford ETB? What is the plan and when will it be implemented? The Irish Green Building Council stated people were not being trained in Ireland in retrofitting, which is appalling. It is the new green economy. Many employees, particularly in the midlands, will need to be retrained and upskilled. What is the plan in that regard?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_37">
          <from> Dr. Mary-Liz Trant<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">We do not have a specific breakdown of where the allocations are being spent in that regard. However, dimensions of the construction apprenticeship curriculums now include those elements and one could look to what is being allocated for those apprenticeships. However, we will examine the matter further to see what further information can be provided.</p>
          <p eId="para_152"> We are very supportive of the work of Waterford Wexford ETB and that previously carried out by Limerick Institute of Technology. I do not have immediate information on the overall plan, but we can revert to the committee with further information on it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_38">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">The committee is always open to receiving further information. Mr. O'Flaherty referred to the apprenticeship skills event in March, which is a super idea. The committee would like to visit it and I ask Mr. O'Flaherty to let us know, if possible. The committee was very impressed by the apprentices who represented Ireland at WorldSkills.</p>
          <p eId="para_154"> I could not agree more on the importance of retail apprenticeships. It is very important to show that there is a pathway through the retail sector. Two of the most recent entrants into the grocery market provide very good pathway and graduate programmes which contribute to attracting people to the area.</p>
          <p eId="para_155"> It has been a very interesting and engaging discussion. We will resume our examination of the issue next Tuesday, 20 November, when representatives of four other groups will appear before the committee. We very much appreciate the time and engagement of the delegates. If they wish to submit anything else to the committee before we complete our report, they should do so.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8">
          <i> Sitting suspended at 12.15 p.m. and resumed at 12.20 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Operation of Caranua: Department of Education and Skills<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:20:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_39">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">The purpose of this part of the meeting is to engage with officials from the Department of Education and Skills in respect of the operation of Caranua, the State agency under the aegis of the Department which is responsible for the administration of the residential institutions statutory fund. On behalf of the committee I welcome Mr. Ned Costello, assistant secretary general, Ms Catherine Hynes, principal officer, and Mr. Aongus Ó hAonghusa, assistant principal officer. The format of this part of the meeting is that I will invite our stakeholders to make a brief opening statement of no more than three minutes' duration, which will be followed by engagement with members of the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_157"> Before we begin, I draw the attention of witnesses to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee. However, if they are directed by the Chair to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence. They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_158"> Any opening statements made to the committee will be published on the committee website after the meeting. Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_40">
          <from> Mr. Ned Costello<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">On behalf of myself and my colleagues I thank the committee for giving the Department the opportunity to come before it today to discuss issues relating to Caranua and the needs of survivors of abuse, including the long-term supports that might be available to survivors into the future. Today’s meeting follows previous engagements with the chair and the then chief executive of Caranua last year and more recent meetings with two former members of the board of Caranua.</p>
          <p eId="para_160"> With regard to the role of the Department and the historical background, it might be useful if I summarised at the outset the Department’s role in respect of supporting survivors. This role extends back many years and arose from the fact that, historically, the Department had a statutory role in respect of the operation of industrial and reformatory schools. Thankfully, those institutions are no longer in existence. When the issue of abuse in those institutions became the focus of public attention 20 years ago, the Government gave the Department the task of implementing a number of measures, including the establishment of the Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse, the Residential Institutions Redress Board, and the Redress Review Committee. These bodies have virtually completed their work and we expect they will be dissolved in the near future.</p>
          <p eId="para_161"> A fourth body, the Education Finance Board, was also in existence but was dissolved and, in effect, replaced in 2013 by the residential institutions statutory fund, also known as Caranua, which has a wider mandate than the finance board and significantly more funding available to it. That funding derives from a commitment by religious congregations to provide funding of €110 million for additional supports to survivors who have received an award from the redress board, equivalent court awards or settlements. Having been in receipt of such an award is a key criterion for applying for and receiving assistance from Caranua. As regards the funding available, to date almost €102 million of the €110 million has been received, as well as an additional €1.3 million in interest associated with contributions. There is clearly an outstanding balance. The Christian Brothers have written to the Department to say that they expect to provide the balance of the funding by the first quarter of 2019.</p>
          <p eId="para_162"> Under its founding legislation, Caranua is statutorily independent in carrying out its functions. With regard to the services provided by Caranua, its board is responsible for strategy, policy, governance, oversight and control, with the executive of the body reporting to it. For example, the board is responsible in law for determining what services are approved services. These must fall under the four classes of services set out in section 8 of the 2012 Act. Those classes are: mental health services, health and personal social services, educational services and housing support services. The board also determines the criteria by reference to which decisions are made on individual applications, but it does not make decisions on them.</p>
          <p eId="para_163"> In the context of the 2012 Act, the Minister’s role relates to matters such as the appointment of board members, the appointment of the independent appeals officer or officers, the approval of contracts and consultancies, and certain staff matters. The Minister is also responsible for managing the process of receiving contributions from religious congregations and making those contributions available to Caranua via the National Treasury Management Agency.</p>
          <p eId="para_164"> With regard to applications and expenditure, since Caranua began accepting them in January 2014, it has received in excess of 6,500 applications, and by the end of October it had expended some €78 million on supports for former residents. To date, 5,000 individuals have benefited directly. The supports from Caranua have made a tangible difference to the lives of many people. Some of the case studies both on the website and in the recent annual report are illustrative of this.</p>
          <p eId="para_165"> The Department is, of course, aware that there is a degree of dissatisfaction with the quality of the service provided by Caranua. We suggest that some of that dissatisfaction should be seen in the context of the fact that Caranua had to be established from scratch from a greenfield site. There was no previous body doing equivalent things. It has to be said there were teething troubles in its formative years. Ultimately, however, while Caranua must speak for itself on these issues as an independent agency, there is strong evidence that it has and is continuing to address the concerns expressed about its operations. For example, following feedback from survivors, the following additional services were introduced: the provision of household goods such as cookers, fridges, floors and home decoration; contributions towards funeral costs; contributions to the cost of reconnecting with family members and home place, from which some 180 people have benefited; and active listening to the stories of survivors.</p>
          <p eId="para_166"> As regards making an application for support from Caranua, each survivor is assigned an application adviser to assist him or her through the process of applying for services. The length of time it takes to process applications very much depends on the specific needs of the individual survivor, consistent with the person-centred approach taken by Caranua. Caranua has two dedicated call line operators who are the first port of call for those who contact the fund by phone. If a survivor does not get a response and chooses to leave a voicemail, the policy is to call that person back within 24 hours. Three further attempts will be made if the call line operator or adviser does not get through to the survivor on the first attempt.</p>
          <p eId="para_167"> It is also proper that there should be a right of appeal against Caranua's decisions. That is enshrined in the legislation. That appeals mechanism is independent of Caranua. With regard to the structuring of the appeals mechanism, initially one person served in this position.</p>
          <p eId="para_168">When that person stepped down in 2017 two appeals officers were appointed. The Minister made these appointments cognisant that a backlog of 140 appeals cases had built up. In May 2018, one of the two officers stepped down for personal reasons. However, as the matter of the backlog had been addressed, the Minister decided to revert to the original arrangement of one appeals officer. We understand that there are currently 45 appeals cases on hand. We are keeping the matter under close review and should there be a question of a backlog arising again, the Minister will think of appointing a second appeals officer.</p>
          <p eId="para_169"> Concerns have also been expressed about the length of time taken to conclude appeals. However, to observe due process, the appeals process requires that the views of all parties be sought on the matters under appeal and as a result, inevitably it takes a certain length of time for appeals to be processed. </p>
          <p eId="para_170"> I would also like to clarify that since mid-2016, applicants to Caranua whose applications are not approved are notified in writing of their right to appeal and how to go about the process of making an appeal. Sample letters are included in the background briefing submitted to the committee, along with a range of statistical information on the appeals. In addition, I would note that since 2016 there has been a sharp downturn in the number of complaints in respect of Caranua. We have provided a graph to illustrate that in the additional material we submitted.</p>
          <p eId="para_171"> I would like to address a number of policy issues bearing on the recent and future operations and future of Caranua. First, it will be recalled that the Residential Institutions Statutory Fund, RISF, is a cash limited fund. Any cash contributions from the congregations in excess of the €110 million statutorily provided for in the fund are statutorily required to go towards the costs associated with the development of the National Children's Hospital. </p>
          <p eId="para_172"> Some survivors and advocates for survivors have expressed their view that the cap of €15,000 which the Board of Caranua introduced in 2016, has resulted in an organisation that is not sufficiently responsive to the needs of survivors, or catering for them sufficiently. I must stress that the application of the limit is a decision for Caranua. However, it might be observed that issues relating to the equitable treatment of the cohort of survivors do arise when decisions of this nature are to be made, and the balancing of an equitable spread of assistance across the population of survivors. It might also be observed that Caranua has to strike a balance in the need to engage as flexibly and compassionately with survivors as possible and its obligations as regards its fiduciary obligations and other accountability requirements. While procedures may be seen by some as too bureaucratic, the fact is that it has been necessary for the organisation to respond to the findings of the Comptroller and Auditor General in this regard. </p>
          <p eId="para_173"> By end October, Caranua had expended €87 million of the €110 million in funds. Cognisant of the rate at which the fund was being expended and the applications on hand, Caranua in May 2018 announced a cessation date for new applications, save for extreme hardship cases. Caranua set the date of 1 August for that. Unlike the earlier experience of the Residential Institutions Redress Board, where there was a large spike in the applications when that board announced the cessation date for new applications, this has not happened in the case of Caranua. This is notwithstanding the fact that Caranua engaged in an extensive publicity campaign including advertisements and engagement with survivor groups. Caranua is still engaging with survivors both in respect of applications on hand, of which there remains a significant volume, and in its support and advocacy function which aims to assist survivors in engaging with other State providers of supports.</p>
          <p eId="para_174"> The objective underpinning the work of Caranua was that it would address the critical needs of former residents. Those needs were identified by former residents themselves in a consultation process undertaken in 2010 as being in areas such as housing, health and related supports. That consultation process informed the drafting of the 2012 Act. </p>
          <p eId="para_175"> The Department is continuing to engage on the future needs of survivors. While conscious of time, I would like to mention three areas. First, we are undertaking a <i>post hoc</i> review of the various redress schemes under the aegis of the Department, including looking at relevant international experience. The purpose of the review is both to reflect on what has happened over the period we have been providing redress and also thinking about what we have learned and what lessons there may be for the future across the whole of Government where issues of redress arise. Second, we are planning to hold a number of consultation sessions which would serve as a forum for former residents and others with close personal involvement to reflect on their experiences, on the State’s response to redress and the issue of institutional abuse and to make any recommendations they wish to make.</p>
          <p eId="para_176"> These sessions will be externally facilitated and we propose to shortly issue a request for tender for the services of a facilitator, who will assist in the process of planning and scoping the sessions. Let me stress that the sessions will be independently facilitated and will be independent of the Department. We are conscious that survivors want the sessions to be delivered by survivors for survivors.</p>
          <p eId="para_177"> Third, we have convened an interdepartmental committee recently to examine how existing mainstream State services can best meet the needs of survivors into the future. The committee met for the first time on 5 November and will meet again in December. We are compiling an inventory of all of the various State services and supports that may be of relevance to survivors and also look at issues such as signposting, and whether the services are sufficiently attuned and how survivors can best be directed to the services and benefit from them.</p>
          <p eId="para_178"> I thank the committee for its attention and that concludes my statement. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_41">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">I thank Mr. Costello. I call Senator Ruane.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LynnRuane" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Senator Lynn Ruane<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">Chairman, in the event I have to leave the committee, it is because I must move some amendments on the Greyhound Racing Bill 2018 but I will return and look at the responses.</p>
          <p eId="para_181"> I thank the witness for the presentation. Let me respond to the point made about teething problems, things not working out and changes made. It is very hard for me to hear Mr. Costello refer to the downturn in complaints when the experience of our offices dealing with and offering supports to survivors paints a very different picture. I wonder why there is a downturn in the number of complaints. Perhaps people are fed up waiting between 18 months to two years in some cases trying to get white goods for their kitchen. They probably have given up and some may have passed away. We do not know the reason for the downturn. It does not necessarily mean it is positive. When I hear of the concept of a person-centred approach, I think of a man who not only has a social worker advocating for him, he also has me stepping in trying to advocate for him and, after years of going through this process, the most he has managed to get is a skip. He has not been able to get simple white goods for his kitchen because when he goes to PowerCity, he is told he cannot get them because of the need to pay through bank transfer or cheque. Then he is sent somewhere else. After all the years, he still cannot get simple white goods for his kitchen. That is not a person-centred approach. I would not put myself through that degrading treatment - of having to beg for a washing machine or a cooker. That is what it feels like when one has to keep coming back with more information. I do not believe this is a person-centred service.</p>
          <p eId="para_182"> I have a number of questions that are focused on the Department's role and I welcome the consultation with survivors. That will be extremely important. It would be great if the Department were to keep the committee updated on the process and if we on the committee can support that process in any shape or form. We need to ask for an independent investigation into the operations of Caranua and its treatment of survivors, whether that feeds into the process of consultation or whether there is an independent investigation into the operation of the scheme. What is really crucial is that we look at the role of the current chairman and chief executive. While there is a consultation process and there are still applications that have not been met, maybe we need to bring in an independent chairperson. I know it has been said that Caranua is independent, but it would help if the Department were to find an independent chairperson and independent acting CEO while we are trying to process some of the applications that are getting lost in the ether.</p>
          <p eId="para_183">On the Department's role, in what way is the Department supervising Caranua, particularly given the widespread reports of poor treatment of survivors? How would it describe Caranua's performance over the past four years, particularly bearing in mind the objective of the fund, which is to help with the recovery of survivors? What measures did Caranua use to come up with its 90% performance rate? We are accepting this 90% but nobody really knows what the measurement was and no one has seen a report. I know the past board members were not part of any sort of survey or report that came up with that 90% rate of satisfactory performance. </p>
          <p eId="para_184"> Caranua committed to a review of the impact of the 2016 changes to services, including the impact of the introduction of the limit of €15,000 by June 2017. Has that review been carried out? What were its conclusions? There is also evidence that the imposition of a cap has had devastating consequences for the applicants with the greatest need. Does the Department wish to comment on that? In giving evidence to both the Committee of Public Accounts and the Joint Committee on Education and Skills, Caranua committed to improvements in communication. These improvements included reaching out to applicants where they lived and the provision of interview facilities at the new premises. Of concern to the committee is whether Caranua has successfully reached out to the most vulnerable such as those in hospitals, in prisons, or on the streets, which it said it would do in past meetings, as there is no evidence of this so far. </p>
          <p eId="para_185"> The residential institutions redress unit, RIRU, is the unit tasked with providing support to Caranua in redress issues generally. The RIRU is reported to be in the process of winding down its operations with a view to closure in the very near future. Given Caranua's imminent closure, is this the best time to close the RIRU? Might it be better for this team to remain to ensure that any post-Caranua measures are embedded and to help ensure that Caranua's closure is achieved with the minimum of disruption to survivors?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">I thank the witnesses very much for coming in today. I was struck by something in Mr. Costello's opening statement which said "The Department is, of course, aware that there is a degree of dissatisfaction with the quality of the service provided by Caranua." There is much more than a degree of dissatisfaction. It was said in a meeting of this committee earlier this year, and I will repeat it, that the State has failed. Worse still, it continues to fail and that is to our shame as a State. Before I ask my questions, I commend and refer to all of those who have advocated and who continue to advocate so courageously for the survivors. They have never given up and they have been so resilient against all the odds. What has been done by the survivors for the survivors has been incredible.</p>
          <p eId="para_187"> My questions centre around the issue of the appeal process. What are the Department's concerns regarding the very different number of appeals granted by the former appeals officers, of which only 8% were successful, and granted by the two appeals officers appointed in April 2017? Under these officers 43% of appeals were successful. How have the officials satisfied themselves that the former appeals officer was not overly harsh, looking at the difference in those statistics? How does the Department explain the very low number of appeals submitted by applicants to the fund? There were 399 over three years. Is the number low because of Caranua's failure to tell applicants they could appeal, which is again a symptom of poor communication? Considering the very high number of appeals won by applicants since 2017, how has the Department ensured that Caranua's refusals are fair and in line with the Act, particularly as we have reports of this not being the case? </p>
          <p eId="para_188"> Similarly there have been allegations of abuse of the appeals process on the part of Caranua, for example the introduction of new reasons for refusal once the appeals process has commenced and refusals on grounds not contained in the Act or in the criteria. Is the Department aware of these allegations? If yes, what has it done to look into them? Has the Department ever seen a list of the reasons given by Caranua in the determination letters or further reasons for refusal only being given after the appeals process commenced? If the Department has not seen the letters, perhaps it would like to ask to do so and to consider that information. </p>
          <p eId="para_189"> We have also heard of several applications for services made in 2015 by applicants who have serious disabilities, who urgently need help, and who are still waiting. In these cases we believe Caranua initially refused to issue a determination letter and then only agreed to issue the letter 12 months later, after investigation by the appeals officer. The applicants were then refused the services. The applicants successfully appealed in 2017, having waited 18 months for the appeal decision, or still have not been provided with the service. Is the Department aware of these particular applications? Does it have any information on them? Is that the case?</p>
          <p eId="para_190"> I believe some applicants who were recently interviewed on radio are now considering legal action. It is estimated that the cost of these cases could exceed €500,000 and that this money might well come out of the fund. Has the Department received reports of this? If the cost was to come out of the fund, at what stage would the Department step in to prevent the fund suffering such losses? What does the Department think of such cases and what do they tell us about the operation of the fund by Caranua? What can we, as a committee, and the Department do to improve matters for survivors in the time the fund has left? The service really has failed to provide survivors with a service.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">I thank all the witnesses for coming in. I want to start, if I may, with a quote from Tom Cronin, who appeared before the committee just a few months ago. He is a former board member of Caranua. It is important to remember the people we are talking about here and what they have gone through. Mr. Cronin said:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_192">What happened to us as children was a shame on the nation but what has been done to us since is a greater shame. As a survivor, I have experienced the anger, hurt, despair and frustration of engaging with the redress commission and other State-established resources. As a survivor advocate for more than 20 years and a former board member of Caranua, I have personally witnessed many survivors experiencing the same. These schemes and the State’s response to our past have failed on an ongoing fashion for one reason, namely, they never listened to survivor needs.</p>
          <p eId="para_193"> As one can hear from that quote, the testimony of Mr. Cronin on that day was absolutely powerful, as was that of Dr. Mary Lodato. I suspect we have unanimity across all parties here because all parties have received representations telling us of appalling experiences at the hands of Caranua. Only this morning I heard that someone who physically handed in an application received a dressing-down; "How dare you come down to our offices". How can anyone imagine that is an appropriate response? This happened in the last month, by the way, to someone who suffered abuse. What kind of culture is there in the organisation Caranua that makes it okay to act like that? It is absolutely shocking. I appeal to the Department because we have to work together. We are not here to give it a hard time. We just need to make sure that Mr. Cronin's request is followed up on and that survivors are listened to. We have to recognise that.</p>
          <p eId="para_194"> I echo my colleague, Senator Ruane's call for an independent investigation. We need that because we are unable to produce a report. We are told that we cannot produce a report as a committee because of conflicting evidence. We cannot leave it as it is so we have to have an independent investigation. Otherwise, we have failed to listen again. I do not believe any of us, including the witnesses, would want to leave it in that position. I call for an independent investigation. I also call for a new management structure to be put in place as a matter of urgency to make sure that things improve from here on in.</p>
          <p eId="para_195"> I have a couple of questions. I am going to rattle through them. I am conscious that the Department's representatives have a lot of questions to answer here today so I will briefly get through as many as I can and then hand over to our colleagues. My questions are around the processing of applications. I am sure the Department will agree that Caranua's primary role is to accept and process applications, applying the criteria to each case, and to either pay for the service or to give the applicant a written determination letter giving the reason for refusal. What can the Department tell us about the 2016 appeal officer's investigation of Caranua and its refusal to process applications?</p>
          <p eId="para_196">We believe that at the time Caranua put these breaches down to an "oversight" on its part.</p>
          <p eId="para_197"> What has been the Department's reaction each year to the "serious concerns" raised in each of the appeal officer's annual reports published in 2016, 2017 and October 2018? Caranua still refuses to process applications, fails to issue written determinations and fails to give information about the right of appeal. Last month, the Taoiseach said he wanted evidence of this, and we assume he has been directed to these reports. I am somewhat concerned by what Mr. Costello said in his opening statement about people now receiving written determinations, because that is not what the appeals officer told us in the report he produced last month in which he said there continue to be cases on this issue. I do not understand, therefore, how the Department included that line when the appeals officer's report told us that is not the case. </p>
          <p eId="para_198"> The evidence from the appeals officer and the other reports demonstrate these failings are widespread and affect hundreds, if not thousands, of applicants. How has the Department responded to the reports of this? Given these practices have been ongoing for four years, in the Department's estimation how many applicants may not have had their applications properly determined and thus denied a right of appeal? It is important to know that and, in fairness, if we do not know, that again tells us why we need this independent investigation. Under the Act which concerns Caranua, the Minister has power to direct it and, while it would be improper for him to give directions in respect of an individual case, it would be appropriate for him to issue a direction to Caranua to compel it to act in accordance with the Act and to stop the unlawful policy of delaying or refusing to process and determine applications. In the context of these widespread abuses, why did the Minister not direct Caranua to act in accordance with the statute at any point in the past three years?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_45">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">On a point of order, the Senator may not ask public servants to answer for the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">The Chair is right and I apologise. It is a fair point and I withdraw that question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_47">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">The Senator also may not use the term "unlawful".</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">I accept that. Many applicants to the fund will not have read the Act or the appeals officer's report. They will not know, therefore, that their application was denied unfairly. How does the Department ensure that survivors who are illiterate, who have only limited literacy or who are in institutional care receive the service to which they are entitled, given these breaches which have been ongoing for four years?</p>
          <p eId="para_203"> I am conscious there have been many questions. I thank the witnesses for their patience and I will finish with this. We understand a request was made to Caranua and the appeals officer for information to be made available to applicants of agencies that may be able to help them, such as Free Legal Advice Centres, Citizens Information or One in Four. It appears, however, that Caranua refused to do this, which is shocking. What is the Department's view of Caranua's refusal to make that information available?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Deputy Jan O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">I welcome the witnesses. I begin by responding to some of Mr. Costello's points. I note the Department acknowledges the problems, which is important, and my colleagues have asked a number of specific questions about the problems. Mr. Costello said there was a commitment to call people back within 24 hours and subsequently to repeat the phone calls. Does that actually happen? I was told the freephone operates only on landlines but most people nowadays operate through mobile phones. Will people be called back on their mobile phones if that is their preferred form of contact? Most people are not there to take a call on their landline.</p>
          <p eId="para_205"> Will Mr. Costello clarify what he said about people being notified in writing of their right of appeal? I think he said this was the practice since a date this year. Many of the complaints we received were from people who did not know they had a right of appeal. Will that practice apply to historical cases or is it only for current cases that have been turned down? People who had previously been turned down should certainly be notified of their right to appeal because many of them may not know about it.</p>
          <p eId="para_206"> I accept Mr. Costello said the limit of €15,000 was Caranua's decision rather than the Department's, but as people get older and more disabled, they may need an extension to their house that will cost more than €15,000. There are specific cases around that. Mr. Costello and Caranua have both stated that, given the reduction in the level of applications, Caranua can concentrate in its strategic plan on improving the quality and impact of its interaction with survivors. What evidence is there of that? There are probably people in the system who need more than the €15,000 limit.</p>
          <p eId="para_207"> On the problems people have in getting what they looking for, such as the white goods that Senator Ruane mentioned, people are being asked for several quotes. It is not only about the price and description of the work but also the materials to be used. I do not know how much guidance the Department can give but if one applies for any kind of grant with a local authority, one must get quotes but there is no need for that level of detail. Is it the case that there are preferred suppliers which are chosen by Caranua? That does not seem to be the norm under procurement rules. These are some of the difficulties people have in getting what they need. </p>
          <p eId="para_208"> The forms, in general, are difficult. Senator Gavan raised the issue of limited literacy, which leads some people to have difficulty with the forms. The independent appeals officer said the applications process is extremely complex. Is help with these complex forms available?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">To avoid repetition, I will confine my contribution to questions. On issues with governance and management, from reading the board's minutes it appears to focus more on governance than trying to improve the services. Will Mr. Costello comment on that? How does the Department ensure the Caranua board achieves the correct balance between governance and the fund's objectives? On the face of it, based on the minutes and discussions with survivors, the board does not appear to consider greatly the needs of survivors. Does it work effectively? How did the Department react to the concerns raised by two survivors who resigned from the board earlier this year over treatment by the other, non-survivor board?</p>
          <p eId="para_210"> There has been much negative feedback on Caranua's treatment of survivors. How did the Department react to those reports? What steps were taken to improve the service delivery? Caranua published a report on feedback earlier this year which claimed that 90% of the feedback was positive. Judging by recent Dáil debates and comments in this room, one would have to question that claim.</p>
          <p eId="para_211"> Will the Department comment on findings of an independent survey carried out in 2017 which showed a different picture? Some 68% of survivors rated their experience with an adviser as either terrible or bad, some 61% rated their experience as extremely negative, while 21% rated their experience as negative. Will the Department comment on those results from an independent survey?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KathleenFunchion" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Deputy Kathleen Funchion<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">I will be brief because nearly everything has been covered. Senator Gavan has done much work on this matter on behalf of our party. It is hard to find the words to describe the history of these people. They have been badly failed by the State, first in these institutions and then in this process. It is as though Caranua's attitude is that people do not deserve this money, not least as there is a cap which it sets. Money is not unlimited but surely the amount should be decided on a case-by-case basis.</p>
          <p eId="para_213">People have varying and different needs and the fact that there is a single cap shows that there has been a very begrudging attitude from the start.</p>
          <p eId="para_214"> I want to make a few brief points on appeals. I have had conversations with people in Caranua who said there was no appeals process. As such, there are huge questions to be asked about the fact that Caranua is now writing out to people to say there is one. I have dealt with a great many people who have been told there was no appeals process and had follow-up conversations with people in Caranua in which it was confirmed that there is no appeals system. I would like to know a bit more about that. As to its closure, although I do not think Caranua is fit for purpose and it is not doing a good job, what will happen to those who have slipped through the cracks and not applied for funding? People may have been abroad or otherwise unaware of Caranua. What will happen to them and who will decide issues of hardship or exceptional circumstances? People do not seem now to be able to get the very basic things they are looking for. What makes anyone believe Caranua will grant anything or deem there to be hardship or exceptional circumstances?</p>
          <p eId="para_215"> I refer to supports going forward. I welcome the consultation which is a great idea. However, one of the supports mentioned was the HSE's national counselling service which is completely overstretched as it is. People who are literally suicidal cannot access that service. One is looking here at a very vulnerable group of people and there is no way they will be able to get access to the HSE service. If Caranua is winding down, I suggest as part of the consultation that a specific counselling service is made available free of charge through some system. Directing people to a national HSE counselling service which is completely overstretched and which will not be able to meet demand is not recommended. I see there is a division in the Dáil.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_52">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">I will add a comment myself before I have to suspend for voting. I am sorry about that. While I accept that there will be a <i>post hoc</i> review on redress schemes in general, I agree with my colleagues here that there should be an independent investigation into the operation and management of Caranua. That should be commissioned and carried out by the Department. I would be interested to know if there is scope for such a review and, if so, what the likely timeframe would be.</p>
          <p eId="para_217"> The survivors in question have been in very vulnerable situations and they have been let down and failed. I anticipate certainly that when Caranua is wound up, extra supports will be needed for them. Can the witnesses indicate what supports will be put in place? There was €18 million available in the investment account by the end of September 2018. That is a great deal of money to have in the account while there has been a hold-up in making payments to survivors. Is that kept there because of the backlog or is there another specific reason?</p>
          <p eId="para_218"> The cap of €15,000 seems quite low. Caranua says the decision came from survivors but there was no consultation with them. I accept that it was Caranua that set the cap not the Department but the witnesses might give us a sense of why that might be. I ask the witnesses to excuse the suspension for voting. As soon as we come back, we will carry on.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_9">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 1.05 p.m. and resumed at 1.30 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_53">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">I apologise for having to suspend the meeting but, as Dáil members, we were under an obligation to vote. All of the members had an opportunity to put their questions to the Department officials and I propose that we start with Mr. Costello.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_54">
          <from> Mr. Ned Costello<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">I shall answer the questions thematically because there are many common threads in the themes.</p>
          <p eId="para_221"> I will first deal with question about the failure of State. There is no question that State failed all of those who were incarcerated in residential institutions. That has been made abundantly clear in the Ryan report, which does make for harrowing reading. The Taoiseach did apologise, on behalf of the State, to all survivors of institutions. That was clearly significant. There can be no question that the State failed and that has been fully acknowledged. It was partly on foot of that that the Residential Institutions Redress Board was established and the payments of approximately €1.2 billion of redress payments made to survivors; approximately 15,000 survivors received a payment from that board. The Caranua funding is in addition to the redress payments that were made.</p>
          <p eId="para_222"> I mentioned in my opening statement that the fund is finite and statutorily limited. That is significant because a significant amount of the tensions that arise derive from the fact that the fund is limited. I will talk about some of the issues that have been raised because a lot of them centre around the €15,000 limit. If one were to consider the population of survivors, and if this matter had been approached in a different way and a flat payment had been given to every survivor who already got an award from the redress board, that would have involved a payment of approximately €7,000 per survivor. It was not done that way. The initial approach was to have an entirely openended fund that was entirely needs based. There is an inevitable tension between that kind of an approach, a limited fund and a population of survivors who have received their redress payments already but might need further assistance from the fund. Again, I must stress that these decisions are statutorily independent by Caranua. That did result in, as one would understand, concerns about proportionality. That is the reasoning that underpins the €15,000 limit. The organisation would have been conscious of the fact that there were cohorts of survivors who had not been reached to date, in the context of the balance of the fund remaining and the need to take as equitable an approach as possible. It is clear that there are different views on that aspect.</p>
          <p eId="para_223"> I might touch on the issue of legal cases that was raised. Yes, the Department is aware that there is a legal challenge. It is complicated and I would possibly confuse things with the detail. Essentially, the legal challenge relates to the €15,000 limit and the application of the €15,000 limit. We have to see where the legal challenge goes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_55">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">As the challenge is not concluded I will not allow any further comment on the matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_56">
          <from> Mr. Ned Costello<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">I thank the Chairman.</p>
          <p eId="para_226"> There is a balance, as we would understand it, that the organisation is trying to seek between a needs-based approach and the fact that it has a limited fund and is trying to get to as many survivors as possible who may have a need. This matter is addressed in the most recent annual report produced by the organisation. There is a specific focus on trying to get to survivors who have not benefited from the fund so far. Many of the organisation's outreach efforts are being directed in that regard. Before the cessation date, it picked up a number of survivors that it had not reached. </p>
          <p eId="para_227"> I shall talk about some aspects of people who are waiting a long time. That issue is somewhat contextualised by the fact that it is not a one-shot application process. A number of clients of Caranua have made a number of applications and, therefore, may still have applications in process. That situation is reflected in the statistics. The latest statistics to the end of October show that Caranua had received 6,526 applications and of those 5,936 were deemed to be eligible but Caranua also has 2,365 open applications. There is still quite a volume of applications that are open. That does not mean that a client has not already received a payment from Caranua because he or she could have a second, third or fourth application submitted. There are quite a number of applications that still require to be worked through. That situation raises the question of why would money be held back, which the Chairman asked. It is because Caranua needs to ensure that it has adequate funds to cater for the applications that it has on hand. It is also why Caranua instituted a closing date for applications because it did not want to take applications and run up a bill that it would not be able to discharge subsequently.</p>
          <p eId="para_228"> Some questions were raised about the making of applications in terms of literacy issues and so on. That is why Caranua operates with application adviser support. That means that when a person makes an application he or she is assigned an adviser. It is not simply a paper-based process and there is a person to assist them.</p>
          <p eId="para_229"> Again, without exceeding the role of the Department and commenting in detail about the operations of Caranua, the operations of Caranua are funded by the fund. There is always a balance to be struck between the amount one spends on operations and the amount one spends on payments to individuals.</p>
          <p eId="para_230">That is a balance that the organisation and its board have to strike. </p>
          <p eId="para_231"> In terms of the general area of applications and the process, some questions were raised about the preferred supplier issue, quotations, etc. On the preferred supplier piece, Caranua did pilot two projects in 2014-2015 with the Clúid Housing Association and then with the Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland, SEAI. The projects were piloted based on feedback given by survivors on the difficulties in sourcing appropriate suppliers to provide quotes. However, the organisation found that fewer than 100 survivors participated in both of the schemes. The schemes were an attempt to assist but there was not a great uptake and, therefore, they have not been pursued.</p>
          <p eId="para_232"> As regards applying quotes, survivors are asked to provide quotes as follows: Where the cost of the work is less than €1,000 only one quote is asked for; where the cost of the work is between €1,000 and €5,000 then two quotes are required; and above that three quotes are required. A proportionate balance has been struck between the cost of the works and the quotations being sought. I commented on this matter in my opening statement.</p>
          <p eId="para_233"> The issues of regulatory impropriety and so on have been raised in terms of Caranua. The organisation has to have regard for that. It is understood that this is a vulnerable population of people and a balance must be struck. Clearly, if there is an entirely <i>laissez-faire</i> approach to that type of issue then it raises the question of that process not being respected, which creates other issues. </p>
          <p eId="para_234"> On the question of customer satisfaction, a number of specific issues have been raised about specific applications. We cannot comment on them as Caranua is a statutorily independent body. Inevitably, as a result we would not have the information.</p>
          <p eId="para_235"> In terms of respect for the independence of the body, it would be inappropriate for us to query specific applications. However, Members of the Oireachtas can contact Caranua and there is a dedicated Oireachtas email address. I know that the body will be very happy to pursue any specific instances that Deputies wish to raise with it and to take those up.</p>
          <p eId="para_236"> We are aware of the survey that was mentioned. It was a survey of a relatively small number of applicants out of the 6,500. Caranua's statistics are somewhat more broadly based but are not comprehensive. There is a question of customer satisfaction surveying. Again, there is a question of balancing how much one spends on such work. A survey costs money versus providing the supports for survivors. </p>
          <p eId="para_237"> My colleague, Ms Hynes, will comment on the questions on appeals. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Ms Catherine Hynes<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">When we realised that a backlog was building up on the number of appeals outstanding we decided that the best course of action would be for the Minister to appoint two appeals officers. In May 2017, two appeals officers were appointed. In May 2018, two appeals officers were offered reappointment. One person accepted the offer and the other person could not because of personal reasons but at that stage the appeals backlog had been eliminated. Our statistics at the moment show that there are 45 appeals of which eight have arrived in the past week. The Department provides administrative support to the appeals officer which is why we can monitor and keep a close eye on the situation. If the appeals backlog starts to build up again then remediation measures will be taken.</p>
          <p eId="para_239"> The appeals process is not straightforward. Let us say a person lodges an appeal. Caranua has the right to respond on the basis of that appeal. We know of one particular case where the applicant was written to over a year ago but the appeals process has not been concluded yet on the basis that information is being sought. We also know that when all of the paperwork has been completed and the appeals officer gets the completed file that his decision, on average, has taken just five weeks to conclude. Unfortunately, because of the backlog and legacy issues, the statistics skew the length of time people must wait to hear the determination of an appeal. We are very conscious that the population of the people out there have particular needs and are an ageing population. What no process wants to do is cause further distress. </p>
          <p eId="para_240"> Mr. Costello mentioned the issue of applicants being assigned to an application adviser. That is the way Caranua operates. When Caranua receives an application and an application adviser is available then the applicant will be assigned to a particular individual who will take over the case. </p>
          <p eId="para_241"> Deputy Jan O'Sullivan mentioned phone calls. We have been assured that whatever phone number the person chooses to use is the one that Caranua will use to communicate with the person. The volume of phone calls is such that the preferred method of communication is by phone. Again, returning to the literacy issues that people have mentioned, there is a realisation that for people with literacy issues their preferred method of communication is the phone.</p>
          <p eId="para_242"> When Caranua was established it was designed in order that it would complement not replace State services. In terms of an ageing population and the mainstream services such as housing assistance and whatever, our job in setting up the interdepartmental committee is to consider how mainstream services can support people as they age and whether existing services, such as the adaptation of bathrooms, for example, are sufficient to enable survivors to continue to live in their own homes for as long as they wish.</p>
          <p eId="para_243"> The staff of Caranua have continually offered us, as the Department, the opportunity to sit in and listen to how they deal with people. Indeed, an invitation has been extended to Members of the Oireachtas; if they want to visit Caranua and see how staff deal with survivors, on an individual basis, then they would be more than welcome to do so. Obviously the arrangements would have to be cleared with survivors beforehand. </p>
          <p eId="para_244"> Again, because we have no access to and cannot access the personal data that is held on individuals, if there are instances, which Senator Gavan has mentioned, where an individual was treated ignorantly by Caranua staff at their premises then I ask the member to raise the matter directly with Caranua. I am sure that Caranua would be very anxious to correct any mistreatment of people. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_58">
          <from> Mr. Ned Costello<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">A question was raised about the future of the residential institutions redress unit. The so-called RIRU is a unit within my division in the Department that deals with anything concerning institutional abuse or other cases of abuse, for example, in day schools, which arose in the past. Obviously due to the structure of the Department there are political decisions involved. There are no plans to close down the residential institutions redress unit, to the contrary. We have a large work programme, an interdepartmental committee, the post hoc review and continued oversight of Caranua, which are all major issues. We also have the Retention of Records Bill, for which we were before the committee for pre-legislative scrutiny. We hope to bring the legislation forward in the course of next year. We will actively consider the question of memorialisation, which is of concern.</p>
          <p eId="para_246">As members of the committee will be aware, a memorial was planned a number of years ago for the Garden of Remembrance but it did not get planning permission. Coming up to the anniversary of the Ryan report, there is still very much a live issue around how we commemorate, memorialise and mark what was a very sad period in Irish history. They are all activities on which we will be focusing in the coming year.</p>
          <p eId="para_247"> On the question around the board of Caranua, investigations are, ultimately, political decisions but we expect that the Minister will shortly fill the two vacancies on the board of Caranua with survivors.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_59">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">If anybody wants clarification on what Mr. Costello or Ms Hynes said, I will be happy to allow it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KathleenFunchion" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Deputy Kathleen Funchion<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">I had asked a question about the fact that people were told there was no appeals process. What is the situation and where can people go from here?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_61">
          <from> Mr. Ned Costello<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">I apologise for not responding. The appeals process is statutory and provided for in the Act so there are appeals officers. As I said earlier, there was a period, historically, when people were not sufficiently made aware of their right to appeal and this was reflected in the reports of the appeals officers, to which reference was made. That was corrected from mid-2016 and people are now informed in writing. We have provided sample letters to the committee showing the correspondence people receive in the supplementary information we provide. That piece of bad practice has been corrected.</p>
          <p eId="para_251"> Senator Ruane asked about the volume of complaints. We have attempted to make it clear that we are aware of a significant focus on the part of Caranua, since around the middle of 2016, on customer service issues. There may be other interpretations but we believe there is a correlation between the fact that people are less dissatisfied now than they were in the earlier period of Caranua's operations. The current acting chief executive, whom we meet regularly as part of our governance supervisory role, is absolutely dedicated to customer service. I believe improvements are being seen but there is a legacy period when there were teething or establishment troubles while the organisation was getting off the ground and finding its feet while trying to develop processes on a greenfield site. There continue to be repercussions for people from that period, which we have heard about today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">I appreciate the witnesses have had many questions to answer but I still do not understand why the statement says that since mid-2016, applicants to Caranua whose applications are not approved are notified in writing of their right to appeal and how to go about this, when the appeals officer himself, in the report published just one month ago, says "we continue to experience cases on this issue". There is a fairly fundamental difference from the appeals officer. I would like clarification on that.</p>
          <p eId="para_253"> Mr. Costello spoke about customer service and the passion of the CEO but it was the CEO who ran the applicant from the building three weeks ago. I am saying this because there is a huge contradiction here, which is why all of us are asking for an investigation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_63">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">That is hearsay and we cannot comment on somebody who is not here to defend themselves. I am going to disallow that particular question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">I want clarification on a matter. It was said that the Department had no details on the survey that showed 90% positive feedback and that we had to contact Caranua for it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_65">
          <from> Mr. Ned Costello<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">No. I said the number of responses to the survey was around 300 in an average year and that it is clearly not a census; it is a survey. I said that, because of the operational independence of Caranua from the Department and client confidentiality issues, the Department cannot pursue individual cases relating to Caranua's decisions but Members of the Oireachtas can pursue any of the cases directly with Caranua.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">It strikes us as quite unusual that there was 90% positive feedback, considering the fact that this is not what we hear. Has it not struck the Department as a little bit strange? The Department has a role in oversight and accountability in matters relating to governance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_67">
          <from> Ms Catherine Hynes<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">This is the feedback Caranua gets from its client base. Of the feedback it receives, 90% is positive. It looks for feedback on its website and publishes statistics on that feedback.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_68">
          <from> Mr. Ned Costello<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">This is the point I am making. It is not a population survey. There is a frequency, volume and amplitude issue in this, however. There may be people who are extremely dissatisfied but a large body of people who are generally satisfied. That may explain an apparent disjunction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_69">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">It is something we need to delve into a bit more.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">Is the freefone number available from a landline and is it free from the UK? I believe 40% of the survivors are in the UK. Is it free from a mobile or just from a landline?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_71">
          <from> Mr. Ned Costello<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_262">We will check and come back to the Deputy on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_263">It is something we need to establish.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_73">
          <from> Mr. Ned Costello<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">In response to Senator Gavan's question, our belief is that it refers to the legacy period. This is because, in addition to the fact that we have the documentation, which I have supplied to the committee, Caranua asked people to come back and let it know of any individual instance where somebody did not receive the information. It has not had anybody come back on that. I am not sure if it was Members of the Oireachtas it asked.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from> Ms Catherine Hynes<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">No. It was advocacy groups.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_75">
          <from> Mr. Ned Costello<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">It was advocacy groups, not Members of the Oireachtas. Caranua is in regular contact with advocacy groups and it asked for those groups to bring forward any cases where somebody had not received the information.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_267">Does that include the UK?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_77">
          <from> Mr. Ned Costello<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_268">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_269">The number of applicants there is very-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_79">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_270">I ask the Senator to put his questions through the Chair.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_271">The number of applications from Britain is particularly low and this is another indication that Caranua has not succeeded in reaching out to victims over there. There is so much evidence that Caranua is not fit for function. I understand-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_81">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_272">As I reminded the Senator before we started, he cannot make comments like that about an organisation that is not here to defend itself.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_273"><b>
						</b>I kind of have to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_83">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_274">The Senator cannot. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_275">I hear what the Chairman is saying. Someone has to say it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_85">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">We have had a very interactive session. While not all members will be happy with some of the responses, there is a great deal of food for thought in what has been said. This does not end here for any of us. There is an onus and duty on all members of the committee to think about what has been submitted in writing or stated to us. As a committee, we will consider how we want to progress this but a likely recommendation will involve the commissioning of an independent investigation. We have heard that from a number of members. At a future stage, we will have the opportunity to set out what we would like that independent investigation to cover. A number of members queried whether the Department was of the view that a review would happen but the committee did not necessarily get a response to the effect that it would. It will therefore be incumbent on the committee to make a recommendation to the Minister in that regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_277"> This is a sensitive and delicate matter and we are very conscious that we are representing thousands of people. By the end of 2017, almost 5,500 people had come forward. There is no doubt that far more people than that are affected. The committee wants all survivors to be dealt with in a very understanding, compassionate and practical way having regard to their needs. Bearing in mind that a great many survivors emigrated to England, there is a particular need to make contact with the population overseas. We appreciate the attendance of Mr. Costello, Ms Hynes and Mr. Ó hAonghusa. We will come back to this matter again. Mr. Costello wishes to make a point of clarification.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_86">
          <from> Mr. Ned Costello<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_278">I apologise. I may not have made matters sufficiently clear having regard to what the Chairman has just said. One of the things we will be doing in our consultation process with survivors is asking them for their views and feedback on both Caranua and the redress schemes generally. As such, we are going to garner feedback on the feelings of survivors on that issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_87">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">I thank Mr. Costello. The consultation is absolutely vital and we appreciate that. We ask that consultation is as full and whole as possible and that it involves all individuals who contacted Caranua, not just a cohort with whom it is easy to engage. Everyone should be consulted. That concludes this part of the agenda. I propose that the committee defers consideration of the private housekeeping matters to next Tuesday. Is that agreed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">Unless it is inconvenient for members, I would like the private session to take place now. If it is not convenient, I will not insist.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_89">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_281">A number of members have indicated difficulties.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_282">That is fine. I would like the issue we have just discussed to be included on the private session agenda.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_91">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-11-15T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_283">It will be, absolutely. Is the proposal to defer matters to next Tuesday agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_10"> The joint committee adjourned at 2.05 p.m. until 3.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 20 November 2018.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
