<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_media_tourism_arts_culture_sport_and_the_gaeltacht/2020-10-07/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_media_tourism_arts_culture_sport_and_the_gaeltacht/2020-10-07/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-10-07" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/33/select_committee_on_media_tourism_arts_culture_sport_and_the_gaeltacht"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_media_tourism_arts_culture_sport_and_the_gaeltacht/2020-10-07/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_media_tourism_arts_culture_sport_and_the_gaeltacht/2020-10-07/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-10-07" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_media_tourism_arts_culture_sport_and_the_gaeltacht/2020-10-07/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_media_tourism_arts_culture_sport_and_the_gaeltacht/2020-10-07/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2021-04-27" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AlanDillon" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Alan-Dillon.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Alan  Dillon"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BrendanGriffinFG" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Brendan-Griffin.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Brendan Griffin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CatherineMartin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Catherine-Martin.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Catherine Martin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ChristopherOsullivan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Christopher-O'Sullivan.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Christopher O'Sullivan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ImeldaMunster" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Imelda-Munster.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Imelda Munster"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JackChambers" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jack-Chambers.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Jack Chambers"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnnyMythen" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Johnny-Mythen.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Johnny Mythen"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MattieMcGrath" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mattie-McGrath.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Mattie McGrath"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NiamhSmyth" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Niamh-Smyth.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Niamh Smyth"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister/tourism__culture__arts__gaeltacht__sport__media" showAs="Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN ROGHCHOISTE UM NA MEÁIN, TURASÓIREACHT, EALAÍONA, CULTÚR, SPÓRT AGUS GAELTACHT</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Select Committee on Media, Tourism, Arts, Culture, Sport and the Gaeltacht</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2020-10-07">Dé Céadaoin, 07 Deireadh Fómhair 2020</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2020-10-07">Wednesday, 07 October 2020</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Roghchoiste le chéile ag 02:00 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Select Committee met at 02:00 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2"/>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#AlanDillon">Alan Dillon</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#BrendanGriffinFG">Brendan Griffin</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#MattieMcGrath">Mattie McGrath</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#ImeldaMunster">Imelda Munster</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#JohnnyMythen">Johnny Mythen</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#ChristopherOsullivan">Christopher O'Sullivan.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">I láthair / In attendance: Deputy Danny Healy-Rae.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#NiamhSmyth">Teachta / Deputy Niamh Smyth sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Business of Select Committee<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Estimates for Public Services 2020<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:10:00+01:00"/></heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Vote 33 – Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media (Further Revised)<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:10:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#NiamhSmyth" eId="spk_1">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_9">I welcome the Ministers with us today. I remind members, officials and those in the Gallery to please ensure their mobile phones are switched off for the duration of the meeting as they interfere with the broadcasting equipment even when on silent mode.</p>
          <p eId="para_10"> This meeting has been convened to consider the Further Revised Estimates for Vote 33 - tourism, media, arts, Gaeltacht, sport and media, which was referred to this committee by Dáil Éireann. I welcome the Minister, Deputy Catherine Martin, and the Minister of State, Deputy Jack Chambers, and their officials to the meeting. I also thank the Minister and her officials for the briefing documents provided for this meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_11"> As the Minister and Minister of State are present, officials should not speak in public session. Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official, either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable. I also wish to advise speakers that the opening statements and any other documents they have submitted to the committee may be published on the committee website after this meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_12"> I ask the Minister, Deputy Martin, to make her presentation to the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media (Deputy Catherine Martin)<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_13">Táim thar a bheith sásta a bheith anseo inniu chun labhairt faoi Mheastacháin Athbhreithnithe na Roinne nua do 2020. I am pleased to have this opportunity to address the committee on the 2020 Further Revised Estimates for Vote 33 - tourism, culture, arts, Gaeltacht, sports and media. I will take this opportunity to congratulate Deputy Niamh Smyth on her new role as Chair of the committee. She hails from the constituency I grew up in of Cavan–Monaghan so I am delighted to see someone from that constituency in this role. I know from our previous Dáil term how active a spokesperson she was on this and how familiar she is with the brief on a personal level. I wish her well.</p>
          <p eId="para_14"> The original 2020 Revised Estimates for Vote 33 were passed by the Dáil in July of this year. These Estimates, however, relate to the then configuration of the Vote - culture, heritage and the Gaeltacht. A Further Revised Estimate was necessary for 2020 to give effect to the transfer of functions and resources from and to the Vote to reflect new roles and responsibilities. Responsibility for heritage matters has substantially transferred to the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government and all matters relating to the islands have transferred to the Department of Rural and Community Development. My Department has assumed responsibility for all matters related to tourism, sport and media. I am pleased to speak to the committee today with regard to tourism, culture, arts and media while my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Jack Chambers, will address matters related to sport and the Gaeltacht. </p>
          <p eId="para_15"> The Covid-19 pandemic has utterly changed the landscape of the sectors for which I have responsibility as Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media. There has been a collapse in international tourism which the OECD estimates will be in the order of 80%. The impact of social distancing measures and the required limits on gatherings to protect public health has significantly diminished the domestic tourism and hospitality sectors. </p>
          <p eId="para_16"> Cultural venues and events were among the first to be closed on foot of the crisis and restrictions on social distancing and gatherings has had, and will continue to have, a devastating impact on performance opportunities, displays, festivals and concerts. The impact of the pandemic on the arts sector extends well beyond artists to include crews and the wide range of people it takes to put on live performances in venues and festivals.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> The sport sector has been directly impacted by the pandemic. Like the cultural sector, all sporting activity was suspended in March. Restrictions on attendances since activity resumed has severely impacted revenues and the commercial sports and leisure sectors have been severely curtailed by indoor gathering limits. </p>
          <p eId="para_18"> Across the Gaeltacht, businesses and communities alike have suffered a significant reduction in economic activity, tourism and educational visitors as a consequence of Covid-19.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> The media sector has been especially hard-hit in terms of reduced advertising revenue, in particular, while at the same time having to fulfil a critical role in public messaging around Covid-19.</p>
          <p eId="para_20"> These sectors, individually and cumulatively, are an integral part of the fabric of our society, most particularly, in rural and regional areas where they support economic activity and physical and societal well-being. Well-being is a core principal underpinning the living with Covid-19 plan and it will be fundamental to public confidence and resilience as we emerge from and manage the crisis over the long term. </p>
          <p eId="para_21"> The need for important public health measures such as social distancing has placed necessary limits on gatherings to protect health. This has had a devastating impact on these sectors given their public facing and audience-driven nature. I have worked tirelessly with Government colleagues to ensure that a range of measures have been introduced to help support the tourism, arts, culture, Gaeltacht and sport sectors including: a €26 million adaptation grant for the tourism sector; a €10 million grant for coach tourism; the "stay and spend" tax credit initiative; an additional €25 million in funding for the Arts Council; a €5 million live events pilot grant scheme; a €3 million TV drama fund; €6 million to support the national cultural institutions and nationwide arts infrastructure; an additional €8 million for Údarás na Gaeltachta; €40 million for the three main field sports bodies, namely, the GAA, IRFU and FAI; and a €15 million resilience fund for sports governing bodies and clubs.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> The universal income supports of the pandemic unemployment payment, PUP, and the wage subsidy scheme have also been critical in supporting all sectors through this crisis and the extension of both of these schemes has been important in this regard. The 2020 Further Revised Estimates for my Department, which are under consideration today, reflect the additional funding and measures secured to support these sectors and ensure that as we begin to emerge from the shadow of Covid-19 we will have a vital tourism industry, a vibrant arts and culture sector, a dynamic sports and media sector and a landscape in which our language and our engagement with it can continue to grow and flourish.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> When account is taken of all additional funding allocated in response to the Covid-19 pandemic, including funding awarded as part of the July job stimulus, a gross provision of €1.003 billion is available to the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media in 2020. An additional €32.9 million in funding has been carried over from the 2019 capital provision for expenditure and priority projects in accordance with the provisions of public financial procedures.</p>
          <p eId="para_24"> In broad terms, the 2020 breakdown of allocations to the Vote is as follows: €148.4 million for tourism services, including €22.9 million in additional funding to deal with the impacts of the Covid-19 pandemic; just over €251 million for arts and culture, including an allocation of €105 million for the Arts Council, an increase of 31% on its 2019 allocation of €80 million as well as an additional funding of €5 million for a live events pilot scheme and €3 million for a new TV drama fund; just under €72 million for the Gaeltacht, including an additional €8 million for Údarás na Gaeltachta; €217 million for sports and recreational services, including €40 million for the three main field sports bodies, namely, the GAA, IRFU and FAI, a €15 million resilience fund for sport governing bodies and clubs and €15 million to provide for the GAA, the Ladies Gaelic Football Association, LGFA, and the Camogie Association to stage the 2020 football, hurling and camogie championships; and €278.5 million for media and broadcasting, including an additional €2 million in respect of the broadcasting fund.</p>
          <p eId="para_25"> While the Department did not exist in its current configuration in 2019, a broad comparison of the comparable programme allocation indicates that the 2020 allocations are 25% higher than in 2019 reflecting my commitment, and that of Government, to support these vital yet vulnerable sectors as they navigate their way through the current Covid-19 crisis.</p>
          <p eId="para_26"> This increased funding is targeted at a number of key initiatives. In the case of the tourism programme, the 2020 allocation is some 14% higher than the comparable figure for 2019 and includes additional funding of €10 million to Fáilte Ireland towards a business adaptation scheme to allow the hospitality sector to adapt and reconfigure to comply with restrictions and a further additional €10 million for coach tourism.</p>
          <p eId="para_27"> The tourism recovery task force which was established in May has recently presented its recommendations which will help inform the development of a recovery plan for this important sector.</p>
          <p eId="para_28"> Funding for the arts and culture programme has increased by one third to just over €251 million. As Minister, I am acutely conscious of the devastating impact of the current crisis on this sector.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">I recently established an arts and culture recovery task force and look forward to working with its members to develop a roadmap to recover the viability of the sector.</p>
          <p eId="para_30"> The 2020 allocation includes just under €56 million made available to the sector specifically to address the most severe impacts of this unprecedented crisis. An allocation of €278.5 million is available in 2020 for the media and broadcasting programme, representing an increase of 5% over the comparable figure for 2019. The media sector has a critical role to play in communicating the public messaging around Covid-19, and it is vital that we continue to support it in pursuit of this to the greatest extent possible.</p>
          <p eId="para_31"> My colleague, the Minister of State with responsibility for Gaeltacht affairs and sport, Deputy Chambers, will speak to the Gaeltacht and sports programmes of Vote 33.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_32">I would like to start by wishing Deputy Niamh Smyth well as Chair of the committee. I look forward to working with all of the committee members over the coming period.</p>
          <p eId="para_33"> Táim thar a bheith sásta a bheith anseo inniu le labhairt faoi Mheastacháin Athbhreithnithe na Roinne nua do 2020. Táthar ag leanúint le cur i bhfeidhm na Straitéise 20 Bliain don Ghaeilge agus leis na spriocanna ar leas na Gaeilge agus na Gaeltachta atá leagtha amach sa Phlean Gníomhaíochta 2018-2022. Beimid ag foilsiú an chéad tuarascáil bhliantúil maidir le cur i bhfeidhm an phlean sin ar an Aoine beag seo, rud a sháraigh leibhéal níos airde trédhearcachta den mhéad atá á dhéanamh ag an Stát agus ag na heagraíochtaí Gaeilge leath-Stáit agus neamh-Stáit ar mhaithe leis an teanga a chur chun cinn.</p>
          <p eId="para_34"> Tá maoiniú suntasach de níos mó ná €70 milliún curtha ar fáil i mbliana don Ghaeilge agus don Ghaeltacht. San áireamh anseo, tá an pacáiste spreagtha post a d'fhógair an Rialtas nua i mí Iúil. Cuirfidh an pacáiste seo €8 milliún breise ar fáil d'Údarás na Gaeltachta chun uasghrádú riachtanach a dhéanamh ar a stoc foirgneamh agus ar chórais chóireála uisce. Crutheoidh sé seo idir 40 agus 50 post nua tógála ar fud na Gaeltachta sa ghéarchéime agus tacóidh sé le 320 post nua níos fadtréimhsí a chruthú sa Ghaeltacht ag líonadh cuideachtaí de chuid Údarás na Gaeltachta. Cuireadh airgead breise isteach sa phleanáil teanga agus sa chlár tacaíochtaí pobail agus teanga i mbliana. Mar aon leis sin, cuirfear maoiniú breise de €250,000 ar fáil d'Ealaín na Gaeltachta chun tacaíocht a chur ar fáil do na healaíona traidisiúnta. Beidh suntas mór ag baint leis an infheistíocht breise seo do cheantair Ghaeltachta.</p>
          <p eId="para_35"> Tá sé i gceist go dtionólfar cruinnithe den Chomhairle Aireachta Thuaidh-Theas arís go gairid agus pléifear ansin gach gné d'obair an Fhoras Teanga, an buiséad do 2021 san áireamh. Níl aon dabht faoi ach go raibh an chéad leath den bhliain reatha dúshlánach do lucht na Gaeilge agus muid ag cur impleachtaí Covid-19 ar an ngeilleagar san áireamh. Tuigim go maith go bhfuil na heagraíochtaí Gaeilge agus Gaeltachta tar éis teacht tríd roinnt blianta crua agus is féidir leis an gcoiste glacadh leis go mbeidh mise, fad mo chumas, ag lorg acmhainní breise do chúrsaí Gaeilge agus Gaeltachta ón Státchiste le linn mo théarma oifige.</p>
          <p eId="para_36"> Funding for the sports and recreation programme has increased by 72% to just over €217 million. As Minister of State, I am acutely conscious of the devastating impact of the current crisis on this sector. Additional funding of almost €94 million has been made available to the sector in 2020 and is being used to address the most severe impacts of this unprecedented crisis, including: €40 million for the organisations that oversee the three main field sports, the GAA, IRFU and FAI; a €15 million resilience fund for sport governing bodies and clubs; and €15 million to the Ladies' Gaelic Football Association and Camogie Association to stage the 2020 football, hurling and camogie championships.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_4" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_37">The 2020 allocation of €1.003 billion for the Vote of the Department with responsibility for media, tourism, arts, culture, sport and the Gaeltacht will allow for the continuation and enhancement of its diverse but critical work programme. Both my officials and I are in regular contact with stakeholders and representatives in all of the sectors for which I have responsibility, and their views and recommendations will inform any refinement of existing supports or introduction of new supports, as required. As Minister, I intend to do everything possible to ensure these sectors remain viable and resilient as we continue to deal with the ongoing impacts of the Covid-19 pandemic.</p>
          <p eId="para_38"> I am happy to take any questions Deputies may have in respect of the 2020 Further Revised Estimates for my Department.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiamhSmyth" eId="spk_5">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">I thank the Minister and Minister of State for their presentations. I will say at the outset that we are under pressure timewise, as we know. I am advised that we must be finished by 2.40 p.m. which gives us a short timeframe.</p>
          <p eId="para_40"> I have one question, if that is okay. Will the Minister comment a little further on the task force on arts and culture? I was delighted to hear it has been established. The remit of the committee is broad. Is there a timeframe in which a roadmap will be set out? Will it be ongoing or will we see results and a plan put in place in the short term?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_6" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_41">As the Chairperson knows, the task force was set up recently and is chaired by Ms Clare Duignan. It held its first meeting two weeks ago. It is due to report on 31 October, but at the first meeting, I asked the members of the task force to identify key priorities that would feed into the budget. I received those last week and they are helping me in negotiations for budget allocations. There is ongoing communication with the officials and chair of the task force. The report is expected at the end of the month.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiamhSmyth" eId="spk_7">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">I thank the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_8" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_43">Speed is of the essence when it comes to supporting our culture and arts sectors.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiamhSmyth" eId="spk_9">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_44">I absolutely agree. We will now begin questions from committee members. As members know from the most recent meeting, we will follow the same rota as applies in the Dáil Chamber. We will start with Government representatives before moving to the Opposition.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrendanGriffinFG" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy Brendan Griffin<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">I will be brief. I congratulate the Minister on her appointment. I want to ask about the report of the tourism recovery task force. There is obviously quite an amount of financial assistance required for the extraordinary response that will be needed for the industry. What measures have been taken to date to try to secure the level of funding that will be required to match the issues that have been identified by the task force?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_11" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">I brought that report before Cabinet yesterday. The key recommendations in the report relate to survival, recovery and stabilisation. The measures in the document will apply for three years so it is an ongoing process that will need oversight of its implementation.</p>
          <p eId="para_47"> I met the tourism and recovery task force for its final meeting this morning. I will not have the negotiations here but I have consistently voiced the supports that the members of the task force and stakeholders have said are needed. I have brought them to the attention of the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, and the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Michael McGrath. I will meet them again this week to discuss same. The document is essential for budget allocations and the national economic plan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy Alan Dillon<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_48">I wish the Minister and Minister of State the very best in their portfolios. I thank them for their presentations on the accounts.</p>
          <p eId="para_49"> There are two topics on which I wish to touch relating to sport. The allocation of €40 million to the three main sporting bodies was welcome and badly needed at the time. The €15 million provided to the Ladies' Gaelic Football Association and Camogie Association was also welcome.</p>
          <p eId="para_50"> The fear at present is that we might not see an intercounty championship because we are facing additional levels of restrictions. Has there been consultation with the GAA about the provision of testing to ensure that we have a senior intercounty championship? It is important that we have clarity on screening for intercounty footballers. We are dealing with two different jurisdictions, North and South, which has a risk factor associated with it, especially on the back of last weekend when there were numerous challenge matches around the country. We want to see an intercounty championship so it is crucial that a rapid testing approach is put in place. Such a regime was implemented previously for elite level rugby and soccer players. The GAA equally needs to be brought into focus in that regard. The GAA needs to provide guidance on this.</p>
          <p eId="para_51">I am aware they were putting a rapid testing system out to tender. That was in September. We need clarity on that. The national league will start at the end of October. We are then into intercounty championship games without any real window for postponements. In the likelihood of a county increasing its level of restriction, it will have to forfeit games, which I would not like to see at the latter end of the championship. I ask the Minister of State to comment on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">Collectively, we share the ambition to see the 2020 championship take place this year. That is why the Minister, Deputy Martin, and I worked with the GAA's ladies football and camogie to secure that funding and make it possible in financial terms. The return to sport expert group, in which the GAA is essentially involved, with Sport Ireland and the other key associations, is considering how we can have a safe return to sport. That covers a range of items, including matters around public health and the safe return to sport. Protocols are being developed, for example, but it is also examining the spectator issue at level 3. That is in a different space than it would have been in a level 1 or 2 scenario. It is considering, particularly for the large stadia which are referenced in levels 1 and 2 of the roadmap, how we could have a safe return for spectators but part of that are the overarching protocols for athletes with the GAA and also for high-performance athletes. The protocols and bilateral engagement with the GAA is ongoing on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ChristopherOsullivan" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Christopher O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_53">The Minister, Deputy Martin, outlined the figures for the extra expenditure this year compared with that in 2019, which was 25% overall for tourism and 14% for the arts, which is a difference of approximately one third. That is impressive and it shows a level of commitment.</p>
          <p eId="para_54"> Speaking specifically on tourism, there is anecdotal evidence in specific parts of the country where, depending on the nature of the business and whether it is accommodation-based or involved in outdoor activities, there is quite an increase for the months of July, August and even September. Some tourism-related businesses experienced a small boost. That was certainly the case in my area but, unfortunately, that was not the case in all scenarios. We have been plunged now into a nationwide level 3 and there are major challenges involved in that. I take this opportunity to reaffirm my plea to the Minister to consider the report and the extra supports that will be required. She has stated that she will do that and she has brought it to the attention of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Michael McGrath, and the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe.</p>
          <p eId="para_55"> In respect of the arts, the Minister might try to answer these two questions as best she can. First, I asked this question in the Dáil yesterday and having listened again to her summation at the end of her reply I did not get an answer to two questions. This might be a social protection issue but it ties in with the Minister's Department. It relates to allowing arts and events workers in the entertainment industry avail of unique, individual social protection supports. I mentioned the return to work enterprise allowance whereby if people have been on social welfare but want to start up their own business they are allowed claim social welfare for a two-year period and also earn income on the business. I believe that because of the unique circumstances now for events and arts workers that is something that could apply to them. I ask the Minister to comment on that or at the very least liaise with the Department of the Minister, Deputy Humphreys.</p>
          <p eId="para_56"> Second, on the pandemic unemployment payment, PUP, the plea from arts workers is that they be allowed retain their PUP but take very little work when it comes up, and that a specific allowance would be made to allow arts and events workers to do that. As the Minister said in her opening address, they are specifically impacted because we will not be able to see large crowds gather for a long time. I ask the Minister to touch on the two suggestions I made in the Dáil yesterday. I do not expect her to have a detailed answer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiamhSmyth" eId="spk_15">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_57">If the Ministers agree I will allow all the members ask their questions and they can then respond individually. We are very tight for time and I want to make sure the members get a chance to ask their questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">In respect of the tourism services, Programme A in the Revised Estimates refers to €12.9 million and €10 million for tourism product development. Is that the sum total of additional spend for 2020 for Covid-19? There was also a reference to a €6 million carryover in tourism capital from 2019. Can we get information as to where that came from? The Minister said that Tourism Ireland had received funding of €45 million. Does the Minister anticipate any change in the funding for tourism given that the primary function is to market Ireland abroad and that was not possible for 2020?</p>
          <p eId="para_59"> Regarding the arts, the Minister said that there was additional funding of €25 million. Given the dire straits the arts sector is in, does she believe that that funding will be sufficient to sustain them through this pandemic?</p>
          <p eId="para_60"> Regarding sports, the Estimates indicate that there is an additional €94 million. Can we be provided with a breakdown of who got that funding? There was also an underspend that led to €23.4 million being carried over in capital expenditure. Will the Minister expand on that also, please?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MattieMcGrath" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Deputy Mattie McGrath<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_61">I, too, would like to congratulate the two Ministers and wish them all the best in their role. I look forward to working with them in this committee. Games are very important in sports. The Minister went through the different funding amounts that she has given to the GAA, soccer and rugby. I am glad that ladies football and camogie have got funding now but they had been left behind. Those sports are very important and they need to be treated equally. The pandemic has been hugely challenging for all those clubs, players, their families and friends. We need rapid testing in those associations to be able to play games. Reportedly, there was a case last weekend in Dungarvan involving a player who said he had Covid-19 and the mentor told him to say nothing and go ahead and play. I have no information on that but those kinds of situations should not arise. There should be a rapid test system in place. This is probably outside the scope of the Ministers' Department but I cannot understand why we have not considered rapid and more cost-effective testing.</p>
          <p eId="para_62"> The arts and entertainment sector is vital, even more important than the last one mentioned. They are all very important because they give us solace, joy and a bit of an uplift, and the public miss them very much. They miss the showbands, the shows, the one-man bands and whatever. The sole traders are in an awful situation, especially now with the ending of the bank moratorium. Many of these people have mortgaged their houses against the cost of vans, equipment, lighting, etc., and the PUP has been cut. I support the previous speaker who said the full level of the PUP should be continued for those people and for the workers in the arts and events sector. If a limited number of entertainment shows go ahead, and God knows we need them, they should be allowed cross-reference them with the PUP.</p>
          <p eId="para_63"> I am not sure if this comes under the Ministers' remit but staycations were mentioned. The tax breaks should apply to everyone and the cost should be given back in tax, and I hope it will be done in the budget, rather than waiting for one's tax returns for next year. Pensioners and people who are unemployed, and there are many of them now, are being denied any hope of getting that tax break so we need equality in the system also.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">I thank the Ministers. I do not believe we got a copy of the tourism recovery task force report. Can we get that? I have not seen it.</p>
          <p eId="para_65"> On the media sector, I think the Minister said funding was up 5% from last year. As she is aware, many local newspapers, especially those in rural areas, are facing insolvency. Many of them are working with a skeleton staff. </p>
          <p eId="para_66"> In terms of radio stations such as Beat 102-103, will the broadcasting fund be beefed up?</p>
          <p eId="para_67"> On the sporting issues, the GAA, the IRFU and the FAI are very strong organisations. They get a lot and are open to a lot of private donations as well. In contrast, local clubs in rural areas must raise funds by organising pub quizzes and field days but their insurance premiums have increased so they really need help.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_19" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">I hope I can address all of the issues raised but if not I ask members to talk to me afterwards.</p>
          <p eId="para_69"> Deputy Christopher O'Sullivan mentioned that some people in the tourism area felt the support was a small boost that only lasted for a short period during the summer. I am very aware of how difficult business has been and the decision to move to level 3 across the country has made it much more difficult. That is why the tourism recovery report and the engagement with stakeholders is key. I vigorously advocate for the tourism sector, especially in the context of the budget.</p>
          <p eId="para_70"> On another issue that the Deputy raised yesterday, I am very conscious of the challenges facing workers in the arts sector. I am happy to liaise with the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Deputy Humphreys, on the issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_71"> In response to Deputy Munster, the carryover expenditure is normal when money is simply carried from one year to the next. If she needs technical details, I will revert to her and get my officials to contact her.</p>
          <p eId="para_72"> On Tourism Ireland, we will keep Ireland's presence in our key markets that have the best chance of recovery. The July stimulus included €10 million for the adaptation fund, which now stands at €26 million, in addition to the €20 million for product development. Some 2.8 million people are eligible for the stay-and-spend scheme, which is a demand generation initiative. It will be reviewed as it is challenged by changes in levels.</p>
          <p eId="para_73"> Deputy Mattie McGrath and another Deputy mentioned the pandemic unemployment payment. I am very conscious that the changes in the PUP scheme and the employment wages subsidy scheme affect the lives of thousands of artists and workers in the culture, arts and live entertainment sectors. I understand that these supports are needed now more than ever. I have raised these matters with my Cabinet colleagues in the context of the budget. I recognise that there will be a long and extended period in which we will have to live with the virus. That presents difficulties for this sector because of the people-facing nature of performance. These supports are important now more than ever.</p>
          <p eId="para_74"> We should not see performance as a luxury, but as an absolute essential because culture, arts and music define us as a people. We are talking about people's livelihoods. We rely on performers for the societal well-being of the nation. As I come from that background, I am conscious of the well-being of performers and their need to earn a living. Performers need to perform and feed off an audience. That is why my Department developed the pilot live performance scheme worth €5 million, in consultation with the sector. The scheme has been inundated with applications to the value of €15 million. We did the pilot scheme before the budget because we felt the scheme would be well received. Performers have seen merit in the scheme. The main objective of the scheme is to provide employment for artists, creative technicians and support staff. It also seeks to carry the risk of planning and performances.</p>
          <p eId="para_75"> I have a copy of the report and I am happy to supply the report to the Deputy who asked for it. If other Deputies want it then I am quite happy to share it with them too. I will get copies to them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">I thank all of the Members for their questions. I shall first give Deputy Munster a breakdown of the €94 million. There has been a 72% increase and it focuses on subhead D5 of the Estimates. A sum of €70 million is part of the July stimulus. A sum of €15 million had been given to the GAA and the camogie and ladies football associations to run their championships. Last February, the FAI received nearly €5.5 million. Finally, there was over €2.5 million for a lot of the leisure facilities that closed. People will be aware of the huge difficulties being experienced by swimming pools at the moment and the funding was given to support them.</p>
          <p eId="para_77"> Deputies Dillon, Mythen and Mattie McGrath referenced the sporting organisations. We are working with the GAA and the other associations to try to ensure the championship happens during the current pandemic. That is why funding has been put in place but protocols have to be developed so that we can make sure it is safe. That is why the expert group on the return to sport is working with the GAA on the protocols. The GAA has similar testing protocols to many other associations and that work is ongoing. As we head into a difficult winter, it is important that sport continues, in particular the GAA championships.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">I asked about the underspend that led to €23.4 million being carried over in capital expenditure. Does the Minister of State know where that underspend occurred?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">We will shortly announce the sports capital programme for clubs. The carryover will be reflected in trying to support clubs in the context of the sports capital programme for this year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">Does the Minister of State know where the underspend occurred?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">I will revert directly to the Deputy on that matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">I thank the Minister of State.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiamhSmyth" eId="spk_26">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">I thank the Minister, the Minister of State and their officials who accompanied them, Ms Katherine Licken and Mr. Joe Healy. We appreciate the presentations.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_5">
        <heading>Message to Dáil<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:40:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#NiamhSmyth" eId="spk_27">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2020-10-07T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">In accordance with Standing Order 101, the following message will be sent to the Dáil:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_85">The Select Committee on Media, Tourism, Arts, Culture, Sport and the Gaeltacht has completed its consideration of the following further Revised Estimate for public services for the year ending 31 December 2020: Vote 33 - Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6"> The select committee adjourned at 2.47 p.m.<i> sine die</i>.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
