<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2022-11-24/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2022-11-24/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2022-11-24" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/house/seanad/26"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2022-11-24/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2022-11-24/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2022-11-24" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2022-11-24/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2022-11-24/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2022-12-17" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AidanDavitt" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aidan-Davitt.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Aidan Davitt"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AislingDolan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aisling-Dolan.S.2020-06-29" showAs="Aisling Dolan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ColmBrophy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Colm-Brophy.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Colm Brophy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DiarmuidWilson" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Diarmuid-Wilson.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Diarmuid Wilson"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="EmerCurrie" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Emer-Currie.S.2020-06-29" showAs="Emer Currie"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ErinMcGreehan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Erin-McGreehan.S.2020-06-29" showAs="Erin McGreehan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="EugeneMurphy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Eugene-Murphy.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Eugene Murphy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FrankFeighan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Frank-Feighan.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Frank Feighan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="GerardPCraughwell" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Gerard-P-Craughwell.S.2014-10-10" showAs="Gerard P. Craughwell"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnMcGahon" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-McGahon.S.2020-03-30" showAs="John McGahon"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LisaChambers" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Lisa-Chambers.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Lisa Chambers"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LynnBoylan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Lynn-Boylan.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Lynn Boylan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MalcolmByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Malcolm-Byrne.D.2019-11-29" showAs="Malcolm Byrne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MariaByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Maria-Byrne.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Maria Byrne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MarkDaly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mark-Daly.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Mark Daly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MartinConway" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Martin-Conway.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Martin Conway"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MartinHeydon" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Martin-Heydon.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Martin Heydon"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaryFitzpatrick" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mary-Fitzpatrick.S.2020-06-29" showAs="Mary Fitzpatrick"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MarySeeryKearney" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mary-Seery-Kearney.S.2020-06-29" showAs="Mary Seery Kearney"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichealCarrigy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Micheál-Carrigy.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Micheál Carrigy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NiallODonnghaile" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Niall-Ó-Donnghaile.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Niall Ó Donnghaile"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulGavan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Gavan.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Paul Gavan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PippaHackett" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pippa-Hackett.S.2019-11-01" showAs="Pippa Hackett"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanKyne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Kyne.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Seán Kyne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SimonCoveney" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Simon-Coveney.D.1998-10-23" showAs="Simon Coveney"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TimLombard" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Tim-Lombard.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Tim Lombard"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Acting_Chairperson" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/office/acting_chairperson" showAs="Acting Chairperson"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_for_Foreign_Affairs" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister/foreign_affairs" showAs="Minister for Foreign Affairs"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/agriculture__food__marine" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/foreign_affairs" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Health" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/health" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Health"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>SEANAD ÉIREANN</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>SEANAD ÉIREANN</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2022-11-24">Déardaoin, 24 Samhain 2022</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2022-11-24">Thursday, 24 November 2022</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="volume">
        <docNumber refersTo="#vol_290">Vol. 290</docNumber>
      </block>
      <block name="number">
        <docNumber refersTo="#no_5">No. 5</docNumber>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus>Unrevised</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus>Neamhcheartaithe</docStatus>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30 a.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">Machnamh agus Paidir.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Reflection and Prayer.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:30:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_1">I have received notice from the following Senators that they propose to raise the following matters:Senator Erin McGreehan - The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to engage with local authorities on the implementation of the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.Senator Emer Currie - The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs to make a statement on the UK Government's Northern Ireland Troubles (Legacy and Reconciliation) Bill.Senator Lynn Boylan - The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to make a statement on current capacity issues at animal shelters.Senator Maria Byrne - The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the measures being taken to alleviate pressures on GPs.Senator Fintan Warfield - The need for the Minster for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to ensure the preservation and future use of the Iveagh Markets, Dublin 8.Senator Tim Lombard - The need for the Minister for Education to make a statement on capacity issues in secondary school places in Clonakilty, County Cork.Senator Seán Kyne - The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on Saolta plans to redevelop facilities at University Hospital Galway and Merlin Park Hospital.Senator Aisling Dolan - The need for the Minister for Transport to make a statement on the closure of waiting rooms at train stations, including Ballinasloe, and train time punctuality on the Galway-Dublin line.Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators Erin McGreehan, Emer Currie, Lynn Boylan and Maria Byrne and they will be taken now. I regret that I had to rule out of order the matters raised by Senators Warfield and Dolan on the ground that the relevant Ministers have no official responsibility in the matters. The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
          <heading>Local Authorities<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:30:00+00:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" eId="spk_2" as="#Acting_Chairperson">
            <from>Senator Erin McGreehan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:30:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_2">The Minister of State is welcome. I wish him to ask the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government to engage with local authorities to request clear actions, targets and reporting regarding implementation of the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, UNCRPD.</p>
            <p eId="para_3">It is about time the Departments, local authorities and State agencies got real and serious about implementation of the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities. It should never be a box-ticking exercise or personality policy where one person in a local authority or Department has an interest in doing the right thing and brings up the standards within that local authority or Department.</p>
            <p eId="para_4"> I wrote to the Department recently asking that it write to the local authorities to ask each of them its action plans for the implementation of the UNCRPD. If the Department was serious, it would be investing and making it mandatory to do these things. However, when the Department responded to my questions on making it mandatory for disability staff training or on what it is doing in regard to upskilling or, indeed, on implementing any article of the UNCRPD, what I got back was jargon. To be honest, I was quite upset about it. What I got back was that section 47(1)(a) of the Disability Act 2015 requires public bodies in so far as is practicable to take all reasonable measures to promote and support employment by them of people of disabilities. "As far as practicable" is not an answer. As far as reasonable measures are concerned, there is no mandatory reporting. There are no concrete guidelines. There is nothing to ensure people with disabilities who work within the authorities are looked after and protected. I know first-hand there are people being bullied and abused every day and there is no way to report it and no line manager to go to. This is because, going back to the start, it is personality policy. If one has a good personality and is in control of these situations, one has a good policy. At present, there is no uniformity with regard to any of this.</p>
            <p eId="para_5"> The Department would not even write to me when I asked whether there was disability awareness training. It could not even ask a county manager whether he or she conducted or provided his or her staff with disability awareness training, disability equality training or any type of accessibility auditing training.</p>
            <p eId="para_6"> The Minister of State, Deputy Brophy, is here delivering a speech to me written by the said Department. To be honest, it is relentless. It is depressing if the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage, which is at the front line in delivering housing and public realm projects, is not willing to accept that we need to start making it mandatory that policies are disability proofed. When we are putting in public realm projects and "improving" our local towns and we do not put in the proper tactile footing or do not mark our streets, we are making it dangerous for people with disabilities. It is cost neutral. If we are not spending money properly, that is a disgrace. It means the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage is not planning for the future and not looking after potentially 15% of the population and is discriminating against them and making sure they are not allowed into our local centres.</p>
            <p eId="para_7"> The Minister of State should not get me started on the inaction in relation to making public partnership networks, PPNs, more attractive, suitable and welcoming for people with disabilities. I look forward to his response.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#ColmBrophy" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs" eId="spk_3">
            <from>Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Deputy Colm Brophy)<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:40:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_8">I thank the Senator for raising what I think is a very important issue. Obviously, I am replying on behalf of my colleagues, the Minister, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, and the Ministers of State, Deputies Peter Burke and Rabbitte, who all collectively launched a new joint national housing strategy for disabled people, as the Senator will be well aware, on 14 January 2022. In that strategy, they set out the vision for the co-operation and collaboration of Departments, State agencies, including local authorities, and others in delivering housing and related supports for disabled people over the next five years.</p>
            <p eId="para_9"> The areas that are to be addressed to deliver on the vision of the strategy are set out across a number of themes, namely: theme 1, accessible housing and communities; theme 2, inter-agency collaboration and the provision of supports; theme 3, affordability of housing; theme 4, communication and access to information; theme 5; knowledge, capacity and expertise; and theme 6, strategy alignment, which focuses on ensuring that all Government strategies and polices promote the rights of disabled people from a housing perspective, in line with the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.</p>
            <p eId="para_10"> Among the objectives of the strategy is to meet our commitments under the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities to facilitate disabled people to live independently and as part of the community by ensuring that disabled people have equal access to housing and clearer pathways to accessing support services, promoting their inclusion in the community from a housing perspective.</p>
            <p eId="para_11"> Housing and disability steering groups, which were established by all 31 local authorities under the previous strategy, are reaffirmed under the new strategy as the most effective forum for delivery of the outcomes of the strategy at the local level. The role of the housing and disability steering groups will be strengthened over the lifetime of the national strategy. Housing and disability steering groups are chaired by the directors of services in the local authority and membership includes representation from the Health Service Executive, disabled persons' organisations and approved housing bodies.</p>
            <p eId="para_12"> The strategy will operate within the framework of Housing for All - a New Housing Plan for Ireland which is committed to ensuring that affordable quality housing with an appropriate mix of housing design types provided within social housing, including universally-designed units, is available to everyone in Irish society, including those with disabilities. Preparation of the implementation plan for the national housing strategy for disabled people is at an advanced stage and will be completed by year end.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" eId="spk_4" as="#Acting_Chairperson">
            <from>Senator Erin McGreehan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:40:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_13">I reiterate what I have said to Ministers over the past number of years. Visions are not mandatory. There is no sign in this of mandatory funding to be earmarked for capacity building, for training to help communities and to help staff make sure they are not making mistakes. Staff are not making mistakes and making things inaccessible for people on purpose. They are doing it because they are not trained. They are doing it because they cannot see or they do not have that lived experience of someone in a wheelchair or someone who is visually impaired trying to get around our streets and our communities every day. We do not have accessible toilets. None of this stuff is mandatory. Visions are not mandatory. It is about time that we make these things mandatory within the local authorities.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#ColmBrophy" eId="spk_5" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs">
            <from>Deputy Colm Brophy<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:40:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_14">I hear Senator McGreehan clearly. The points she makes are important. The Senator is absolutely right to raise the issue of the availability of such basic things for people with a disability and they should continue to be highlighted. I will certainly take back the Senator's remarks to the Minister. It is important that local authorities, in particular, are the lead in recognising how services should be provided. I thank the Senator.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" eId="spk_6" as="#Acting_Chairperson">
            <from>Senator Erin McGreehan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:40:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_15">I thank the Minister of State.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#MariaByrne" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_7">
            <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Maria Byrne)<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:40:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_16">I concur with the Senator. I mention my local authority even in respect of getting footpaths fixed for people with disabilities in wheelchairs.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
          <heading>Northern Ireland<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:40:00+00:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#MariaByrne" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_8">
            <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Maria Byrne)<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:40:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_17">I welcome the Minister, Deputy Coveney, and call on Senator Currie to raise her Commencement matter.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#EmerCurrie" eId="spk_9">
            <from>Senator Emer Currie<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:40:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_18">I appreciate the Minister coming in today. I watched with interest last night the Second Reading of the Northern Ireland Troubles (Legacy and Reconciliation) Bill in the House of Lords. Lord Caine gave an overview of the British Government's amendments that will be brought forward on Committee Stage. As the Minister will be aware, the Joint Committee on the Implementation of the Good Friday Agreement, of which I am a member, last week visited Westminster and we had the opportunity to meet Lord Caine. The committee, which is chaired by our colleague, Deputy O'Dowd, met Lord Caine and the North Ireland Affairs Committee representatives from the Labour Party and the Conservatives to impress upon them our opposition to this Bill and the importance of legacy, which was definitely top of the agenda. I was interested to hear Baron Murphy of Torfaen, a former Secretary of State, last night say that, of all the speakers who spoke last night, he counted that 19 were against it, four were for it and four were in between.</p>
            <p eId="para_19"> The House of Lords does not have the capacity to reject a Bill.</p>
            <p eId="para_20">It is more about oversight and scrutiny. However, it can send out a very strong message about whether a Bill is workable or if it fulfils the rule of law, or about the impact it has on Northern Ireland. There were some very powerful contributions last night. It is no secret that I fear the impact this Bill will have on Northern Ireland. I think it is just as important as, if not more important than, the protocol Bill. I think common sense will prevail on the protocol but I worry that common decency will not prevail on this Bill. It continues to hurt people profoundly - victims and survivors. It re-traumatises them. They feel robbed of their opportunity for justice, having dedicated their lives to getting justice for their loved ones. There is such strength of feeling that this allows the baddies to win; it legislates for people to get away with murder. When we say the rule of law does not matter, we also say that the truth does not matter, and we then allow statements to come out like, “There was no alternative to what happened”, and we end up in this moral lawlessness.</p>
            <p eId="para_21"> The trauma has highlighted to us the impact this could have in terms of the taunting of victims and survivors. That still happens, and we saw it ourselves this weekend, when a survivor of the Troubles - a victim of the Troubles in regard to her father - was taunted with chants at an event. We can see the repercussions now of that moral lawlessness, so where would the introduction of this legislation bring us?</p>
            <p eId="para_22"> The amendments that were highlighted last night include strengthening the review process so it would be compliant with the European Convention of Human Rights, ECHR, and there would be criminal investigations, if appropriate. There was reference to independence. There would have to be consultation with individuals before the Secretary of State would appoint the chief commissioner, although I do not know what that means, and there would be consequences for a lack of co-operation. However, there is not a lot of faith in those amendments.</p>
            <p eId="para_23"> I want to hear a statement from the Minister today and to give him the opportunity to restate our opposition to the legislation. Nothing is off the table when it comes to how we proceed or react to this legislation going forward.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#SimonCoveney" as="#Minister_for_Foreign_Affairs" eId="spk_10">
            <from>Minister for Foreign Affairs (Deputy Simon Coveney)<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:50:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_24">I thank Senator Currie for bringing this important matter to the attention of the Seanad but also for her ongoing work in regard to campaigning for change in this area and on the approach the British Government has decided to take in recent months.</p>
            <p eId="para_25"> The Government has been clear from the outset that the UK legacy Bill, as it stands, is not fit for purpose and it represents a unilateral move away from the Stormont House agreement. We also have serious doubts about whether the Bill is compliant with the European Convention on Human Rights. Overall, we are deeply concerned about the impact this Bill, if enacted, may have on the fragile process of reconciliation in Northern Ireland.</p>
            <p eId="para_26"> There is near-universal opposition to this Bill in Northern Ireland, including from the five main political parties and those representing victims and their families. This opposition was echoed by the UK Parliament's own joint committee on human rights, which has urged the UK Government to reconsider its whole approach. The Bill had its second reading in the House of Lords yesterday and opposition to it has become more vocal. This week, the Roman Catholic Archbishop of Armagh and Primate of all-Ireland and the Church of Ireland Archbishop of Armagh and Primate of all-Ireland stated jointly that this Bill will deepen division and further demoralise all but a tiny minority of those it purports to help. It seems almost as though it has been designed to fail.</p>
            <p eId="para_27"> I raise our concerns about the Bill regularly in my contacts with the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland. I have also had discussions with the Northern Ireland political parties, with victims and their families, and with senior US politicians in recent weeks. Thanks to the Senator, I met with the Truth and Justice Movement in Leinster House. Following that meeting, I urged the Secretary of State to engage directly with victims to get their perspective on this legislation. The Secretary of State has indicated that he is open to considering amendments to the Bill. However, I have been very clear that any amendments would need to be radical and fundamentally change the substance of this Bill for it to meet our core concerns around immunity, compliance with human rights obligations and victims' participation. The Government cannot support a process which is not compliant with our obligations under the ECHR.</p>
            <p eId="para_28"> I am aware of increasing calls for Ireland to consider the initiation of an inter-state case at the European Court of Human Rights in regard to the Bill. The Government's current assessment is that such a step would be premature for now. The Government's approach to legacy and reconciliation has been always that it should be victim-centred, taking the Stormont House agreement as its starting point. We will continue to use all avenues, bilaterally and multilaterally, to effect change to this legislation. I welcome the Senator's continued engagement on the issue.</p>
            <p eId="para_29"> On a matter as sensitive as how we deal with the legacy of the past, of all things in Northern Ireland, it is the area where we should try to seek accommodation of each other's views and try to put in place a collective approach that communities, political parties and both Governments can buy into, support and advocate for, and ensure is a success. The idea that anyone would take the direct opposite approach on something as sensitive as legacy, with all of the trauma, hurt and really difficult memories that families are trying to cope with, and act unilaterally against the advice of virtually everybody in Northern Ireland, seems to me to be extraordinary. That is why we continue to urge the Secretary of State to reconsider this approach.</p>
            <p eId="para_30"> I have to say I have had good conversations with the Secretary of State on this. We have not agreed to a new approach but, certainly, I think he is listening, and it is important to say that. However, we have a long way to go, I am afraid, and we do not have much time to get there, given the movement of this legislation through Westminster, potentially, in the coming months. What we hear has got to be based on what is good for Northern Ireland, its communities and the families that have been traumatised by violence and brutality at times in the past. That has to be the only and primary consideration. If we do that, the two Governments, working with parties and, in particular, with victims groups and their families, can find a way forward that we can all support, but the current approach of the British Government and the legislation it has advocated for is not the way to do this.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#EmerCurrie" eId="spk_11">
            <from>Senator Emer Currie<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:50:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_31">If the intent of a Bill is rotten at the core, then the Bill, even with amendments, remains rotten at the core, and I personally do not believe there are any amendments that would fix this. I think the only way to proceed is to bring people with you, and for the Irish Government, the British government, all the parties and the victims to work together and to learn that lesson that you have to bring people with you. All of the parties are against it, as well as NGOs such as Amnesty International, our Government, the human rights commissioner and victims. It is important that we are clear that nothing is off the table if it comes down to this legislation proceeding, and it is important for us to say we are looking at all options if the legislation does proceed.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#SimonCoveney" eId="spk_12" as="#Minister_for_Foreign_Affairs">
            <from>Deputy Simon Coveney<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T10:50:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_32">It is a requirement for any process dealing with the past to be credible and to be effective. Victims must be at the centre. The current UK proposal lacks that credibility and runs the risk of being more perpetrator-focused than victim-focused. The Government is using all avenues to try to effect change to the UK Bill. My Department raised the legacy Bill at the United Nations Human Rights Council earlier this month, which I think is an indication of how concerned we are in terms of the direction of travel. We have also drawn particular focus on this issue at the Council of Europe. The decision by Committee of Ministers' Deputies in September, reflecting the views of member states, noted concerns about the lack of formal consultation and compatibility with the European Convention on Human Rights.</p>
            <p eId="para_33">The committee urged the UK to reconsider the unconditional immunity scheme, which is the essential problem with this approach. My focus on the human rights aspects arises from the fundamental importance of human rights to the settlement reached in Northern Ireland and in the Good Friday Agreement.</p>
            <p eId="para_34"> Among other things, what is proposed in the UK Bill could amount to immunity for gross violations of human rights and a low bar to achieving immunity. I remain open to engaging and considering options, but I will remain guided by fundamental human rights principles and the needs of victims and their families. The UK Bill does not meet either of those tests at the moment. We will work hard to continue to try to engage with the Northern Ireland Office and the Secretary of State and between the Taoiseach’s office and the Prime Minister’s office, where there have been conversations on this issue. I hope the British Government will see sense and engage with us. We will be constructive in trying to find solutions, compromises and middle ground positions, where appropriate, should the opportunity arise, and I hope it will.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_13">
            <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Erin McGreehan)<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T11:00:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_35">I support the Minister in what he has been doing. The legacy of hurt and pain will never be healed and those wounds will never clear up if we allow the British Government to pass this Bill. I support the Minister in all of his work in bringing it further to the UN and to the Council of Ministers. I thank the Minister for his work on this and we support him.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_5">
          <heading>Animal Welfare<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T11:00:00+00:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#LynnBoylan" eId="spk_14">
            <from>Senator Lynn Boylan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T11:00:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_36">I have raised this issue a number of times in the past couple of weeks. Unfortunately, we are all familiar with the post-Christmas puppy regret and with the large numbers of surrenders that are seen in January. However, it appears that Christmas has come early this year, with four shelters in the past 24 hours announcing they are at capacity and 17 in the past three weeks having announced they are full.</p>
            <p eId="para_37"> Unfortunately, it is a combination of the now unwanted post-Covid-19 lockdown dogs and the housing crisis forcing tenants to choose between their beloved pet and putting a roof over their heads. It is leading to a large number of dogs being surrendered. While I am not excusing anybody who got a dog during lockdown and who did not do the proper assessment as to whether they would be able to look after an animal for the 15 years it can take, that is not to say that a number of the dogs that are being surrendered are being so because they have behavioural issues caused by the fact they were bred in industrial puppy farms, where they were inbred and deprived of human interaction for those important first few weeks of their lives.</p>
            <p eId="para_38"> It is the Government's failure to regulate those puppy farms and to ensure the dogs are properly socialised that has led to this glut in dogs being available for people to buy during lockdown and that is now leading to the glut of those being surrendered. I asked for the Minister of State to come before the House today because I did not get an adequate response from the Department of Rural and Community Development, which has responsibility for the dog breeding establishments and the Control of Dogs Act, while animal welfare falls under the brief of the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine. What is the short-term plan by the Department to support these shelters with their capacity issues? Will funding be put in place so that they can foster the dogs out or provide new accommodation for them? They are under extreme capacity pressure.</p>
            <p eId="para_39"> What is the plan in the long term for dealing with the dog breeding establishments, which are churning out dogs, as if on a conveyer belt, making them readily accessible to people to get, and then, when the behavioural issues manifest or when people who are irresponsible no longer want these dogs, they are turning up at the shelters? Again, it is the public who are picking up the paycheck for those surrendered dogs.</p>
            <p eId="para_40"> What is the short-term plan to help those shelters to deal with the capacity issues and the long-term plan actually to stem the flow of dogs in this country through the puppy farms?</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#MartinHeydon" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine" eId="spk_15">
            <from>Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine (Deputy Martin Heydon)<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T11:00:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_41">On behalf of the Minister, Deputy McConalogue, I thank Senator Boylan for raising what is a very important issue. I am delighted to have the opportunity to outline the work across government in this area, the commitments we have made in the programme for Government and how we are acting on them and what the different Departments are doing. The Senator has directed this question towards me and my Department today from an agricultural perspective, and I take that on board. As the Senator rightly outlined, there are a number of different areas of responsibility and I am happy to outline them.</p>
            <p eId="para_42"> I acknowledge the fantastic effort and commitment made by animal welfare organisations and the many volunteers dedicated to the care and welfare of canines, who often operate in challenging and stressful circumstances. Animal welfare charities play a crucial role in helping animals in need, educating people and raising public awareness around improving animal welfare. Those who work in the sector treat it as more than a career. They are passionate about this area and the Government recognises the huge work these key workers do. It is truly front-line care.</p>
            <p eId="para_43"> In relation to capacity issues, as the Senator has outlined, the Department of Rural and Community Development has policy responsibility for dog control and dog breeding establishments, while the local authorities are responsible for the operational activities. These include dog licensing, the dog warden service and the management and operation of local authority pounds or shelters. The Department of Rural and Community Development's 2021 dog control statistics, which are compiled from returns from all local authorities, indicate there are 34 local authority dog shelters or pounds. The Control of Dogs Act empowers the local authorities to enter into arrangements with any other local authority, with the Irish Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, ISPCA, or with a person connected with animal welfare. The procurement of any service, therefore, in relation to local authority pounds is a matter for each local authority and the management, and operation of such pounds or shelters are matters solely for the relevant local authority.</p>
            <p eId="para_44"> Animal welfare is increasingly important to people in Ireland, and I consider it a priority for my Department. The Department's animal welfare grants programme is a clear acknowledgement of the vital work of animal welfare charities in delivering on the care and welfare of animals, including the neutering and rehoming of dogs. On Animal Welfare Awareness Day last December, the Minister, Deputy McConalogue, announced record animal welfare grant funding of €3.7 million to 98 animal welfare organisations. Of this funding, €2.7 million was awarded to 68 organisations that deal with the welfare and rehoming of dogs.</p>
            <p eId="para_45"> The Department of Rural and Community Development statistics indicate that almost 2,000 dogs were transferred from the local authorities to dog welfare groups for rehoming in 2021. These figures are down from 2,500 in 2020. All of the figures in this area are showing a dramatic change and improvement. These statistics also demonstrate the success of the various neutering and microchipping programmes operated by these animal welfare charities. I acknowledge that, their ongoing work in this area and how we are working to support them in that.</p>
            <p eId="para_46"> The Minister, Deputy McConalogue, intends to deliver on the programme for Government commitment to further increase the funding allocated via the grants programme in 2022. He will announce details of these awards later this month. As with last year's awards, this year's funding will recognise the importance of education and dissemination of knowledge to improve animal welfare and, indeed, educating the public on the responsibilities involved with dog ownership.</p>
            <p eId="para_47"> Imparting knowledge on animal welfare and responsible pet ownership plays a crucial role in improving standards nationally and can help to reduce the number of dogs which are abandoned, surrendered or rehomed. That is ultimately the point. We will work, as will the Department of Rural and Community Development and the local authorities, to address any short-term pressures. The absolute approach, however, has to be reducing, and I am sure the Senator agrees with me on this. We have made huge progress in this area on better breeding techniques and education. We must drive home the message now at this time of year that a dog is for life and not just for Christmas. Everybody who is contemplating getting a family pet this Christmas should bear that in mind.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#LynnBoylan" eId="spk_16">
            <from>Senator Lynn Boylan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T11:00:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_48">I thank the Minister of State for outlining the valuable work the shelters do, because we know the pounds rely on them to move the dogs on that are not reclaimed in the pounds so that they are not euthanised. It is welcome that the figures for euthanasia have gone down year on year. That said, we have a particular issue this year because of the rush to buy dogs during Covid-19 and, post-Covid-19, those dogs now being surrendered. There is a need for a short-term emergency measure to engage with those shelters that do not have capacity.</p>
            <p eId="para_49">They are openly saying they cannot take more dogs. That is a concern because, while we are not excusing people surrendering their dogs, if they cannot do so they will find other ways to get rid of them. There is nothing to address that very short-term issue we have this year, particularly post Covid. I hope the Minister of State will take back to the Department that we are in a unique situation this year and it requires an emergency plan.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#MartinHeydon" eId="spk_17" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine">
            <from>Deputy Martin Heydon<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T11:10:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_50">I will bring the points raised by the Senator directly back to the Minister, Deputy McConalogue. The Commencement matter tabled by the Senator referred to capacity in the shelters and contingency plans. The broad approach the Government takes feeds into that. The programme for Government includes a commitment to promote responsible pet ownership. The Senator's point in respect of welfare is currently being advanced by the Department on various aspects relating to ownership. The Animal Welfare Strategy 2021-25: Working Together for Animal Welfare reflects the programme for Government commitment on responsible pet ownership and includes a commitment to establish an advisory council on companion animal welfare. I know the Senator is making a point in respect of an immediate issue, and I will bring that back, but it is important to recognise the broader points in the context of welfare because significant progress has been made in recent years. That can be seen from all the key statistics and we should acknowledge that. We will work with animal welfare groups and State agencies to address any issues there may be in the short term but we are heading in the right direction in the longer term and we will double down on that work in future.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_6">
          <heading>General Practitioner Services<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T11:10:00+00:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#MariaByrne" eId="spk_18" as="#Acting_Chairperson">
            <from>Senator Maria Byrne<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T11:10:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_51">I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House to discuss this important issue. What will the Department do to alleviate the pressure general practitioners, GPs, are under, but also to improve the delivery they are able to provide? In Limerick, which is my area, many people cannot get a GP appointment. They are waiting three or four days for an appointment. I recently met a person who had to wait two weeks for an appointment. In addition, many people cannot get on GP lists. GPs are under enormous pressure. The population is growing, especially in Limerick, and there are not enough doctors to facilitate people who want to get on a GP list.</p>
            <p eId="para_52"> On the other hand, University Hospital Limerick is in the newspapers every day in the context of overcrowding. Part of the reason for that overcrowding is that people are presenting at the hospital because they cannot get an appointment with their GP. I ask the Minister of State, on behalf of the Government, to lay out the resources that will be given to doctors to help to alleviate waiting lists.</p>
            <p eId="para_53"> People deserve to get good medical care. It is not the fault of doctors that their waiting lists are so long; it is just that there are not enough doctors. People become ill at different stages and they deserve to receive good care. I look forward to hearing the response of the Minister of State.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#FrankFeighan" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Health" eId="spk_19">
            <from>Minister of State at the Department of Health (Deputy Frankie Feighan)<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T11:10:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_54">I thank the Senator for raising this important issue. The Government recognises that there are significant challenges facing general practice and that those challenges can limit access to GP services in certain areas and negatively affect the timely provision of care. We all know that is the case. Some issues are specific to certain areas. There is no doubt there has been a general increase in demand for GP services, due in part to demographics and our ageing population.</p>
            <p eId="para_55"> In recent years, general practice has had to do a lot more. GPs were called on to provide additional services such as Covid referrals and vaccinations. At times, that impinged on routine care delivery. In addition, the services provided by GPs in the community have been expanded, and rightly so, to reduce patients' need for hospital attendance. The chronic disease management programme is now almost fully rolled out and has transformed the management of severe conditions. It is improving the lives of patients.</p>
            <p eId="para_56"> The Government has taken a number of measures to improve the recruitment and retention of GPs in order to increase the number of GPs practising in the State. It has provided substantial resources to help to strengthen general practice. Since 2019, baseline funding for general practice has been increased by more than €200 million, or approximately 40%, per annum under the 2019 GP agreement. Furthermore, budget 2023 provides additional funding for GPs to recruit extra capacity, with a focus on nursing, administration and IT. The resulting increased capacity will support the planned expansion of GP care without charge for those who earn the median household income of €46,000, or less, from April next year.</p>
            <p eId="para_57"> The GP agreement provides for significant increases in capitation fees rates for participating GPs, as well as new fees and subsidies for additional services. It also provides for improvements to maternity and paternity leave arrangements and increases to rural practice supports, as well as introducing a support for practices in areas of urban deprivation. These measures increase the attractiveness of general practice as a career choice for doctors. The roll-out of the enhanced community care programme and direct access to diagnostics is of major assistance in the delivery of GP care. More than 200,000 diagnostic scans have been already provided this year and the funding for 2023 has been increased to €45 million, from €35 million this year. Some 30 community specialist teams for older persons and 30 teams for chronic disease management are to be in place by year end. Most of them are now in place and are reducing the need for patients to attend their GP practice.</p>
            <p eId="para_58"> A sign that the measures undertaken are having the desired impact is that the number of doctors undertaking GP training has more than doubled in recent years, from 120 in 2009 to 258 in 2022. Working with the Irish College of General Practitioners, which now has responsibility for GP training, 350 training places are planned to be available in 2026.</p>
            <p eId="para_59"> Finally, the Department of Health and the HSE are preparing for a strategic review of general practice to commence shortly. The review, with stakeholder input, will examine the issues facing general practice and set out the measures needed for a sustainable GP service across the country in the long term.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#MariaByrne" eId="spk_20" as="#Acting_Chairperson">
            <from>Senator Maria Byrne<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T11:10:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_60">I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive response. He indicated that the number of GP training places will increase by 2026. We have a problem in the short term, however. He referred to enhancements that are happening in rural areas. During Covid, there were a number of mobile units. Doctors held clinics in villages one or two days a week. Many of those clinics have not reopened. That is something the Minister of State might be able to consider. The local doctor in Cappamore used to attend at the dispensary in the village of Moroe, County Limerick, once a week. Many people in the area do not have a car and were finding it difficult to get to a GP. That is one of the many issues.</p>
            <p eId="para_61"> In addition, I would like the Minister of State to consider how we can incentives some of the doctors who are working abroad to come back here to work. That would help to ensure people do not have to wait days or weeks for a GP appointment.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#FrankFeighan" eId="spk_21" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Health">
            <from>Deputy Frankie Feighan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T11:10:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_62">I thank the Senator. I hear what she is saying in respect of practices closing down after Covid. Many things have changed. However, general practice is providing more to the community and, although demand for services has increased, steps have been taken to increase GP capacity and support general practice and those steps are having a positive impact. The increased investment in general practice, with improved fees and supports, is attracting more doctors into general practice. As I stated, the number of doctors training to work as GPs has increased in recent years. The establishment of community-based specialist teams will ease the demand for GP services from older persons and those with chronic diseases. The swift provision of scans through the direct access to diagnostics programme eases the burden on GPs to manage patients awaiting testing. The Senator and I would agree that more work needs to be done to improve GP services further and to cater for increasing demand as the population continues to increase and age and more people are provided with GP care without charges.</p>
            <p eId="para_63"> The planned strategic review will examine a comprehensive range of issues. It will identify changes and the need for a better GP service into the future.</p>
          </speech>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <i> Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionraí ar 11.20 a.m. agus cuireadh tús leis arís ar 12.02 p.m.</i>
          </summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <i> Sitting suspended at 11.20 a.m. and resumed at 12.02 p.m.</i>
          </summary>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_7">
        <heading>Teachtaireacht ó Chomhchoiste - Message from Joint Committee<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:00:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_22">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">The Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine has completed its consideration of the Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund Regulations 2022.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="orderofBusiness" eId="dbsect_8">
        <heading>An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:00:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#LisaChambers" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Senator Lisa Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding extension of period of operation of sections 1 to 7 and 9 of the Civil Law (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2021 to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MalcolmByrne" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Senator Malcolm Byrne<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">I am conscious that today we are marking nine months since the Russian invasion of Ukraine. We will shortly be joined by the Ukrainian ambassador, H.E. Larysa Garasko, and that a motion around the Ukrainian man-made famine and genocide will be moved in this House. I strongly support this motion. Ireland's strong support for Ukraine continues to be evident. This is a very difficult period for that country but we must continue to hold to account the dictatorships in place in both Russia and Belarus.</p>
          <p eId="para_67"> Yesterday, I was glad that the European Parliament decreed by an overwhelming majority that Russia was a terrorist state. I am glad the majority of Irish MEPs voted in favour of the motion. Even MEP Luke 'Ming' Flanagan, who would normally be questionable in terms of his stance, supported it. Unsurprisingly, there were two MEPs who again supported the Putin regime. Sinn Féin failed to turn up, but given Sinn Féin's continuous record in the European Parliament in support of Russia, that it not a surprise.</p>
          <p eId="para_68"> Yesterday, a cyberattack took place on the operations of the European Parliament. This emanated from Russia. We had a very useful debate around Ireland's security strategy last night. The continuing threat of state-sponsored cyberattacks is something I have spoken about previously and I think that we are not taking it sufficiently seriously. We need to continue to up our game and our cyber defences. The fact the European Parliament's web system was attacked last night shows how vulnerable democratic institutions are in these circumstances.</p>
          <p eId="para_69"> I would also like to raise the ongoing challenges we are facing as a result of climate change. Yet again, we are seeing in Wexford and in other parts of the country, some appalling weather conditions. This morning we saw flooding and weather events that only happened every few years or even once in a generation. Now they are happening with increased regularity. We agreed in this House that we would look at having a debate or statement on different aspects of climate change almost every week. I would ask that the Deputy Leader would ensure in the schedule for the new year that we do not just debate the issues but look at the potential solutions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanKyne" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Senator Seán Kyne<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">I have raised on numerous occasions issues regarding Inland Fisheries Ireland and fisheries matters and angling over a number of months. As a former Minister of State with responsibility for natural resources, I have some insight in relation to the issues at stake there. The Minister for the Environment, Climate Action and Communications, Deputy Eamon Ryan, initiated a review into the functioning of the board of Inland Fisheries Ireland and a report was published on 12 July by Conleth Bradley SC. This was received by the Department of Environment, Climate Action and Communications on 22 July. It was sent to the Chair of Inland Fisheries Ireland on 26 September and published by the Minister, Deputy Ryan, on 7 November. There was quite an elongated process to publish what is quite a simple report and review.</p>
          <p eId="para_71"> I have read the report and the most pertinent point was point No. 103 on page 37. Members will have to listen carefully to follow this because it uses legalese. Whether it is purposefully confusing or not, I do not know. It reads:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_72">There is not a basis, from the alleged disclosures and the information and documentation which have been reviewed, for the Minister to be satisfied that the functions of IFI are not being performed in an effective manner such as to give effect to the removal of all members of IFI from office.</p>
          <p eId="para_73">Talk about a long way of saying that there were no issues with the board and that the Minister should be happy. In plain English, that is the summary of the report. It makes a number of other recommendations. Over the coming weeks, I intend to read into the record, issues of corruption within Inland Fisheries Ireland, within senior management and cover ups by the Department of the Environment, Climate Action and Communications. The whole Inland Fisheries Ireland organisation is rotten and corrupt. Do not worry, a Chathaoirligh, I am not going to name any individual, but it is rotten and corrupt. </p>
          <p eId="para_74"> The Minister, instead of carrying out an investigation into the organisation, decided to carry an investigation into the board and once the report was received took months to send it to the chair of IFI. There are reasons behind all of this but I will not say any more.</p>
          <p eId="para_75"> However, I intend over the coming weeks to read into the record issues pertaining to Inland Fisheries Ireland. It can be on notice, the Minister can be on notice and the Secretary General of the Department, who has taken a hands off approach to the matter of Inland Fisheries Ireland, can be on notice as well.</p>
          <p eId="para_76">It is not my issue. It is a matter that Inland Fisheries Ireland can take note of as well. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GerardPCraughwell" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Senator Gerard P. Craughwell<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">I rise today to propose a motion that Seanad Éireann recognises the Holodomor - inflicting death by starvation - of 1932 to 1933 as a genocide on the Ukrainian people and that its 90th anniversary, which will fall on 26 November 2022, we show our solidarity with Ukraine in commemorating this man-made famine, which was inflicted on the Ukrainian people by the deliberate policies of a totalitarian Stalinist regime, which resulted in millions of innocent lives being lost. I want to recognise the ambassador of Ukraine, who is currently in the Distinguished Visitors’ Gallery.</p>
          <p eId="para_78"> There is a background statement to this, which will be made available to people later. One of the paragraphs is horrific and states:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_79">At the height of Holodomor, Ukrainians died at a rate of 25,000 per day, nearly a quarter of rural Ukrainians perished, more than 3 million children born in 1932 and 1933 died of starvation. [Remember that this was inflicted on the people.] In the same two years, the Soviet Union sold 1.7 million tons of grain on western markets.</p>
          <p eId="para_80">These deaths were planned. It was the murder of so many people. We should hold today that we stand in solidarity with the people of Ukraine in remembering this issue. </p>
          <p eId="para_81"> Over the past day or two, I have spoken about the Irish Coast Guard. Yesterday, I spoke about the issue of lifejackets and the day before I spoke about the failure to have an inquest into Caitríona Lucas’s death. The Coast Guard has been without a director for a considerable time now. There are massive issues with respect to the way volunteers have been treated in that organisation. There are outstanding grievances that have never been heard. To my mind,and from my point of view, the organisation appears to be toxic. I ask the Deputy Leader to bring the Minister before this House for a debate on the Irish Coast Guard and where exactly it is going. Volunteers put themselves forward to this organisation. They give of their time freely and to have senior members of the Coast Guard arriving at their house to tell them that they are fired is simply not good enough. I am therefore asking for a debate on that. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_27">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">Before calling on the Minister of State, Senator Hackett, I wish to clarify that Senator Craughwell intends to propose an amendment to the Order of Business, that No. 122, motion No. 5, be taken before No. 1.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GerardPCraughwell" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Senator Gerard P. Craughwell<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PippaHackett" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Senator Pippa Hackett<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">Tomorrow, we will shop. In fact, such is the pull of black Friday for Irish consumers that AIB recently suggested that over the next few days, we will shop at the rate of €18,000 per minute. I am planning to speak here for three minutes, and I will let you do the calculations yourselves. What is this draw to shopping? One theory is that our new purchase lifts our mood because it gives us a brief sense of control over our environment. Yet, it is brief, is it not? This is not least because much of the time, many of us are now not only balancing whether we can afford it financially but also are balancing whether we can afford it environmentally. Tomorrow will be the last in my seasonal tour of small business owners across Laois and Offaly and it has been a real pleasure to meet people like Danielle at Naturally at the Wrens Nest, Declan McCraith, woodturner, and all the other makers, bakers, artists and artisans in between. Across the board, they have been champions of local. They have been thankful for their customers and they are passionate about what they do. Every euro that is spent locally can multiply to €2.50 in the local economy, whereas €1 spent online with an overseas retailer has next to no impact on your local economy. Tomorrow, if you do choose to shop, shop locally for Irish-made products and Irish-made food. It is even better if they are made in the locality. Shop for gift vouchers for local venues or workshops. Shop where money brings meaningful employment and pride to a local producer. Shop where you can afford to shop. Shop second hand for products that are pre-loved and are new to you. Items that are kept in use or that are repurposed for new use have a much lower carbon footprint. We are currently transitioning to a circular economy and away from our traditional take, make, use and dispose linear one. We must do so as we come to terms with living on a planet with finite resources. Shop happily and mindfully. Open your hearts to the experience. Chat with the retailers and producers. Hear their stories. Hear what your purchase means from them, because that is where the endorphins will really flow, namely, with that human connection. Shop slowly, feel the fabric and smell the handmade soaps. Use it our lose it is the motto of this year’s green Friday campaign. If we, the consumers, do not play our part, we will lose those local businesses and the employment they sustain.</p>
          <p eId="para_85"> Check your local chambers of commerce. In Laois and Offaly, they are offering gift cards that can be spent in locally-owned shops. On this black Friday, or cyber Monday, or whatever new buzzword title will be next, think about the power that you have in your wallet. The choice on how you spend your money will make all the difference and this year, be that champion of local. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">I wish to begin by welcoming the Ukrainian ambassador. I was extremely disappointed to hear Senator Malcolm Byrne use an issue like the horrific invasion of Ukraine to try to score a cheap party-political point. He could have taken one moment before speaking today to check with me or with any of my Sinn Féin colleagues and we would have informed him that our MEP, Chris MacManus, is unwell at the moment and that is why he missed the vote. This issue is surely beyond party politics. He should do better.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MalcolmByrne" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Senator Malcolm Byrne<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">For the record-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">The issue I want to raise this morning-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_33">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">The Senator should be allowed to speak without interruption.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p>
          <p eId="para_91"> The issue I want to raise this afternoon is the Raise the Roof protest, which will take place on Saturday. I urge as many people as possible to come out onto the streets at 1 p.m. on Saturday to call out this Government for its housing failure. It was truly shocking to see the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Darragh O’Brien, last week declare that in fact there was no housing emergency. I think that is a statement that will come back to haunt him for some considerable time to come. Perhaps the same Minister might be able to explain why last week in Limerick, a four to five-bedroom house was advertised on Wolfe Tone Street for a rent of €3,250 per month, with the suggestion that perhaps between five and ten people could inhabit the house. I do not know what Government Senators would describe that as, but I would describe it as greed. It is important to also point out the impact that the housing crisis is having on other key areas of our economy. There is a story about the Psychiatric Nurses Association of Ireland, PNA, today in <i>The Irish Times</i> which states that there are 700 staff vacancies. The head of the PNA union makes it very clear that the issue is that a number of their members are emigrating because they cannot afford to live here. He has called for housing supports. I notice that Phil Ní Sheaghdha of the Irish Nurses and Midwives Organisation, INMO, wrote to the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage two weeks ago again calling for accommodation supports because again, people are voting with their feet and they are leaving. I have asked for figures relating to University Hospital Limerick on the number of vacancies it has at the moment. The hospital has not been able to confirm this to me yet but I note that one maternity ward in Limerick Hospital has already closed because they simply cannot staff it. The extent of the crisis is horrendous and the fact that the Government has an underspend of €500,000 for the first nine months of this year is frankly disgraceful. The fact it has finally admitted it will not meet its affordable or social housing targets this year is simply failure. We must do better and I believe this rally this weekend will be particularly important. I want to salute the trade unions, which have played such an important role in bringing this together.</p>
          <p eId="para_92"> In the few seconds that I have left, I will take a moment to congratulate Sally Hayden on her award at the Irish Books Awards, which were held last night, for her fantastic book, <i>My Fourth Time, We Drowned,</i> which details the horrors that human beings trying to access Europe have to face. It details in particular with the horrors of the Libyan Coast Guard. The Deputy Leader will know that I have raised the issue of the Libyan Coast Guard on a number of occasions. There is a failure on behalf of the Government to call out the Libyan Coast Guard, which is a bunch of gangsters who are involved in rape, torture, murder and imprisonment. The European Union continues to fund them. When I asked the Minister of State, Deputy Thomas Byrne, at the Council of Europe about it, he had nothing to say. When I asked the Minister of State at the Department of Justice, he had nothing to say. How this Government can be silent in the face of the horrors that human beings are experiencing trying to access Europe is frankly beyond me. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">I wish to second the amendment to the Order of Business proposed by my colleague, Senator Craughwell on behalf of everyone who signed the motion that was circulated last week. It is to commemorate the Holodomor, which means in Ukrainian “inflicting death by starvation” on the Ukrainian people, which happened during 1932 and 1933.</p>
          <p eId="para_94">This was an horrific genocide cast upon the Ukrainian people during those years by the totalitarian Stalinist regime. I was not aware of the genocide until it was brought to my attention by the chairperson of the friendship group here in the Oireachtas, my colleague Deputy Brendan Smith. When I started researching the matter I could not believe that it is not listed as one of the most horrendous genocides remembered throughout the world. Unfortunately, there have been too many genocides down through the generations.</p>
          <p eId="para_95"> In spite of the horrific circumstances the Ukrainian people are enduring because of the Russian dictatorial Stalinist regime that is in existence at the moment, the Ukrainian people will commemorate next Saturday the 90th anniversary of the genocide perpetrated on their people. I ask the Deputy Leader to accept this motion without debate so that Seanad Éireann can join the many Parliaments throughout the European Union and the world that have commemorated this horrific disaster. They have already passed a motion in support of the commemoration and I ask that this House does the same.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Senator Tim Lombard<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">I wish to discuss the human tissue Bill. This is legislation that has been talked about for decades. The original report that brought the legislation forward was commissioned by the then Minister for Health, Mary Harney. The legislation has been sought since 2005 or 2006 and there have been false dawns all the way regarding the legislation. I mention in particular the Kelleher family from Cork who have campaigned online for the legislation to be put in place because they experienced a terrible and horrendous situation in which their child's organs were, unfortunately, sent to another country to be disposed of in a very inhumane way. This legislation will guarantee that such carry-on cannot continue. I ask the Deputy Leader to get a timeline from the Minister for Health on when the legislation will be brought forward. It is supposed to be published by the end of the year and we need to have that done.</p>
          <p eId="para_97"> The other issue I wish to raise is about the driving test centre in Skibbereen, in regard to which the Road Safety Authority has produced figures that prove the waiting list is exceptionally low and this talk of closing the centre is not going to happen. It comes back to this false narrative or false media output by some politicians who will do anything to make a headline or talk down west Cork. This has been a very unfortunate situation. We have seen with Bantry General Hospital over the years and now with the driving test centre where they are playing politics. There has to be a news outlet that makes sure proper information is put out there rather than going on social media with absolute lies, according to what we have heard today. That is something that very much affects how west Cork is going to drive and go forward. We need the Minister for Transport brought before us to clarify the figures and make sure they are appropriate, which they are, because if we continue the way we are going, the false narratives will erode confidence and erode how west Cork and other regions will develop.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Senator Erin McGreehan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">I welcome the Ukrainian ambassador and support the motion that calls on us to remember the Ukrainian atrocity of Holodomor. It is very important we do these things because we are quite possibly walking into a similar atrocity in Ukraine where people have no water, heat or light and they will literally freeze over the winter. It is very important we remember the past and stay strong in the present.</p>
          <p eId="para_99"> Will the Deputy Leader organise a debate on the UK legacy Bill? It is important this House is strong and very determined in ensuring the British do not continue with this unilateral legislation. The Irish Government must take this issue as far as it can and as far as the European Court of Human Rights, if necessary. It would be very opportune for us in this House to have an opportunity to put on the record how we absolutely detest the fact that murderers could get away with murder. In this country we have an awful legacy of hate and hurt, and the wounds are still wide open. If this Bill is passed, we are rubbing salt into those wounds. None of us could look the victims in the eye ever again if we did not do absolutely everything we can to stop the British Government from passing this absolutely disgusting and rotten Bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MariaByrne" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Senator Maria Byrne<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">I welcome the announcement by Shannon Airport this morning that two extra routes, one to Porto and one to Naples, will be added to its complement of flights from Shannon Airport, starting in the summer of 2023. That means people can travel to more than 26 destinations from Shannon Airport. I compliment Ms Mary Considine, CEO, and her team on their hard work that has resulted in expanding the offering from Shannon Airport. The airport can be easily accessed and can be got in and out of quite quickly. Again, I compliment all of the team.</p>
          <p eId="para_101"> The other issue I want to raise is University Hospital Limerick, UHL, and the fact that today it is encouraging people not to go to the hospital unless they are seriously ill. This is an ongoing crisis I keep raising and it is really frightening. Last night, I raised with some of my own colleagues the staff shortages in different areas which is adding to people having to wait longer to be seen. This morning, I tabled a Commencement matter about people having to wait to see GPs. The Government needs do something to widen the services provided by GPs because some people must wait between a week and ten days for an appointment with a GP and then they present at hospitals. The two must happen in tandem. It is frightening to see that the hospital is encouraging people not to come to the hospital unless they are seriously ill. There are smaller injury units in Nenagh, St. John's and Ennis hospitals. I know people are being encouraged to attend these but it is frightening that UHL has had to give the warning today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AidanDavitt" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Senator Aidan Davitt<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">I congratulate the Cathaoirleach on his very successful trip representing our country abroad. He must be praised for his work.</p>
          <p eId="para_103"> I often avail of the train service from Mullingar to Dublin. It is something that certainly should be upgraded. Mullingar, as we know, is quite a large town. There is a serious upgrade of the line to Maynooth with more services being laid on and a slight follow-on to Enfield in the next while. There is only a single rail line beyond Maynooth to Mullingar, which is a problem for anyone travelling west. Certainly, we should roll out the second line as far as a large hub like Mullingar, maintain it and provide a more regular service, because the reality is any train that leaves Mullingar to go to Dublin is full, particularly any one in the early hours with people going to work or coming to Dublin about their business.</p>
          <p eId="para_104"> We might bring in the Minister for Justice for a talk about gardaí dealing with victims of aggravated burglaries and serious assaults. It would be just about the general process from start to finish. I highly commend the Garda for having broken up several of these gangs that have been carrying out these aggravated burglaries. We see people in front of the courts at present and there have been many serious convictions in this regard recently. The Garda has been very successful in this regard. I am curious how the Garda deals with the victims after such an incident, regardless of whether somebody was convicted or the Garda got somebody who had been involved in it. There seems to be a variation in how victims are dealt with in these types of cases.</p>
          <p eId="para_105">Perhaps the Minister for Justice might come to the House to discuss that particular matter some day.</p>
          <p eId="para_106"> Finally, if the Minister of State, Senator Hackett, was available for half an hour to talk to my wife before the Christmas shop, I would really appreciate it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_40">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">I will see if that can be arranged.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">(Interruptions).</summary>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Senator Micheál Carrigy<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">I welcome the Ukrainian Ambassador to the House and pledge my support for the motion. I wish to voice my personal support, and the support of all the Members, for President Zelenskyy. There is continuing support for Ukraine from Ireland.</p>
          <p eId="para_109"> I echo the comments of Senator Davitt, but I must remind him that all the commuter trains coming into Dublin actually start in County Longford, so any investment must be stretched out a little.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Senator A<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">They start in County Sligo.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Senator Micheál Carrigy<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">We need balanced regional development. We must ensure that everyone gets the funding.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GerardPCraughwell" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Senator Gerard P. Craughwell<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">It is great to see the coalition working.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">(Interruptions).</summary>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_45">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">It is the Order of Business, not a debate. Continue, Senator Carrigy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Senator Micheál Carrigy<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">I also want to support the comments made by Senator Malcolm Byrne yesterday on the increase in cases being brought to the High Court in respect of assessments of needs. I support the call for a debate on the issue. Both the HSE and the Minister have attended the Joint Oireachtas Committee on Autism, and the reality is that people are waiting over two years on assessments of needs. Indeed, they are lucky if they get an assessment within two years. The legislation states that children or young people are entitled to an assessment, but there is no provision for an entitlement to a service and access to supports. It is something that needs to be looked at. There are too many children who are not getting interventions at an early age. That is limiting their possibilities in later life. We must get to the stage where early intervention means early intervention.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EugeneMurphy" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Senator Eugene Murphy<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">First, I welcome the Ukrainian Ambassador. Like many in the Chamber today, I express my solidarity once again for the people of Ukraine. As Senators McGreehan and Wilson referenced, they could be facing another holocaust. What is being done by the Russian leader and some of his people to the Ukrainians is shocking, brutal and outrageous. We must think of them now because they are experiencing shortages of heat, water and food. Obviously, this could have huge consequences for the population of Ukraine. We hope and pray that they will be okay.</p>
          <p eId="para_116"> I want to refer to the growing difficulty that people are having in getting home insurance. They are being told that because there is a threat of flooding in their area, even if there has never been a flood before and possibly never will be, they will not qualify for insurance. The issue is getting so serious that we need a proper debate on it. There is a growing number of people who are being affected by it. Insurance companies are saying that there is a possibility of flooding in 50 or 60 years' time in different regions. It is just not on. We need to get real. Where there are flood plains, we do not allow building. Where there are no flood plains, there is no danger, in my view, of flooding occurring. We must get on with it and ensure insurance companies do not do that to people. Perhaps the relevant Minister, whether it is the Minister of State, Deputy Fleming, or the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donovan, might come to the House to discuss the issue in the new year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarySeeryKearney" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Senator Mary Seery Kearney<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">I rise today to welcome the ambassador, to voice my absolute support for the motion of commemoration and to note that what is going on at present in Ukraine is an attempted genocide. That the sanctions placed on Russia are not even more dramatic, given the intended annihilation of an entire nation, is really shocking. We cannot understate how appalling it is and we cannot convey enough our solidarity with the Ukrainian people.</p>
          <p eId="para_118"> I wish to support a great announcement that was made earlier today by the Minister of Justice and the Minister of State, Deputy Browne, in Cherry Orchard, namely, the establishment of the Cherry Orchard implementation board. It comes after a year of listening and work that I have advocated for with the Department of Justice. We are ensuring that there is official recognition and support for the work of the organisations on the ground and the plans that were made in conjunction with the community there. Earlier today, the establishment of the board was announced, with the appointment of Brendan Foster as chair. The next stage is to recruit a co-ordinator, which will be done immediately, to ensure there will be supported services, similar to those rolled out very successfully in Drogheda, for a community that needs to be supported and needs infrastructure.</p>
          <p eId="para_119"> Cherry Orchard is a unique community with its own culture, and is full of really fantastic people. Unfortunately, the infrastructure is not there, and it was not there when it was built. The area has two prisons and one shop, which is consists of the converted ground floor of one house, for a population of more than 10,000 people. The people have come together and created a plan. They are supported by fantastic organisations operating there. The people need a town centre, a dentist, a doctor, and all of those basic services within their unique community to support what is already there. They also need an enterprise centre. Brilliant plans for that are already well advanced. The implementation board is going to be about accessing Government at the highest level, speaking to the right people, supporting funding applications and amplifying their voice. The people of Cherry Orchard really deserve to have their voice heard. I am very grateful to the Minister and the Minister of State. They came out and listened and came back not with just a plan that was pie in the sky, but with the action, the personnel, the funding and the establishment of the office to ensure Cherry Orchard is recognised and has a name for the great place that it is, and not for the thuggish element that seeks to drag it down.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryFitzpatrick" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Senator Mary Fitzpatrick<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">I, too, welcome H.E. Ms Larysa Gerasko, the Ambassador of Ukraine, who is the Ukrainian people's representative in our country. I join with others in condemning Russia's invasion and attempted annexation of an independent state. I reiterate our resolve to stand in solidarity with the Ukrainians and utterly condemn Russia's attack not just on Ukraine, but on our democracy and Western democracy.</p>
          <p eId="para_121"> I wish to raise again the issue of public transport in Dublin city and the greater Dublin area. Specifically, I draw the House's attention to the announcement earlier today that the statutory planning application deadline for the MetroLink has been extended. The deadline for submissions - an issue I have raised in the House - was 25 November, which has now been extended to 16 January. I welcome the extension and the additional six weeks for people to make submissions. I am critical of the fact that for my constituency and community, this is the second statutory planning application taking place at the one time, which is putting a financial burden of €100 on people in my community who wish to make a submission. I also must question how it could be that a planning application for a public transport infrastructure project that is estimated to require an investment of €9 billion at current costs - and God knows what it will cost when it goes ahead - could actually have an error and an omission that would require this amendment to a statutory planning process. I renew my request for a debate in this House on the National Transport Authority, NTA, and the public transport plans for Dublin city.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinConway" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Senator Martin Conway<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">I, too, welcome the Ukrainian Ambassador. I wish to voice my support for the motion and call out, as we do here regularly, the actions of Putin and Russia, and what is going on in Ukraine. It is genocide and it is horrific. We stand in solidarity with the ambassador and her people.</p>
          <p eId="para_123"> I also welcome the two new routes announced by Ryanair to and from Shannon Airport to Porto and Naples. The more routes we have from Shannon, the more people will fly in and out of the airport. That is something that is to be welcomed.</p>
          <p eId="para_124">I call for a debate on gift vouchers and the legislation governing them. Many people will purchase gift vouchers in the run-up to Christmas and give them as presents during the festive season. In a particular case of which I am aware, during the pandemic a One4all gift card was given to an elderly person as a token by FBD insurance company because it had a reduced number of claims. The gift card was worth €35 but when the person went to spend it a couple of weeks ago, the card had to be activated and registered, which required access to a computer. When the card was registered for the person, the value had gone down to less than €15, or less than 50% of its original value. I suspect that is happening with thousands of these gift cards. People get gift cards and put them into a drawer or press and forget about them. They only spend the gift card when it comes to their attention. Of course, all this is included in the small print but that is not good enough. People pay cash for these gift cards on the assumption that the person receiving it will have access to the face value on the card and be able to spend that amount. However, the small print says otherwise. The value drops. We need to legislate to prevent that happening. I will call out the company in this case because my office did the registration for the elderly person. It is One4all gift cards. I warn those watching or listening to these proceedings to be very careful if they buy a One4all gift card. They would be far better off buying a voucher for a local shop because that would really be supporting Irish business.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMcGahon" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Senator John McGahon<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">Last week in my home town of Dundalk the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, Deputy Harris, was present for the announcement of €11 million for the advanced manufacturing training centre. That brings the total amount of Government funding for the centre to €25 million. This is the only centre of its kind on the island of Ireland. It is the brainchild of Martin O'Brien, the chairperson of the Louth and Meath Education and Training Board. The centre is allowing Ireland to compete on an international level when it comes to advanced manufacturing. It is enabling us to compete in new areas of technology, jobs and innovative science and creation - things such as green technology and cybersecurity. What we have done in Dundalk and that part of the north east is to provide the blueprint that other parts of Ireland should follow. It is important that we have an advanced manufacturing training centre in each region - in the north east, north west, south east and south west. As a nation, we can get much stronger by providing that information and ensuring other parts of the island can do it. It would be useful to have a debate in the new year on the advanced manufacturing sector, what we can do to enhance it and to compete on a wide scale international level. The centre in Dundalk has allowed us to mitigate some of the effects of Brexit by making sure people are trained up in certain sectors. It is also allowing us to compete in a volatile international market. The stronger the economy is, the better. I would very much appreciate a debate on how we can use the successful blueprint that has been provided in Dundalk and replicate it across the island.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiallODonnghaile" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Senator Niall Ó Donnghaile<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">I join colleagues in welcoming the Ukrainian ambassador. To her, I express Sinn Féin's continued solidarity with the Ukrainian people and again condemn in the strongest possible terms the immoral war being waged against her people by Russia.</p>
          <p eId="para_127"> I welcome the announcement this week by the Minister of State with responsibility for international development aid and the diaspora, Deputy Brophy, that the global Irish civic forum will return to Dublin in April next year. When the Oireachtas Joint Committee on the Implementation of the Good Friday Agreement travelled to London last week, we visited the Irish Cultural Centre in Hammersmith and met with the fantastic staff and volunteers there who are doing great work in engaging with and supporting the long-standing and established diaspora community, as well as the many new arrivals from Ireland who are setting up home in London. The centre does fantastic work and that was particularly the case during the pandemic, when many older Irish citizens abroad experienced feelings of isolation. I have asked several times for statements on the work of the Minister of State in respect of the diaspora. In light of the debate in the House last night, it would be timely for the House to also receive an updated on the work internationally on development aid. The Minister of State made the point that the issue of a referendum on voting rights will be a key component of the civic forum next April. It is an issue I raise often and I welcome the confirmation by the Minister of State that it will form part of the forum. We do not have to wait until April for an update in that regard or to engage with the diaspora on this issue. It is broader than that. It also impacts Irish citizens in the North. I would welcome the Minister of State coming to the House early in the new year, allowing a substantial lead-in to the forum, to give us an opportunity to air these issues, reflect on them and encourage the Minister of State to take on board our views.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LynnBoylan" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Senator Lynn Boylan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">I, too, welcome the Ukrainian ambassador to the House and offer my solidarity to the Ukrainian people.</p>
          <p eId="para_129"> This Friday is International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women. Earlier this week, the annual report of the Director of Public Prosecutions highlighted an increase of more than one third in domestic violence case files, with high conviction rates in serious crime cases, including murder and rape. The growth in the number of files being referred to her office is unprecedented, with a 23% rise in the total number of files received in the three years up to this reporting period. Such violence against women is one of the most widespread and persistent human rights violations in the world and remains largely unreported due to the stigma and shame surrounding it. This is a crisis that needs more attention. The campaign this week, leading up to Friday, is important. It calls for action to increase awareness of violence against women, as well as aiming to prevent and eliminate such violence. Of course, extreme violence against women can lead to femicide. Since 1996, when Women's Aid began collecting data, 242 women have died in that context. While some of the cases are notorious, others are all but forgotten. We remember all those 242 women this week, from Marilyn Rynn, a civil servant at the Department of the Environment who went missing after she got a Nitelink bus home from her office Christmas party on 22 December 1995, to the women who were killed this year and whose families await justice. We must also be aware of changes across the world in recent years and how they affect women. There is little doubt that there has been a roll-back on women's rights across the globe of late. That has contributed to the demeaning of women, which can contribute to violence. As a society, we need to mobilise and become activists for the prevention of violence against women. We need to stand in solidarity with women's rights activists and support feminist movements across the world to resist the roll-back on women's rights.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">Well said.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AislingDolan" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Senator Aisling Dolan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">I welcome the Ukrainian ambassador, who is here representing her country which is fighting for democracy.</p>
          <p eId="para_132"> This weekend, the Minister for Transport, Deputy Eamon Ryan, will visit Athlone. He will probably travel there by train. He will see the fantastic newly painted bus station, which is very integrated, being located beside the train station in the town. Athlone will have soon have electric buses. There are many bus services from the town, such as a bus service to Dundalk for students. However, there is no service from Dublin to Galway, apart from private coach services, that stops in towns. I hope the Minister will recognise that this is a main artery and we need a bus service from Dublin to Galway. However, I wish to address the train service on the Dublin to Galway line. There is currently a 6.25 a.m. service from Galway to Dublin that stops at Athenry, Athlone and Tullamore. It does not stop in Ballinasloe, however. There are five services from Athlone to Dublin before 7.30 a.m. and they are much needed for a town of 25,000 people. The services mean people can get to work, college or appointments in Dublin by 9 a.m. Ballinasloe, however, only has one train service. It is not served by a bus route from Dublin to Galway and it has only one train service. I ask the Minister to consider adding Ballinasloe to the service that leaves Galway at 6.25 a.m. Yesterday, there was a call for the Minister, Deputy Ryan, to come to the House. I wish to add that issue to the matters he will address when he does so. I would like to find out about the punctuality of trains on that line in the past six months. There is also the fact that waiting rooms in train stations across the country are closed. That issue relates to staffing rosters. In Ballinasloe, for example, there are no staff after 1 p.m. on Mondays, Fridays and Saturdays. Last week, coming into winter, a person in his or her 70s had to wait at the station in the rain and cold even though there is a perfectly wonderful waiting room there. The waiting room was locked. People could not get into it.</p>
          <p eId="para_133">I would like to see what sort of smart solutions we can put in place for people to access waiting rooms at train stations. We have those services. They need to put in place, especially if one wants to use more public transport in rural areas.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LisaChambers" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Senator Lisa Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">I will be accepting the motion as put forward by Senator Craughwell and seconded by Senator Wilson.</p>
          <p eId="para_135"> I welcome also H.E. Ms Larysa Gerasko, the Ukrainian ambassador, to the Gallery. It is always great to see the ambassador. I thank the ambassador for her consistent attendance in these Houses and engagement with Members across both Houses. It is welcome.</p>
          <p eId="para_136"> Senator Malcolm Byrne kicked off this morning. The Senator spoke about the motion as put forward by Senator Craughwell, and Senator Wilson in full support. Senator Malcolm Byrne spoke also about the European Parliament declaring Russia a terrorist state. The Senator also spoke about climate and the significant weather events that we are now seeing on a much more regular basis and stated that he wants to have a debate in this House to talk about not only the issues around climate change but also the solutions that we might have.</p>
          <p eId="para_137"> Senator Kyne spoke this morning around Inland Fisheries Ireland. The Senator raised particular issues with the review that was conducted of the board as opposed to the organisation, the lengthy time it took for the report to be published and the seemingly convoluted way in which it was finally published. The Senator stated that he will continue to raise issues around that and is not satisfied that the report dealt with the matter correctly.</p>
          <p eId="para_138"> Senator Craughwell put forward a motion to this House on the famine in Ukraine in the early 1930s, the fact that it was a genocide and that thousands of people lost their lives - the Senator stated that at one stage it was 25,000 per day. It was a huge loss of life. I concur with the remarks of both Senator Craughwell and Senator Wilson in remembering that atrocity and acknowledging that it happened. As the 90th anniversary of that atrocity approaches, we all continue to stand with Ukraine, not only on that issue but also on the illegal invasion of Ukraine by Russia. Ukraine will always have a friend in Ireland. I thank both Senators for giving the House the opportunity to pass the said motion.</p>
          <p eId="para_139"> The Minister of State, Senator Hackett, spoke this morning about shopping and the black Friday sales that many citizens right across the country will participate in. The Senator had an important message. The Senator stated that for every €1 one spends locally it multiplies to €2.50. I thought that was €1 to €5. In any event, the message is that if one spends it locally, it boosts and benefits one's local economy and that if one purchases online, often the money goes straight out of the country and is of zero benefit to anything in one's locality or one's own place. The Senator is urging Members to shop local, to consider it being green Friday as opposed to black Friday, to reuse, to get pre-loved new-to-you and second-hand items and to maintain a circular economy as opposed to use and discard. It is an important message in advance of the sales that are currently ongoing, but tomorrow being the big day.</p>
          <p eId="para_140"> Senator Gavan spoke this morning around the Raise the Roof protest. Clearly, I disagree with many of the Senator's comments around the housing debate. There is a lack of acknowledgement by the Senator and others in the Sinn Féin Party of the difficulties the current Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage has had to deal with. No previous Minister has had to deal with a global pandemic and a war in Europe, which has disrupted supply chains. While, of course, there are challenges and housing is the key issue for all of us here, the Senator has to acknowledge that there are major obstacles that no Minister, no matter what party he or she is in, would have been able to breeze through. Those particular challenges are so significant and severe. There is a housing crisis in many countries. It is not only here. We are not alone in dealing with those incredible once-in-a-generation challenges that the Minister is having to deal with. It is important to say that the numbers are going in the right direction. There are challenges but the Minister, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, is doing a very good job in extremely challenging circumstance. It is also important to point out, as the Minister has on several occasions, that there are members of local authorities in the Senator's party who are consistently objecting to delivery of housing in their communities. The Senator cannot have it both ways. The Senator should get behind the programme of building houses and delivering houses and stop objecting because it lacks credibility when he criticises the Minister in question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LynnBoylan" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Senator Lynn Boylan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">You will find Fianna Fáil rejecting them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_58">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">The Deputy Leader, without interruption.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LisaChambers" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Senator Lisa Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">It is important to visit those facts.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LisaChambers" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Deputy Lisa Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">It is interesting whenever I respond to questions raised and give my views that I am interrupted when I do so. I did not interrupt any Member in this House when he or she was making his or her contributions because I have my opportunity to reply at this juncture. That is the way that the House works.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8">(Interruptions).</summary>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_62">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">The Deputy Leader, without interruption.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LisaChambers" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Deputy Lisa Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T12:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">Heckling will not stop me saying my piece.</p>
          <p eId="para_148"> I challenge as well the response to Senator Malcolm Byrne, who raised the record and the facts in relation to Sinn Féin and Russia. Last week, Senator Gavan put on the record of this House a challenge to two members of Government who were doing their job on trade missions and he linked that to human rights abuses in Qatar. I disagreed with that connection. Today, however, the Senator is not facilitating other Members doing what looks to be something quite similar. The Senator cannot have it both ways. The Senator is entitled to make his remarks, as is any other Senator in this House, on that issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_149"> I take on board the comments that Senator Gavan made on the book by Ms Sally Hayden which, I think, we would all agree, is a fine publication and a good worthwhile read. I congratulate Ms Hayden on the book. Many Members in this House would concur with the Senator's remarks on the challenges and obstacles being put in the way of migrants trying to access Europe. The many lives being lost at sea is appalling and is an atrocity. We would all condemn that. One thing the Senator and I agree on this morning is on that issue. I concur with the Senator's remarks in that regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_150"> Senator Wilson seconded the motion this morning on Ukraine. I have dealt with that matter. I commend the Senator on circulating the motion to the House and for giving the House an opportunity to show its support for Ukraine on that issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_151"> Senator Lombard asked for an update on the human tissue Bill. I suggest that the Senator raise a Commencement matter on that particular issue as it is quite a specific question. I note the Senator's comments that he wants the Bill dealt with before the end of term. To be honest, I am not sure it is due before the House before the end of term. We have a packed schedule and many Ministers are looking to get Bills passed. Obviously, we have the Finance Bill and the Social Welfare Bill as well. We will have a busy number of weeks as we head towards the Christmas break. The Senator raised a particular issue around the Road Safety Authority and testing centres and in particular, on the test centre in Skibbereen. I suggest the Senator might raise a Commencement matter on that particular issue in relation to that test centre.</p>
          <p eId="para_152"> Senator McGreehan asked for a debate on the UK Northern Ireland Troubles (Legacy and Reconciliation) Bill, which I have requested with the House Leader.</p>
          <p eId="para_153"> Senator Maria Byrne welcomed the two new routes to Europe from Shannon Airport, as did Senator Conway. I congratulate Shannon Airport on expanding its services yet again. Senator Maria Byrne also raised again the issues and ongoing challenges at University Hospital Limerick, UHL.</p>
          <p eId="para_154"> Senator Davitt raised the issue of rail services, in particular, highlighting Mullingar as being a significantly-sized town from which there should be a second line to service commuters and the population of the area. The Senator also requested a debate with the Minister for Justice on how the Garda deals with victims of burglary. We will request that debate. It will most likely be in the new term, as we have only recently had the Minister for Justice in on a number of occasions.</p>
          <p eId="para_155"> Senator Carrigy spoke about the train service as well, and wanting that extended to Longford. The calls were across the board here to extend the trains to other areas as well. Senator Dolan also spoke about the train service to Ballinasloe. I concur with the remarks of both Senators in terms of regional connectivity, that all lines and roads lead to Dublin and that is fine as it is the capital city, but we need to start connecting the regions as well. Obviously, I have been a strong proponent of the western rail corridor and a line from Galway to Mayo, connecting up the region and providing a good service. There is no reason the train should not stop in Ballinasloe. Why would it not? That service should be provided. If we are looking to get people out of their cars and into public transport, we have to provide an alternative option to the car, which simply is not there for most of the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_156"> Senator Carrigy also spoke about the assessment of needs issue and referenced Senator Malcolm Byrne's comments from yesterday around what appears to be an increase in litigation and, as was put by Senator Byrne, the lawyering up of HSE officials in dealing with parents who are rightly demanding services for children with disabilities.</p>
          <p eId="para_157"> Senator Seery Kearney welcomed the Cherry Orchard implementation board that was announced by the Minister for Justice, Deputy McEntee, and the Minister of State, Deputy James Browne. The Senator welcomed and thanked both them for setting up the board and spoke about the need for additional services in that community across all areas in terms of services.</p>
          <p eId="para_158"> Senator Fitzpatrick asked again for a debate on public transport in Dublin city, specifically around the National Transport Authority, NTA, and public transport plans for the area. The Senator criticised the significant fee being attached to contributing to the planning process for citizens. It is €100, if one wants to make a submission. It seems like quite a high fee for somebody to make a submission for their local community. It is an amount that might be beyond the means of many citizens.</p>
          <p eId="para_159"> Senator Conway spoke about Shannon Airport but also gift vouchers, and raised particular concerns about how they operate among different retailers.</p>
          <p eId="para_160"> Senator McGahon raised the advanced training centre in Dundalk. The Senator asked for a debate on regional balance and the potential to roll out similar training centres across all regions. We will request that debate with the Minister, Deputy Harris.</p>
          <p eId="para_161"> Senator Niall Ó Donnghaile raised the Irish centres and asked for a statement on that. I have put that request in to the Leader's office for a debate with the Minister of State, Deputy Colm Brophy, on the diaspora, development aid and the extension of voting rights. We will get that, most likely, in the new year. We will not get a chance to do it before the end of the term.</p>
          <p eId="para_162"> Senator Boylan made a very important contribution in the context of highlighting that tomorrow is International Day for the Eradication of Violence against Women. The Senator put some very stark statistics on the record in terms of the increase in the number of women coming forward and the number of files going to the Director of Public Prosecutions. There has been much debate in this House, and in the Lower House as well, particularly in the past couple of years, around violence against women. There is a huge amount of work happening in the Department of Justice in respect of this matter, and funding being put behind a plan to try to reduce and, hopefully, at some point eradicate violence against women. The numbers are quite shocking. The Senator rightly pointed out that we had some very high-profile cases that the entire country would have been aware of. Some 242 women have lost their lives since we started counting in this regard. It is important to remember and acknowledge all of those lives lost and not just focus on the cases that made the headlines. Every life lost is a life that should not have been lost.</p>
          <p eId="para_163"> Senator Dolan spoke on the issue with trains in Ballinasloe. I think I have dealt with that matter. We will request a debate on rail services in the new year. There has been a request for a debate from other Members as well around the all-island strategic rail review and the plan for rail services across the country, with a particular focus on regional rail and bus services as well. I take on board the Senators point. I would have often used the service operated by Citylink and GoBus from Galway to Dublin. That is operational there. In some ways, the private sector has filled the gap.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AislingDolan" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Senator Aisling Dolan<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T13:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">The coach operator does not accept the travel pass.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LisaChambers" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Senator Lisa Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T13:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">Of course. Yes. It has been kind of a lazy response from the Department in that it is quite convenient that there is a private operator servicing most of the needs of the area. It probably gets it off the hook to a certain extent. However, it is not providing the service that Bus Éireann could and should provide. There needs to be a service. There are black spots across the country where there just is not adequate public service. It is not even close. If we are to meet our climate targets, we need to get public transport up and running across the regions as well, not just in our cities. I thank the Senator for raising the issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_66">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T13:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">Senator Craughwell has moved an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 122, motion 5, be taken before No. 1." Senator Wilson seconded the amendment. Is the amendment agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_9"> Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="motion" eId="dbsect_9">
        <heading>Holodomor Genocide: Motion<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T13:00:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#GerardPCraughwell" eId="spk_67">
          <from>Senator Gerard P. Craughwell<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T13:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">I move:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_168">That Seanad Éireann recognises the Holodomor (inflicting death by starvation) of 1932-1933 as a genocide on the Ukrainian people and on its 90th anniversary on 26th November, 2022 we show our solidarity with Ukraine in commemorating this man-made famine which was inflicted on the Ukrainian people by the deliberate policies of the totalitarian Stalinist regime which resulted in millions of innocent lives being lost.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T13:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">I second the motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_69">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T13:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_170">I welcome the Ukrainian ambassador. I thank all the Members who spoke on this important issue of genocide 90 years ago, in which millions of innocent Ukrainian men, women and children died needlessly due to a policy inflicted by a larger neighbour. We remember them today as we approach the 90th anniversary. I thank the ambassador for being here for the taking of this motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_10"> Question put and agreed to.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="motion" eId="dbsect_10">
        <heading>Civil Law (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2021: Motion<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T13:00:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#LisaChambers" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Senator Lisa Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T13:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">I move:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_172">That Seanad Éireann resolves that the period of operation of sections 1 to 7 and 9 of the Civil Law (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2021 (No. 14 of 2021) be extended for a further period of 6 months, beginning on the 1st day of December, 2022 and ending on the 31st day of May, 2023.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_11"> Question put and agreed to.</summary>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_71">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T13:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">When is it proposed to sit again?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LisaChambers" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Senator Lisa Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T13:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">Next Tuesday at 1 p.m.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_73">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-24T13:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_12"> Cuireadh an Seanad ar athló ar 1.33 p.m. go dtí 1 p.m., Dé Máirt, an 29 Samhain 2022.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_13"> The Seanad adjourned at 1.33 p.m. until 1 p.m. on Tuesday, 29 November 2022.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
