<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2018-10-11/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2018-10-11/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2018-10-11" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/house/seanad/25"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2018-10-11/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2018-10-11/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2018-10-11" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2018-10-11/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2018-10-11/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2019-09-24" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AidanDavitt" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aidan-Davitt.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Aidan Davitt"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AnthonyLawlor" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Anthony-Lawlor.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Anthony Lawlor"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CatherineArdagh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Catherine-Ardagh.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Catherine Ardagh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CiaranCannon" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ciaran-Cannon.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Ciaran Cannon"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DavidStanton" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/David-Stanton.D.1997-06-26" showAs="David Stanton"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DenisODonovan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Denis-O'Donovan.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Denis O'Donovan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DiarmuidWilson" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Diarmuid-Wilson.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Diarmuid Wilson"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DrJamesReilly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/James-Reilly.D.2007-06-14" showAs="James Reilly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FintanWarfield" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Fintan-Warfield.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Fintan Warfield"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FrancesBlack" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Frances-Black.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Frances Black"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="GerardPCraughwell" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Gerard-P-Craughwell.S.2014-10-10" showAs="Gerard P. Craughwell"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="IvanaBacik" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ivana-Bacik.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Ivana Bacik"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JerryButtimer" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jerry-Buttimer.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Jerry Buttimer"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="KevinHumphreys" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Kevin-Humphreys.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Kevin Humphreys"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaireDevine" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Máire-Devine.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Máire Devine"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MariaByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Maria-Byrne.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Maria Byrne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MarkDaly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mark-Daly.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Mark Daly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MartinConway" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Martin-Conway.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Martin Conway"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaryMitchellOConnor" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mary-Mitchell-O'Connor.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Mary Mitchell O'Connor"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NealeRichmond" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Neale-Richmond.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Neale Richmond"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NiallODonnghaile" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Niall-Ó-Donnghaile.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Niall Ó Donnghaile"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PatBreen" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pat-Breen.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Pat Breen"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulCoghlan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Coghlan.S.1997-09-17" showAs="Paul Coghlan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RobbieGallagher" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Robbie-Gallagher.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Robbie Gallagher"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RoseConwayWalsh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Rose-Conway-Walsh.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Rose Conway-Walsh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TimLombard" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Tim-Lombard.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Tim Lombard"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="VictorBoyhan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Victor-Boyhan.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Victor Boyhan"/>
        <TLCEvent eId="bill.2018.40.seanad.3_sub" href="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2018/40/seanad/3_sub" showAs="Criminal Justice (Money Laundering and Terrorist Financing) (Amendment) Bill 2018: Committee and Remaining Stages (Seanad)"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Acting_Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/office/acting_chairman" showAs="Acting Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Business,_Enterprise_and_Innovation" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/business__enterprise__innovation" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Education_and_Skills" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/education__skills" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Education and Skills"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs_and_Trade" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/foreign_affairs__trade" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice_and_Equality" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/justice__equality" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>SEANAD ÉIREANN</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>SEANAD ÉIREANN</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2018-10-11">, 11 Deireadh Fómhair 2018</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2018-10-11">Thursday, 11 October 2018</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="volume">
        <docNumber refersTo="#vol_260">Vol. 260</docNumber>
      </block>
      <block name="number">
        <docNumber refersTo="#no_10">No. 10</docNumber>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30 a.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">Machnamh agus Paidir.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Reflection and Prayer.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Business of Seanad<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#DenisODonovan" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_1">I have received notice from Senator Tim Lombard that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_2">The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for training, skills, innovation, research and development to provide adequate support to transport children living on Sherkin Island to and from school on the mainland. </p>
          <p eId="para_3">I have also received notice from Senator Niall Ó Donnghaile of the following matter:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_4">The need for the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to provide an update on his Department's practical plans to Brexit proof existing services for Irish citizens resident in the North.</p>
          <p eId="para_5">I have also received notice from Senator Neale Richmond of the following matter:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_6">The need for the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation to address the delays in processing work permit applications.</p>
          <p eId="para_7">I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_8">The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to provide an update on the status of his Department's review of councillors' terms and conditions.</p>
          <p eId="para_9">I have also received notice from Senator Máire Devine of the following matter:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_10">The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to outline the plans in place following the collapse of the construction firm MDY, with particular reference to Dolphin Park senior citizens' unit and the primary care centre, both of which are in Rialto, Dublin 8.</p>
          <p eId="para_11">I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_12">The need for the Minister for Health to outline the action being taken to increase the availability of therapeutic services in line with current best practice and the growing needs of the students in Scoil Cara junior school, Banduff, Mayfield, Cork.</p>
          <p eId="para_13">I have also received notice from Senator Anthony Lawlor of the following matter:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_14">The need for the Minister for Health to confirm that the number of home care packages in CHO area 7 will be increased to meet current needs.</p>
          <p eId="para_15">I have also received notice from Senator Frank Feighan of the following matter:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_16">The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the planned central sterile services department for Roscommon University Hospital.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion. I have selected the matters raised by Senators Tim Lombard, Niall Ó Donnghaile, Neale Richmond and Robbie Gallagher and they will be taken now. Senators Máire Devine, Colm Burke, Anthony Lawlor and Frank Feighan may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise. Senator Robbie Gallagher has withdrawn his matter which I had selected for discussion.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Commencement Matters<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
          <heading>School Transport<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#DenisODonovan" eId="spk_2">
            <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_18">I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Mary Mitchell O'Connor. Senator Tim Lombard is, in my view, somewhat trespassing into the territory of the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Jim Daly, but I will let him off.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_3">
            <from>Senator Tim Lombard<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_19">What can I say? If one gets the call, one has to do the work. I got the call from the community of Sherkin Island about what was happening there.</p>
            <p eId="para_20"> I welcome the Minister of State. Sherkin Island is a wonderful little island, the community of which is doing its best to survive. It has a population of 100. The school on it closed in 2016. The major issue since has been trying to find school transportation from the island to the mainland. It is a unique case. What is actually happening is that there is a ferry that takes the children to the mainland to go to school in Rath which is near Baltimore. However, the issue is one of timing. Let me give the Minister of State an example. If a parent has a child in junior or senior infants and he or she finishes at 2 p.m, the parent or guardian must catch the ferry at noon, land in Baltimore at 12.15 p.m., wait one hour and 45 minutes to pick up the child at 2 p.m. and catch the ferry at 3 p.m. to arrive back at the island at 3.15 p.m. One would drive to Dublin in the time it takes to get a child home from school. It is bizarre, to say the very least. In 2016, when the school on the island closed, commitments were given that something would be done to provide transportation for the children to the mainland. It would not be a major issue if the Minister of State were to sit down with the community and thrash it out.</p>
            <p eId="para_21"> There are 183 school days in the year. There is a need for a dedicated ferry service to match school pick up times between 2 p.m. and 3 p.m. Arranging transport for the children to school is becoming a major drain on the community. Obviously for child protection reasons, a parent or grandparent has to accompany a schoolchild on the boat as there is no chaperone on it. There is a need to have a dedicated chaperone it for the children. We know that having to make a round trip of three hours to collect a child from school is not sustainable. We all know what will happen. People will not send their child to school on the mainland from the island; rather, they will move to the mainland and the ethos that has been built on the island for generations, decades, if not millennia, will slowly drift away.</p>
            <p eId="para_22"> There is a need for a real conversation with the community. Departmental officials need to travel to Sherkin Island to sit down with the community association to put a proactive plan in place in order that the community will be able to ensure the children can be educated in a timely fashion and the way of life they have worked so hard to instill can continue. This is about communication. I agree that the case is unique and that the Department must work to resolve the issue. I know of no other school where a ferry is used as school transportation. Because the case is unique, we need to look for a unique solution. It will involve interaction between the Department of Education and Skills and the community. What I really want - I implore her do so - is for the Minister of State to have her officials travel to the island to engage with the community.</p>
            <p eId="para_23">We do not need more letters or emails, of which we have seen enough since 2016. We need departmental officials in place in order that we can work towards a solution.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#MaryMitchellOConnor" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Education_and_Skills" eId="spk_4">
            <from>Minister of State at the Department of Education and Skills (Deputy Mary Mitchell O'Connor)<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_24">I am taking this matter on behalf of the Minister of State at the Department of Education and Skills, Deputy John Halligan. I thank Senator Lombard who has made his case very strongly. I do not know either of another case in Ireland like the one he describes. I was a principal in a rural school and an urban one and attended a two-teacher school as a child. As such, I understand how important it is to have a school in a community. </p>
            <p eId="para_25"> Regarding supports for the transport of children from Sherkin Island to schools on the mainland, the ferry passenger service described by the Senator involves parents having to arrive at 12 noon and they must sit waiting for their children for an hour and a half and then two and a half hours. They are great and very patient parents. A ferry passenger service is provided under a subsidy from the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht with several daily sailings. Once children are at the pier on the mainland, a number of services are available to provide transport to the primary school in Baltimore and post-primary schools in Rosscarbery, Clonakilty and Skibbereen. Regarding the Senator's question, a request has been received for the establishment of a dedicated school transport facility separate from the current service to transport children to Rath national school in Baltimore. Discussions are ongoing between officials in the Department of Education and Skills and the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht on this request.</p>
            <p eId="para_26"> I will take what the Senator has said and his description of the hardship experienced by parents and children and ensure the Department of Education and Skills knows exactly what is happening. Discussions must speed up between the two relevant Departments.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_5">
            <from>Senator Tim Lombard<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_27">Discussions between the Departments are very important, but the community must be involved. The community believes this has involved only a paper and email trail, whereas what is needed is a meeting on Sherkin Island. They have to see it and smell it to understand what is really happening. To think one could be in Dublin in the time it takes to collect one's child is an unbelievable scenario. Nowhere else in the State does that happen. There was a similar issue with the secondary schools 20 years ago and the Department came down at the time to put a service in place which has worked very well ever since. That connection and communication is required again. I implore the Minister of State to ensure a meeting takes place on Sherkin Island. We need to get all those people down to thrash out what is required.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#MaryMitchellOConnor" eId="spk_6" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Education_and_Skills">
            <from>Deputy Mary Mitchell O'Connor<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_28">I will ensure the message is given to the Minister of State, Deputy John Halligan, that the Senator has requested a meeting on Sherkin Island.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_5">
          <heading>Brexit Supports<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:40:00+01:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#NiallODonnghaile" eId="spk_7">
            <from>Senator Niall Ó Donnghaile<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_29">Cuirim fáilte roimh an Aire Stáit. The Minister of State, Deputy Cannon, is very welcome and I thank him for taking the time to address the issue. The purpose of the Commencement matter is self-explanatory. We have heard that for reasonable, logical and understandable reasons the State intends to get Brexit-ready by hosting a series of positive engagements nationally. It would be more positive again if they were to come North also. We have heard a great deal about the Brexit-proofing of this week's budget, which is, again, necessary, given the context. I have sought to find out whether as part of those plans and engagements consideration is being given by the Department and the Government more generally to investing in services to meet citizens' needs where they are, as is happening with investment in animals and businesses. I refer to this investment with a specific focus on the North of Ireland where citizens are very mobilised on this issue. They are concerned and engaged with the Government. If we are to affirm the statement about not leaving citizens behind, which is welcome, it is time to, at least, plan in our future work programmes, whether it is via the budget or in other ways, to provide the direct interface citizens will need in the live dynamic of Brexit and, in particular, post Brexit. People are uncertain and will need to engage with the Government and Departments not only on Irish rights and entitlements but also on their existing EU rights and entitlements.</p>
            <p eId="para_30"> I am not asking for an update on the state of play in the negotiations. I appreciate the juncture we are at and the fluidity of the live negotiations. An té nach gcuireann san earrach ní bhaineann sé san fhómhar. If we do not plan ahead, we will be in a worse position when trying to provide these services further down the line. I hope that is part of the consideration of Government and, in particular, the Department.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#CiaranCannon" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs_and_Trade" eId="spk_8">
            <from>Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade (Deputy Ciarán Cannon)<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_31">I thank the Senator for raising the matter of protecting services for Irish citizens in Northern Ireland post Brexit. As the Senator pointed out, we are at a critical phase of the Article 50 negotiations. As President Tusk stated in Salzburg in September, we must seek to maximise progress and results in the negotiations in the coming weeks in order that we can finalise and formalise a deal in November. Our preference remains for an overall EU-UK relationship which would resolve all issues, but it remains essential that a backstop is agreed which provides the certainty that there will be no hard border in any circumstance. We need that certainty now because uncertainty is already causing grave concern among communities, North and South.</p>
            <p eId="para_32"> At paragraph 52 of the joint report of December, the European Commission and the UK acknowledged that the Good Friday Agreement recognised the birthright of all the people of Northern Ireland to choose to be Irish or British or both and to be accepted as such. The joint report also confirms that the people of Northern Ireland who are Irish citizens will continue to enjoy rights as EU citizens, including where they reside in Northern Ireland. Both parties agreed that the withdrawal agreement should respect and be without prejudice to the rights, opportunities and identity that come with European Union citizenship for such people. It was further agreed that the next phase of negotiations would examine the arrangements required to give effect to the ongoing exercise of and access to their EU rights, opportunities and benefits. This position is recognised in the draft protocol. As the UK leaves the European Union, there is an onus on its government to ensure it provides as necessary for the recognition in the joint report that the people of Northern Ireland who choose to identify as Irish, and therefore as citizens of the EU, will continue to enjoy the rights, opportunities and benefits of EU citizenship, including where they reside in Northern Ireland.</p>
            <p eId="para_33"> In the context of the UK’s withdrawal from the EU, the Government is committed to ensuring the common travel area, or CTA, and the associated rights and entitlements of Irish and British citizens under this long-standing reciprocal arrangement which dates back to the 1920s will continue. This is also recognised in the text of the withdrawal agreement. The CTA allows Irish and British citizens to move and reside freely in either jurisdiction and enables access to a range of similar associated rights in the other country. Under the CTA, Irish citizens in the UK and British citizens in Ireland have the right to reside, work, study and access healthcare, social security and public services in the other country, as well as to vote in certain elections.</p>
            <p eId="para_34"> Since the UK referendum decision to leave the EU, we have seen a 20% rise in passport applications from Irish citizens resident in Northern Ireland. Since 2016, a significant programme of reform to enhance passport services for citizens has been under way, including the introduction of online passport services. The distribution of tasks across the passport service has also been refined and improved. The Passport Office in Cork processes applications from Northern Ireland. An anticipated 230 temporary clerical officers will be recruited in 2019, over 40 of whom will be assigned to the Cork office, in addition to 11 permanent officers.</p>
            <p eId="para_35">In summary, the Government is acutely conscious of the potential impact on Northern Ireland of the UK decision to leave the European Union. We are determined to ensure the Good Friday Agreement in all its parts and the gains and benefits of the peace process are protected for people on the island of Ireland, North and South, as the UK leaves the EU.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#NiallODonnghaile" eId="spk_9">
            <from>Senator Niall Ó Donnghaile<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_36">I appreciate the update and fully understand the restrictions on the Minister of State. He acknowledges and reaffirms a number of important positions of the Government, which is welcome and encouraging. If raising this seems somewhat unfair of me, I am not trying to dupe the Minister of State or get him to reveal his hand. I am trying to encourage and sustain the pressure because citizens in the North would expect me to do as much. As well as the macro-political negotiations, people also want to see physical, visible manifestations of Irish Government support and continued endorsement. This is perfectly in line with the word and letter of the Good Friday Agreement when one considers that there is existing Irish government infrastructure in the Six Counties. The issue is one of determining how best we utilise that to support the needs of citizens who are crying out for greater Irish Government investment. When they look across the water and see what is happening there, they do not have much faith in or support for what the British Government is doing.</p>
            <p eId="para_37"> With regard to the Passport Office, it is no wonder that we need to employ an additional 230 staff, given that the Secretary General of the Department has acknowledged that the passport service is under immense pressure. Last year more than 82,000 passport applications came from the Six Counties and that figure is anticipated to rise again this year. Would it not make far more sense to locate some of those 230 people in the North rather than in Cork? The radically increasing number of passport applications is being processed at the farthest possible point from where they are originating. With regard to how we utilise the existing infrastructure and deal with people directly in service interface and delivery, it would make much more sense to invest for the future and direct some of those staff to where the growing demand is generated. I will raise the matter again, no doubt.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#CiaranCannon" eId="spk_10" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs_and_Trade">
            <from>Deputy Ciarán Cannon<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_38">The Senator has referred before to the need to establish a passport office in Belfast.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#NiallODonnghaile" eId="spk_11">
            <from>Senator Niall Ó Donnghaile<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_39">Once or twice.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#CiaranCannon" eId="spk_12" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs_and_Trade">
            <from>Deputy Ciarán Cannon<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_40">Yes. In addition to the staff costs that might arise which are already subsumed into the service, very significant capital investment of more than €1.5 million would be required for the machine required to print the passports. A passport express service is available in Northern Ireland through more than 60 post offices dotted throughout the province. There is also an online service. A resident of Belmullet is much farther away from the Dublin Passport Office than a resident of Belfast.</p>
            <p eId="para_41"> That current service works exceptionally well, not just for citizens residing on the island of Ireland but also for citizens across the world too. In providing that service we need to ensure we have sufficient staff capacity to process all the applications that are arising. We expect further increases in passport applications in the future. We are recruiting staff and an excellent ongoing recruitment process is in place. The resources and capacity of the Passport Office are such now that we are confident that it will be capable of catering for additional demand in the future.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_6">
          <heading>Work Permits Applications<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:50:00+01:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#NealeRichmond" eId="spk_13">
            <from>Senator Neale Richmond<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_42">I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Pat Breen, and thank him for taking this Commencement matter. I also thank the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Heather Humphreys, for the reply to the letter I sent her in September about this issue.</p>
            <p eId="para_43"> I will address three key areas related to work permits, an issue that presents a growing problem in the State. Applicants for work permits are waiting on average for eight or 12 weeks for their applications to be processed. These people are living in limbo. They may come here under other arrangements or are waiting in third countries to see when they can move here or arrange the practical aspects of life. The long waiting time is having such a negative impact that we see many job offers withdrawn and many lives being put on hold owing to the delays in the processing system.</p>
            <p eId="para_44"> The work permits system also has a major impact on employers. This is one of the biggest challenges facing the State as we hurtle brilliantly towards full employment. Much of the credit for this is due to the Department and its hard work. There are a number of key sectors, especially in my area of south Dublin, which simply cannot recruit staff. These are good, high paying, highly skilled jobs, for which we need citizens from third countries, that is, countries outside the European Union, because people from the European Union either will not or cannot do them. These are in many areas, including IT, financial services and hospitality. Every day costs are being imposed on customers because businesses cannot maintain the requisite level of competitiveness. It stops businesses from expanding and trying to address the issue of Brexit. The high level financial services companies we are trying to attract need to know they will have enough bookkeepers, accountants and IT professionals to fill the gap. We are not quite able to provide them with that assurance.</p>
            <p eId="para_45"> Tied into that issue is the issue of companies that wish to invest in Ireland or locate here, whether financial services or technology companies. These are companies from outside the European Union that want to set up an office here. They view Dublin or Ireland as an excellent hub or base for the European market with obvious ties to the UK market. However, they cannot bring key personnel to this country to work in their Irish operations. They are waiting for at least 12 weeks, often much longer, before they can open their operations because they cannot secure a work permit for a chief financial officer, CFO. He or she may be from South Africa, the United States or Asia, but he or she has to wait. Every day that businesses cannot open here costs them money. It also costs employees their livelihoods and forces many of them to give up their rental accommodation or jeopardise their chance to apply for a mortgage.</p>
            <p eId="para_46"> I cannot stress strongly enough how important it is that we have this matter resolved as soon as possible. Can resources be reallocated to speed up the applications process? Much has been done by the Department to change the eligibility criteria for work permits, which is excellent. However, those who need work permits are waiting for too long, as are employers who need employees. I fear this is having a detrimental effect on a booming economy.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#PatBreen" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Business,_Enterprise_and_Innovation" eId="spk_14">
            <from>Minister of State at the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation (Deputy Pat Breen)<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_47">I thank the Senator for raising this important issue. Many of us as public representatives, whether Senators or Deputies, confront this problem every day with employers in a similar predicament to what the Senator has raised. Ireland's overarching economic migration policy is to source skills and labour needs from within the workforce of Ireland and the European economic area, EEA. Ireland operates a managed employment permits system which maximises the benefits of economic migration, while minimising the risk of disrupting Ireland's labour market. That market is very important to us, as the Senator rightly pointed out, particularly as we approach full employment.</p>
            <p eId="para_48"> To work in Ireland, a non-EEA national must, unless exempted, hold a valid employment permit. The employment permits section of the Department administers the employment permits system. All applications for employment permits are processed in line with the employment permits Acts and associated regulations.</p>
            <p eId="para_49"> As the economy improves and we approach full employment, my Department has experienced a high volume of employment permit applications in recent months. This has led to some delays in processing applications. I have seen this at first-hand among employers who are in a similar position. At the end of September 2018, the total number of employment permit applications accepted was 12,530, which represents a 29% increase on the figure for the same period in 2017. During this period, 9,284 employment permits were issued in total, which represents a 10% increase on the figure for the same period in 2017. The employment permits section is working to reduce the current waiting times of six weeks for applications from trusted partners who are regular users of the service and 16 weeks for standard applications.</p>
            <p eId="para_50">It is much too long. I even had a case this morning of a permit required for someone for next week. It is unacceptable and we are dealing with it.</p>
            <p eId="para_51"> My officials are engaging proactively with customers by notifying them of current delays through email, meetings and regular updates on the employment permits section of my Department’s website. To reduce processing times, the employment permits section has introduced several operational changes, streamlined processes and implemented ICT solutions. Additional staffing resources have also been assigned to the section and a fast-track training programme has been devised. All available resources are being deployed, with the aim of reducing processing times. In one way, the number of applications is a sign of the success of the economy.</p>
            <p eId="para_52"> Overall, the number of applications awaiting processing is starting to reduce as a result of the changes implemented. I expect this to continue. A reduction in processing times is anticipated in the coming weeks as the changes being implemented start to bear fruit. The Department is getting on top of the issue.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#NealeRichmond" eId="spk_15">
            <from>Senator Neale Richmond<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_53">I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive reply and the heartening statistics he outlined. I acknowledge the efforts of his Department and appreciate its ongoing engagement in this area. It is open and recognises there is an issue which needs to be addressed.</p>
            <p eId="para_54"> However, as we face into a chaotic global economic scene with Brexit approaching and the regressive trade policies of President Trump and certain other colleagues on the Continent, Ireland must seize every opportunity and ensure everyone knows that it is open for business. We must ensure corporations know that not only can they move here but also that the labour from abroad needed to staff these organisations can look to Ireland as an open, welcoming and efficient place in which to move and work. We need that talent to come into the country. While a slowdown might be forecasted, if we want to fulfil the aim of being an island at the centre of the world, we need to address this issue now and maintain that level of proactivity to ensure we can ride out what will be a difficult economic period.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#PatBreen" eId="spk_16" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Business,_Enterprise_and_Innovation">
            <from>Deputy Pat Breen<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_55">The Department is conscious of this matter. We believe having an efficient and responsive employment permit system is critical in addressing the economy's skills needs and in ensuring talent is attracted to Ireland. There are people from all over the globe working in multinational companies here. Recently, I was at Google’s headquarters in Barrow Street where there are 65 nationalities.</p>
            <p eId="para_56"> It is important we attract these people into the country and monitor the skills shortages. With the changes we have made in the employment permits section, with the provision of additional resources and efficiencies in skills training and computers, we can get on top of the issue. To be fair to the staff, they are working hard and doing overtime to deal with it.</p>
            <p eId="para_57"> I am conscious that our reputation is at stake. The flow of talent is crucial. At this time of the year, there is a large volume of permit applications as we are coming towards the end of the year. We are also reviewing the type of employment shortages to be able to deal with them. It is crucial as the economy grows. The Senator referred to trade wars. We want this to be seen as a country that is leading when it comes to attracting multinationals to locate here.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_7">
        <heading>Message from Joint Committee<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_17">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">The Joint Committee on Justice and Equality has completed its consideration of the following motions:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_59">(i) Proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Council Regulation (EC) No 1206/2001 of 28 May, 2001 on cooperation between the courts of the Member States in the taking of evidence in civil or commercial matters,</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_60">a copy of which was laid before Seanad Éireann on 6 July, 2018; and</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_61">(ii) Proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Regulation (EC) No. 1393/2007 of the European Parliament and of the Council on the service in the Member States of judicial and extrajudicial documents in civil or commercial matters (service of documents),</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_62">a copy of which was laid before Seanad Éireann on 21 June, 2018.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_4">
          <i> Sitting suspended at 11.05 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="orderofBusiness" eId="dbsect_8">
        <heading>Order of Business<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re EU regulation on the service in member states of judicial and extrajudicial documents in civil or commercial matters, back from committee, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of the Order of Business; No. 2, motion re EU regulation on co-operation between the courts of member states in the taking of evidence in civil or commercial matters, back from committee, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of No. 1; and No. 3, Criminal Justice (Money Laundering and Terrorist Financing) (Amendment) Bill 2018 - Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken at 12.45 p.m.</p>
          <p eId="para_64"> This is International Day of the Girl. In that context, I wish all of our female colleagues a good day.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineArdagh" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Senator Catherine Ardagh<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">In the context of Brexit, we all know how important it is for small businesses to have access to high-speed broadband. Anyone running a small business knows that if the broadband service is down, one may as well go home because no work can be done. However, there are many companies, particularly in rural Ireland, that do not have access to high-speed broadband.</p>
          <p eId="para_66">They lack a competitive edge when it comes to doing business in this country. In the light of Brexit especially, it is almost impossible to keep on top of things if a company does not have proper access to broadband. Communities in rural Ireland are suffering massively because of the failed roll-out of the broadband plan.</p>
          <p eId="para_67"> It is clear that the Government has made an absolute hames of the tendering process and, ultimately, the rolling out of broadband for communities in rural Ireland. Recent revelations about the Minister and certain meetings do not instil much confidence in the tendering process, in particular among communities nationally which require, as a matter of urgency, access to high-speed broadband. The Minister should know, as the old maxim has it, that justice must not only be done but be seen to be done. The maxim applies equally to a tendering process and to public procurement law. The Minister's actions have potentially exposed the process to judicial review and those who will suffer are the communities in rural Ireland which do not have access to broadband.</p>
          <p eId="para_68"> The Government must make it an urgent priority to sort out this mess to ensure the last mile of broadband is rolled out in order that all communities nationally have access to broadband, especially small businesses. I have a small business myself in Crumlin village. If I went to work tomorrow morning to find I had no access to broadband, I might as well shut up shop. My phones rely on broadband, as do my email, Internet service and entire system. Being able to use broadband also makes my business a great deal more efficient. I would be out of business if I did not have it. As such, I do not know how small businesses in rural Ireland survive without access to decent and efficient broadband.</p>
          <p eId="para_69"> As the Leader said, it is International Day of the Girl. We must think about what we are doing to nurture and protect girls in Ireland. A report published by Plan International Ireland shows that 93% of women feel vulnerable just because they are women. A report on Dublin as a capital showed that one third of girls felt unsafe on public transport. It is incumbent on us as policymakers to ensure women and girls throughout the country feel safe when they are going about their day-to-day business. That includes doing simple things like taking public transport.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">I raise with the Leader the matter of the Land Development Agency which was established by the Government in September 2018. It falls within the remit and is the direct responsibility of the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy. We need to see as soon as possible the general heads of a scheme of legislation to underpin the establishment of the agency which will deal with vast amounts of public land and millions of euro of public money. There are huge issues surrounding how it will be structured. Is it going to be a commercial entity? What about accountability and who will have responsibility for the transparency and oversight of the agency which will engage in vast landbank deals and land exchanges with private developers? We have always spoken of accountability and transparency and this agency has the potential to create a toxic mix for Ireland if we do not get it right. While I welcome the establishment of the agency in principle, we need the legislation to underpin it. Therefore, I ask the Leader to arrange a statement from the Minister in the House on the scheme and an indicative timeframe for legislation in the hope that at some stage we will see a Bill to give legislative effect to the proposal.</p>
          <p eId="para_71"> I understand the report of the Charleton commission may be published today or tomorrow. The Leader will recall I gave a robust defence of the former Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Fitzgerald, while she was still in office. I stand over it and printed off the contribution for reference today. I look forward to having the commission's report before the House for a debate at the earliest convenience, this week or, certainly, the week after. I hope the report will exonerate Deputy Fitzgerald who was, in effect, hounded out of office by certain politicians who wanted a head on a plate and blood on the walls. I am not a personal ambassador for her, but I saw a wrong at the time and articulated it. I read again today what many Members in this and the Lower House said about her. If the report exonerates her, I hope they will take the opportunity to come back, man up and acknowledge that they did a wrong. No one from any party or none should be hounded from office until due process is complete. Mr. Justice Charleton will, I am glad to say, have done his work and we will have his report. Let us make our call and judgment on that work. As such, I appeal to the Leader to arrange as soon as practically possible to have the commission's report before the House for a frank and open debate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_21">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">The Senator's assessment of the situation is fair and objective.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireDevine" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Senator Máire Devine<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">I acknowledge International Day of the Girl. As was said, Plan International Ireland has reported that the vast majority of women in Ireland feel vulnerable because of their gender. A worldwide report was published in which Dublin was considered one of the safest cities. I am pleased with that, albeit we need a cultural change to ensure young women feel safe and are safe in public spaces. Crucially, they must be consulted on policy decisions. They need allies to achieve this. We all need allies to achieve our goals. As such, men have a critical role to play.</p>
          <p eId="para_74"> The lesser known International Day of the Boy is on 16 May. We need to promote and celebrate it and use it as an opportunity to educate boys in the cultural change needed to respect girls and women. As to those who engage in the intimidation, one's fears as a mother for one's teenage children as they seek to find their independence and dip a toe into young adulthood are very different, depending on whether they are boys or girls. For girls, one fears they will be harassed and intimidated sexually, while one's fear for boys is that they will be harassed and intimidated physically. Those involved are inadequate bullies who have issues of their own. As International Day of the Girl is celebrated, let us promote and use International Day of the Boy to facilitate a cultural shift.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FrancesBlack" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Senator Frances Black<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">I mark the passing of the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill in the House last night, which legislation is now being brought to Áras an Uachtaráin. I made a speech last night during which I forgot to thank a number of people. I take the opportunity to mention their names. One is Ms Kathryn Reilly who worked on the Bill. She is a former Senator and did a great deal of work on the legislation. I thank also Aengus Ó Maoláin who works with the Civil Engagement group and did a phenomenal amount of work on the Bill. I thank the Leader, Senator Buttimer, for his work, in particular as previous chairman of the alcohol committee. It is important to thank people and I do not like to forget to do so. This is historic legislation which will change and save many lives. There are many people in the RISE Foundation who are very happy.</p>
          <p eId="para_76"> I did not get a chance earlier in the week to express my condolences to the family of Emma Mhic Mhathúna. She was a beautiful woman and I met her a few months ago. She was a stunningly beautiful person and almost a warrior in a sense. She was a wonderful mother and represented many of the amazing women who are going through tough times today. I express my condolences to her lovely children and her family in general.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvanaBacik" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Senator Ivana Bacik<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">I join colleagues in expressing my condolences to the family of Emma Mhic Mhathúna. It was such a tragic death. For those of us who were outside Leinster House when the funeral cortège passed, it was unspeakably sad.</p>
          <p eId="para_78"> I also join Senators in marking International Day of the Girl. In the Seanad and Leinster House we are celebrating the centenary of women's suffrage in Ireland with the Vótáil 100 programme and an exhibition in the Seanad antechamber. We have to remember that for many girls and women worldwide their gender is still a source of oppression, discrimination and poverty. Plan International Ireland highlights the low levels of education and high levels of poverty of many girls, particularly in developing countries worldwide. We need to bear that in mind and work as much as we can to ensure the day means something and is not just a symbolic gesture. We need to advance measures to challenge and address gender discrimination.</p>
          <p eId="para_79"> We have had statements on the budget, but last night in the Dáil my colleague Deputy Jan O'Sullivan spoke about the need to advance the equality proofing of budgets in future years. I ask the Leader for a debate on the equality proofing of budgets and mechanisms for proofing them in respect not only of gender but also of poverty and disability to ensure we move beyond token references and achieve real progress on the issues.</p>
          <p eId="para_80"> I also call for a stand-alone debate on climate change, given the very disappointing lack of action to address climate change in the budget, in particular the absence of any increase in carbon tax, despite it being flagged. Environmental groups such as Stop Climate Chaos and Friends of the Earth have raised this issue and the budget was very disappointing from that point of view.</p>
          <p eId="para_81"> I ask the Leader for a debate on press freedom. This week we saw the brutal murder of Viktoria Marinova, a journalist in Bulgaria, which is being investigated by the Bulgarian authorities. It follows two other murders of investigative journalists in EU countries, namely, Maltese journalist Daphne Caruana Galizia in October 2017 and Slovak journalist Ján Kuciak in February 2018. Very serious concerns have been expressed by the international Committee to Protect Journalists about these attacks on press freedom and I know the concerns are strongly shared by the National Union of Journalists in Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DrJamesReilly" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Senator James Reilly<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">With deference to my colleagues and as it is girls' day, I will await my turn after Senator Byrne.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MariaByrne" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Senator Maria Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">As it is not often that happens, I thank Senator Reilly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_27">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">The age of chivalry is not dead.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KevinHumphreys" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Senator Kevin Humphreys<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">There are very few gentlemen in Fine Gael.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MariaByrne" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Senator Maria Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">There are very few gentlemen around here, whatever the party.</p>
          <p eId="para_87"> I acknowledge International Day of the Girl. I also acknowledge the findings of the report from Plan International Ireland. Dr. Scally and Dr. Denton were before the Joint Committee on Health yesterday to discuss their findings that some of the people whose results were not referred within 18 months were not sent back a second time. That is frightening and I understand Dr. Scally has committed to examine some of the scans and how they were investigated by different groups. It appears some were investigated by one clinic and then sent to another, with both clinics coming up with different results. A lot of what came out of the meeting yesterday is frightening for women in this country. There is a fear that there are more than the 221 women of whom we know. It is welcome that the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, has asked Dr. Scally to play a further role in the investigation and come up with terms of reference for how doctors should be trained to handle scans in the future. When people receive a bad diagnosis, they should be told about it. It is important that Dr. Scally come back with suggestions for how to deal with these things in the future.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">Yesterday I was alerted to a Government-backed publication, Ireland's Ancient East, which is supported by the Office of Public Works. I was disappointed that the illustration fails to recognise County Monaghan. It is included in the map, but they have decided to rename it as Armagh, which is very disappointing. Some may see the humour in that, but it is very disappointing that counties such as Monaghan, Cavan and others along the Border which do their best to attract tourists find that Departments let the side down.</p>
          <p eId="para_89"> With the 4.5% VAT increase in the budget, people in the Border counties are very disappointed with the outlook. Tourist figures have increased by 5% countrywide, but if we drill down, we see that in the six southern Border counties the figure has decreased by 12% and 16% in some cases. The Government talks about preparing for Brexit, but Brexit has been with us in the Border counties for quite some time and we deal with it daily. We are trying to cushion business from the effects, but the VAT blow for the hospitality sector is very serious and the reasons for doing it fail me. I appreciate that the Government has to find revenue, but surely the sensible thing to do, with Brexit on the horizon, would be to stall the process until we see what happens. I highlight my disappointment at the Border counties being forgotten yet again and ask the Leader to ask his colleagues in the Cabinet to consider that the Border counties are in a unique position and deserve to be treated differently from the rest of the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DrJamesReilly" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Senator James Reilly<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">I mark International Day of the Girl and welcome all the girls in the Gallery. It is appropriate that it is nearly all girls who are here. My issue has been raised by a female constituent, though not alone as many others have raised it too. On 3 September Iarnród Éireann decided to change its timetables and since then has become utterly unreliable. It used to be a service by which one could set a clock and we were very proud of our commuter train service, but in the past month it has been reliable in only one aspect, which is that it is continually late. This is causing commuters from Balbriggan, Skerries, Rush, Lusk and Donabate to miss meetings in town and children to have to wait until late to be picked up from their crèches.</p>
          <p eId="para_91"> It is a cause of great anger to people living in Fingal that they pay their taxes and fares which are more expensive than DART fares, yet they are late. One ludicrous excuse I was given was that it was because of leaves on the line. We are very proud of our parks, trees and countryside in Fingal, but we are pretty certain there are trees and parks on the south side of the city too and we do not see any problem there or on the west side. I was asked to raise this issue by my constituents and Councillor Tom O'Leary who has also received numerous emails. The problem is caused by congestion on the line with DART trains and the fact that the commuter train is not given precedence, which means that people are regularly ten or 11 minutes late. That means a 30-minute journey becomes a 40-minute or a 41-minute journey, which represents a 33% increase in the time of travel. It makes making connections in town unreliable and means that it is difficult to make commitments.</p>
          <p eId="para_92">We have a huge number of people who want to use public transport who do serious business. We have people working in Google, solicitors, barristers and all kinds of businesspeople and others who have commitments in town. They cannot make plans because the trains have become utterly unreliable since 3 September. </p>
          <p eId="para_93"> I urge the Leader to ask the Minister to contact Iarnród Éireann to find out what the problem is. If the Minister cannot have the matter corrected, he needs to come into this House, take his portfolio and responsibilities seriously and explain to us why commuters in Dublin north, Fingal, are being discommoded in this fashion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_32">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">I remind Senators that at this stage slots are two minutes' each and that only the leaders have three minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoseConwayWalsh" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Senator Rose Conway-Walsh<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">I want to speak about the autism assistance dogs programme provided by Autism Assistance Dogs Ireland. Yesterday we learned about the programme at a presentation given in the AV Room in Leinster House. The programme has transformed the lives of children with autism and that of their families. The organisation trains and provides highly skilled, task-specific assistance dogs for children with autism who struggle with the sometimes distressing elements of this invisible disability.</p>
          <p eId="para_96"> We know that one in 65 children in Ireland has autism. Yesterday at the presentation we heard from some of the families whose lives have been transformed as a result of getting one of the dogs. Edel talked about her son, Jack, who is 14 years of age. He has a complex brain disorder, which means that he has no sense of rule awareness or danger. He is also hypersensitive to noise, which means that he cannot decipher sounds. His mother described taking her son shopping as being equivalent to him experiencing a full-on assault and complete meltdown because of the noise and lights. She described the additional stress caused by what she called the "tutting brigade". She meant the people who looked disapprovingly and judged parents for allowing their children to behave in such a way. All of this meant that the family stayed at home and did not participate in normal activities. She said their assistance dog called Thorpe had given them the confidence to walk out of their front door again. She also said people became aware that there was an issue, not a spoiled child throwing a tantrum.</p>
          <p eId="para_97"> A woman called Sue who is the mother of Gearóid described how getting their dog, Ruby, had transformed their lives from feeling like they lived in a coffin to being able to live full and active lives. A man called T.J. who is the father of a girl named Rebecca described how a great trust had grown between his daughter and her assistance dog called Bella. He said an assistance dog provided a link between a child with autism and other children in the same way that a guide dog did. </p>
          <p eId="para_98"> The bottom line is that Autism Assistance Dogs Ireland needs funding. The organisation has achieved full international accreditation, but there are 200 children on its waiting list. The organisation wants to train 20 dogs this year, but it costs €22,000 to train just one dog. This week we have all heard about the billions of euro in the budget. Surely, funding for this organisation should be a priority for the Government. I ask for the support of the House in trying to obtain a small bit of funding amounting to €500,000 to fund the very valuable work done by the charity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnthonyLawlor" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Senator Anthony Lawlor<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_99">On International Day of the Girl, I was lucky enough to be in Benin in west Africa. The trip highlighted for me the role played by women and young girls in developing countries. A credit union had been established and it was the first time dividends were being paid. All of the women who collected their dividends did so in order to educate their young children. The credit union initiative is working in places in west Africa and across the African continent and means that women are more empowered in certain countries than in others. I urge people here to take heed and learn that lesson.</p>
          <p eId="para_100"> I want to talk about the €17 billion----- </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_35">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">The Senator has only one minute left.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnthonyLawlor" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Senator Anthony Lawlor<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">I will be as brief as possible. If the Leas-Chathaoirleach keeps interrupting me, my time will be shorter still.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">(Interruptions).</summary>
        <speech by="#MaireDevine" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Senator Máire Devine<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">I urge the Leas-Chathaoirleach not to accept such a reply.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_38">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">Order, please. I call for respect to be shown to the Chair.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">Senator Lawlor has less time now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnthonyLawlor" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Senator Anthony Lawlor<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">I want to talk about the €17 billion plus that has been allocated to the health service. I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on the matter. I ask him first to arrange a debate on the excess of €700 million that was overspent by the HSE last year and where that money was spent. We should have a debate on why in my community health region there was a 100% increase in the number of people waiting for home care packages and why we did not get any of that €700 million.</p>
          <p eId="para_107"> I ask the Leader to invite the Minister to discuss the health service plan before it is announced by the HSE, thus enabling us to have an input into the plan. We should also consider why there has been an increase of 12,000 in the number of staff in the HSE since 2014, which is more people than in the entire armed forces.</p>
          <p eId="para_108"> I would also like to have a discussion on the capital side of the health service plan in order that we know what is happening around the place, whether it is in our constituency or other constituencies.</p>
          <p eId="para_109"> I ask the Leader to invite the Minister or someone senior to facilitate a debate on health spending.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_41">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">I remind Senators that is it only lead spokespersons who are allowed to discuss two items on the Order of Business. All other Senators are really only allowed to raise one item. I just want to remind Members of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">Senator Lawlor has ambitions to be a leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_43">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">When Senators are addressing matters, I urge them to get to their main item straightaway because they are really only allowed to raise one.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">(Interruptions).</summary>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_44">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">I just wanted to remind the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KevinHumphreys" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Senator Kevin Humphreys<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">I echo the comments made by a previous Senator about public transport and certainly in terms of Irish Rail. We do need reliable rail transport. When a person boards a train, he or she should have a reasonable expectation to arrive on time, no matter whether it is on the northside or the southside of the city. Above all, what we need is investment in public transport. We need reliable public transport. If we are going to reduce carbon emissions, we need a proper public service. Above all, we need a Minister who cares about transport, not just about granny grants. We need a Minister who cares about transport, not just about judicial appointments.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GerardPCraughwell" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Senator Gerard P. Craughwell<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">Or Stepaside.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KevinHumphreys" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Senator Kevin Humphreys<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">Above all, we need a Minister who will concentrate on his brief and provide a proper public transport service for the country. I call on my colleagues in the Government and Fine Gael to try to ensure we get Ministers who care about their portfolios, not about everything else. What is happening across the country in areas ranging from the carbon tax to public transport and the fodder crisis is that we have Ministers who do not really matter and do not really care about their portfolios.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">Name them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KevinHumphreys" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Senator Kevin Humphreys<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">I just did.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Senator Mark Daly<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">Senator Humphreys was a Minister of State.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">Senator Humphreys has only mentioned one Minister. He said "Ministers," plural.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_52">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">Order, please.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AidanDavitt" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Senator Aidan Davitt<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">I want to say a couple of things about the budget. I welcome the introduction by the Government of one stage approval by councils when it comes to building new, affordable and mainly social homes. I think it was led through discussions involving Deputies Cowen and Michael McGrath. Every council in the country now has a fund of €6 million and does not have to ask the Government or go further than the county manager. That is the least amount the councils have to spend. I want to know the timeframe and, most importantly, what procedures will be put in place to ensure county managers, with the help of their councillors, identify sites and build houses on them as soon as possible. The initiative should streamline the process. The councils do not have to go looking for the moneys and the fund is available to spend immediately. The initiative should speed up the process, but I am keen to learn more about the procedures.</p>
          <p eId="para_123"> Yesterday there was almost a 50% increase in VAT for hotels and restaurants announced in the budget. The rate of 9% VAT has been increased to 13.5%. The increase was very extreme. a slower increase spanning a couple of budgets would have been the way forward, particularly in rural Ireland. As the Leader knows, rural Ireland will suffer the most from the increase. As trade in the bigger establishments in Dublin is booming and thriving, they will not be as badly affected as rural restaurants and hotels, as outlined by the Restaurants Association of Ireland and the Irish Hotels Federation. Hotels and restaurants in provincial towns will be massively affected by the increase in VAT.</p>
          <p eId="para_124">It will definitely cost jobs. Since 2011 the hospitality sector has provided an extra 65,000 jobs and this will certainly do some harm in that area.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinConway" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Senator Martin Conway<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">I acknowledge and salute the fact that this is International Day of the Girl, but I wish to point out that it is also World Sight Day, which helps to raise awareness of issues of blindness and visual impairment. It is a fact that four out of every five people in this country who lose their sight do so unnecessarily. I appeal to people on World Sight Day to have their eyesight checked. Once a person turns 50 years, he or she should have his or her eyes checked, preferably every year but certainly every two years. There are opticians throughout the country who are exceptionally well qualified, very professional and very dedicated to what they do. They can perform an eye check on someone very quickly and will make a referral if there is an issue. The easiest way to ensure people retain their eyesight is by having it checked and dealing quickly with whatever issues might arise. Time is of the essence.</p>
          <p eId="para_126"> I request of the Leader that we have a debate with the Minister for Health in this Chamber at some stage in the not too distant future on the subject of sight loss. It is worrying that we have too many people on waiting lists for cataract surgery and other eye related care. We should always strive to reduce and ultimately eliminate any significant waiting list in this area because the use of their eyes is something many people take for granted, but those of us who do not have full eyesight would never take it for granted.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_55">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">Very well said.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FintanWarfield" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Senator Fintan Warfield<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">I wish to talk about young people in the context of the budget and express my disappointment that those who are under the age of 26 have yet again been left out in the cold. From March, those aged 18 to 24 years will receive €112.70 and those aged 25, €157.80, while everyone else will receive €203 a week. The financial disparity in this measure is frightfully ageist. It treats as children those who are legally adults and have adult financial responsibilities. This discrimination creates a poverty trap which the likes of Focus Ireland have stated is one of the biggest contributors to youth homelessness. We should remember that youth unemployment is double the overall rate. I call on the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection to come to this House. She boasted about a €361.6 million expenditure increase in the social welfare budget. This could have been catered for on a phased basis.</p>
          <p eId="para_129"> We should also remember that every €1 spent on youth services saves the State €2.20 in the long run. Youth work took a 31% cut during the crisis. It still has not benefited from the recovery. Yesterday the National Youth Council of Ireland expressed its disappointment at the Government's announcement of just €1.5 million in additional funding for youth services. In the youth work sector we are talking about 1,400 staff supported by 40,000 volunteers and supporting 380,000 young people. With further resources, youth organisations could make an even greater contribution towards addressing issues of youth unemployment, social exclusion and poverty. There will be a growing demand for these services as the youth population hits 1 million by 2025.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">Like my colleague, Senator Conway-Walsh, I attended yesterday evening the presentation in the audiovisual room on autism assistance dogs, which was arranged by our colleague Deputy Cahill. Like other colleagues from this and the Lower House who attended, I was very impressed by the positive impact the dogs have not only on young people in improving the way they live their lives but also on their families. Autism Assistance Dogs Ireland made a very emotional presentation on how the dogs had transformed the lives of their children and made a plea that €500,000 be put aside annually for the training of 20 dogs. Even though the organisation has more than 250 young people on a waiting list, this is all it is requesting the State provide. Until now, the dogs have been provided by charitable organisations. I very much support the call for this money to be provided annually.</p>
          <p eId="para_131"> I support my colleague Senator Gallagher in his comments on tourism, particularly on the neglect of the part of the country from which we come, namely, the Cavan-Monaghan area, and the midlands. We are part of a tourism promotional area called Ireland's Ancient East, even though we are in the midlands and, in the case of counties Cavan and Leitrim, veering towards the west. While some other regions that have been designated have had huge success, I think we are entitled to a specially designated tourism area covering the north midlands.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">I thank the 15 Members of the House for their contributions on the Order of Business. I will begin by again paying tribute to Emma Mhic Mhathúna, to whom Senator Bacik and other Members referred, to the other lady who died, to all victims of cancer and to all the victims of the CervicalCheck screening programme. As Senator Byrne said, Dr. Scally was before the Joint Committee on Health yesterday. It is imperative that answers be given and that accountability be the order of the day. No words can adequately condemn the way in which women have been treated in the cervical cancer screening debacle. The real terms are that Emma Mhic Mhathúna should not be where she is today. She should still be very much with us. We must all put in place a process such that this will never happen again.</p>
          <p eId="para_133"> On International Day of the Girl, it is important to acknowledge the day, support and empower young women across the world and in our own country and help them to overcome adversity, as many Senators said. UNICEF estimates that 600 million young girls will start work in the next decade. It is important that we provide for these young women to have the tools to develop and reach their full potential not only in their professional lives but also in their personal lives. As Senator Lawlor rightly said, there are young women across the world who are living in absolute poverty and being treated abysmally and appallingly. It is our duty and job, not only as legislators but also as citizens, to ensure as we celebrate so proudly Votáil 100, on which I again commend Senator Bacik and all those involved, gender should not be about repression, denial or discrimination. We must all work to ensure, on International Day of the Girl, women will take their rightful place in all nations of the world.</p>
          <p eId="para_134"> Senator Ardagh raised the issue of broadband. The Government is committed to the national broadband plan. To support the plan, €87 million has been put in place, in addition to cybersecurity measures and the promotion of digital skills among small businesses and citizens.</p>
          <p eId="para_135">It is important to recognise that the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Naughten, and the Government are determined to have the national broadband plan unfurled. It is also important to recognise, as Senator Ardagh rightly said, that funding is required by many small and medium enterprises nationally. That is why the national broadband plan is so important to the Government and it is being rolled out across the country under the programme for Government. To provide the House with some figures, I note that in April last year Eir signed a commitment agreement with the Department on its plan to provide high speed broadband for 300,000 premises in rural areas on a commercial basis. The commitment signed between the Minister and Eir does not reflect the limit but rather is a beginning. Equally, the intervention strategy of the Government for download speeds is one we are committed to seeing through. We all acknowledge that broadband is now a necessity in rural Ireland. I hope that in the lifetime of the Government we will see the plan brought to fruition.</p>
          <p eId="para_136"> I note in response to Senator Victor Boyhan that the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government will attend the House next week to discuss the issue of housing. The matter of the Land Development Agency will, I am sure, form part of that discussion. I hope the Charleton report will be published today. I have not had sight of it, but I certainly hope, as many of us on this side of the House said at the time, that it will find that a good woman, namely, Deputy Fitzgerald, was hounded from ministerial office by many here who called on her to go. They were looking, as Senator Boyhan said, for a political head. I hope the report will exonerate her.</p>
          <p eId="para_137"> I thank Senator Black for her commitment to support the passage of the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill which is landmark legislation. I commend our colleague and friend Senator Reilly who, as Minister for Health, brought forward the Bill with the former Minister of State, Alex White, following its gestation in committee. Yesterday it was passed under the Minister, Deputy Harris. It is very important to understand the Government is committed to tackling the misuse of alcohol in Ireland.</p>
          <p eId="para_138"> Senator Ivana Bacik raised a number of matters, including the equality proofing of budgets. The Committee on Budgetary Oversight is producing a report which is imminent. On foot of its publication, I will be happy to have a debate in the House on this important matter. </p>
          <p eId="para_139"> The Senator also referred to climate change. I do not want to repeat my remarks in the last couple of days, but climate change is the global challenge of this and the next generation. It is important in the post-budget debate to discuss things sensibly and with a view to creating a long-term plan, rather than have a short or medium-term reaction to two very important reports. The national development plan commits to spending €1 of every €5 on climate change measures. On the issue of sustainability, the Department's new climate change action fund of €500 million will support a broad range of innovative projects. It will also help Ireland to address its climate change and energy targets. I accept, however, that we have a road to travel. I refer to the Minister's comments in the Budget Statement on the Paris Agreement commitments.</p>
          <p eId="para_140"> I always hear Senator Humphreys when he embarks on his daily mantra against the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross. I acknowledge that the Senator has to be that adversarial politician at times, but it is becoming a little like the Abbey, or perhaps it is like the Gaiety or the Opera House in Cork. We will soon be in pantomime season and telling the Senator, "He's behind you," to which he will reply, "Oh no, he's not." Deputy Shane Ross is the line Minister with responsibility for transport-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AidanDavitt" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Senator Aidan Davitt<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">And Garda stations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvanaBacik" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Senator Ivana Bacik<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">And judicial appointments.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">-----and overseeing new investment in public transport.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_62">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">All Senators will have an opportunity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">The Minister is implementing an ambitious public transport plan for the types of vehicle we use.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">Has the Leader ever heard of Dickie Rock?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_65">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">Order, please.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_148">I did not hear what Senator Diarmuid Wilson said.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_67">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">I ask the Leader to respond, without interruption. We are trying to get through the business ordered.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">The term "eunuch" comes to mind, but I will not paraphrase what Deputy Barry Cowen said.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_69">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">We are not giving out any address.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_70">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">Order, please.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">The Government has set an ambitious plan to have all new cars in 2030 zero-emissions capable. It is one of the most ambitious plans in Europe. Budget 2019 introduces a 1% VRT surcharge for new and imported diesel cars, in addition to an investment of €13 million in support of the use of electric vehicles. It also provides for the extension of VRT relief for hybrid cars to the end of 2019 and the 0% benefit-in-kind rate for electric vehicles for a further three years. In addition, there will be increased investment in public transport under Project Ireland 2040. I will be happy to have another debate on Project Ireland 2040 to remind Members opposite of what the Government is committed to doing in capital investment terms.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">Fiction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">In addition, an investment of €9 million is being made to improve the public lighting network which will cut lighting costs for local authorities by 50%. All new buses bought for Bus Éireann which covers rural Ireland and Dublin Bus will be low emissions vehicles. I repeat for Senator Kevin Humphreys that the Government is committed to ensuring no further coal will be burned at Moneypoint after 2025. These are just some of the things we are doing in the budget to tackle climate change.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvanaBacik" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Senator Ivana Bacik<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">It is the things the Government is not doing that are important.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_75">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">As I said in the last couple of days and will say again-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_76">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">The Leader does not have to. I do not want anybody to repeat anything.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">On climate change, the Leader could contribute by speaking less.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_78">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">I call for order and the Leader to speak, without interruption.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_79">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">That is the best suggestion Senator Wilson has made all day. </p>
          <p eId="para_162"> I agree fully with Senator Bacik on the need for freedom of the press and to support members of the media in reporting unhindered and having access to institutions. We can never condemn in anything other than the strongest terms the deaths of journalists or interference with their work. We have had a tragic case this week, as outlined by the Senator. It is reprehensible. We cherish having a free and independent press. We may not like some of the things journalists write, but that is their prerogative. I hope the Saudi Arabian journalist who is missing in Turkey will be found safe and well because we must at all times uphold the freedom of the press.</p>
          <p eId="para_163"> Senator Robbie Gallagher mentioned Ireland's Ancient East. My understanding is it is Fáilte Ireland, not the Government, that engages in the relevant promotional activities. To be fair to the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Heather Humphreys, she is doing a great job in championing County Monaghan, as Senator Reilly is doing with County Cavan being part of his brief. I am sure he is ably assisted by Senator Diarmuid Wilson. I am not familiar with the issue Senator Gallagher raised, but I did a quick check on Google on which I found images of County Monaghan and many other parts of Ireland's Ancient East. If the Senator has an issue, it might be best to communicate with Fáilte Ireland or raise it by way of a Commencement matter.</p>
          <p eId="para_164"> It is important to recognise, as Senator Davitt noted, the importance of the tourism sector. As the Leas-Chathaoirleach knows well, coming from beauty's home in Killarney, the tourism industry had the benefit of a temporary measure for seven years. The former Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, introduced the measure to create jobs in a sector which now has 235,000 people in employment, while visitor numbers are at an all-time high. What we must now do is ensure Ireland is marketed properly, including the areas to which Senator Davitt referred where there are insufficient numbers of visitors.</p>
          <p eId="para_165">That is why there is an increase of over €35 million in the budget for the tourism offering. That is for the purpose of allowing us to better manage the industry's success of recent years. There is a sting for members of Retail Excellence Ireland and those involved the restaurant sector. People do not want high prices. The sector can refer to myriad costs that have increased, but we must get the balance right. I will be happy to have a debate on this issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_166"> I commend the Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Griffin, on securing extra moneys for tourism promotion. The moneys realised from the increase in the VAT rate will go towards investment in housing, healthcare and other public services.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AidanDavitt" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Senator Aidan Davitt<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">I just want to clarify the matter for the Leader. Restaurants, with the Restaurants Association of Ireland, have been responsible regarding the rate, but other tourism sectors may have not been as much.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">I think some of it is correct, but in certain places-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_82">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">I cannot allow in other speakers. The Leader should reply through the Chair.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_170">Gabh mo leithscéal, a Chathaoirligh. In certain places prices are unacceptably high. We must give value for money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AidanDavitt" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Senator Aidan Davitt<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">We disagree.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">I will support the restaurant sector across the board.</p>
          <p eId="para_173"> Senator Reilly referred to changes to the Iarnród Éireann timetable. I do not have the relevant information to hand, but it is important to acknowledge that there is a need to bring balance to timetabling. I support Senator Reilly in that regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_174"> Senators Conway-Walsh and Wilson referred to autism assistance dogs. Irish Guide Dogs in Cork has a similar scheme. It is a wonderful initiative to provide support for people. I congratulate those involved in Clonakilty on their autism-friendly approach and making it a better place in which to live. I will be happy for the Minister responsible to attend the House for a debate on the matter.</p>
          <p eId="para_175"> Senator Lawlor referred to the €17 billion health budget. There is a need for accountability and a debate on the service plan. Yesterday I said there was no accountability or questioning of executives. I hope that will happen in the future.</p>
          <p eId="para_176"> We all welcome the amount of money allocated for housing in the budget. It is important to recognise it. We want to see people living in their own homes.</p>
          <p eId="para_177"> Senator Conway mentioned that this was World Sight Day and that four out of every five people who lost their sight lost it unnecessarily. More work needs to be done to raise awareness of this issue. It is important that people go to their optician to have their eyesight checked.</p>
          <p eId="para_178"> Senator Warfield referred to the disparity in the youth part of the budget. To be fair to the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Zappone, she has seen an increase in the budgets for youth work, childcare and a package to tackle child poverty. The point the Senator made about the social protection budget was about activation measures and people being able to find a job. We will be happy to have a debate on the matter in due course.</p>
          <p eId="para_179"> The current forecast for Storm Callum warns of 130 km/h winds that will pose a risk to life and property. I hope people will take care and check on their elderly neighbours. A clear code warning has been issued by Met Éireann. I hope the emergency services will be assisted by people in not taking risks but in being cautious.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7"> Order of Business agreed to.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="motion" eId="dbsect_9">
        <heading>EU Regulations: Motions<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">I move:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_181">That Seanad Éireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_182">Proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Regulation (EC) No. 1393/2007 of the European Parliament and of the Council on the service in the Member States of judicial and extrajudicial documents in civil or commercial matters (service of documents),</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_183">a copy of which was laid before Seanad Éireann on 21 June 2018.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8"> Question put and agreed to.</summary>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_87">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">I move:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_185">That Seanad Éireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_186">Proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Council Regulation (EC) No 1206/2001 of 28 May, 2001 on cooperation between the courts of the Member States in the taking of evidence in civil or commercial matters,</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_187">a copy of which was laid before Seanad Éireann on 6 July 2018.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_9"> Question put and agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_10">
          <i> Sitting suspended at 12.35 p.m. and resumed at 12.45 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" refersTo="#bill.2018.40.seanad.3_sub" eId="dbsect_10">
        <heading>Criminal Justice (Money Laundering and Terrorist Financing) (Amendment) Bill 2018: Committee and Remaining Stages<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <summary eId="sum_11">Sections 1 to 13, inclusive, agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_12">SECTION 14</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_13"> Government amendment No. 1:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_14">In page 19, line 13, after “customer” to insert “to the extent reasonably warranted by the risk of money laundering or terrorist financing”.</summary>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice_and_Equality" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality (Deputy David Stanton)<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">This amendment relates to the requirement for a designated person to monitor customers with whom he or she has a business relationship. The words to be inserted make it clear that the monitoring is to be done only to the extent that it is warranted by the risk in a particular case of money laundering or terrorist financing. This is in line with the directive which mandates a risk-based approach to consumer due diligence.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_15"> Amendment agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_16"> Section 14, as amended, agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_17"> Section 15 agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_18">SECTION 16</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_19"> Government amendment No. 2:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_20">In page 20, between lines 21 and 22, to insert the following:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_21">“(e) in subsection (5), by the insertion of “or financial institution” after “a credit institution”.”.</summary>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" eId="spk_89" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice_and_Equality">
          <from>Deputy David Stanton<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">This measure relates to customer due diligence measures for politically exposed persons. In general, they must be carried out before a customer opens an account. However, a bank can allow an account to be opened without first carrying out the measures as long as no transactions are carried out. The amendment extends that exception to all financial institutions in line with the directive.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_22"> Amendment agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_23"> Section 16, as amended, agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_24"> Sections 17 to 19, inclusive, agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_25">SECTION 20</summary>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Acting Chairman (Senator Diarmuid Wilson)<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">Amendments Nos. 3 and 4 are related and may be discussed together.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_26"> Government amendment No. 3:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_27">In page 24, lines 26 and 27, to delete “and subsection (4)(b),”.</summary>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" eId="spk_91" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice_and_Equality">
          <from>Deputy David Stanton<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">These are technical amendments. They relate to the conditions under which a designated person can rely on a third party to carry out anti-money-laundering measures on his or her behalf. Under the current requirement, the person must be satisfied that the third party will provide him or her with relevant documents or information. The amendments clarify that it is not necessary if certain circumstances apply including that the person and the third party are part of the same group. This is in line with Article 28 of the directive.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_28"> Amendment agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_29"> Government amendment No. 4:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_30">In page 25, lines 1 to 4, to delete all words from “satisfied” in line 1 down to and including “requirements” where it secondly occurs in line 4 and substitute “satisfied that the circumstances specified in paragraphs (a) to (c) of subsection (1A) exist”.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_31"> Amendment agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_32"> Section 20, as amended, agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_33"> Sections 21 and 22 agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_34">NEW SECTION</summary>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_92">
          <from>Acting Chairman (Senator Diarmuid Wilson)<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">Amendments Nos. 5 and 12 are related and may be discussed together.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_35"> Government amendment No. 5:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_36">In page 27, between lines 11 and 12, to insert the following:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_37">“<b>Amendment of section 44 of Act of 2010</b></summary>
        <summary eId="sum_38"><b>23.</b> Section 44 of the Act of 2010 is amended by the deletion of “or 43” in both places where it occurs.”.</summary>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" eId="spk_93" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice_and_Equality">
          <from>Deputy David Stanton<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">The purpose of the amendments is to remove a requirement to report to An Garda Síochána and the Revenue Commissioners all transactions related to what is known as a high-risk third country. Such a country is not considered to have adequate controls for money laundering purposes. This requirement is considered to be unnecessarily broad when complying with the new European Commission designation of states as high-risk. It would also be unduly burdensome for An Garda Síochána and the divisions involved.</p>
          <p eId="para_194"> There is already a general requirement to report any transaction that is suspicious. Almost 25,000 reports were received by An Garda Síochána under this requirement last year. The Bill also contains an obligation to employ enhanced due diligence in respect of customers from high-risk third countries.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiallODonnghaile" eId="spk_94">
          <from>Senator Niall Ó Donnghaile<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">Perhaps the Minister of State might provide some further clarity on amendment No. 5. The amendment involves the deletion of section 23 and involves the deletion of references to section 43 of the parent Act. The section removes the defence, under section 43 of the parent Act, relating to the use of internal reporting procedure established by an employer for the purpose of facilitating the operation of the section in question. If I understand it correctly, the amendment would remove as a defence for a breach the requirement for designated persons to report transactions connected with places that have inadequate procedures in place for detection of money laundering or terrorist financing. I presume this is the reason for the existing section 23, which would have substituted section 43 of the parent Act, and it is no longer required as the section will remain as it is. It seems a defence will no longer be available for using internal reporting procedures. Will the Minister of State clarify the matter for me? It is not entirely clear to me.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" eId="spk_95" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice_and_Equality">
          <from>Deputy David Stanton<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_196">I am not fully sure what Senator Ó Donnghaile is getting at. There is a general requirement to report any transaction that is suspicious. Almost 25,000 reports were received by An Garda Síochána last year under this requirement. The Bill has an obligation to apply enhanced due diligence in respect of consumers from high-risk countries. Adequate safeguards are already in place. The current measures are considered unduly burdensome for An Garda Síochána and the businesses involved. It is unworkable at the end of the day. We believe there is enough in the legislation as it is to keep the safeguards in place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiallODonnghaile" eId="spk_96">
          <from>Senator Niall Ó Donnghaile<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">That is fair enough.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_39"> Amendment agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_40"> Sections 23 to 26, inclusive, agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_41">SECTION 27</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_42"> Government amendment No. 6:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_43">In page 31, line 12, after “direction” to insert “in writing”.</summary>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" eId="spk_97" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice_and_Equality">
          <from>Deputy David Stanton<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">The amendment relates to the power of An Garda Síochána to direct that documents and records be kept beyond the normal five-year retention period. It inserts the safeguard that the direction must be given in writing.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_44"> Amendment agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_45"> Section 27, as amended, agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_46"> Sections 28 to 33, inclusive, agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_47">SECTION 34</summary>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_98">
          <from>Acting Chairman (Senator Diarmuid Wilson)<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">Amendments Nos. 7, 8 and 11 are related and may be discussed together.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiallODonnghaile" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Senator Niall Ó Donnghaile<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">I might come in on amendment No. 11.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_48"> Government amendment No. 7:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_49">In page 35, line 37, to delete “section 109” and substitute “section 108”.</summary>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" eId="spk_100" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice_and_Equality">
          <from>Deputy David Stanton<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">This amendment is to transpose part of Article 37, namely, the second paragraph of the fourth money laundering directive. The provision requires that managers and beneficial owners and providers of gambling services be fit and proper persons. The amendment inserts five new sections. It requires that anyone who is a person directing a private members' gambling club or a beneficial owner of such a club to hold a certificate of fitness. It will be an offence for such a person not to hold a certificate of fitness. The rest of the provisions set out the procedure for applying for a certificate. The application is made to An Garda Síochána. If a person does not reside in the State, it is made to the Minister. A certificate can be refused if a person has been convicted of certain offences. The certificate lasts for three years. There is provision for an appeal to the District Court against the refusal to grant a certificate.</p>
          <p eId="para_202"> Amendments Nos. 7 and 8 are consequential and relate to the numbering of a different section. The committee will be aware of the wider work on gambling that the Government is undertaking. We have approved the establishment of an independent gambling regulator. I have chaired a working group of reform in this area which has recently completed this work. While broader proposals are being developed, the provisions will allow us to ensure persons involved in this sector are fit and proper persons and that our EU obligations are met.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiallODonnghaile" eId="spk_101">
          <from>Senator Niall Ó Donnghaile<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">I welcome amendment No. 11. We will be supporting it. We have raised the issue on various Stages of the Bill. I discussed the matter with the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Flanagan, in the House some weeks ago. The wider issues of the regulation of the betting and gambling industries and gambling control are for another day. However, Sinn Féin contends that the Department has not made sufficient progress on this issue. Having said that, I welcome the amendment because at least it is a step in the right direction. I hope we can build on it and see further regulation in terms of what is required to counter the use of gambling and private members' clubs and gambling activities to launder money. Why does the measure not include bookmakers? I would have thought that was a glaring and obvious avenue where the same practice could occur.</p>
          <p eId="para_204"> I welcome the amendment.</p>
          <p eId="para_205">However, I add a health warning that we probably could have done more and done better on this issue. We should certainly look to do so in the future.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Acting Chairman (Senator Diarmuid Wilson)<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">Does the Minister of State wish to respond?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" eId="spk_103" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice_and_Equality">
          <from>Deputy David Stanton<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">I am informed that bookmakers are already subject to fitness and probity requirements under the Betting Acts.</p>
          <p eId="para_208"> On the other issue of gambling, I agree and I am disappointed that we have not been able to make more progress on it. Before the end of this session I hope to have the miscellaneous provisions (lotteries and raffles) Bill produced. It is extraordinarily complicated and this area is changing by the day. We had a debate here last week on loot boxes, which again is a significant area. I am aware that some other countries in Europe are also seriously looking at this. We are making progress on it. Our working group had five long, detailed meetings with the intergovernmental Departments involved. There is a report being worked on for the Government to move this matter forward. I am determined to get it right and quite anxious that we move on it as quickly as possible.</p>
          <p eId="para_209"> I thank the Senator for his support on this amendment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiallODonnghaile" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Senator Niall Ó Donnghaile<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">That is welcome to hear and I do not doubt the Minister of State's bona fides on this issue. I wanted to take the opportunity to raise it as it looks as if we are going to go through the Bill quite rapidly today. It was a marker that was put down, because it is an important issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_50"> Amendment agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_51"> Government amendment No. 8: </summary>
        <summary eId="sum_52">In page 36, line 1, to delete "<b>109A. </b>(1) Subject" and substitute "<b>108A. </b>(1) Subject".</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_53"> Amendment agreed to.</summary>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_105">
          <from>Acting Chairman (Senator Diarmuid Wilson)<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">Amendment No. 9 is a Government amendment. Amendments Nos. 9 and 10 are related and may be discussed together, by agreement. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_54"> Government amendment No. 9:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_55">In page 36, line 28, after "of" where it firstly occurs to insert "paragraph (a) of".</summary>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" eId="spk_106" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice_and_Equality">
          <from>Deputy David Stanton<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">The purpose of the amendments is to correct a cross-reference.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_56"> Amendment agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_57"> Government amendment No. 10:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_58">In page 36, line 29, to delete "section 24(1)(a)" and substitute "section 24(1)".</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_59"> Amendment agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_60"> Section 34, as amended, agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_61">NEW SECTION</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_62"> Government amendment No. 11:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_63">In page 37, between lines 17 and 18, to insert the following:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_64">
          <b>"Managers and beneficial owners of private members’ clubs - certificates of fitness</b>
        </summary>
        <summary eId="sum_65"><b>35.</b> The Act of 2010 is amended by the insertion of the following sections after section 109:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_66">
          <b>"Managers and beneficial owners of private members’ clubs to hold</b>
        </summary>
        <summary eId="sum_67">
          <b>certificates of fitness</b>
        </summary>
        <summary eId="sum_68"><b>109A.</b>(1) An individual who—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_69">(a) effectively directs a private members’ club at which gambling activities are carried on, or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_70">(b) is a beneficial owner of a private members’ club at which gambling activities are carried on,</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_71">shall hold a certificate of fitness and probity (referred to in this section and sections 109B, 109C, 109D and 109E as a ‘certificate of fitness’) granted by a Superintendent of the Garda Síochána or, as the case may be, by the Minister.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_72">(2) An individual who fails to comply with subsection (1) commits an offence and is liable—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_73">(a) on summary conviction, to a fine not exceeding €5,000 or imprisonment for a term not exceeding 12 months, or both, or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_74">(b) on conviction on indictment to a fine or imprisonment for a term not exceeding 5 years, or both.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_75">(3) Where on the date that is 6 months from the coming into force of this section an individual has applied for a certificate of fitness, this section shall not apply to that individual until such time as the application, and any appeal in relation to the application, has been finally determined.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_76">
          <b>Application for certificate of fitness</b>
        </summary>
        <summary eId="sum_77"><b>109B</b>.(1) Upon compliance with subsection (2), an individual shall make an application for a certificate of fitness—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_78">(a) where the individual ordinarily resides in the State—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_79">(i) to the Superintendent of the Garda Síochána for the district in which he or she ordinarily resides, or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_80">(ii) to the Superintendent of the Garda Síochána for the district in which the private members’ club concerned is located or is proposed to be located,</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_81">or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_82">(b) where the individual ordinarily resides outside the State, to the Minister.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_83">(2) An individual intending to apply for a certificate of fitness under this section shall, not later than 14 days and not earlier than one month before making the application, publish in two daily newspapers circulating in the State, a notice in such form as may be prescribed, of his or her intention to make the application.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_84">(3) An application for a certificate of fitness under this section shall be in such form as may be prescribed.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_85">(4) The applicant for a certificate of fitness shall provide the Superintendent of the Garda Síochána, or as the case may be the Minister, to whom the application concerned is made with all such information as he or she may reasonably require for the purposes of determining whether a relevant consideration referred to in section 109C exists.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_86">(5) A Superintendent of the Garda Síochána, or as the case may be the Minister, to whom an application for a certificate of fitness is duly made under this section shall, not later than 56 days after receiving the application, either—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_87">(a) grant the application and issue a certificate of fitness to the applicant, or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_88">(b) refuse the application.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_89">(6) A certificate of fitness under this section shall be in such form as may be prescribed.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_90">(7) An individual who, in applying for a certificate of fitness under this section, makes a statement or provides information to a Superintendent of the Garda Síochána or, as the case may be, to the Minister, that he or she knows, or ought reasonably to know, is false or misleading in a material respect commits an offence and is liable—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_91">(a) on summary conviction to a class A fine or imprisonment for a term not exceeding 6 months, or both, or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_92">(b) on conviction on indictment to a fine not exceeding €50,000 or imprisonment for a term not exceeding 2 years, or both.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_93">(8) A Superintendent of the Garda Síochána shall, as soon as may be after making a decision in relation to an application for a certificate of fitness, notify the Minister in writing of that decision.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_94">
          <b>Grounds of refusal to grant certificate of fitness</b>
        </summary>
        <summary eId="sum_95"><b>109C.</b>(1) A Superintendent of the Garda Síochána or, as the case may be, the Minister shall not refuse an application for a certificate of fitness made in accordance with section 109B unless—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_96">(a) a relevant consideration exists, or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_97">(b) he or she is not satisfied that the applicant has provided such information as he or she reasonably requires for the purposes of determining whether a relevant consideration exists.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_98">(2) For the purposes of subsection (1), a relevant consideration exists if—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_99">(a) the applicant stands convicted of an offence under—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_100">(i) an enactment relating to excise duty on betting,</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_101">(ii) the Gaming and Lotteries Acts 1956 to 2013,</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_102">(iii) section 1078 of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997,</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_103">(iv) the Criminal Justice (Theft and Fraud Offences) Act 2001, or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_104">(v) this Act,</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_105">(b) the applicant stands convicted of an offence under the law of a place (other than the State)—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_106">(i) consisting of an act or omission that, if committed in the State, would constitute an offence referred to in paragraph (a), or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_107">(ii) relating to the conduct of gambling,</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_108">or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_109">(c) the applicant was previously refused a certificate of fitness and either—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_110">(i) the applicant did not appeal the refusal, or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_111">(ii) on appeal to the District Court, the refusal was affirmed.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_112">(3) In this section, ‘enactment’ means—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_113">(a) an Act of the Oireachtas,</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_114">(b) a statute that was in force in Saorstát Éireann immediately before the date of the coming into operation of the Constitution and that continues in force by virtue of Article 50 of the Constitution,</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_115">(c) an instrument made under—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_116">(i) an Act of the Oireachtas, or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_117">(ii) a statute referred to in paragraph (b).</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_118">
          <b>Duration of certificate of fitness</b>
        </summary>
        <summary eId="sum_119"><b>109D.</b>(1) A certificate of fitness shall remain in force until the expiration of 3 years after the date on which the certificate was issued.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_120">(2) If, before the expiration of a certificate of fitness, the individual to whom it was issued makes an application for a new certificate of fitness, the first-mentioned certificate of fitness shall remain in force—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_121">(a) until the issue of the new certificate of fitness,</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_122">(b) in circumstances where the application is refused by the Superintendent of the Garda Síochána concerned or by the Minister and the individual does not make a request referred to in section 109E(1), until the expiration of the period within which the request may be made,</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_123">(c) in circumstances where the application is refused by the Superintendent of the Garda Síochána concerned or by the Minister and the individual makes a request referred to in section 109E(1) but does not bring an appeal under that section, until the expiration of the period specified in subsection (3) of that section, or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_124">(d) in circumstances where the application is refused by the Superintendent of the Garda Síochána concerned or the Minister and the individual appeals the refusal in accordance with section 109E, until—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_125">(i) the District Court affirms the refusal in accordance with that section, or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_126">(ii) the issue of a new certificate of fitness pursuant to a direction of the District Court under subsection (4)(b) of that section.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_127">
          <b>Appeal where application for certificate of fitness is refused</b>
        </summary>
        <summary eId="sum_128"><b>109E.</b>(1) If a Superintendent of the Garda Síochána, or as the case may be, the Minister refuses an application for a certificate of fitness, he or she shall, on the request in writing of the applicant made not later than 14 days after the refusal, give the applicant a statement in writing of the reasons for the refusal.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_129">(2) A person to whom a certificate of fitness has been refused may, not later than 14 days after receiving a statement in writing under subsection (1), appeal the refusal to the District Court.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_130">(3) A person who brings an appeal under this section shall, in such manner and within such period as may be prescribed give notice of the appeal to the Superintendent of the Garda Síochána concerned or, as the case may be, the Minister.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_131">(4) The District Court may, upon an appeal under this section, either—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_132">(a) affirm the refusal, or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_133">(b) grant the appeal and direct the Superintendent of the Garda Síochána concerned, or as the case may be, the Minister to issue a certificate of fitness to the appellant.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_134">(5) The Superintendent of the Garda Síochána concerned or, as the case may be, the Minister shall comply with a direction of the District Court under this section not later than 3 days after the giving of the direction.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_135">(6) The respondent in an appeal under this section shall not be entitled to advance as a reason for opposing an appeal under this section a reason not specified in a statement of the reasons for a refusal given to the appellant pursuant to a request under subsection (1).</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_136">(7) If the District Court affirms a refusal under subsection (4)(a), it may also make an order requiring the appellant to pay the costs incurred by the respondent in defending the appeal and may determine the amount of such costs.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_137">(8) There shall be no appeal to the Circuit Court from a decision of the District Court under this section.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_138">(9) An appeal under this section by a person ordinarily resident in the State shall be brought before a judge of the District Court assigned to the District Court district—</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_139">(a) in which he or she ordinarily resides, or</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_140">(b) in which the private members’ club concerned is located or is proposed to be located.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_141">(10) An appeal under this section by a person not ordinarily resident in the State shall be brought before a judge of the District Court assigned to the Dublin Metropolitan District.".".</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_142"> Amendment agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_143"> Sections 35 to 38, inclusive, agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_144">SECTION 39</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_145"> Government amendment No. 12:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_146">In page 42, line 16, after "36" to insert ", 43".</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_147"> Amendment agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_148"> Section 39, as amended, agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_149"> Section 40 agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_150"> Title agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_151"> Bill reported with amendments and received for final consideration.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_152"> Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</summary>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Justice_and_Equality" eId="spk_107">
          <from>Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality (Deputy David Stanton)<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">I thank the Members of the House for facilitating the early move to Report and Final Stages of this very important legislation, with a view to concluding scrutiny of the Bill in this sitting of the Seanad. The support from and engagement by Senators on the Bill have been vital in bringing it so close to completion.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_153"> Question put and agreed to.</summary>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_108">
          <from>Acting Chairman (Senator Diarmuid Wilson)<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">When is it proposed to sit again?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinConway" eId="spk_109">
          <from>Senator Martin Conway<recordedTime time="2018-10-11T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">Next Tuesday at 2.30 p.m.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_154"> The Seanad adjourned at 1.05 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 16 October 2018.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
