<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2019-09-24/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2019-09-24/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2019-09-24" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/32/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2019-09-24/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2019-09-24/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2019-09-24" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2019-09-24/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2019-09-24/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-03-05" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="CatherineMartin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Catherine-Martin.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Catherine Martin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DonnchadhOLaoghaire" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Donnchadh-Ó-Laoghaire.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Donnchadh Ó Laoghaire"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FionaOLoughlin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Fiona-O'Loughlin.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Fiona O'Loughlin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JanOSullivan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jan-O'Sullivan.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Jan O'Sullivan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeMcHugh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-McHugh.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Joe McHugh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LynnRuane" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Lynn-Ruane.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Lynn Ruane"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaryButler" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mary-Butler.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Mary Butler"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulGavan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Gavan.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Paul Gavan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ThomasByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Thomas-Byrne.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Thomas Byrne"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_for_Education_and_Skills" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister/education__skills" showAs="Minister for Education and Skills"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM OIDEACHUS AGUS SCILEANNA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Education and Skills</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2019-09-24">Dé Máirt, 24 Meán Fómhair 2019</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2019-09-24">Tuesday, 24 September 2019</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#ThomasByrne">Thomas Byrne</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulGavan">Paul Gavan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#CatherineMartin">Catherine Martin</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#LynnRuane">Lynn Ruane.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#JanOSullivan">Jan O'Sullivan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#DonnchadhOLaoghaire">Donnchadh Ó Laoghaire.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">I láthair / In attendance: Deputy Mary Butler.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#FionaOLoughlin">Teachta / Deputy Fiona O'Loughlin sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Interim Report on Reduced Timetables: Minister for Education and Skills<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T15:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_1">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_9">Apologies have been received from Senator Maria Byrne. </p>
          <p eId="para_10"> We will engage with the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Mc Hugh, on the interim report on reduced timetables. We will deal with some housekeeping matters in private session afterwards. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_11"> I remind members to either turn off their mobile phones or switch them to flight mode as they interfere with the sound and broadcasting systems and make it difficult for the parliamentary reporters to report the proceedings of the meeting. Television coverage and web-streaming would also be adversely affected.</p>
          <p eId="para_12"> No. 1 on the agenda is, as mentioned, engagement with the Minister on the interim report on reduced timetables. I welcome him on behalf of the committee. Earlier this year it shone a light on a very worrying practice which had been hidden in plain sight for a long period, namely, reduced timetables. We held three stakeholder sessions, at which some of the evidence unveiled was, to be perfectly honest, quite shocking and appalling. While members of the committee welcomed the Minister's announcement yesterday that schools would be required to give formal notification to Tusla of the use of reduced timetables - one of the recommendations we made in the interim report - we will be seeking further information on the announcement and the proposed guidelines for notifications. It was quite ironic that the news was released yesterday prior to our engagement today, but we take it in the spirit in which we hope it was intended. I understand the Minister has to attend the Dáil to take two Topical Issue matters and that his time is tight; therefore, I ask both him and members to be very focused in the questions and answers throughout this engagement.</p>
          <p eId="para_13"> The format of the meeting will be that I will issue an invitation to the Minister to make an opening statement which will be followed by engagement with committee members. As the Minister is aware, the committee will be publishing his opening statement on its website following the meeting</p>
          <p eId="para_14"> I remind members of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against any person outside the Houses or an official, either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_15"> I invite the Minister to make his opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" as="#Minister_for_Education_and_Skills" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Minister for Education and Skills (Deputy Joe McHugh)<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_16">Gabhaim buíochas leis an gCathaoirleach agus leis an gcoiste fosta. I thank the joint committee for its invitation and affording me the opportunity to speak about the issue of reduced timetables. I also thank the representative bodies who presented on the issue at previous hearings for their input and contributions. </p>
          <p eId="para_17"> The basic aim of the Government is to use our economic success to build a fair and compassionate society. Equality of opportunity is at the heart of our vision. As I stated on many previous occasions and reiterate today, each and every child has a right to an education to enable him or her to live a full life and realise his or her potential. I have made my position clear that all pupils enrolled in a school should attend for the full day, unless exempt from doing so for exceptional circumstances. Reduced timetables are not in any way a standard aspect of a child’s experience of school and must not be allowed to become such; rather, they are an exceptional measure. While it may be necessary in some circumstances to use a reduced timetable, for example, as a means of assisting the reintegration of a pupil into a school routine, such arrangements should only be put in place in limited and time-bound circumstances. </p>
          <p eId="para_18"> Officials of my Department have been working closely with officials from the Department of Children and Youth Affairs and Tusla which is within the remit of that Department in the monitoring of and reporting on this practice to address the issues raised in the committe's interim report. A set of guidelines is being prepared jointly by my Department and the Department of Children and Youth Affairs and Tusla. The purpose of the guidelines is to provide clarity for school authorities and parents or guardians on the reporting of reduced timetables in schools to ensure their use is limited to those circumstances where it is absolutely necessary and, where in the rare circumstances such usage occurs, schools follow best practice, with the interests of the student to the fore. As is normal practice, prior to finalising the guidelines, my Department, the Department of Children and Youth Affairs and Tusla are arranging for a consultation process with education stakeholders, including the school management bodies. </p>
          <p eId="para_19"> Provision of support is critical and I want to highlight the investment the Government is making. This year’s education budget is €10.8 billion. This highlights the Government’s strong belief in and commitment to the power of education. Nearly €1 in every €5 of this year’s budget, or about €1.9 billion, is being invested in supporting children with special educational needs, including those with challenging behaviour, in school. This is the highest ever level of Government expenditure on special education. It provides for a continuum of special educational provision to be made available to children with special educational needs, including those with challenging behaviour, in order that, regardless of the level of need of the child, educational provision can be made for them. </p>
          <p eId="para_20"> The number of special education teachers has increased by 37%, from 9,740 in 2011 to over 13,400. The number of special needs assistants, SNAs, has risen by 51%, from 10,575 in 2011 to 15,950. Schools can now allocate additional teaching support to a child whose challenging behaviour is having a significant impact on his or her ability to learn in school. Children do not need a special educational needs diagnosis to access these supports and parents or guardians will no longer be required to have their child receive such a diagnosis. Schools may also access SNA support for children with additional care needs, including challenging behaviour. All schools can access in-school supports and continuous professional development through the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, to assist teachers in working with children who display challenging behaviour. </p>
          <p eId="para_21"> The number of specialist placements for children with complex special educational needs has also been significantly increased by the Government. Over 1,050 additional special placements have been provided in the new school year. There are now 1,621 special classes, compared to 548 in 2011, including 1,355 to cater for children with autism. Some 125 special schools, including a new special school to be established this year, also provide specialist education for students with complex special educational needs. These schools provide over 8,000 places compared to 6,848 in 2011.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> I note that the committee questioned whether SNA support was the most appropriate in dealing with a child’s challenging behaviour. As committee members are aware, the view of my Department and that of the NCSE is that students need the right support from the right person at the right time to achieve his or her full potential. To that end, a preschool and an in-school therapy demonstration project is being undertaken in 75 preschools and 75 schools to provide in-school therapeutic support for students. In addition, €4.75 million was allocated in budget 2019 for the trialling of a new school inclusion model of support to include in-school provision of behavioural practitioners, psychologists and regional support teams to build capacity in schools to meet the needs of their students. The outcome of the pilot scheme will inform future policy and service provision, including the provision of behavioural support. </p>
          <p eId="para_23"> The National Educational Psychological Service, NEPS, works with both primary and post-primary schools and is concerned with learning, behaviour, social and emotional development. The Government has recognised the valuable input of the NEPS for pupils and schools. Over its lifetime it has increased psychologist numbers from a sanctioned level of 173 whole-time equivalents in 2015 to 204 whole-time posts, with a commensurate increase in investment, from €18 million to €20.75 million per annum in the period.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">There are 190 posts in the system, with recruitment to fill 14 new posts and vacancies under way. Supports are also provided for DEIS schools, at an overall cost of €125 million for 891 schools serving approximately 190,000 pupils to improve attendance, retention and school participation. </p>
          <p eId="para_25"> Enhanced capitation payments for Traveller children in the system are provided, at a cost of €1.1 million. Actions are being progressed under the national Traveller and Roma inclusion strategy to improve education outcomes for Travellers, including a pilot project to target school attendance, retention and participation, commencing this September. Additional supports have been provided to support this pilot project in the form of home-school-community liaison officers funded by my Department, in addition to Traveller education workers funded by the Department of Justice and Equality and educational welfare officers employed by Tusla. </p>
          <p eId="para_26"> In summary, I anticipate that the guidelines and notification system will allow us to monitor the use of reduced timetables and, ultimately, address the issues raised. If parents have concerns about the use by a school of a reduced timetable for their child, they can contact their local educational welfare officer who has statutory responsibility for ensuring the rights of the child to an education are upheld and will advise them on the most appropriate action to take. My Department will continue to work closely with Tusla's educational welfare service and the NCSE to ensure that where in the very limited number of cases a reduced timetable is deemed to be necessary, such measures will be used for time-limited periods only. </p>
          <p eId="para_27"> I again thank the committee for highlighting this issue. I am aware that it is an interim report and that the committee will be working on new proposals and suggestions in the not too distant future. I look forward to working with and hearing from it in that regard. I thank the groups and individuals who have contributed. As a Government, we have demonstrated and will continue to work to realise our commitment to ensuring all children receive the fullest possible education. I am also very conscious that there are challenges and that parents and children are facing them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_28">I thank the Minister for his presentation. I am glad that various charities, including AsIAm, and the Traveller organisations highlighted this issue for the joint committee and that we put the spotlight on it at the start of the summer because as I noted then, the practice is a national scandal and must end. I think everybody sitting around the table is in agreement. What the Department states in reply to parliamentary questions is correct. The practice is different and I hate to say it, but the guidelines differ from it. The guidelines open everything up and that will not be acceptable to Fianna Fáil. We must start from the premise that every child has a legal right to an education. We cannot start from the premise that this practice is allowed if procedures are followed. That is what I worry will happen.</p>
          <p eId="para_29"> The Minister mentioned challenging behaviour quite a number of times. The committee does not have evidence that challenging behaviour is the primary reason for engaging in the practice. In fact, we do not have much evidence at all and we certainly do not have evidence that challenging behaviour is the reason for it. It should not be because in replies to parliamentary questions the Department states reduced timetables can only be in place for medical reasons. Therefore, I am not sure from where the reference to challenging behaviour comes. It can be dealt with in many other ways. The guidelines also do not address the issue of Travellers being disproportionately affected by reduced timetables. </p>
          <p eId="para_30"> I have been criticised by some teachers for highlighting this issue. They say they operate in difficult circumstances. I have no doubt that many of them do, but we all have a role to play in the education system, regardless of whether we are policymakers, Ministers or teachers, to ensure each child's right to an education is upheld. I would worry about anything the Minister proposed that moved away from the words of the Department in replies to parliamentary questions about exceptional cases and involved a return to a school acting on professional advice. Doing anything else would be wrong. </p>
          <p eId="para_31"> The representative from Tusla was excellent at the last meeting. I was delighted when he was very clear that where it was not done in accordance with the guidelines, it amounted to suspension or expulsion. I do not think that is mentioned in the information that is required to be given to parents. We must take a really hard line if we are to take the issue, the needs of children and their right to an education, seriously. The committee has blown it up. Schools need to get the message that this is not the way to deal with disciplinary issues. The premise of the Minister is almost that this is a disciplinary issue when it cannot be. Under the law, as he has set out in replies to parliamentary questions, disciplinary issues do not come into it at all. Therefore, I do not know why challenging behaviour has been mentioned, unless, of course, it is a medical issue, but it does not look like that. </p>
          <p eId="para_32"> The Minister mentioned the special school that is to be established this year. Will he confirm whether it has opened and, if not, when will it open? </p>
          <p eId="para_33"> I am not entirely satisfied, but I am glad that action is being taken. However, it requires a change of mindset - even on the part of parents. For all the good work they do, some advocacy organisations seem to think it could be possible to do it in circumstanes even broader than those outlined by the Minister as long as there are guidelines. I would take a much harder line. I do not think it should be possible, except where there are medical issues, as the Minister mentioned in replies to parliamentary questions. If schools cannot cope with children with special needs, clearly the required resources and training are not available and it is up to policymakers and the Government, in particular, to make sure they are provided. The bottom line is that each child is entitled to an education and there are no "ifs" or "buts. I am afraid that this document brings in a lot of "ifs" and "buts" and does not address a number of the recommendations we made during the summer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">I am not convinced that the guidelines released to the media yesterday ahead of this meeting will ensure the use of reduced timetables is the exception rather than the norm. I welcome the Minister's statement, but when one looks at it, one can see that it is seven pages long, with the issue of reduced timetables dealt with in three very small paragraphs on the last page. In the rest of it it seems that the Department is patting itself on the back, stating, "Aren't we great in the Department of Education and Skills.? This is what we are doing." However, it is not tackling the issue. On the form use, will the Minister consider requiring a school to document the other measures taken to deal with an issue before a child is placed on a reduced timetable? I know that the form asks for information on the support the school has sought, but it needs to outline exactly what has been done.</p>
          <p eId="para_35"> Who has the right to say "No" or "Stop, we don't want this"? What happens when a parent says he or she does not want it to happen? What are the guidelines given to the school? What monitoring or reporting will take place during the time a child is placed on a reduced timetable? At the end of each plan, is there a requirement to notify all parties concerned of progress, regardless of whether it is being sought to renew it? Even renewing it is bizarre. Is there a requirement to report progress on how a reduced timetable is working? </p>
          <p eId="para_36"> According to the guidelines, the NCSE must be notified when a reduced timetable is agreed to for a student with special educational needs. Does the Minister intend to include or specify a further role or will it remain the case that the NCSE or the special educational needs organiser, SENO, must be notified and that is it, full stop? What is the role of the educational welfare officer or the SENO, particularly when it comes to renewals? </p>
          <p eId="para_37"> Regarding guideline K which stipulates a school must only consider an extension in exceptional circumstances and only with the further written consent of the parents, it should be made very clear in guideline A that the practice should only be considered in exceptional circumstances.</p>
          <p eId="para_38">There is a mention here of when a reduced timetable might be used, but I think it should start in the key requirements, stating that this is only to be used in a exceptional circumstances. That should be reiterated to the school if it is considering it.</p>
          <p eId="para_39"> Would the Department consider making it a requirement not only to consult the parents or to get their written consent but also at least to have consultation with NEPS or another outside disability service provider relevant to the child in question? I am sure the witnesses read the Inclusion Ireland report, Education, Behaviour and Exclusion, in which it seeks that. I think it should be done. Does the Department intend to put a hard limit on the use of reduced timetables? Six weeks is given as a guideline and I think the word "ideally" is used. "Ideally" is not the word that should be used here because that leaves a lot of scope for abuse. I would prefer to see a hard limit. I think six weeks is an extraordinarily long time for a student be removed from school, to be on a reduced timetable, and to be isolated socially from his or her peers. Maybe the witnesses will look at that again. I notice on the information collected in the form - it may be an oversight - that there is no reference to gender. I see ethnicity but not gender. Is there a particular reason it has been left out?</p>
          <p eId="para_40"> What assurances can we be given that the teachers placed with these students have been given the robust training that they need? It cannot be a case of a teacher drawing the short straw and being told he or she will have the students on the reduced timetable because he or she happens to be free. That is not fair to the students, to the parents or the teacher. It is a disservice to all involved. What guidance is given to the school about what subjects the students will have access to? When one starts probing into a reduced timetable, there are questions of what teachers will be qualified and what subjects will be taught. It is very problematic.</p>
          <p eId="para_41"> Deputy Byrne referred to challenging behaviour. There is no definition of challenging behaviour and this is an ongoing issue across the world with departments of education. It leads to abuse of the term "challenging behaviour". There has to be training in challenging behaviour and resourcing of teachers, staff, schools and principals to address challenging behaviour. That means it is not child-centred, and instead of trying to support those children, they are just removed because of the so-called challenging behaviour that no one can define. Is the Department liaising with or does it intend to liaise with the Minister for Health and the Minister of State with responsibility for mental health to ensure that child and adolescent mental health services, CAMHS, and the National Educational Psychological Service, NEPS, are properly resourced to provide the necessary assistance? What interdepartmental communication has taken place since we discussed this in Joint Committee on Education and Skills during the summer? We must make sure that at-risk children are given the appropriate help.</p>
          <p eId="para_42"> I know that one recommendation in our interim report is that any guidelines relating to the use of reduced timetables must also outline the complaints process if a parent is dissatisfied. Parents must know how they can complain and the process must be in black and white. Where is that? The guidelines do not include that and I think that should be put in place. At the root of all this is the question of why schools are resorting to the use of reduced timetables, especially for children with disabilities. The Inclusion Ireland report stated that one in four children with a disability had been placed on a reduced timetable, with half of those being for more than 20 days. How can we ensure that every student with a disability or learning need has access to an appropriately trained teacher? How will schools be supported with these issues so they do not have to go to reduced timetables?</p>
          <p eId="para_43"> If the Department is going to go ahead with these guidelines, which I have a problem with because I do not think they are rigid enough, could we have an annual report on the use of reduced timetables? Everyone could see every year the gender, socio-economic background, ethnicity, if there is a disability, and the length of reduced timetables. We need to see that every year. I have raised the issue of the inspectorate's critique every year since I was inspected. The inspectorate has to be asked to remove the question of why there are so many students with special educational needs as a critique of a school, whereas schools that do not have many students with special educational needs should be asked why and what they intend to do about it. That attitude needs to be changed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DonnchadhOLaoghaire" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Deputy Donnchadh Ó Laoghaire<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_44">Gabhaim buíochas leis an Aire agus leis na hoifigigh atá os ár gcomhair tráthnóna. This is an issue that, anecdotally, people would have had some sense of. Unfortunately, with regard to the Traveller community, there would have often been a tacit awareness that in many instances they were not getting the full benefit of the school places that they held down. Great credit is due to this committee and also to Inclusion Ireland and Technological University Dublin for the report. The committee and report have forced action on this issue. It is unquestionably the case that the mechanisms that exist were being abused in a way that frustrated these children's ability to gain an education and their full potential. There is no question that the level of the abuse in the examples that were given and the frequency or the time that people were out for is absolutely unacceptable. I am glad that there is movement now. There are difficulties, as has been outlined with regard to the guidelines. While it is an interim report, the Minister has, as I understand it, had sight of it. Does he accept what is outlined in that document and does he agree with the recommendations made in it? I particularly endorse recommendation No. 9, which outlines the need for additional psychological supports. The Minister needs to provide additional resources in the upcoming budget.</p>
          <p eId="para_45"> Section 2 refers to regulations and guidelines and I ask for clarification about which it is. I do not view a regulation as being the same as a guideline. I would imagine a regulation as having much more effect. It comes to a point raised by Deputy Martin. Point E states that, ideally, the period on which a student is on a reduced timetable should not exceed six weeks, and a reduced timetable must not be carried forward from one academic year to the next. Ideally, it would allow some wriggle room. An issue with the guidelines as a whole is that if a school does not comply with the objections that have been set out by the Department, what are the consequences and the sanction? I do not see any and that is a difficulty. It will always be open to a school to try to point to the extraneous circumstances it has had to go beyond what the Department has in mind. How do we avoid that and ensure that schools do not frustrate the intention of the Department and that there is a sanction if a school is once again using some mechanism, either through this set of guidelines or any other way, to frustrate the intentions of the Department, the committee or the entitlement of these children to gain a full education?</p>
          <p eId="para_46"> I have a query relating to point H, a requirement to provide appropriate work to the student while not in school and to arrange for this to be checked. Instinctively, I am not sure if that is necessarily always appropriate. It may be appropriate in some circumstances, but I can imagine a situation where that might be the source of conflict or disagreement or that it might not be appropriate or aid the reintegration of a student into the class, which is intended to be the objective of having any kind of flexibility with regard to this. The purpose of any kind of flexibility is to enable reintegration. I have a query about whether that is appropriate.</p>
          <p eId="para_47"> There is no excuse for the fact that some schools allowed this abuse to happen, but this would probably have occurred in schools that were under significant pressure.</p>
          <p eId="para_48">That has to be acknowledged and additional resources need to be allocated to those schools. There is no excuse for the manner in which the mechanism was used. A very robust line needs to be taken to ensure that procedures such as this are not abused in future.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Deputy Jan O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_49">I thank the Minister and his officials for coming before us. I agree with others that this is a very important issue that the committee has highlighted. There was very little public information on this practice and it was only when parents came across it with their children that they realised that it existed. It came to light when we looked at the transition of Traveller children from primary to secondary level. We realised that a very large number of Traveller children were being subjected to reduced timetables. There was very little knowledge about it.</p>
          <p eId="para_50"> Community Law &amp; Mediation did a study on reduced timetables among children in Limerick, the city I represent. It established that only 27% of education welfare officers knew that a child was on a reduced timetable. It is crucial for that information to be conveyed and known. We need to have good data collection. We frequently heard in our hearings that there were no data. Cases of reduced timetables were not registered by schools because they were not considered to be either suspensions or exclusions. I understand from the Minister - he might clarify - that there will be much more comprehensive collection of data. The data need to be continually updated and shared. I agree with Deputy Catherine Martin who said they should be reported back to the committee. We need public reporting of how frequently this mechanism is used and why it is used. There needs to be intervention so that there is an alternative arrangement for the children in question when this occurs and the measure should only be used in exceptional cases.</p>
          <p eId="para_51"> On the issue of this being used in exceptional cases, in all of this parents need to have equal power in the relationship. It should not be a case of schools saying they need to remove a child for a period with the possibility of being suspended or expelled. There should not be pressure on parents. It should be a relationship where the parents are genuinely involved and have the power to say they do not want their child taken out of school. As Deputy Thomas Byrne said, education is a right. The Ombudsman for Children referred to the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child - the right of the child to have an education. It is vital that that power relationship is changed.</p>
          <p eId="para_52"> The representatives of management bodies told the committee that they agreed that reduced timetables should be exceptional, time limited and apply only after consultation with parents. Parents' groups, Inclusion Ireland, AsIAm and the Traveller representatives all had a different story about this measure being used quite widely, with parents being phoned to come in to collect their child to be taken out of school. It was not planned or recorded. They did not feel they had any real power in the decision-making.</p>
          <p eId="para_53"> It is important that we have shone a light on the issue. It is important that we get it right. I hope the Minister will take note of the submissions we got. I have a question on the role of the inspectors in gathering the information. It should not be seen as negative for a school to be inclusive; it should be seen as positive. However, the data need to be gathered.</p>
          <p eId="para_54"> I agree that there must be consultation with the various educational partners on any proposals and the Minister has said he will have that consultation. How long will that consultation take? When will we have something final in place providing full information for everybody involved? The welfare of the child must be paramount. There need to be alternative supports and educational opportunities where it is agreed that it is in the best interests of the child. Everyone who appeared before the committee agreed with us that this option should only be taken in very rare cases and should not be something schools use to deal with children whose behaviour is perceived to be difficult.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">I had a conversation yesterday with a parent whose child is six years of age and has access to one hour of school a day. That is what she has been offered. When she asked what she should do when she is in difficulty at home, she was advised to contact the Garda. I welcome that the Minister is here and I welcome the statement he made. It is important for him to acknowledge that his Department has failed children consistently. I join my colleague, Deputy Ó Laoghaire, in acknowledging the work of this committee in shining a light on this issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_56"> The issue of data collection is key. It is shocking that we do not know how many children are affected by reduced timetables. Will the Department pursue an overhaul of its data collection, maintenance and presentation policy? If so, will this include an expansion of proper data management practices to other areas affecting children with special educational needs such as the provision of ASD special classes in post primary education? I note that the Minister's opening statement did not highlight the drastic difference in numbers between primary and secondary schools when it comes to ASD classes. I ask him to comment on that.</p>
          <p eId="para_57"> What will the Department do to address the lack of specialist training regarding special needs education for teachers in mainstream schools? Continuing professional development for special needs education is currently available for teachers. Will the Department open this continuing professional development to special needs assistants who are currently left out of such CPD programmes? </p>
          <p eId="para_58"> The Minister will know the Special Needs Parents Association has recognised the role of home tuition in supporting children who have fallen through the gaps left behind by the Department. Will the Department take any action to expand access to home tuition and home tuition payments for students on reduced timetables?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LynnRuane" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Senator Lynn Ruane<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">I thank the Minister. Much has already been said. We need to look beyond the reduced timetables. Other speakers have already mentioned why reduced timetables have become such a norm in so many schools. We need to look at pupil-teacher ratios. Teachers will say reduced timetables are being used because of the number of children they are trying to teach in a class. All of a sudden one disruptive child becomes a problem that needs to be removed so that the teacher can adequately teach the rest of the class. There is a major issue with classroom size and the ability of teachers to work effectively with children.</p>
          <p eId="para_60"> Based on how they are being used, if reduced timetables had existed when I was in school, there would have been very few people in my classroom. Something has gone wrong. Outside intellectual disability such as ASD etc., which is very widespread across all backgrounds, it is a socio-economic issue. The parents who are involved come from the most vulnerable families that one could meet. Irrespective of how much it might be written into guidelines, the power balance is not there. There are groups who have had a negative experience of the school education system. Travellers have negative experiences of the education system daily. Who effectively will advocate for a parent in this situation where they will say "No" to a school?</p>
          <p eId="para_61">No matter how much we try to address the power imbalance in guidelines that everything needs to be black and white, there needs to be an advocate. There needs to be somebody, within the community or within the system, who is only there to support the family and the student in situations where this type of stuff is beginning to happen.</p>
          <p eId="para_62"> In Tallaght, there are two families that I support at present. One child has narcolepsy and that is why he is being sent home. The father rang me one day almost crying, stating that he does not know what to do. The child slumped in the classroom and the school rang for him to be taken home instead of waiting for him to come back around out of the condition that he has. They started sending him home every day at 10 a.m., one hour in, in secondary school. Now he has to re-engage. I will not name schools because it is not fair to do so. In another school, in west Tallaght, there is a child who has dyslexia, who has no behavioural issues and who loves school. They are trying to influence that child's mother to put the child on a reduced timetable because she struggles in some subjects in terms of dyslexia. This is how it is being used. There would be nobody left in the classroom if we were to keep allowing this to be implemented in the way that it is. We need to look at having a support service or a support person outside of the school community, not necessarily the school liaison teacher because he or she at one stage was a teacher in the classroom the year before or the year before that who, sometimes automatically, will understand why teachers feel they may need to do this.</p>
          <p eId="para_63"> When they report to Tusla, I wonder whether it is merely the filling of this form or is there some sort of supporting document? On ticking boxes, it asks whether there was parental involvement. How do we know what that involvement looks like for a parent and what support that parent received? Any school could tick many of the boxes on this form and send it off. It is not representative of the experience that the family and student have had over a period with the school. That is why I favour some sort of advocate who would exist within the Department or within the school system and who would be part of those conversations and a witness to the parental and student involvement in processes such as this. There will be medical situations. As the mother of someone on the autistic spectrum, I am aware there will be medical situations where it will be better for one's child to take him or her out for a period of time. I am talking about doing so for a few hours within one week, because a day is particularly difficult for sensory reasons and so on. I am not talking about six weeks, which is a long time. Consider how quickly one moves through a mathematics curriculum in six weeks. Sometimes a class spends a week in school on one part of the curriculum and it will have already gone three or four times' further along the curriculum than the child is able to catch up with. Parents in communities where there is high deprivation and low educational attainment are already under-resourced and cannot support their children at home to keep up with that curriculum. In many cases, the parents left school at 15 or 16 years of age.</p>
          <p eId="para_64"> I have one more question, which seems a little off-topic and has to do with children's allowance. Many children have been suspended or expelled from school over the past number of years and while I do not know where it came from, there is an idea that when one's child reaches 16 years, one must get the school to stamp a form to say that he or she is still in full-time education or one's children's allowance is stopped. This disproportionately affects working-class communities where on many occasions, because parents have refused reduced timetables their children have been expelled and the welfare system has come in and removed their children's allowance. Somewhere along the line, children's allowance, which was not set up as an educational payment, has been linked to educational attendance. It will disproportionately affect some of these families that are falling through the cracks in relation to reduced timetables, expulsions and suspensions. Such measures should not be the option but their families are also ending up in even worse positions than they were in because now they are attaching a social welfare payment to it. It is something the Department should look at. I do not know where that relationship originally developed from.</p>
          <p eId="para_65"> My main point is that there should be some sort of parent support worker or advocate who is engaged in any process that happens between a school and Tusla because of the distrust in institutions. When parents feel they have been targeted by institutions their whole life, it is difficult to go into a school and have a conversation with a principal in a suit. Parents end up agreeing with everything the principal says because they nearly feel inadequate to be able to put up some sort of advocacy for themselves and their children.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_9">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">I thank Senator Ruane. I will make a few brief comments before I come back to the Minister.</p>
          <p eId="para_67"> I will taking up on that issue. Many parents have difficulties with their children having shorter school days. People have asked me on occasion what does "reduced timetables" mean. It means reduced hours within a school. Children are not in school for the recommended level of hours. Many parents, because of different issues, and possibly because of challenging behaviour and intellectual disability, are exhausted trying to deal with the system. I would agree that they need to have an advocate, such as a guardian <i>ad litem</i>, GAL, who would help support them with it.</p>
          <p eId="para_68"> It is important, no matter what, to remember that schools are not only a place for academic learning. They are a place where children grow socially and develop social skills. It is a place where they also develop emotional skills. Children who are not in school for full days are losing out on that. I am aware of a school in my own area where eight children did not have any school for six months and then got a second-level placement. These are children with intellectual disabilities. Last year, they only started school in November. They straight away went onto a reduced timetable for every single day. When they started this year, in September, they were told that there would be a reduced timetable for the next two years, that is, for each one of the 167 days of the school year. That is not good enough.</p>
          <p eId="para_69"> The Minister spoke of the financial investment in special education, the number of the special teachers and the number of special needs assistants, SNAs. While that is acknowledged, it is not only about the funding that is invested. It is about the outcomes for the children. That is the most important part of it.</p>
          <p eId="para_70"> In the draft recommendations the Minister has made, I note that the Department will have full consultation with educational stakeholders. I would ask that the Minister ensure that a copy of the interim report that we have made is sent with that consultation request. It is important that we as a committee have the opportunity for our voices to be heard. This was a cross-party committee. We were all shocked by what we learned. We acknowledge that the topic is multifaceted but we feel strongly that it has to be taken out of the shadows. We intend to have further engagement. That is why we brought out the interim report.</p>
          <p eId="para_71"> We appreciate the Minister coming today to engage with us on this issue. We wanted that to be part of where we as committee need to go next with this. Education is the constitutional right of all children and cannot be undermined at any level in terms of unregulated practice. I call the Minister. I am conscious of his time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_10" as="#Minister_for_Education_and_Skills">
          <from>Deputy Joe McHugh<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">I thank the Chairman and members of the committee for their contributions. There were a number of questions but there were a number of suggestions as well. That is helpful. As I stated at the outset, this committee did quite a bit of the heavy lifting around this issue. When one considers that the committee submitted its interim report in June - I propose to take the Chairman's last suggestion first - it would be important to keep the committee involved right through the consultation. I am happy to provide a copy of the committee's report to the stakeholders. In fact, many of the committee's suggestions and recommendations frame these guidelines.</p>
          <p eId="para_73"> On top of that, in response to Deputy Jan O'Sullivan's question on a timeframe, I would like to work within quite a tight timeframe on this consultation. It will be up until 18 October. We are looking at this year to try to get something in there and get something working for the new year or the new term. Let us work together on that. I would be happy to include the committee on that.</p>
          <p eId="para_74"> On Deputy Thomas Byrne's questions, first of all,every child has a legal right to education. The Deputy spoke about the evidence and the lack of evidence. Let us face it, the committee was working on anecdotal evidence but the Department was working on anecdotal evidence as well. The idea of this exercise and of these guidelines, is to find out the scale and the nature of the issue we are dealing with here.</p>
          <p eId="para_75">That will determine where resources will flow thereafter and how practice will be shaped. The Deputy mentioned behavioural issues and there are medical and mental health issues. As I stated previously, the position of the Department is that all pupils who are enrolled in a school should attend school for the full day unless exempted from so doing for exceptional circumstances, such as medical reasons, and that reduced timetables should not be used as a de facto suspension or as a behavioural management technique. That is what was happening, it was being used as an intervention in such cases. That is still very much the case and my position has not changed. There will be a process and guidelines. The principal will inform Tusla and if reduced timetables must be used, there must be a reason, as well as an outline process and continuum explaining that this part of the reintegration. We are going to be very clear and transparent around that.</p>
          <p eId="para_76"> The Deputy also mentioned issues regarding when a special school in Dublin 15 will open. As far as I am aware, the training for the entire team has been completed and consequently we now are in a position to start. I will inform the Deputy as soon as I have that information readily available but we are on the cusp in that if it does not happen next week, it will be the following week. One demand from the parents was very clear. As they want it done in a phased process, that is something we are adhering to as well. The Deputy also made a point about resources and training. As there is no point in having a guideline on reduced timetables if we do not put adequate resources, training and support into schools, that will come hand in glove.</p>
          <p eId="para_77"> Deputy Catherine Martin referred to scepticism. When one embarks on anything new that has been basically left out and where there has been a gaping hole, it is a case of figuring it out and doing so properly. That is why the consultation with the key stakeholders will be so important. I mention in particular the parents' council. Members spoke about empowering parents. Their voice will be really important in that consultation. The Deputy asked what will happen when the parent says "No". That parent will be empowered, will have a right to say "No" to a proposed reduced timetable and will have the right to state this is still a de facto suspension. If parents are not satisfied, there is a process to deal with this by appealing directly to the Department through section 29 of the Education Act. We must be very clear and continue to empower the parent in that regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_78"> In terms of the consultation with NEPS, the guidelines are underpinned by the principles that a reduced timetable or reduced day should never be used as a sanction, offered as an alternative to a sanction or used as a behavioural management tool. It should be applied proportionately and should last only as long as is necessary to facilitate a return to school on a full-time basis. The guidelines should be read in conjunction with relevant guidelines from Tusla, including developing a code of behaviour, guidelines for schools and a statement of strategy for school attendance. Other resources include information on NEPS and support from the Department. It is important that lines of communication are always open. We are all trying to achieve the aims set out in the school inclusion pilot, whereby we have the HSE and the Departments of Education and Skills, Children and Youth Affairs Health working hand in glove together. That is why we will be informed by the school inclusion pilot.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">The last two replies are connected. What happens when a parent says "No"? The Minister said it would be a de facto suspension.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_12" as="#Minister_for_Education_and_Skills">
          <from>Deputy Joe McHugh<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">Yes, it would be treated as a suspension.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">The Minister also said they have recourse to section 29.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_14" as="#Minister_for_Education_and_Skills">
          <from>Deputy Joe McHugh<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">Yes, they have a right of appeal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">The next answer the Minister gave me is that it should not be used as a sanction. Surely a suspension is a sanction?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_16" as="#Minister_for_Education_and_Skills">
          <from>Deputy Joe McHugh<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">Yes, it is being used as a sanction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">Then it is being used as a sanction, even though it should not be used as a sanction. How will the Minister address that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_18" as="#Minister_for_Education_and_Skills">
          <from>Deputy Joe McHugh<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">That is what we are trying to do in this regard. We are trying to ensure that the information we have includes the scale and extent of the issue and to find out if there are resource deficiencies or a weakness within the school system. We are not informed at the moment because we have only anecdotal evidence. What we are trying to do is to ensure we get the process right first. That is why the guidelines will be so important, as will be the consultation with the educational partners and members' continued observations, in ensuring that the parent and the young person will know what the transparent process is. We are not starting from scratch or a blank page but we have a very complex issue where parents and students naturally feel aggrieved on the one hand and we have issues in schools on the other hand, where members of boards of management, principals and teachers will state they do not have adequate resources to work through the situation. It is about informing ourselves of the scale and extent of the issue. That is the reason I do not want to see this used as a behavioural mechanism. I acknowledge it is being used as a tool for dealing with behavioural issues and as a sanction at present and I want to move away from that.</p>
          <p eId="para_87"> Deputy Catherine Martin also asked about the higher limit on the use of reduced timetables. While six weeks is a long time, a plan must be put together. Senator Gavan referred to one hour a day. It is not acceptable that one could have one hour per day over a period of six weeks. There must be a progression. It could be one hour a day on the first day and then there must be a progression towards reintegration within that period. Six weeks is the one that has been suggested for the consultation. The feedback varies on whether that period is appropriate. We are open to receiving feedback on it.</p>
          <p eId="para_88"> There is no reference to gender but there is a reference to ethnicity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">Is that an oversight?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_20" as="#Minister_for_Education_and_Skills">
          <from>Deputy Joe McHugh<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">No, my personal opinion is that a young person is a young person whether they he or she is male or female. This is about equal treatment for each individual.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">It might be interesting when gathering the data to see whether it is young boys from a certain socio-economic background or if it is young girls.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_22" as="#Minister_for_Education_and_Skills">
          <from>Deputy Joe McHugh<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">It is something to consider for inclusion. The Deputy also referred to the need for more consultation and suggested an annual report. The data we receive will be important in informing the Department as to where resources are needed and where they should be directed. She also raised the issue of capacity, which is something of which I am very conscious. We must ensure there is sufficient capacity and support under the new model for schools. I have already covered the Deputy's point on the need for the complaints structure to be transparent.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">May I seek a further clarification, Chairman?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_24">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">I am conscious that the Minister has to go the Chamber soon. However, if there is any time remaining when he has finished responding, I will allow the Deputy to put her question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_25" as="#Minister_for_Education_and_Skills">
          <from>Deputy Joe McHugh<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">Deputy Ó Laoghaire spoke about anecdotal evidence, which I have covered. The Department is working on anecdotal evidence on this particular issue. I accept and agree with many of the recommendations in the guidelines, most of which came from the report. The Deputy referred to regulations versus guidelines. No matter what issue one is dealing with, it is usually, in the first instance, covered in guidelines and circulars that are given to schools. Once we have a system in place whereby Tusla is informed when a reduced timetable is being introduced, that information will be recorded and will form part of the data.</p>
          <p eId="para_96"> On the scale and nature of resources, the Deputy referred to reintegration, process and flexibility and there being no excuses as to how things were done in the past. I agree there is no excuse for allowing a situation to emerge where a child is being disadvantaged in his or her constitutional right to an education. That is an issue which we are all working to resolve. There is no specific sanction where a school is not complying in this regard but I intend to ensure we are informed as to the scale and extent of the resourcing need.</p>
          <p eId="para_97">If extra resources are needed in these areas, we will certainly do that.</p>
          <p eId="para_98"> Deputy Jan O'Sullivan observed that 27% of education and welfare officers were aware of schools using reduced timetables and highlighted an information deficit in that regard. She said a more robust collection of data was required. The Deputy spoke about parents' consent and an equal power relationship but I also talked about the voice of the child. She mentioned different groups having a different story, the importance of getting this right and the role of the inspectorate. The Deputy will be aware that the specific role of the inspectorate in the Department of Education and Skills is to examine the quality of learning and teaching. The inspectorate will continue, in the context of the work, to evaluate the effectiveness of schools' implementation of specific interventions and initiatives and to provide up-to-date information to the system. On the timeframe, the consultation period ends on 18 October.</p>
          <p eId="para_99"> Senator Gavan made a reference to one hour per day, which is unacceptable, and not having a plan as to how to reintegrate that student back into education. Data collection is key, and that is a gaping hole. We do not have those data and if the practice was and is being used as a behavioural tool, that is not acceptable.</p>
          <p eId="para_100"> I referenced the social inclusion pilot because the Senator also mentioned autism spectrum disorder, ASD, classes, the difference between primary and post-primary and where the investment is going. We have 4,000 schools. Currently, we have upwards of 1,500 special classes. Some schools are providing up to four classes. Others are providing one class. If we do a quick mathematical summary of that, less than 25% of schools have special classes. It is an enormous challenge to try to get that right. As the Chairman pointed out, we are investing a great deal of resources - one out of every five euro - in special education but we still have a long way to go. Parents today are having difficulties accessing special classes in preschool and primary school and at post-primary level. That is a major challenge that we want to meet head-on.</p>
          <p eId="para_101"> The Department of Health has a budget of €17 billion and the Department I preside over has a budget of nearly €11 billion. I see enormous potential for much greater collaboration between the two Departments. </p>
          <p eId="para_102"> Mention was made of behavioural issues. The school inclusion pilot will look at speech and language therapy, occupational therapy, the potential for physiotherapy, even though it is not in the pilot, but also to have a behavioural therapist in the school. We are trying to get from where we are now to a place where there is much more joined-up thinking and integration at an interdepartmental level and between State agencies. </p>
          <p eId="para_103"> Senator Ruane's contribution on empowering parents was very interesting. She referenced Tallaght, although she did not want to highlight any school in particular. I have fond memories of Tallaght, having done my teaching practice in St. Mark's school, in Springfield. The present-day classrooms are in a different country to the classroom I was in back in 1993 . I went in as a student teacher, stuck to the subject area and got on with it. It was a different scenario to the classrooms I go into in either primary or secondary schools. There is much more complexity. If something is needed in terms of empowering parents in their decision-making as to what is best for their sons or daughters, we will have to be open to that.</p>
          <p eId="para_104"> The Senator referenced medical situations. Perhaps there could be a reduced timetable for a particular day. We have to be open to all the new ways of thinking in terms of how we deal with complex issues. I refer to the notion of having some sort of support for parents to help them make the decision.</p>
          <p eId="para_105"> I am reminded of when I was a youth worker in Letterkenny. When parents would approach me informally about something that was happening in primary school, they were looking for my advice and advocacy. It may not have been right all the time but they were reaching out and had a level of trust. That goes back to all the different informal places, whether it is community groups, youth groups or whatever. The Senator may have hit on something that I have experienced in terms of helping parents make that decision. I would like to explore that further.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_26">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">We received a note five minutes ago that they were waiting for the Minister in the Dáil Chamber. I assume he received it also. We will excuse him if he needs to attend the Chamber or he can continue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_27" as="#Minister_for_Education_and_Skills">
          <from>Deputy Joe McHugh<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">I think I am required to deal with a Topical Issue matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_28">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">He is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_29" as="#Minister_for_Education_and_Skills">
          <from>Deputy Joe McHugh<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">I was very obedient and switched my phone off. The Chairman asked me to do that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">I know they cannot contribute but can the officials stay to listen to any observations we may make?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_31">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">We had waited to get this date with the Minister. It was less than satisfactory but we were asked that if the Minister needed to go to the Chamber to try to accommodate that. We agreed to that. I ask that the Minister might come back in, say, a month's time or following the consultation because members will have follow-up questions. I agree with Deputy Thomas Byrne about the officials staying - I appreciate they cannot respond - to hear further comments seeking clarification. We will release the Minister-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">Can they respond?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_33">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">No. They are not allowed. We will release the Minister to attend to other duties. I thank him for attending and for his contribution.</p>
          <p eId="para_114"> Do any members want to comment further or make observations based on what the Minister has said?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">The more I look at the document that is written, it does not look like the type of document that normally emanates from the Department of Education and Skills. That may be because it emanated from Tusla but it does not look like a circular the Department would issue. I say that without disrespect to anybody. It does not appear to be written with the same level of precision one normally associates with Department of Education and Skills documents or circulars. They are normally extremely precise. This document needs to be much clearer as to the circumstances in which these reduced timetables can happen and the procedures thereafter. In terms of No. 4, the key requirements, that mixes up the reasons for this with the procedures. The procedures are long and drawn out and could be easily reduced to bullet points in terms of doing this or that.</p>
          <p eId="para_116"> The form does not require any evidence as to the necessity for the reduced timetables when that is a key requirement, according to what the Minister said today. From my reading of it, that is not required to be provided. The form also refers to a right of appeal. I am not clear on that right of appeal. The only appeal I am aware of would be under section 29 in terms of appeals against suspension or expulsion. To what does that refer?</p>
          <p eId="para_117"> The document would do well to quote what the gentleman from Tusla - I do not recall his name-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Deputy Jan O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">Mr. Noel Kelly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">Noel Kelly. He was superb. He was very clear that this was a suspension or an expulsion where these reduced timetables were being brought in in an unorthodox fashion. It would be useful for the document to remind school authorities of that also.</p>
          <p eId="para_120"> There is also a section 5 on this about supports available to schools.</p>
          <p eId="para_121">I am not sure it is required to have a plug for the Department of Education and Skills or another body. We know everything that is done but the document needs to take the form of a circular. It does not appear to be written in that way, although it may have been rushed. I do not mean any disrespect because to be fair to the Minister, if the document is read in the way I would like it to be read, it can be considered to be very strict. However, if it were more precise, it would help everybody. I do not mean to be facetious or to be nitpicking but we all agree-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_37">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">It is a fair point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">-----this is an important issue and we have to get it right. If a private meeting with the officials is available, I would welcome that in order to discuss this. I hope that would be of help and that it would not be an inconvenience to the Department.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_39">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">We will ask the Department for a meeting. I cut Deputy Catherine Martin off earlier but I was conscious of the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">That is fine. I was not sure if the Minister was talking about a capacity issue for an annual published report because I was about to say that has to be done and we need to be able to see that report. The form does not leave much room for detail. It asks whether a plan has been developed to support the student's return to full education and provides for a "Yes" or "No" answer. I would like to see the plan and Tusla should also see it. There is a lot of box-ticking and little detail available. We want this to be child centred.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DonnchadhOLaoghaire" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Deputy Donnchadh Ó Laoghaire<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">I emphasise a point on which the Minister did not respond and while I accept the officials cannot respond, I hope it will be taken into account. I am not sure bullet point H makes sense. I am not sure if additional work should always be provided or if that would always be suitable. What are the consequences if a school does not comply? It is not immediately clear to me that it would be possible for the Department to enforce this requirement.</p>
          <p eId="para_127"> There has been some discussion of resources. When the previous round of additional DEIS designations was announced a few years ago, no new schools were added to the DEIS band 2 category. While many of those schools are much less resource-intensive than DEIS band 1 schools and would not require the same reduced pupil teacher ratios, but they would avail of school completion and home school liaison supports. That is a resource that needs to be looked at again. In many instances, good work done with school completion and home school liaison would prevent some of these issues arising as the relationship between the family, the child and the school would be maintained in a much better way. That is a point that needs to be considered.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Deputy Jan O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">To take up Deputy Thomas Byrne's point on cases where a parent does not agree with a decision on reduced timetables and it effectively becomes a suspension, there should be some intermediate step between this and a section 29 appeal. The decision should not have to go straight to a section 29 appeal where it would become confrontational. I do not know whether there is a role for education welfare officers. Senator Ruane mentioned advocates but maybe an education welfare officer could have a role in advocating for the child in such circumstances. I agree that some avenue other than a section 29 appeal must be available to parents who do not agree to a reduced timetable.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">This is very important for children with special needs. I agree with Deputy Jan O'Sullivan that there should be a middle ground. The only reason I wanted to mention this in terms of a suspension or expulsion was that it prods people into acting because it highlights how serious this is. If this is done incorrectly, a child will be suspended or expelled and that is a whole different ball game from the school's point of view.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_44">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">The joint committee will suggest that reduced timetables be classified as a separate category and not recorded as a form of suspension because the latter is viewed as a sanction or punishment when that is not always the case.</p>
          <p eId="para_131"> I thank the officials from the Department. We will be in contact about the possibility of members meeting officials to discuss some of these issues privately. It would be useful for us to have a conversation. I thank the members for their valuable contributions. We will suspend briefly to allow the next witnesses to take their seats.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 4.55 p.m. and resumed at 4.57 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>WorldSkills Competition 2019: Discussion<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:50:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_45">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">The next matter on the agenda is engagement with SOLAS and Ireland's representatives at the WorldSkills competition in Russia. The purpose of this part of the meeting is to welcome Mr. Andrew Brownlee, the new chief executive officer of SOLAS, who will talk to us about the success of the team that represented Ireland in Russia earlier this year. We take this opportunity to wish Mr. Brownlee well in his new role. The Irish team has again done us proud by winning four gold medals, one bronze medal and seven medallions for excellence at the WorldSkills Competition. This is an excellent achievement and I have no doubt all of the competitors are proud. We are interested in hearing about their experiences at the competition.</p>
          <p eId="para_133"> On behalf of the committee, I welcome Mr. Brownlee, CEO; Mr. Ray English, chair of WorldSkills Ireland; Mr. Luke O'Keeffe; Mr. Ryan Dempsey; Mr. Ryan McLoughlin; Ms Megan Yeates; Ms Hanna Mathe; Mr. Pat Twomey; Mr. Chris Kehoe; Mr. Adam Flynn; Mr. Jack Lynch and; Mr. Mark Wasson, who all represented Ireland. I also welcome a number of people in the Gallery. Every team needs to have a good and supportive team beside them. I welcome Ms Shauna Dunlop and Mr. David Tracey, who were official observers; Mr. Michael Hourihan, who was an official delegate; Ms. Nikki Gallagher, director of communications and secretariat of SOLAS; Ms Emma Kelly, communications officer with SOLAS; and Ms Vivienne Patterson and Ms Louise Sherry from the Higher Education Authority.</p>
          <p eId="para_134"> The format of this part of the meeting is that I will invite Mr. Brownlee to make a brief opening statement. Mr. English will then contribute, after which we will have an engagement with members. If any of the other witnesses would like to contribute thereafter at any point, I ask them to indicate and I will be more than happy to allow them to do so.</p>
          <p eId="para_135"> Before we begin, I draw attention to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to this committee. However, if they are directed by myself, as Chair, to cease giving evidence in relation to a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in relation to their evidence. They are directed by myself that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise nor make charges against any person, persons or entity, by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable. I also wish to advise witnesses that any submission or opening statements that they make to the committee will be published on the committee website after this meeting. Members are also reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice members to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses, or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_136"> I now invite Mr. Andrew Brownlee, CEO of SOLAS, to make his opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_46">
          <from> Mr. Andrew Brownlee<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">I thank the Chairman for the good wishes. I look forward to working with the committee and helping it in anyway I can as we move forward. I will keep this brief as I know the committee really wants to hear from the WorldSkills team. On behalf of SOLAS, the HEA and WorldSkills Ireland, I would like to thank the committee for the opportunity today to celebrate the excellent performance by a brilliant team of young apprentices, trainees and students at the WorldSkills Competition in Russia in August. I am delighted to be joined today by members of the team, including Ray English, chair of WorldSkills Ireland, and his colleagues, and Vivienne Patterson of the HEA.</p>
          <p eId="para_138"> I would like to provide a short overview of the WorldSkills competition, and explain how SOLAS, the HEA and the Department of Education and Skills and provide support to the Irish team. The WorldSkills competition, which is held every two years, has a 60-year history and is the biggest vocational education and skills event in the world. The competitors represent the best of their peers in 56 different skills and are selected from skills competitions in over 77 WorldSkills' member countries and regions. The Department of Education and Skills introduced national and international skills competitions to Ireland in 1957 and Ireland has taken part in every single competition since. Funding of almost €400,000 for the WorldSkills team comes through a number of sources, namely, SOLAS, the HEA and the Education and Training Boards Ireland, ETBI.</p>
          <p eId="para_139"> WorldSkills Kazan took place from 22 to 27 August. It involved 63 countries, more than 1,300 competitors, and had over 200,00 visitors. The opening and closing ceremonies, which were held in the Kazan Stadium, were attended by more than 40,000 people and were broadcast live on Russian TV to approximately 45 million viewers. Ceremonies were also streamed live on the Internet - I know many people in Ireland tuned in - so that everybody could be part of these Olympic-style spectacular shows. The closing ceremony was addressed live by President Putin.</p>
          <p eId="para_140"> The WorldSkills Conference, which was run in parallel to the competitions, included contributions from people such as Scott Kelly, a NASA astronaut, and our very own Minister of State with responsibility for skills, Deputy John Halligan. The Irish team was made up of 17 young apprentices, trainees and students. They are Cormac Thompson, Allanagh O’Sullivan, Ryan Dempsey, Luke O’Keeffe, Jack Lynch, Olivier Bal-Pétré, Hanna Mathe, Glen McNamara, Adam Flynn, Mark Wasson, Megan Yeates, Patrick Twomey, Jack O’Donnell, Ruairí Grealish, Jennifer Mangan, Christopher Kehoe, and Ryan McLoughlin. They showcased their skills in the areas of aircraft maintenance; beauty therapy; building information modelling; bricklaying; cabinet-making; cloud computing; construction metal work; cookery; electrical installation; freight forwarding; industrial mechanic millwright; joinery; plumbing and heating; restaurant service; visual merchandising; and welding.</p>
          <p eId="para_141"> The competitors spent several months prior to the competition being trained by experts at TU Dublin; the institutes of technology in Cork, Limerick, Waterford, Dundalk, Carlow and Athlone; the education and training boards in Kerry, Waterford, Wexford, Limerick, Clare, Donegal and Dublin-Dún Laoghaire; and Shannon College of Hotel Management.</p>
          <p eId="para_142"> The training and the hard work paid off. Ireland has a long history of winning medals and Medallions for Excellence and this year was no different. The team won four gold medals, one bronze medal, a Best of Nation medal, and seven Medallions for Excellence. Ireland is also now ranked tenth in the world for skills in terms of the medal rankings. I am sure the members will hear from the team themselves in more detail about this remarkable achievement.</p>
          <p eId="para_143"> Ireland has also been chosen to host the next WorldSkills General Assembly and Conference which will take place on 5 to 8 October 2020 in Dublin and plans are progressing to finalise this and the next Ireland Skills Live event, following the success of the inaugural event in March this year.</p>
          <p eId="para_144"> I would like to conclude by saying that WorldSkills competitions are an excellent way to promote Ireland’s skills to a global audience. Our brilliant teams benchmark the quality of further education, training and skills against the best in the world. They are also incredible role models here at home for anyone considering their post-secondary education choices.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_47">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">I thank Mr. Brownlee. I would like to welcome the Deputy Butler, Chairman of the Joint Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation, which is also doing a report on apprenticeships. Would Mr. English like to say a few words?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_48">
          <from> Mr. Ray English<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">I will say a few words. It is worth noting that WorldSkills Ireland remains primarily a volunteer organisation from the competitors themselves who, after selection commit to training to the experts who we rely on to train to WorldSkills standards, often for up to 40 hours a week. All of that is all done on a voluntary basis. That training takes place in education and training boards, institutes of technology, and Technological University Dublin.</p>
          <p eId="para_147"> The basis of this team came from the 2019 Ireland Skills Live Competition, which was held in March in the RDS, as has been noted. That attracted 15,000 young people who came to look at the skills. A number of young people went to Kazan and many others did not. The support of the Higher Education Authority, SOLAS and industry partners, such as John Sisk &amp; Son, in delivering Ireland Skills Live needs to be noted. That led to the great success that we saw in Kazan. It is important to note that it was each team member who gave us that overall tenth position. In any of the indices, Ireland came in the top 20 of the 63 countries that participated in Kazan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_49">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_148">I thank Mr. English.</p>
          <p eId="para_149"> On behalf of the committee, I want to congratulate everyone on their achievements. Given the Olympic standard, it is incredible to think how well everyone did, and across such a wide breadth of different skills and areas. It is really fascinating. On behalf of the State, I thank everyone and acknowledge the positive impression of Ireland I have no doubt everyone gave in Russia. That is hugely important. We want to send our best people because they are ambassadors for us abroad. Given their significant achievements, I have no doubt that they played that role really well.</p>
          <p eId="para_150"> Most importantly, I acknowledge the inspiration I have no doubt the competitors are to the young people in Ireland. They are an inspiration to their fellow citizens, to their fellow students and to us, as committee members. I have no doubt that they, along with their families, are very proud of what they have achieved.</p>
          <p eId="para_151"> The team had the opportunity to sit in on our earlier hearing on reduced timetables. Normally, parliamentary committees discuss what is wrong in society and the difficulties and problems we have, in particular within the education and skills system, which we deal with in this committee. In our experience, these problems affect younger and vulnerable people, in particular. It is so refreshing and encouraging to have the team here to shine a light on what they have achieved. Despite the difficulties and problems we have in society, the work they do and their achievements will give all of us better hope for the future.</p>
          <p eId="para_152"> I would like to ask our guests to say a few words about their experience and about their particular skill and achievement. If they are not comfortable doing that, that is absolutely fine. If anyone who would like to speak, perhaps they might indicate. We will be more than happy to welcome them to do so.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_50">
          <from> Ms Megan Yeates<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">I would like to thank the committee for inviting us in. This is an amazing opportunity to speak on behalf of the team. I know everybody will want to give their input.</p>
          <p eId="para_154">I also thank the team we have behind us. As was said, a great team supports us and brings us along. To give a little background, I won gold in the freight forwarding category at WorldSkills. It was the very first year in which freight forwarding made it to the WorldSkills. Two years ago it was a future skill that was being tested. It was an amazing opportunity to be able to take part in it the first year going.</p>
          <p eId="para_155"> WorldSkills is an absolutely amazing opportunity to get to represent one's country at an international level. There are not enough words to say how great this year's event was. What one takes away from it is the training opportunity we had leading up to it. I had ten weeks of intensive training from June to August, which was supported by TU Dublin. As Mr. English mentioned, I had my chief expert, who worked with me on a volunteer basis, and I was training five days a week, Monday to Friday, from 9 a.m. until 5 p.m. It is intense and a lot goes into it. When we travel over there we are up against the best in the world so we have to give it our all and be as informed as possible. We go over there almost wanting to know more than our experts. My expert is quite a few years ahead of me, but the support we get from the institutes is amazing. I know that some of my colleagues here had the opportunity to train with different institutes across the country. I was very lucky that I got to go out into my industry. My background is that I completed my logistics and supply chain management level 8 undergraduate programme in TU Dublin, so a lot of the companies that support the college through the work placements were very welcoming and opened their doors to me throughout the summer, took me on and gave me training. Not a single person in industry who was approached refused to get involved. It is very refreshing to see that and that all the companies out there are very supportive of the younger generation coming up and want to give that support to nurture our skills and help to educate us to make us the leaders and the industry experts into the future.</p>
          <p eId="para_156"> I would now like to pass the floor to one of my colleagues, who would like to continue the discussion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_51">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">The partnership Ms Yeates highlighted is incredibly important. Of course, we in Kildare are very proud of her as a Kildare person.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_52">
          <from> Ms Megan Yeates<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">I thank the Chairman.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_53">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">Would anybody else like to say a few words about how they found the experience and perhaps something about their own areas of expertise? Perhaps they might do so after the members have asked a few questions. I will hand the floor over to the members.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Deputy Jan O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">I join the Chairman in congratulating all the participants. It is an incredible achievement, and I know that Ireland has been really successful over the years. Well done to everybody involved. One thing I feel strongly about is the fact that opportunities for young people coming out of school do not have to be the standard go-to-college, get-a-degree opportunities. I commend SOLAS on the work that has been done on apprenticeships, including the new apprenticeships that are now available. My main question is this, and Ms Yeates has already given us an example: have some of the participants some experience of how what they have done will help them in terms of a career and job opportunities? It is so important for young people to recognise that by going down the skills route, there are fantastic opportunities out there, particularly for those of them who have represented the country so well.</p>
          <p eId="para_161"> I congratulate each and every one of the participants. I do not know if SOLAS would like to respond about the new apprenticeships and whether some of them are tested. Traditionally, there were a number of skills. I think Mr. Brownlee said there were 56 different ones.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_55">
          <from> Mr. Andrew Brownlee<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Jan O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">Has the number increased in recent years? Is Ireland participating in a wider range now than previously?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">We will wait until everybody has had an opportunity before coming back to the witnesses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">Congratulations, comhghairdeas, on the participants' wonderful achievements at WorldSkills this year. I also commend the work of SOLAS, the HEA and the volunteers and WorldSkills Ireland on what they are doing for our youth. The participants should not underestimate the inspirational role models they are on that world stage for the youth of Ireland as they ponder their next careers. They are showing them the potential they have. Do the participants think their schools or career guidance counsellors give them enough encouragement to consider apprenticeships? What was their experience in secondary school and so on? Furthermore, I noticed that of the 17 participants, four were women. That is roughly the percentage of women we have in the Dáil, so we definitely need more women in the Dáil and more women apprentices. I, therefore, ask the following question of the women in particular, although I would like answers from some of the young men here as well. What has the women's experience been and what can we do to get more women involved in this? What do the men think we can do to get more women involved in apprenticeships? It is an untapped resource. There is such potential there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DonnchadhOLaoghaire" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Deputy Donnchadh Ó Laoghaire<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">Congratulations - comhghairdeas libh go léir. I thank the witnesses for coming before us. At the risk of singling him out, I think I saw Mr. Twomey in <i>The Echo</i> in the run-up to-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_60">
          <from> Mr. Pat Twomey<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DonnchadhOLaoghaire" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Deputy Donnchadh Ó Laoghaire<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">He is a Coolea man, I think, but I congratulate all the participants. It is an amazing achievement. There has clearly been a strong track record over recent years.</p>
          <p eId="para_169"> I have a few questions for the participants but also for SOLAS. New courses are opening up and we are moving in the right direction, but we are still a long way behind the likes of Germany and Austria in that I think they have occupations well into the hundreds. I am not sure how many occupations we have. The witnesses can tell me now. It is certainly fewer than a hundred, I would say. It is in the 40s. There is surely significant scope for enhancing that, so perhaps the witnesses could tell us a bit about how they intend to move in that direction and how we might move towards the way in which they manage things in Germany or Austria.</p>
          <p eId="para_170"> I have a very specific question about something that has come up with industry. Are there many apprenticeships in instrumentation and electrical instrumentation at the moment? As far as I know, there is a serious shortage in this regard. It comes up with businesspeople in Cork - pharmaceutical companies and so on. There is a gap there. It is a really attractive trade but not many people seem to be going into it. If the witnesses have not already answered that, perhaps they might do so. It is an anecdotal matter.</p>
          <p eId="para_171"> It is probably difficult for the participants to say what about the system could be fixed, given the current environment, but perhaps they could tell us what the best elements of the apprenticeship system in Ireland are and what we need to work on. Also, many schools across the country do not really give many students the option of entering apprenticeships. It is not really open to them as an option. People are discouraged and it is not really considered a viable option. Do the participants think there is a role for them as well as SOLAS in going into schools and outlining the positive experience they have had and how apprenticeships can be an attractive option? I know they might be reluctant to speak but perhaps they could give us just a sense of how diverse their ranges are. Could they tell us in just a phrase what competitions they entered and competed in?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">I thank everybody for coming in. I reiterate the congratulations that everyone here has expressed to the participants for their participation, their representing the country and their achievements at the world games in becoming world leaders in their particular fields, and that is the way they have to look at it. Part of their being here is recognition for that. The Minister quite rightly criticised some of the media here, who shall remain nameless, for not giving the games the recognition it merited. It is important we give it that recognition. I note that 45 million people saw the participants on Russian television. It is up to us as public representatives to do our best to promote this because it is certainly one of the few world championships on this scale - and it is a huge scale - that has a lower profile here, which is a problem. If the media are listening - there is always someone listening - I urge them to show this hearing rather than us. We get on the telly all the time, and we hope to put the participants on the telly to show the achievements they have made. That is really important. They have represented the country at the highest possible level in their chosen fields.</p>
          <p eId="para_173"> I do not expect them to answer questions but I have a couple. They have all come to apprenticeships. Do any of them have any ideas or suggestions as to how we can promote apprenticeships and skills at school? Perhaps some of them had a good intervention, a good guidance counsellor, a good teacher, a good ETB person - whatever.</p>
          <p eId="para_174">Does anyone have suggestions on that? What can be done to encourage more women to become involved? The apprenticeship field is the outstanding example of underrepresentation of women in Irish society. The number of women is crazily low. I would like to ask Ms Yeates in particular what brought her to her category of apprenticeship, which is relatively unusual. How did that happen? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_63">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">It is quite shocking to think that only 4% of apprentices last year were female and the number prior to that was only 2%.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryButler" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Deputy Mary Butler<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">I thank the Chairman for her warm welcome. I am the Chairman of the Joint Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation. There is a bit of an overlap between our briefs. I congratulate the Irish WorldSkills team on being ranked tenth in the world with four gold medals, one bronze medal, a best of nation medal and seven medallions of excellence. We could say it all day long. It is a phenomenal result. This is an amazing opportunity to represent one's country at an international level. I have no doubt that of the team members' commitment and determination, and as Ms Yeates rightly pointed out, the five days a week of training for eight weeks. I am sure all of the witnesses did the same. We recognise the commitment and dedication they gave to representing Ireland. On behalf of the Joint Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation, I congratulate each and every one of the competitors and their mentors. It is a fantastic achievement. The committee will write to each one of them individually.</p>
          <p eId="para_177"> As the Chairman said, last year there were 15,500 apprenticeships in Ireland but only 400 were undertaken by women, which is an appalling number. Apprentices have a key role to play in addressing future skills needs. My committee looked at the role of apprentices in respect of work permits. We found that during the recession, secondary schools focused more on academia than on apprenticeships that allow students to earn as they learn. We also lost a lot of guidance counsellors during the recession. It is very important that it is not only ETB schools that encourage students to consider the various trades. My daughter is only 13 years old. She started secondary school last year and her favourite subject is technical graphics because she loves maths. I never thought she would be drawn to that. If she had not had the opportunity to engage with a subject like technical graphics at her school we would never have known that this could be the way she would like to go. </p>
          <p eId="para_178"> It is great to see Ms Mathe and Ms Yeates here. Were there only two female representatives on the team? I concur with the Chairman. I noticed that when the competitors returned, my constituency colleague, the Minister of State, was disappointed by the lack of media coverage. As a Deputy from Waterford, I to congratulate Mr. Flynn and Ms Mathe. I compliment the Chairman for inviting the delegation and acknowledging what they have done. Onwards and upwards. I wish the witnesses the best of luck in their future careers. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_65">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">I will put the witnesses on the spot. I have given them enough time to warm up. I wish to ask about their areas of expertise. When I heard about the various areas, I thought it was incredible to have such a wide variety. I ask them to say a little about their area and how they think apprenticeships or training can be given more prominence. It seems there is not parity of esteem between apprenticeships and academic subjects or degrees. We have discussed this several times as a committee. We believe that is completely wrong. We want to help to raise the profile of apprenticeships and we would like ideas from the witnesses on how to do that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_66">
          <from> Mr. Luke O'Keefe<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">I thank the committee for invitation. My skill is building information modelling, BIM. Mr. Ryan Dempsey and I were a team in Russia, where we had to make 3D models of buildings. It is an architectural skill. We went to college. I did not undertake an apprenticeship from the outset, mainly because it was not encouraged in secondary school. I always loved woodwork and making stuff with my hands. I always wanted to go down the apprenticeship road but I was discouraged by school and a little by my parents, as if one should not do that. One should go to college, get a degree and then get a job. Finally in college I found something I enjoyed, that is, architecture. It is still pertains to apprenticeships in some ways.</p>
          <p eId="para_181"> The experience in Russia was unreal. The scale of everything there is immense. If it was not for Ireland Skills Live last year, half of the team would not have done as well as they did this year. Ireland Skills Live brought everyone under one roof. We competed and saw some of the scale we would see in Russia. Without that we would have struggled. We would have been caught in the limelight as there was so much going on around us. Ireland Skills Live got us in the right mindset. We knew what we were expecting when we went over there. The Government should focus on that event, because it helps students. Other colleges and secondary schools are invited to Ireland Skills Live to see apprentices and apprenticeships and meet the best people working in those areas. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_67">
          <from> Mr. Ryan Dempsey<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">I thank the committee for inviting us. As Mr. O'Keeffe said, our skill is building information modelling. This is a new skill so it is in the "Future Skills" category. The event took place over 19.5 hours over three days. As Mr. O'Keeffe said, our background was in college but I see potential for BIM to become an apprenticeship. There is a skills shortage in the construction industry at the moment. There must be a greater emphasis on bringing people into the industry, including other apprentices. Speaking from a selfish point of view, there must be a better roadmap so that students know the options out there. There is an emphasis on going to college, but if the right roadmap is in place, students will know that apprenticeships are a viable option and they can get great careers from them. The people around me show the immense potential of apprenticeships, which can allow people to represent their country. It is not just about college. It is important to push apprenticeships and get the message into schools by inviting people in to speak.</p>
          <p eId="para_183"> The Ireland Skills Live event was a great success this year. It was great to see the students come in and walk around. One never knew who might come along. I even sensed a bit of inspiration from what we were doing and had the feeling students might follow us down this road. Ireland Skills Live should continue and the media must be involved. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_68">
          <from> Mr. Ryan McLoughlin<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">I thank the committee for having us. I represented Ireland in bricklaying. I did not like school at all. It did not work for me. Apprenticeship was looked down on when we received career guidance. No one spoke about it. When we received career guidance, we were given a stack of books on all the colleges around the country but all we were given on apprenticeships was a leaflet. There was no emphasis on trades or anything like that. I followed the norm; I filled out the Central Applications Office, CAO, form and applied for colleges, but I did not want to do that. I started an apprenticeship and enjoyed it. Many more people could do the same. I was the first bricklayer to register in counties Longford or Westmeath since 2009 and I do not know of one since. There is a massive shortage of bricklayers and so on around the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_185">In schools, there is a massive emphasis put on Higher Options and going to see colleges. I believe there should also be an emphasis on Ireland Skills Live to see what apprenticeships are about and what people do in the trades, because currently a person cannot see what is done in each trade just by looking at a leaflet or researching it. A person would have to see it to find out what it is about and it should be emphasised more.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_69">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">Ms Yeates told us about freight forwarding earlier. Perhaps she will tell us what attracted her to that as opposed to anything else, and respond to any of the questions that have been put.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_70">
          <from> Ms Megan Yeates<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">I will address the couple of questions directed towards me, but I will respond to the Chairman's question first. It is a question people love to ask me, because the industry I am in of freight forwarding and logistics is quite unusual. My degree title is logistics and supply chain management. I did my work placement with DHL in my third year and I moved into the transport sector. I also completed my certificate of professional competence management examinations at the end of second year. Like many others I meet in the industry, I was not especially attracted to it, but I ended up in it by default.</p>
          <p eId="para_188"> I was only aged 17 when I did my leaving certificate. I considered myself quite young to be leaving school and to be deciding what I wanted to do moving on. I took the initiative to have a year out and took a gap year, during which I worked. In that time I decided I would like to do a business course because I was drawn towards that area. In school, however, I had done all science subjects and I never completed a business subject to the leaving certificate. I was looking for a business course that was a bit more detailed and specific as opposed to a broad business subject. By chance I stumbled across the course in the Dublin Institute of Technology, which is now Technological University Dublin. I had studied applied maths and higher-level maths and I enjoyed them so it drew me to the course with its spreadsheet modelling and other maths subjects it offered. As I get more into the industry and the more business events I attend, I find that most people working in the logistics have just stumbled into it. One does not go through secondary school saying, "I know what I will do when I leave school; I will go into freight, or transport or supply." As I attended events, and especially over the summer as I met people, I have started working more on telling my story and I have taken time over the summer to write a blog. I cover topics such as why I chose freight forwarding, why I got into logistics and my WorldSkills journey. I have tried to share that journey to perhaps inspire somebody else along the way who might be looking for that little bit of inspiration.</p>
          <p eId="para_189"> My course is not an apprenticeship but TUD launched the logistics associate apprenticeship last year, which ran successfully for its first year and is now in its second year. It has also launched in Cork this year with significantly high numbers.</p>
          <p eId="para_190"> Reference was made to the gender gap, which is a topical issue at the moment, especially in the industry itself. I sat in on some of the meetings for the apprenticeship programme. There was quite a high proportion of males. My graduating class numbered 53 in total, of whom only eight were women. We can see a gender divide in this regard but it is interesting that it was 95% women to 5% men competing in the WorldSkills competition. In Europe, there appears to be a greater emphasis on women in the industry. Noting the other competitors in my category, there was a higher percentage of apprentices than students in the competition. There is a greater emphasis in Europe on freight forwarding and so on in apprenticeships.</p>
          <p eId="para_191"> A question was asked about school support at leaving certificate level. I believe that honesty is the best policy here. No support was given by my school in respect of leaving certificate choices for other options afterwards. Once a week, career guidance time was set aside where we were given time but it was very much a case of, "Go and work in the computer lab and work on it yourself." When I came to leaving certificate level, I was unsure. I was only 17 and it is quite a big life decision to make at such a young age. I took the decision to take a year out to do further research, so I knew I was going into the right course. Many of my classmates went straight into college and then dropped out within their first year. This is quite normal. I must give credit where credit is due. The push by SOLAS now, and the Generation Apprenticeship launch is doing a fabulous job at the moment. We are definitely starting to see it more across social media and reaching out to that younger generation. As Mr. Dempsey pointed out, there is no support from schools for apprenticeships. They are still struggling to get over the kind of image problem at the moment. As Mr. O'Keeffe said earlier, even parents will still discourage apprenticeships because they were always seen at one level while third level education was at another level. That is the way they were pushed. A lot of positive work is being done at the moment. It will just take some time to build up the momentum. It has to be a case of going into secondary schools and starting with the students at an earlier level, perhaps at third year and transition year and fifth year. If it starts at sixth year, it is too late. As Mr. Dempsey referenced, the student fills in his or her CAO application in October or November just for the sake of getting it done and out of the way so he or she can focus on the leaving certificate at that point. This is definitely something that could be taken into account moving forward to target the younger audience.</p>
          <p eId="para_192"> My younger brother is currently in sixth year. The students were brought to the Higher Options conference but there has been no push to bring them to any of the Generation Apprentice events. Schools could be encouraged to cast a wider net. The apprentice events are out there so there are opportunities to bring them along. Ireland Skills Live does a great job at showcasing apprenticeships and we ourselves show what can be achieved, be it through an apprentice route or a third level education route. There are amazing opportunities. The content of the logistics apprenticeship is quite similar to the third level content, so the opportunities are available at the end are also quite similar and there is huge scope for opportunity with either path.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_71">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">During transition year, all students should have the opportunity to attend a taster session of a skill or apprenticeship and learn a little more about the options through that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_72">
          <from> Ms Hanna Mathe<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">I thank the committee for inviting us. It is a huge honour, especially considering that we were 17 men and four women going to Russia for the competition. I was grateful to have the opportunity to be one of them. I can only speak for my own skill and I believe there are a couple of things that need to be addressed in terms of cookery nationwide - worldwide is a whole other conversation - especially for women.</p>
          <p eId="para_195"> I did not decide to go into cookery. I finished the leaving certificate and took a year out as I was not really sure what I wanted to do. I stumbled upon the four-year bachelor of arts honours course in Waterford Institute of Technology. I was attracted to that course because the third year is done abroad. I have just come back from that. I was placed in a one-Michelin starred restaurant in Budapest, and then at the Institut Paul Bocuse in France. I do not know if any member is familiar with it. I believe that one of the major issues in the industry that scares women off - and men as well - is the toxicity of the long hours and the fact that we will always work on those occasions other people are off. That is a whole other conversation and is something that needs to change within the job itself. Women are put off the industry when they see that working kitchens generally are made up of 80% men and 20% women, and I saw this even in Budapest and France. Head chefs and sous chefs are mostly men. A woman has to go into a kitchen and doubly prove herself. If a woman in a working kitchen asks anyone else to lift a heavy bag that she cannot, she will be looked down upon. It is extremely unfair.</p>
          <p eId="para_196"> Apprenticeships were not encouraged. My parents were not aware of the job I was going into but were very supportive. Ireland had not put forward competitors for the cookery element of the competition in a very long time so I am the first one to go in eight years. Ireland is a lot better than what we are putting forward. More funding could go towards cookery and towards publicising and advertising the fact that there are good restaurants in the country. Our food is some of the best in Europe and we should be showcasing that by sending more cookery competitors over there. I must also say a major "Thank you" to Alan McCabe - who is not here today - who was my mentor.</p>
          <p eId="para_197"> Another issue I have seen relates to training for cookery. Institutes of technology are mostly the institutions that provide cookery training. I mostly had people from other institutes of technology who came to train me, which was incredible, but younger members of the industry need to be involved too.</p>
          <p eId="para_198">People who are out working in industry need to be called on to work together with the institutes of technology to train the competitors. Having been over there, competitors need to be warned about the vast numbers of people who will be there. There were 46 competitors in my skill. I observed the skill sets and the experience they had. We could put more training into Irish competitors to compete against them. We are well able for it. This is something that should definitely be done. More encouragement should be given to women to go into kitchens. I have absolutely no idea how we can make it easier for them, but I think we could be doing much better.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_73">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">I thank Ms Mathe. It is a shame that this is not a practical session because she could have cooked dinner for all of us. It would have been nice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from> Mr. Pat Twomey<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">I represented Ireland in the construction metalwork category and, luckily enough, I came out with a medallion. I will explain how I came into the job. I would not say the career guidance I was given in secondary school would have been much of a help. Like others, I found there was a focus on college and on filling in the CAO form just for the sake of it. I was offered an apprenticeship by a man for whom I was working in a summer job. That was how I got to learn about apprenticeships. The school did not help at all, really. To be fair, SOLAS gave me some good help. Any time I had questions, I could ring them up and that was good. As I come from a Gaeltacht, I also got support from Údarás na Gaeltachta, which was a great help. My experience at Ireland Skills Live was of great assistance when I was in Kazan. I was used to having to deal with crowds passing by, and watching everyone as they did so, and that helped to calm me down and to get a little more used to it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_75">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">Mr. Twomey enjoyed it anyway.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_76">
          <from> Mr. Pat Twomey<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">I enjoyed it all right.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_77">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">Good.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_78">
          <from> Mr. Pat Twomey<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">I can answer any other questions that members might have later in the meeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_79">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">I thank Mr. Twomey.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_80">
          <from> Mr. Mark Wasson<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">I thank the committee for having me here today. I am originally from Donegal. I started secondary school, just like everyone else, and when I came to leaving certificate, there was no word of apprenticeships. When I was going through school, I had slight learning difficulties. I was not very much into books and all of that. I was always into physical tasks, like those we did in woodwork and metalwork. As everyone has said, there was a focus on going to college or to university but nothing was said about apprenticeships. The big problem with being from Donegal, or from rural Ireland in general, is that it is difficult to find employers who take on apprentices. Many employers do not know what apprenticeships are. Many of them do not want to hear about apprenticeships because they are not interested in young fellows who will be going away for weeks. This is a big problem up with us. I went through the whole of Donegal before finally getting an apprenticeship after a while. I could only get one company. After I started out, I went from strength to strength. I have done three years so far. I represented Ireland in the joinery category and I definitely enjoyed the whole thing. It was an unbelievable experience. It definitely enjoyed it all. I thank the committee for having us here today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_81">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">Mr. Wasson is welcome.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_82">
          <from> Mr. Chris Kehoe<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">I can definitely say that I cannot recommend an apprenticeship enough. It is amazing. Ireland Skills Live needs to be addressed more. It needs to be bigger. The route towards apprenticeship needs to start in primary school. People can leave secondary school at the age of 16. My dream started at primary school. Things like posters are needed to give apprenticeships a higher profile. They have to be seen more. When school pupils come to Ireland Skills Live, they get an idea of what is going on and they want to have a chance to do an apprenticeship. A greater focus on apprenticeships would strengthen Ireland's WorldSkills team. A wider level of involvement will lead to more competition and a greater number of competitors. If this sector is broadened, we will have a much better team and it is to be hoped we will get more medals.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_83">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">What is Mr. Kehoe's particular skill?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_84">
          <from> Mr. Chris Kehoe<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">I am a welder.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_85">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">Good man. I saw a video that Kildare and Wicklow Education and Training Board did about a female welder as a really good way to encourage women to get into this area of activity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_86">
          <from> Mr. Adam Flynn<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">I competed in the industrial mechanic millwright category. In Ireland, our trade is known as mechanical automation and maintenance fitting. Luckily enough, I had a brilliant engineering teacher in secondary school. Without her, I would not be here today. There was no focus whatsoever on apprenticeships other than in her class. Going into her class every week was the light at the end of the tunnel. I hated school otherwise. I had a career guidance teacher, and I could not say she was a help. Everything was focused on open days in institutes of technology and universities or on the agricultural side of things. Absolutely nothing was done to encourage people to go down the apprenticeship road. Why could they not have brought us out to industry or even to a pharmaceutical plant for an open day? There was absolutely none of that. I would like to see a greater emphasis on apprenticeships in secondary schools. If it is not driven into us when we are younger, we will not bring it with us to this kind of level. We will not get any further without somebody guiding us in the right direction. That is basically what I would like to say about it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_87">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">I thank Mr. Flynn for his observations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_88">
          <from> Mr. Jack Lynch<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">I competed in the cabinet-making competition. Like other speakers, I found when I was in school that apprenticeships were not really pushed at all. All of the focus was on the third level sector. I got sucked into that and I went to college. As I was going from third year into fourth year in college, it struck me that I would have preferred to go down the apprenticeship route. When I was in school, apprenticeship did not seem accessible to me. It seemed a bit too complicated. It was not well enough advertised. It was harder to get into an apprenticeship than to go to college. College was easy to get into because it was a case of filling out the CAO forms and there you go. The other thing seemed a bit harder to me. Basically, that was it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_89">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">I thank Mr. Lynch. It has been interesting to listen to the experiences and observations of the witnesses. On behalf of all of us, I congratulate them and assure them that they are ambassadors for Ireland in this area. We will call on them when we need to avail of more expertise as we make a input into the whole apprenticeship area. I think they have shone a light on where we need to go in this regard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_90">
          <from> Mr. Ray English<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">I would like to make a couple of points. We recognise as champions the 17 people who went to Kazan this year and indeed all of those who competed in the competition in previous years. WorldSkills has also recognised them by giving them special pins to mark their achievements as competitors and champions. We do not make enough use of that when they are back here. Why are we not sending them out to second level schools and other places? We should tell them that we are going to send them around the second level schools for a couple of weeks as part of a sort of roadshow. We need to look at how we are going to develop that idea further on.</p>
          <p eId="para_217"> Interestingly, we have just started a conversation with WorldSkills about the One School One Country programme, which the guys would have seen in Kazan. The programme involves the creation of links between schools in Kazan and teams elsewhere. When I discussed this in general terms with Dr. Mary-Liz Trant of SOLAS and Dr. Vivienne Patterson of the HEA recently, we looked at how we can translate One School One Country into a much bigger event with the involvement of Generation Apprentice and the team. We want this programme to grow dramatically within Ireland. We will propose that to the WorldSkills board when it meets here in October.</p>
          <p eId="para_218"> Although we did not have a competitor in the painting and decorating competition in Kazan, it is interesting to note that 80% of the competitors were young females. Most of them were from European countries. It is also interesting to look at some of the results from Ireland Skills Live, which was attended by 15,000 people. Slightly more young women than young men turned up at the event. The ratio was approximately 51:49 in favour of young women. This is interesting given that the event was aimed at skills, apprenticeships and undergraduate studies. We really targeted the Saturday for parents. We were not sure how it was going to work out. It was really interesting to see a huge return on one of the days from young people who were saying that this is what they want to do and asking how they can move from an undergraduate course into an apprenticeship.</p>
          <p eId="para_219"> WorldSkills Ireland runs 56 competitions.</p>
          <p eId="para_220">Some of them are new apprenticeships, so there is a changing demographic in the skills that we are involved in. It is also interesting that Ireland promoted cloud computing as a competition and it is now a WorldSkills competition. We have promoted building information modelling, BIM, as a competition, and it will be a full competition in Shanghai. We are starting to use our awareness of our economic key factors and to promote those to WorldSkills as competitions. New apprenticeships are coming on board which, when we build capacity, will also become apprenticeships. The comment about technical graphics was very interesting. That is a real lead-in to BIM as the guys there can tell the committee. How it is not an apprenticeship at this stage is beyond me, because there is a huge economic demand for it as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_91">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">It seems that there needs to be greater educational awareness, not just for the students but for the parents and for the schools, about the opportunities that exist when we think about the world that will open up to us in terms of new jobs opportunities. It was highlighted earlier by Mr. McLoughlin that we need interchangeability between courses so that people can start off something and then possibly transfer into a more niche area.</p>
          <p eId="para_222"> I congratulate all of the participants. They are all great ambassadors and we will be back to them again. We look forward to hearing all about the conference that is going to be in October. If there is a possibility for some committee members to attend, we would like to do that.</p>
          <p eId="para_223"> We are going to ask everyone, and they are very welcome to do so, to take a photograph with all of the participants, because we want to do our bit to highlight their achievements and to spread the message to media outlets that it is very important what they have, their achievements, and the fact that they are 10th in the world. That is quite incredible. That will bring them a long way in terms of future career opportunities. I thank the volunteers and mentors who were mentioned. I thank Ms Nikki Gallagher who organised today's meeting. I will see everyone outside for a quick photograph and we will resume in private session because we have a huge amount of correspondence to get through.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_92">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">I have another parliamentary party meeting to attend now. Can we postpone the next part of the meeting?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_93">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">We will deal with some of the correspondence.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DonnchadhOLaoghaire" eId="spk_94">
          <from>Deputy Donnchadh Ó Laoghaire<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">Does Mr. Brownlee wish to respond to some of the points raised at the end?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_95">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">As Mr. Brownlee did not indicate his wish to comment, does he wish to comment now?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_96">
          <from> Mr. Andrew Brownlee<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">Yes. I know specific questions were asked. On general promotion, it is using these guys as incredible ambassadors. The mainstream media did not cover the events in the way that we wanted, but the participants were stars on social media and that is the type of stuff that gets traction with young people. We need to look at different ways to get the message across.</p>
          <p eId="para_229"> We talked a lot about guidance. I do not think that it is just about guidance. We need to look at how we develop vocational options and pathways in second level as well. The last time I attended a meeting of this committee, there was a female apprentice who talked about the fact that she had to change schools because she did not have the subject options that she needed to pursue a vocational pathway. We need to look at how the role of further education and training, FET, can deliver vocational options, vocational pathways and apprenticeship-type taster programmes in transition year or as part of a junior cycle and senior cycle. There are a lot of things to think about.</p>
          <p eId="para_230"> New apprenticeships are rolling up. We are targeting about 70 by the end of the year. I understand the committee has looked at apprenticeship issues separately, and I am sure it will coming back to that. There are issues to be addressed. We need to get more employer buy-in. We are kind of getting traction in terms of changing the culture and getting families and young people more interested in vocational options. It is not just about apprenticeships. It is about traineeships, vocational degree programmes in institutes of technology, and post-leaving certificate, PLC, courses that lead to exciting careers. There is so much opportunity that we are pushing an open door if we can get the product right and promote it effectively. Mr. McLoughlin mentioned that there are prospectuses for higher education. We give a leaflet to people who are interested in apprenticeships. Therefore, we need to package things a bit more, which is a big challenge.</p>
          <p eId="para_231"> There was a specific question on instrumentation and pharma. There are new traineeships in that space. I am happy to come back to the committee members to talk about the things that are being worked on in these areas. I thank the Members for their time today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_97">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2019-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">I thank Mr. Brownlee. It has been our pleasure. We will go outside now and will resume afterwards in private session. We may not deal with everything that is on the agenda because we have a large amount of correspondence to get through after we pose for a photograph. We will get through some of the correspondence.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">
          <i>The joint committee suspended at 5.55 p.m., resumed in private session at 6.05 p.m. and adjourned at 6.25 p.m. sine die.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
