<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2003-11-26/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2003-11-26/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2003-11-26" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/29/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2003-11-26/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2003-11-26/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2003-11-26" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2003-11-26/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2003-11-26/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference showAs="Vol. 1" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/1" eId="#vol_1"/>
          <oir:numberReference showAs="No. 40" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/1/no/40" eId="#no_40"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AengusOSnodaighSF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aengus-Ó-Snodaigh.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Aengus Ó Snodaigh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BreedaMoynihanCronin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Breeda-Moynihan-Cronin.D.1992-12-14" showAs="Breeda Moynihan-Cronin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CharlieOConnorFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Charlie-O'Connor.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Charlie O'Connor"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FinianMcGrath" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Finian-McGrath.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Finian McGrath"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeCostelloLAB" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Costello.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Joe Costello"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MargaretCox" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Margaret-Cox.S.1997-09-17" showAs="Margaret Cox"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MarieHoctorFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Máire-Hoctor.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Máire Hoctor"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelMcDowellPD" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-McDowell.D.1987-03-10" showAs="Michael McDowell"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulMcGrath" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-McGrath.D.1989-06-29" showAs="Paul McGrath"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanArdagh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Ardagh.D.1997-06-26" showAs="Seán Ardagh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanOFearghaillFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Ó-Fearghaíl.S.2000-06-09" showAs="Seán Ó Fearghaíl"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SheilaTerry" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Sheila-Terry.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Sheila Terry"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chair" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chair" showAs="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chairman" showAs="Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister/justice__equality__law_reform" showAs="Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>COMHCHOISTE UM DHLÍ AGUS CEART, COMHIONANNAS, COSAINT AGUS CEARTA NA mBAN</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>JOINT COMMITTEE ON JUSTICE, EQUALITY, DEFENCE AND WOMEN’S RIGHTS</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2003-11-26">Dé Céadaoin, 26 Samhain 2003</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2003-11-26">Wednesday, 26 November 2003</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="volume">
        <docNumber refersTo="#vol_1">Vol. 1</docNumber>
      </block>
      <block name="number">
        <docNumber refersTo="#no_40">No. 40</docNumber>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 9.35 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">Members Present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeCostelloLAB">Deputy J. Costello,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#SeanOFearghaillFF">Deputy S. Ó Fearghaíl,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#MarieHoctorFF">Deputy M. Hoctor,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#CharlieOConnorFF">Deputy C. O’Connor,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#FinianMcGrath">Deputy F. McGrath,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#MargaretCox">Senator M. Cox,*</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulMcGrath">Deputy P. McGrath,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#SheilaTerry">Senator S. Terry.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#BreedaMoynihanCronin">Deputy B. Moynihan-Cronin,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">*In the absence of Senator J. Walsh.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_4">In attendance: Deputy A. Ó Snodaigh.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#SeanArdagh">
   DEPUTY S. ARDAGH in the chair.
  </person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Council Framework Decisions: Ministerial Presentation.</heading>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_10">I welcome the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, Deputy McDowell, and his officials. I invite him to make a brief presentation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Deputy McDowell)</from>
          <p eId="para_11">I thank the Chairman and committee members for coming in to deal with this matter today. It relates to a motion in Dáil Éireann and Seanad Éireann approving the draft Council framework decision on the application of the principle of mutual recognition to financial penalties. The proposal is before the joint committee on foot of motions in accordance with advice from the Office of the Attorney General regarding securing the approval of the Houses of the Oireachtas before we adopt such framework decisions. The origins of the measure are that the Tampere European Council in 1999 declared the principle of mutual recognition to be the cornerstone of judicial co-operation, particularly in criminal matters. That is the strategic alternative to the choice of harmonisation, uniformity and approximation, which is the other way of approaching criminal law in Europe. We agreed to make all the systems interoperable and base them on mutual recognition.</p>
          <p eId="para_12">At the Brussels Justice and Home Affairs Council meeting in November 2000, a programme of measures to implement the mutual recognition principle was adopted. One of those measures called for the preparation of an instrument enabling the state of residence to levy fines by way of a final decision on a natural or legal person by another member state. "Legal person" in European legal language usually means a body corporate of some kind. The purpose of the framework decision, which was proposed by the United Kingdom, Sweden and France, is to provide that a fine imposed in one member state can be recognised and executed in another.</p>
          <p eId="para_13">The substantive text of that instrument was politically agreed at the last Justice and Home Affairs Council meeting on 8 May 2003. Discussions are to continue on the text of the recitals and the certificate with a view to concluding a final text for adoption by the Council by early next year. The main provisions are as follows. Article 1 defines decisions which come within the scope of the instrument, and those include decisions regarding criminal offences, whether taken by a court or an administrative authority, where the decision of the latter is appealable to a court with criminal jurisdiction, and decisions taken by an administrative authority regarding an administrative offence where such decisions are appealable to a court with criminal jurisdiction.</p>
          <p eId="para_14">It is important to recognise here that the effect of that definition is that all offences must fall within certain criminal criteria. For example, if they are not classified as criminal offences in the state which made the decision or are not dealt with at the criminal court, they must at least be appealable to a criminal court. I point that out to the committee because we do not have administrative offences on the same basis as they do in continental Europe, where road traffic offences, which are expected to make up a large proportion of the fines concerned, may be dealt with by way of administrative fines, though I would say that we are now moving in that direction. On several fronts, the Minister for Transport, Deputy Brennan, and I are discussing ways to introduce non-court solutions for traffic offences so that gardaí do not have to spend so much time in court. The framework decision says that, if the fine is imposed by a body other than the court, it must be appealable to a criminal court to fall within the purview of the framework decision.</p>
          <p eId="para_15">Article 1(<i>b</i>) defines a financial penalty so that it can be the fine imposed in the decision, the compensation for victims imposed by the same decision, the cost of administrative proceedings or moneys to be paid to a public fund or a victim support organisation as appropriate. Articles 1(<i>a</i>) and 2(6) provide for central and competent authorities to deal with requests for mutual recognition and enforcement under the instrument.</p>
          <p eId="para_16">Article 4 is a key provision as it sets out the grounds for non-recognition and non-execution; in other words, grounds on which Ireland might refuse to recognise, say, a French fine or whatever. The first is the <i>ne bis in idem </i>principle. That means one cannot be prosecuted twice for the same offence. The second is that there is immunity under the law of the executing state. If somebody was immune under Irish law from the particular penalty they could not be prosecuted on foot of a foreign demand for a penalty. The third is where someone is not yet liable on age grounds. The fourth is where there is a decision <i>in absentia</i>. That means not simply that the person was not present but that he or she was not notified. For instance, if one was convicted of a driving offence in France or whatever, the mere fact one did not turn up for the trial would not exclude collection of the fine as long as one had been notified of the hearing in some way. The next one is a <i>de minimis </i>rule which says the fine has to be equal to or above €70.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">The last one states that if the offence is not punishable in both states there is a concept of dual criminality. However, that does not apply to the offences listed in Article 2(<i>a</i>). This is a list of offences which does not need to be verified. In other words, it is not necessary that it is an offence in both states. However, I must emphasise dual criminality is an important requirement for us to generally recognise decisions. The departure from the strict need to prove it as regards the list of offences is because the items on the list are known in this jurisdiction. Enforcement of fines for offences not on the list will still have to meet the dual criminality requirements in the ordinary way.</p>
          <p eId="para_18">While the decision requires us to execute the fine it does not contain binding requirements on us in terms of enforcement, for instance by way of imprisonment. Article 7 provides that if the fine is not paid alternative sanctions, including imprisonment, may be applied if the law of the executing state allows and the state which made the decision consents. I would, however, point out that this is not a binding provision and that Ireland will not be obliged to provide for imprisonment in default of fines imposed in other member states, nor to impose alternative sanctions.</p>
          <p eId="para_19">The general rule is that the fines collected under this instrument will go to the exchequer of the collecting state. That is interesting. One might think that if the French courts imposed a fine on an Irish motorist that the French would want that money. To make this system work it has been decided that the benefit should go to the person who does the collection and the hard work. That is to incentivise the system and make it effective. Otherwise, these requests would lie on shelves and not be executed. The exception is the case where there is a compensation award to a victim included in the amount being recovered.</p>
          <p eId="para_20">As regards the declarations on this draft framework decision, an important one from Ireland's point of view and one which we were instrumental in developing is No. 3, which provides that the agreement on the list of offences - Article 2(<i>a</i>), decisions <i>in absentia: </i>Article 4(2)(<i>e</i>), fundamental rights and legal principles and Article 16(1)(<i>b</i>) - is without prejudice to solutions for future instruments on mutual recognition and to the interpretation of existing instruments on mutual recognition. What is possible as regards minor mutual recognition instruments of this sort may not be appropriate as regards instruments which would have a greater impact on fundamental rights and requirements necessary to guarantee those rights.</p>
          <p eId="para_21">I am advised it will be necessary to make some amendments to Irish legislation to provide for the recognition and execution of fines in accordance with this framework decision. When the Oireachtas gives me the green light to agree to the framework decision and when it is put into place Ireland will then have a legal obligation to bring its law into conformity with this measure and to provide by statute for some of the provisions of the framework decision.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_22">Thank you. What about the next one?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_4" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_23">The next one is on the initiative of the Danish Presidency and relates to the 1990 Council of Europe convention on laundering, search, seizure and confiscation of the proceeds of crime and the 2001 Framework Document on money laundering, the identification, tracing, freezing, seizing and confiscation of instrumentalities and the proceeds of crime. It builds on initiatives by requiring member states to take the necessary measures to confiscate the instrumentalities and proceeds of crime from criminal offences which are punishable by deprivation of liberty of more than one year. It extends the obligation on member states to apply their confiscation measures, in addition to drug trafficking, to certain other offences committed within the framework of a criminal organisation as defined in the joint action of 21 December 1998, making it a criminal offence to participate in a criminal organisation in the member states of the European Union. That is a matter which the committee will be coming back to from a different angle shortly, criminalisation of membership of a criminal organisation. That is coming down the tracks. Just now the criminal organisation and a gang of teenagers are not the same. Bear in mind we are talking about slightly different things.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">Looking at the detailed provisions of this Framework Document on the confiscation of crime-related proceeds, Article 1 defines "proceeds", "property", "instrumentalities", "confiscation" and "legal person". The main provisions are contained in Articles 2 and 3. Article 2 requires members states to take the necessary measures to confiscate the instrumentalities and proceeds of crime from criminal offences which are punishable by deprivation of liberty of more than one year.</p>
          <p eId="para_25">Article 3 extends the obligation on member states to apply their confiscation measures, in addition to drug trafficking, to certain other offences committed within the framework of a criminal organisation. These offences include counterfeiting in connection with the euro, facilitation of unlawful entry, transit and residence, trafficking in human beings, sexual exploitation of children and child pornography and money laundering. The framework decision also extends to terrorism offences. Articles 3(<i>a</i>) and 3(<i>b</i>) make provision to ensure that interested parties who may be affected by the measures in the preceding articles have effective legal remedies to preserve their rights and ensure that fundamental rights and principles are respected.</p>
          <p eId="para_26">Article 4 is a standard provision which obliges member states to adopt measures to comply with the obligations of the instrument within two years of adoption and to transmit the text of the transposing measures to the Council secretariat. Article 5 provides that the framework decision will come into force on the day of its publication in the <i>EU Journal</i>.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">The Irish position on all of this is that the Attorney General is advised that Ireland has no difficulty with the confiscation of property or its equivalent value from a person following conviction on indictment, where this represents the proceeds of crime now set out in Article 3 of the Framework Document. However, the advice from the Attorney General's office went on to say that some limitation on the amount to be confiscated should be included to comply with the findings of the European Court of Human Rights in the Phillips <i>v. </i>UK case, 5 July 2001, where the court found, among other things, that as regards the compensation penalty to be imposed, a reasonable relationship of proportionality must exist between the means employed and the aim sought to be realised. In other words, for a trivial offence, if some vast amount of money was effectively confiscable, there would be a lack of proportionality.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">During the negotiations a proposal to resolve this issue was made by Ireland and the wording of the Irish proposal was added to the text in Article 3, paragraph 2. That inclusion limits the confiscation of the proceeds to property which has been derived from criminal activities of the convicted person during a period prior to conviction, which is deemed reasonable by the court in the circumstances of the particular case. By a decision of 17 December 2002 the Government had agreed that Ireland could give political agreement at the JHA Council of 20 December 2002 to the draft framework decision, subject to a satisfactory outcome on the limitation issue that I mentioned. The agreement by Council to inclusion of the addition enables Ireland to give political agreement at that Council meeting, subject to a parliamentary scrutiny reservation.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">This is now the parliamentary scrutiny stage. I am asking the committee to give me the green light for the adoption of a resolution in both Houses to that effect.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_30">Are there any items coming up on the JHA Council meeting agenda which are relevant to those two motions?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_6" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_31">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_32">As regards the Criminal Assets Bureau and the experiences Ireland has had as a result of it, has that had an input into the thinking on this particular motion on confiscation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_8" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_33">Conceptually these are slightly different ideas. Many countries in the European Union have what the British have, which is equivalent to a criminal bankruptcy order. This means that on the conviction of certain persons their property and money may be confiscated, if these appear to be the proceeds of crime. The triggering mechanism in many countries is a criminal conviction. The concept in Ireland is different. The Irish Criminal Assets Bureau is based on the concept, which the Supreme Court has upheld, that the proceeds of crime are not an individual's legal property and therefore their removal is not a criminal penalty. It is the removal of property that in the first place does not belong to the individual but effectively to somebody else.</p>
          <p eId="para_34">It does not require a prior criminal conviction to trigger the activities of the Criminal Assets Bureau. For instance, should the Criminal Assets Bureau bring a case before the courts, suggesting that on the balance of probabilities the €1 million in a Dublin bank account represents the proceeds of drug trafficking or whatever, it is not necessary that the account holder be put on trial and convicted of a criminal offence before the money can be taken away. In most European states, the confiscation law is at a lower level. When people are convicted of crimes, their assets are looked at and confiscation orders are then made. The United Kingdom is beginning to follow our lead on the assets recovery agency model. In one sense we are ahead of other member states and when I have explained the criminal assets bureau legislation and the Supreme Court jurisprudence they have been quite surprised that the Irish are ahead of them on the confiscation of criminal assets.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_35">It was stated in <i>The Irish Times </i>yesterday that VAT fraud is one of the areas where criminals garner major moneys. Is there a suggestion that the confiscation of money resulting from tax crime would not be enforceable in another country?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_10" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_36">The Buchanan &amp; McVeigh case law, that you could not be extradited for tax and that countries did not enforce each other's tax laws, is now crumbling and disappearing and a new principle of mutual respect and cohesion on tax is supplanting it. Generally, the drift in European law is that rebates that result from an abuse of the system are recoverable, despite the fact that they are fiscal in origin.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_37">Do they come under this motion?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_12" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_38">I think so; in principle they would.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcGrath" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Deputy P. McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_39">On that issue, I have never been aware of a case before the courts of a person being extradited because of a tax matter. There is certainly a great deal of bar talk of people having to flee from the UK with no hope of returning because of tax offences, and there is a history of subcontractors operating in the black economy in the UK returning to Ireland to set up legitimate businesses. I am not aware of extradition cases in those instances, but have there been such cases? Will these new regulations put an end to all of that? Can the UK seek retrospective retribution?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_14" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_40">The old law on extradition was set out in the case of Buchanan &amp; McVeigh, which was a classic Irish High Court decision and was followed by the English courts - that was that extradition did not apply to Revenue offences - much as it did not apply in the old days to political offences either. Deputy McGrath is correct that Irish people in the UK who were suspected of diddling the Inland Revenue were not liable to extradition under the classical law, but things have moved on since then.</p>
          <p eId="para_41">The European arrest warrant permits extradition for tax fraud - it is coming in from 1 January 2004 - and that is a point on which I have to talk in private to the Chairman. If we do not have the legislation in place by 1 January, we face a situation that we will not have extradition arrangements of any kind with the United Kingdom. That puts very considerable pressure to have the legislation through both Houses and enacted into law. It would be very embarrassing for the Irish Presidency if both Houses had not delivered a very clear commitment of that kind. I ask the committee to confer with the officials on a Committee Stage debate. I have a Second Stage debate lined up in the Dáil and I will be requesting this committee for a committee stage debate so that the Bill will be debated in both Houses as quickly as possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcGrath" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Deputy P. McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_42">Will it be taken before Christmas?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_16" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_43">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_44">We have facilitated the Minister in the past and I am sure we will do so again.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_18" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_45">My problem is that the framework decision was written in very ambitious terms, which not merely provides for a new system of rendition between member states, but abolishes the old system. This was done in the heat of the moment after 11 September and to make sure it would be done, the old system was abolished by the framework decision. We are now faced with the proposition that there will be a vacuum in law unless we get this legislation through.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcGrath" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Deputy P. McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_46">This is very important legislation that has very serious consequences from the point of view of criminal law and other aspects. It would be very interesting to learn if the possibility of extradition on fiscal matters still applies to tax exiles in the south of Spain and so on. Why is it left to the last minute to deal with this important Bill?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_47">We will take that up later.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_21" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_48">Deputy McGrath is asking a fair question. I have had the Bill published but the problem is that there is an accumulation of non-processed legislation from the Department for which I will need more time in both Houses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_49">Is the Minister proposing extending the framework decisions of 2001 and the earlier Council of Europe convention so that it would apply to confiscation of assets from drug trafficking as well as from other offences coming under the framework of a criminal organisation, as defined in the Joint Action 21 1998? I see nothing wrong with this; in fact it is very desirable the proposed legislation will extend to counterfeiting the euro, trafficking in human beings and so on.</p>
          <p eId="para_50">I would like to question the Minister on how a criminal organisation differs from a criminal gang that he has trouble with. This is essential to the issues of the clusters of lawlessness around the country. There is a structure under the 1998 joint action that covers a major part of dealing with criminal gangs or organisations and seizing their assets. In essence we are extending the provisions to apply to others in addition to drug traffickers. All we are doing in this instance is extending it beyond drug trafficking to others under a format that is already in place. Will the Minister explain how, on the one hand, he can rule out what appears to be a similar definition of a criminal organisation as it applies here in terms of trying to deal with some of our more serious crime and, on the other, indicate that this can operate in a European context when it deals with, say, another set of criminal activities which are very much related?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_23" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_51">That is a good question but there is a distinction and that is that in international law, and certainly in respect of the decision we referred to on organised crime in Europe, we are referring to structured organisations. The point I have been making to anybody who will listen to me is that we cannot say that a group of out of control teenagers in some area amounts to a structured organisation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_52">Nobody is saying that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_25" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_53">The point is that people are using the term "gang" indiscriminately to cover very different aspects. If three or four people in a particular road who are drinking pals rob a bank on the odd occasion or do over a neighbour's house or something like that, many people would refer to them colloquially as a gang. However, what the European Union insists on, and what we are dealing with here, is a structured organisation established over a period of time of more than two persons acting in concert with a view to committing criminal offences which are punishable by deprivation of liberty of a maximum of at least four years, or more serious penalties, where such offences are an end in themselves or a means of obtaining material benefits and, where appropriate, of improperly influencing the operation of public authorities. We are dealing with structured organisations, not just casual alliances of people who get together to commit individual crimes or habitual accomplices in crime.</p>
          <p eId="para_54">I have been making that point but some people like to confuse the idea of organised crime and what happens when a number of people act in concert on a series of non-organised crime. There is a difference and that is the whole problem with people using terms carelessly, if I may say so.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_55">Chairman——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_27" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_56">The difference is that if three, four or six people from a particular neighbourhood are associating with each other socially and also commit crimes, that is not organised crime within the meaning of the European statement. It must be a structured organisation. It must effectively have some permanence about it. It must operate as a structured group. If, for instance, three or four people from a particular neighbourhood or encampment commit a crime, it does not follow in those circumstances that they are a gang that falls within the definition of organised crime. A very loose analogy has been drawn between them and illegal organisations. The IRA and groups like that are structured organisations. We know they exist; that they have meetings to decide policy and that they have internal rules. We know that they are not just a casual group of republicans who, every so often, have a pint together and do something of one kind or another.</p>
          <p eId="para_57">The problem with some of the calls that teenage members of gangs should be capable of being brought before the Special Criminal Court and that a member of the Garda Síochána above a certain rank should be able to swear his belief that they are a member of a gang raises many civil liberties questions. For instance, who is and is not in this gang? If it were unstructured, surely we would have to put all the members on trial. For example, how can somebody swear on oath that Deputies McGrath and Costello form a gang - or the Technical Group - and that Deputy McGrath is a member of it without prosecuting Deputy Costello on the same evidence?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_58">The Minister is doing a lot of twisting and turning trying to suggest that a gang is not an organised, structured group.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_59">We can return to this item again.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_60">We would not expect such a gang to have a set of articles of association, hold an AGM, elect officers, take minutes and make sure they are in good standing and that they pay their subscriptions. We are not just talking about the IRA, the Mafia or the triads. There is organised crime and it is still structured. To call it, on the one hand, organised crime and then say that it does not have a formal structure is a contradiction in terms. If someone intended to import drugs from a country in Europe, Afghanistan, Colombia or wherever, it is wrong to think that can be done by a few people having a chat in an encampment somewhere - I do not know why the Minister used that particular word. It does not happen in that fashion. People have to meet and put structures and an organisation in place. Trafficking in people, child prostitution and drug trafficking cannot take place unless it is, in strict formality, in the form of organised crime.</p>
          <p eId="para_61">We can go a step further on this matter and look at the established organisations or paramilitary organisations that have existed since year one but that is not referring to the current nature of organised crime. That is probably what the Minister is not taking on board. There is no reason we cannot do this without infringing civil liberties. I do not see any reason for bringing the Special Criminal Court into the matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_31" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_62">At least we agree on that point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_63">We agree on that point. That is emergency legislation but we can deal with organised crime without bringing emergency legislation into the reckoning. It is very close to what we will be looking at over the next number of days in our hearings——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_64">That is right.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_65">——and what the country will be trying to deal with.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_35" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_66">There is that conflict. I should indicate that I will be writing a letter to the committee on these issues and dealing with the distinction between organised crime, gang crime and the like. I have a first draft of the letter available and I intend to perfect it in the next few days because a number of issues arise, such as the one I am talking about, criminal organisation joint action, which we have to examine. I agree with Deputy Costello that it is not simply a matter of something as classic as the IRA or the paramilitary gangs. We are dealing with triads, Mafia type organisations and the like but all I am saying is that it does not follow from that that every group of hooligans, teenage——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_67">That is the point. The Minister is going from a classic organisation to the exact opposite——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_37" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_68">Exactly, but there is a middle ground.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_69">——but there are many organisations in between which are well structured and organised.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_39" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_70">I agree with the Deputy that there is a middle ground of organised crime.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_71">They have everything except the set of meetings and so on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_72">I must ask Deputy Costello to put aside that item because it will be discussed in depth in our hearings.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_73">I certainly support what the Minister——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_74">I have just got confirmation that the hearings will be televised by TG4. We have a substantial list of contributors and we will hold a press conference tomorrow at 11 a.m. to announce the format in terms of who will appear, when and so on. I hope we will have a strong viewing audience for the hearings so that we engage the public in this as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FinianMcGrath" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Deputy F. McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_75">The Minister mentioned the Criminal Assets Bureau and, generally, the European Union. Are there examples of good practice in this regard? Many people believe that the money that has been confiscated by the Criminal Assets Bureau is kept in cold storage and that there is no distribution of such funds to the poorer sections of society. Are there examples of EU member states making more effective use of such proceeds? Many citizens are extremely angry about the fact that millions of euro collected by the Criminal Assets Bureau is merely lying in an account? Is there any more effective way to distribute such proceeds? Is there an example of an EU member state using such proceeds more effectively than ourselves?</p>
          <p eId="para_76">I will not harp on the issue of gangs involved in crime because we will deal with that in more detail. We are talking about a structured organisation. Those concerned organise, have weapons and are involved in drug-related and other crimes. That is not the interpretation some people have concerning those involved in anti-social behaviour, hooliganism and other such behaviour. I am surprised that I agree with the Minister on the point, that civil liberties do not have to go out the window when one is tackling crime. However, I add a word of caution in that a number of people mentioned the word "encampment" when referring to crime - I hope that is not labelling any sections of society, in particular, I refer to the Traveller community.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_45" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_77">Certainly not. I am merely making the point that on occasion people come from the same street, locality or encampment and have committed crimes in the past. One cannot say that because they have that common link and happen to know each other that they fit into the category of organised crime. From wherever they come, be they from the settled community or the non-settled community, the mere fact that they are acquaintances when they commit crimes does not make them into organised criminals. That is my point.</p>
          <p eId="para_78">The Deputy asked what should be done with the proceeds of the Criminal Assets Bureau's activities. First, unpaid tax liabilities should go back into the tax pool because they should not be earmarked for particular purposes. On other assets, after the statutory period for any claim in respect of them is exhausted, they become liable to be appropriated by the State. I have heard people suggest that they should be earmarked for particular socially beneficial activities, whereby there is a direct link between the act of confiscation and a positive benefit to the community, particularly communities which have been ravaged by crime.</p>
          <p eId="para_79">The seven year period is supposed to allow all claims that would be usually brought within six years to be dead in the water. A property is taken into ownership and if a person wants to make a claim in regard to it, he or she has six years in which to do so. After that period - this is from where the seven year period comes - it is then property which has been in the possession of somebody else for seven years and all claims in respect of it would appear to have lapsed.</p>
          <p eId="para_80">The idea of linking - the term used is "hypothecating" - individual flows of money to individual purposes is sometimes a good idea and sometimes a bad one. Given that a great deal of CAB's activities is drug related, one might say that drug rehabilitation projects should benefit from the proceeds of such activities, and that is a point of view. Much of its activity relates to the smuggling of oil and the question arises as to what should be done with the proceeds of such activities. What should be done with the proceeds in the case of the non-declaration of tax where there is vast tax evasion by what appears to be a legitimate business? People think that CAB deals only with the proceeds of drug-related crime, but much of the money it got was planning corruption money. In that context, one could argue that such proceeds should go to disadvantaged communities who are suffering from bad planning.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FinianMcGrath" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Deputy F. McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_81">Can the Minister give examples of EU member states where there is good practice in this regard?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_47" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_82">I do not know about that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_83">If a link could be made whereby money taken out of a community, as a result of which it has been decimated, as in the case of drugs, was put back in the community in the form of the proceeds of the ill-gotten gains of those concerned, that would be a powerful mechanism to empower people to believe that the system responds to their needs. That is the point Deputy Finian McGrath made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_49" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_84">I understand the point. The Exchequer has a huge pool of cash.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_85">The Exchequer wants to take everything in. It would be helpful if such proceeds could be identified and used separately for such purposes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_51" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_86">I do not know whether the members want to deal with the agenda.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_87">I want to deal with the motions first.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_88">Perhaps we might deal with a matter covered in the other document we did not discuss, the question of a levy that will be imposed in one state in respect of certain offences and collected in another state. The Minister indicated that would relate mainly to traffic offences.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_54" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_89">It probably will, but it is not confined to such offences. The great probability is that Irish people will be fined in France for traffic-related offences rather than substantive infringements of——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_90">They will be fined in France?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_56" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_91">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_92">If an offence is something more than one which would collect a penalty point, will there be a process whereby such a penalty point will be added on to one's licence, on the one hand, and, on the other——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_58" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_93">That would be a matter with which the Minister for Transport, Deputy Brennan, would have to deal. There must be - I believe some preliminary work is being done on this - mutual recognition in the case of disqualification, but this is not a matter for which my Department has responsibility and I cannot really say anything useful on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_94">This concerns a matter on which there is mutual recognition. How would an injury resulting from a road traffic accident or other offence be dealt with? In the case of an offence for which a fine would be imposed, there would be no need for anybody to travel between the countries, but in a case where somebody would be expected to be in court, is provision made for those types of cases?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_60" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_95">This area presents an interesting dilemma for Ireland. In the Road Traffic Act of 1961, there is provision for a court where it came across uninsured drivers to levy compensation as well as punishment, but that was found to be unconstitutional at a later stage because it was regarded as a civil sanction dressed up as a criminal sanction and was not limited in the manner required by law. That is a matter we will have to re-examine. Ireland had this provision in law and the courts disapproved of it. The question of compensation and the amount of compensation is a serious issue. I note the point the Deputy is making. If a French court was to award, say, €10,000 against an Irish person for knocking someone down in France, on the face of it that is recoverable from the Irish person under this system in Ireland, but the question of whether one is insured to deal with it is another day's work.</p>
          <p eId="para_96">The distinction between civil and criminal is not as clear in the continental system. I remember when I was a law student going into the Palais de Justice in Paris and seeing a poor North African fellow who was up for a mugging. He faced a <i>populaire d’état </i>acting as a prosecutor, he had the police lawyer against him and three victims, who were separately represented, were claiming compensation. It looked a bit intimidating; all the victims were separately represented in the court claiming compensation, as part of the criminal process against him. The French system is slightly different from ours and we will have to take on board differences in the systems. France would not recognise many aspects of our adversarial system and the fact that there are only two sides in a criminal case.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_97">This is a good measure but I am sure its application in the courts and the penalties that will be imposed on foot of it will cause all sorts of headaches.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_62" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_98">The direction of this measure is right. Undoubtedly, there will be headaches in terms of how we transpose it into Irish law, but that is a matter for another day.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_99">That completes consideration of the proposals.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_100">Have we dropped the clause about there being no debate in the Oireachtas?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_101">I doubt that it would be prudent of us to tell the Dáil whether I should debate it.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Messages to Dáil and Seanad.</heading>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_102">In accordance with Standing Order 85, the following message will be sent to the Dáil:</p>
          <p eId="para_103">The Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women's Rights has completed its consideration of the motions that Dáil Éireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion provided by Article 1.11 of the Treaty of Amsterdam to take part in the adoption of the following proposed measures: a proposal for a Council framework decision on the application of the principle of mutual recognition to financial penalties, a copy of which proposed measure was laid before Dáil Éireann on 23 September 2003, and a proposal for a Council framework decision on confiscation of crime related proceeds, instrumentalities and property, a copy of which proposed measure was laid before Dáil Éireann on 12 May 2003.</p>
          <p eId="para_104">In accordance with standing order 67, the following message will be sent to the Seanad:</p>
          <p eId="para_105">The Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women's Rights has completed its consideration of the motions that Seanad Éireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion provided by Article 1.11 of the Treaty of Amsterdam to take part in the adoption of the following proposed measures: a proposal for a Council framework decision on the application of the principle of mutual recognition to financial penalties, a copy of which proposed measure was laid before Seanad Éireann on 23 September 2003, and a proposal for a Council framework decision on confiscation of crime related proceeds, instrumentalities and property, a copy of which proposed measure was laid before Seanad Éireann on 12 May 2003.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Justice and Home Affairs Council: Ministerial Presentation.</heading>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_67">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_106">The next item is the briefing by the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform on the JHA meeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Deputy McDowell)</from>
          <p eId="para_107">The JHA meeting will take place tomorrow and on Friday in Brussels. I will briefly outline to the committee the outcome of the last meeting, which took place on 6 November. The committee will be aware of the topics under discussion at that one-day meeting as a pre-Council briefing was given to the committee by the Minister of State, Deputy Roche. General agreement was reached on a number of the proposals discussed. These were the Council directive on the residence permit issued to third country victims of trafficking in human beings and the decision on the European Union and Norway-Iceland mutual legal assistance. Two proposals regarding repatriation of asylum seekers were also agreed. These were the Council decision regarding refunding the costs of removals of third country nationals and the decision on the organisation of joint flights for removals.</p>
          <p eId="para_108">A preliminary debate took place on the Council directive on compensation to victims of crime, focusing on the scope of the directive, the recipients of compensation, the injury giving rise to compensation and the amount of compensation. Some countries have no compensation system. The Irish State has a non-statutory criminal injuries compensation tribunal. I outlined to the Council meeting that in the case of the Italian student who was injured in Dublin, he was awarded significant compensation. I believe it was a seven figure sum. However, the State gives compensation for what we call special damages only, not for general pain and suffering. Other countries have different models in which they give compensation for pain and suffering but the amounts are tiny. They could be as low as €1,000.</p>
          <p eId="para_109">There was an interesting <i>tour de table </i>with all Ministers contributing their tuppence worth on this complex issue. The size of the problem in providing for a general uniform approach was made clear. Holiday destination countries such as Malta, Cyprus and Greece would have significant problems in compensating, for example, two British people who get involved in a fight in a bar in one of the resorts and in which one of them sustains injuries. The question is whether it is fair on a holiday destination country to have to give money to all the people who get involved in fracas of that type. It is a serious problem for a state the size of Malta. Does it undertake to compensate everybody who gets injured, even by their compatriots, simply because it happens in that state? The Commission was impressed by the fact that it will have a significant problem trying to resolve this. In the Czech Republic the maximum amount of compensation that can be awarded is, if I remember the figure correctly, less than €5,000. Saying there is a uniform system is all very well but if it does not approximate to anything like compensation, that is another day’s work.</p>
          <p eId="para_110">The outstanding issues on the asylum directive regarding minimum standards on procedures in member states for granting and withdrawing refugee status were discussed. These issues concern the designation of safe third countries and border procedures. There are two fundamental issues in this regard. The safe third countries issue is causing unease among some member states. With regard to border procedures, some states, particularly Germany, have executive procedures for people who are found within their borders. In Germany, the police effectively physically remove them without any process in certain circumstances. There is a good deal of difficulty in getting everybody agreed on that.</p>
          <p eId="para_111">No agreement was concluded on the <i>ne bis in idem </i>proposal, which is that people should not be tried for the same offence in two jurisdictions. The Presidency will examine the proposal further. The question is arising as to whether the existing law is inadequate and whether this will add anything substantial to it. There is an existing doctrine of international law that applies in all member states, with variations between them, and the question is whether this proposal will advance the situation. It is not clear that it will.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_69">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_112">Was anything agreed at the meeting?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_70" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_113">There was agreement on the residence permit. The Chairman will remember that victims of trafficking were to be given residence permits if they came forward and co-operated with police investigations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_114">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_72" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_115">That was one matter on which there was agreement. There was agreement on the Norway-Iceland decision and on two decisions about removal of third country nationals and joint co-operation on flights.</p>
          <p eId="para_116">Turning to this week's agenda, the first item is a draft framework decision on the minimum provisions regarding the constituent elements of criminal acts and penalties in the field of drug trafficking. That is most important. The aim is to get a European baseline for dealing with drug offences across the European Union. It provides for minimum rules for punishment levels and for what constitutes drug trafficking. One of the basic problems in the past was the Dutch attitude to coffee houses and marijuana. There is hope that some type of compromise will be arrived at which will enable this to go forward. It requires unanimity and there was no unanimity between Holland and its close neighbours until now. We have no difficulty with that framework decision. We have been waiting for agreement to emerge among others.</p>
          <p eId="para_117">The EU convention on mutual legal assistance will be agreed. We have no problem with it. Ireland will make a statement to the Council that it will comply with the requirements of the instrument subject to constitutional procedures. Legislation will be required to be enacted by the Oireachtas to give effect to the proposed agreement before it can be ratified. A Bill on mutual legal assistance is being drafted in the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform and the convention will be part of that package.</p>
          <p eId="para_118">Within the area of civil law, the Presidency will be seeking political agreement on the proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council creating a European enforcement order for uncontested claims. In other words, if a person sues somebody and they do not, in Irish terms, enter an appearance or a defence and allow judgment to be entered against them, there will be a uniform system across Europe for uncontested claims against debtors.</p>
          <p eId="para_119">The next item will be preparations for a meeting on the western Balkans, which corresponds to the former Yugoslavia, Albania and so forth. The EU western Balkans forum arose from the conclusions of the Thessaloníki Summit and among the issues to be discussed will be the follow up to the London conference on organised crime in the western Balkans.</p>
          <p eId="para_120">In the asylum area the first item for discussion is a proposal for a Council directive on minimum standards for procedures for granting and withdrawing refugee status. That proposal has a deadline of 31 December 2003 for adoption on the agenda set out at Thessaloníki. It appears increasingly likely that the directive will not be agreed during the Italian presidency, as certain member states still have reservations on the proposal, and that it will fall to our EU Presidency to reach a final agreement on that matter.</p>
          <p eId="para_121">Another asylum directive concerns the qualification and status of third country nationals and stateless persons, such as refugees or persons who otherwise need international protection. On that issue, it is expected that the Presidency is likely to inquire from member states that have difficulties with the current text, whether they are in a position to resolve those difficulties. Ireland opted into that proposal on 13 February 2002 and we have no outstanding reservations on the text. We are ready to go when there is general agreement on that.</p>
          <p eId="para_122">It is also understood that the Council will be asked to note the conclusions of the seminar, "Towards More Orderly and Managed Entry in the EU of Persons in Need of International Protection", which the presidency hosted in Rome in October this year. That seminar, which was attended by my Department, was organised to discuss issues of protected entry procedures and resettlement in the EU of persons in need of international protection. The seminar is intended to inform ongoing work on this idea in the Council framework, which is required to report back to the European Council on the subject next year. The Italians have been keen on the notion of quotas and nation states' burden sharing as regards people who are in need of international protection.</p>
          <p eId="para_123">Discussions will then turn to a proposal for a Council directive on the conditions of entry and residence of third country nationals for the purpose of paid employment and self-employed economic activity. The first reading of that directive has been completed at the working group but a number of member states have expressed problems with the current draft. The JHA Council will now ask the Commission to redraft the proposal following wide consultation.</p>
          <p eId="para_124">The agenda also includes a report on the outcome of the eighth meeting of the task force of chiefs of police of EU member states, which took place in Rome in October.</p>
          <p eId="para_125">The next item relates to the draft Council conclusions on strengthening Community co-operation on civil protection assistance. This is what we would call disaster planning and civil defence issues that fall within the justice and home affairs portfolio. There are conclusions before the Council for adoption following the forest fires in southern Europe this year. The intention is to draw from the lessons of the forest fires and other cases so as to improve the system and be better prepared for future disasters within the European Union.</p>
          <p eId="para_126">Turning to immigration, discussion will focus on the establishment of the European border management agency. This is a body that is supposed to facilitate co-ordination between member states' national border management agencies. It is not supposed to be a super border guard. As the number of staff envisaged to take part in this agency is around 30, according to Commissioner Vitorino, it is not some huge European bureaucracy. It is a small co-operative body.</p>
          <p eId="para_127">The mixed committee is the committee that operates the JHA Council members of the EU and the EEA countries that are party to the Schengen agreement. There is a work programme to combat illegal immigration across maritime borders. That programme attempts to achieve co-ordinated and effective management of maritime borders within a minimum time. While Ireland does not currently experience either a significant level of illegal immigration or trafficking by sea of the type under consideration, we do have an extensive coastline that has been targeted for other forms of clandestine arrival. That is an area in which we have an interest.</p>
          <p eId="para_128">The next item on the agenda relates to two proposals that amend two existing Council regulations: a uniform format for visas; and a uniform format for residence permits for third country nationals. The new proposals seek to enhance further the security of documents by introducing biometric identifiers - microchips, in effect. The measures are on the JHA Council agenda for political agreement and have a deadline of December 2003 for their adoption, as set out at the Brussels summit in October this year.</p>
          <p eId="para_129">The agenda for the Council also includes a number of A items which are for adoption without discussion. As material on those has been included in the information notes, I do not propose to make any comment on them. It is a fairly extensive agenda running over two days. I should remind the committee that I am the Minister responsible both for home affairs and justice issues. Consequently, I have to stay for two days and listen to two agendas on these occasions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_130">I know the Minister needs to get off to the meeting to discuss so many items and it will take a long time. If members agree, we will bank the questions for the Minister. I know that is not satisfactory but it is less time consuming.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcGrath" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Deputy P. McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_131">I will be very brief, Chairman. I note the Minister is saying that he is busy and overburdened with work, but there is an alternative.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_75" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_132">I wonder what the Deputy means. Is he talking about Deputy Deasy?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcGrath" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Deputy P. McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_133">The Minister can interpret it in his own way, which, no doubt, he will, anyhow. The Minister briefly referred to the difficulties being experienced in obtaining a co-ordinated drugs policy across Europe and how it should be handled. Will he obtain a uniform policy across Europe? If so, does he think that our policy will have to be watered down to bring on board the countries he mentioned, which have a loose and easy approach to what they consider to be soft drugs? How can such a uniform approach be achieved when, for example, we have a law which states that if one is caught in possession of drugs for sale in excess of €10,000 there is a mandatory sentence of ten years? Of the hundreds of cases that have come before the courts, that has only been followed through in about 15. How does the Minister hope to achieve a uniformity of approach in Europe if we cannot even have a consistent policy on punishments for possession of large quantities of drugs?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_134">The point raised by Deputy Paul McGrath is an important one. It seems to me that when the Minister and his colleagues go to European Council meetings, we are homing in on just two issues, asylum and immigration. Some 90% of such Council meetings seem to be dealing with these two issues. An <i>ad hoc</i>, patchwork approach is being taken and there is no policy in the area. None of the member states has a policy in this area, including Ireland. We have no policy on immigration and asylum seekers other than an <i>ad hoc </i>policy, which we make up as we go along. The Minister should raise with his fellow ministers in Europe the possibility of putting together a comprehensive policy that would examine these issues logically.</p>
          <p eId="para_135">The Minister reported on the previous Council meeting but he will essentially be dealing with similar aspects in this area at the forthcoming meeting. It appears that we will have great difficulty in dealing with the issues the Minister has raised, including the introduction of minimum provisions on drug trafficking, because we cannot achieve minimum penalties. We cannot even agree on definitions of what constitutes hard or soft drugs and how each country will deal with them. It is fire brigade action from meeting to meeting and variations on the same aspects are coming up all the time. A consolidated approach is required to some of these issues in order to deal with them. I do not see much difference from what we discussed the last time, which was the removal and repatriation of third country nationals. This time we are looking at standards and plans for withdrawing refugee status, which is all much the same as before.</p>
          <p eId="para_136">Will the Minister elaborate on the need to combat illegal immigration across maritime borders? That does not seem to be a problem for us but what type of clandestine activity, other than illegal immigration or drugs trafficking by sea, could be taking place across our borders? In the Council discussions, will the Minister have an opportunity to raise the fact that we are an island nation and, as such, are subjected to more of such illegal activities. For example, all the drugs that come into this country have to come from abroad and, therefore, we need special measures, including funds, to combat illegal activity across maritime borders. Are such matters acted upon at the Council or do the Ministers just talk about them? At the previous meeting, the Minister appears to have come to a decision on the easy items while there was a general discussion on the hard items but no agreement was reached. What is the value of us having discussions here if the Minister goes to the Council for a further range of discussions with no overall policy? The Minister does not know where he is going. A couple of nice items come up and he agrees to put our stamp on them, but when difficult matters arise he kicks to touch. The nice little talking shop then adjourns for lunch and the Minister flies home.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_78" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_137">I do not relish trips to Brussels for the purpose of sitting through Council meetings for two days for a free lunch. I would much prefer to be doing business of a worthwhile kind, whether in Brussels or Dublin.</p>
          <p eId="para_138">To go back to Deputy McGrath's point about the enforcement of our drugs laws, first, our law is compatible with the EU framework decision, we will not have to change anything. Sitting through those discussions, I know that I will not have to change one word of our law to comply with the framework decision, as it is likely to be adopted. This is about establishing a common floor across the EU and our laws are well above that floor. It does not cause me any great heart searching.</p>
          <p eId="para_139">The Netherlands' cannabis coffee-house issue is significant from the Germans' point of view because they have a harder law on cannabis, yet their population is free to cross the border and purchase the drug in the Netherlands. Trying to enforce such a law in Germany where people are free to cross the border to Holland and purchase cannabis is problematic. Our law is not at issue in this regard and changing our law is not what is involved.</p>
          <p eId="para_140">On the point about minimum sentences, I have said in the Dáil, and I will repeat it here, that that is the law as laid down by both Houses of the Oireachtas. It is the law unless it is found to be unconstitutional and reversed. It is not in some limbo and it is not open to the Judiciary to dine selectively at the Statute Book. If it deals with a case of that kind, it must do so fully. The problem is that in a number of cases we failed to cut off the loophole of allowing suspension of part of the sentence and we may have to deal with that issue under the terms of the Criminal Justice Act. We may have to revisit it and say that the sentence shall not be suspended.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_79">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_141">Maybe it was a bad penalty in the first place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_80" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_142">Maybe it was a bad penalty in the first place but that is an issue we will have to revisit. At present, the courts have the power to suspend a portion of any penalty they impose. As I understand it, they are interpreting this law as giving them the power to suspend a portion of it. Therefore, we arrive at a situation where there is a nominal sentence in conformity with the offence but an actual sentence that is not in conformity with it. As Deputy Costello said, we have to ask whether a deterrent penalty of that kind is effective or whether a lower deterrent penalty of five or seven years might not attract a more full-blooded implementation. I do not know. That is an issue for another day and we will have to come back to it.</p>
          <p eId="para_143">Deputy Costello asked about the asylum and immigration policy. An asylum policy is emerging from these Council directives at present. One of the problems with them, however, is that there is a unanimity rule at present and Ireland favours qualified majority voting on asylum matters in future. The fact that everybody has to agree to every last comma and letter in every framework decision is undoubtedly holding up the process. I share Deputy Costello's sense of frustration; it is frustrating that this is taking so long. There is no doubt about that but that is what happens when everybody can simply raise a finger and say "no". Currently, as we are dealing with 15 member states, any of whom can say they have a difficulty with this or that clause, it goes on to the next Council meeting. That is the situation we are facing. If QMV comes in this area, which the Government believes it should, there would be much more rapid progress towards consensus positions than exists.</p>
          <p eId="para_144">I take on board what Deputy Costello said about an immigration policy. The beginnings of an immigration policy are emerging now in that, whereas now it is a matter for member states to decide on immigration, the Italians have sought a study on quotas. In that respect, the EU - not on the basis of a mandatory imposition of quotas on member states - would ask member states whom they would allow into their countries. A planned approach would be adopted involving how many people would come, and in those circumstances they can go to countries of source and say that this is the kind of orderly migration the EU collectively anticipates will take place. That is on the cards and the Italians have started the ball rolling.</p>
          <p eId="para_145">I mentioned the framework decision on QMV and unanimity, but a directive governs asylum and immigration matters, not a framework decision.</p>
          <p eId="para_146">On maritime boundaries, it is worthwhile remembering that serious people trafficking is taking place in the Mediterranean from the north coast of Africa to Malta, Italy, Greece and Spain. That is in progress virtually all the time. As with the boat people from Indochina in the past, there are hundreds of little boats constantly probing the defences of southern Europe. Some of the voyages have ended tragically with boats sinking and people being lost at sea. Those areas face a serious problem on that front. Recently, we were suspicious about one ship but we have never faced the notion of having gardaí standing on every peninsula with binoculars looking for such boats.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcGrath" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Deputy P. McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_147">The Minister should have them on the streets at night.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_82" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_148">We do not have that problem because of our location but Deputy Costello is correct in saying that drugs and arms are coming into Ireland from Europe. I raised this point with Minister Donner, my opposite number in the Netherlands. We have significant problems in Ireland which are directly connected to the drugs and organised crime scene in the Netherlands. While it does not all originate there, a significant amount of money laundering, firearms dealing, drugs transhipment and synthetic drugs manufacture seems to be centred in that country. That is a significant problem from our point of view and it feeds into the need for the Netherlands to adopt standards with which the rest of Europe can live.</p>
          <p eId="para_149">Deputy Costello is aware that cannabis and amphetamine shipments are carried out on a highly organised basis and that a "lucky bag" of firearms is often included in such shipments. We sometimes take a totally myopic view of the world. In Britain at present, the use of firearms by young gangsters is a major problem and there have been a huge number of on-street shootings. Certain parts of Britain are facing much greater problems than we are at present. We sometimes think that problems only exist in Ireland and that this is a phenomenon that we, uniquely, are failing to address. This problem affects both islands and there is a huge range of weapons available to young gang members to use on each other, for virtually no reason, in Britain and Ireland. That is an issue we will be addressing in the coming weeks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_150">I hope the matter to which I am about to refer was not dealt with prior to my arrival. I refer to the proposal for a Council directive on conditions of entry in respect of paid employment and self-employed economic activity. That directive states that some member states have expressed concerns about the current text of the proposed directive. Is the Minister satisfied with that text and could he outline it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_151">One of the documents states that drug trafficking is a heinous crime. Surely it should be a serious or non-serious crime.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_85" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_152">Did I use the word "heinous"?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_153">No, and I am sure the Minister would not do so.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_87">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_154">The Deputy is referring to the European Council document.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_155">I was referring to the draft framework on the minimum provisions on the elements of criminal acts and penalties in the field of drug trafficking. Are these documents proofed in terms of their use of emotive rather than legal language? For example, the term "the Council is determined to fight with all possible means" is used in the draft framework.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_89">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_156">Those are fighting words.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_157">Yes. Reference is also made to the "intensified fight against drug trafficking". This is quite emotive language.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_91" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_158">It is like something one would see in the manifesto of an Irish political party.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcGrath" eId="spk_92">
          <from>Deputy P. McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_159">Like the promise in the programme for Government in respect of 2,000 additional gardaí.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_93" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_160">On Deputy Ó Snodaigh's point, I understand that the Germans have a difficulty with the Justice and Home Affairs Council trespassing significantly on the area of employment. They believe it is outside our vires. It may be that this difficulty will delay progress on the proposal.</p>
          <p eId="para_161">We are trying to adopt a common approach to people who come into the Union to work and to identify their rights. At present, Ireland allows the entry of, and welcomes, Filipino nurses, but do we inform their spouses that they may not work? That is an issue with which I must frequently deal. The situation is similar with students. If we allow people to enter the country for the purpose of pursuing a course in languages, in what circumstances are they allowed to remain and study? Should these people be allowed to work to support themselves in their studies? There is also the example of those who move across or enter the Union for the purposes of carrying out research. We are seeking to achieve a common approach in respect of such issues. A number of measures are under discussion in respect of those issues. These measures are aimed at bringing about a uniform approach.</p>
          <p eId="para_162">The Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Noel Dempsey, recently visited Beijing to investigate the question of Irish educational institutions offering Chinese people the opportunity to come here to study foreign languages. Chinese students come here, benefit the economy in a number of ways, pay for their tuition, work hard and welcome work while they are in the country. Is Ireland free to develop this relationship with China without regard to its implications for the rest of Europe or should member states adopt and co-ordinate single approaches to issues of this nature? Those are some of the matters under discussion at Justice and Home Affairs Council meetings.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_94">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_163">We have achieved continuity because we discussed certain matters at our meeting before 6 November and we have now discovered the outcomes. We look forward to the Minister's report on the meeting that will take place on the 27 and 28 of November, particularly in the context of the matters we have raised. I thank him for helping us to achieve the continuity to which I refer.</p>
          <p eId="para_164">I thank the Minister and his officials for attending and for briefing the committee. We look forward to his attendance at a meeting in the not too distant future.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">Sitting suspended at 10.57 a.m. and resumed at 11 a.m.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_5">
        <heading>Criminal Justice System: Presentation.</heading>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_95">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_165">I welcome Mr. Caomhín Ó hUiginn and Ms Valerie Fallon. Members of the committee may ask Mr. Ó hUiginn questions on aspects of the criminal justice system. I ask the assistant secretary to tell us his background and responsibilities and how he can assist us in dealing with this matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_96">
          <from>Mr. Caomhín Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_166">I work in the criminal law reform division of the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform. Earlier the Minister mentioned that he is preparing a note for the committee on some aspects of criminal law that he considers may be relevant and helpful when it examines the criminal justice system in the context of recent developments. His note shall deal with a number of issues. In the time available I propose to go through some of the points that he will bring to the committee's attention. The five areas are as follows: substantive criminal law, powers of investigation, unco-operative witnesses, the protection of witnesses and witness evidence, the protection of jurors and the prosecution's right of appeal.</p>
          <p eId="para_167">An extensive body of criminal law already exists and a substantial proportion of it has been updated in recent years. Updated laws include legislation dealing with fraud, including computer fraud, theft, offences against the person, drug trafficking, trafficking in people, sexual offences and money laundering offences. They provide for substantial penalties for the offences concerned. However, the Minister is always open to suggestions to change the law to deal with particular crime problems.</p>
          <p eId="para_168">The Minister, in his note, shall deal with some of the issues and difficulties relating to the possible offence of membership of a criminal gang. For present purposes I draw the committee's attention to international developments for the definition of participation in organised crime. The European Union, in a joint action on participation in a criminal organisation, and the UN, in the convention on transnational organised crime, has attempted similar definitions. In general, the international instance provides that parties to the instruments should deal with organised crime in their legislation either by making it an offence for a person to agree with others to carry out certain serious crimes - that would be equivalent to our offence of conspiracy - or by making it an offence to actively take part in the activities of a criminal organisation, or in its other activities, with the intent or knowledge of either the aim or general criminal activity of the group.</p>
          <p eId="para_169">At present the Minister is examining the definitions contained in the EU and UN instruments with a view to bringing forward whatever legislation is necessary to give effect to them. I can make the text of the relevant instruments available to the committee to facilitate its study of the matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_97">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_170">The secretariat will circulate them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_98">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_171">The Minister will go into more detail in his paper about a number of specific proposals he has for legislative change on conspiracy and the possession of documents or other articles with criminal intent in the context of tackling criminal gangs.</p>
          <p eId="para_172">I shall now deal with the investigation of crime. I know that the committee is already examining the published scheme of the Criminal Justice Bill and that it has been briefed by the Minister on its provisions. Therefore, I will describe it in detail. The Bill shall provide for increased powers of detention for an arrestable offence that is punishable by five years imprisonment or more. The detention period will be increased from a maximum of 12 hours to a maximum of 24 hours.</p>
          <p eId="para_173">An amendment to the definition of an arrestable offence will include common law offences punishable by five years imprisonment or more. This includes conspiracy. A general power shall be given to the District Court to issue a search warrant in respect of arrestable offences and also to provide that, in exceptional circumstances of urgency, a senior member of the Garda, not below the rank of superintendent, will be empowered to issue a warrant that expires after 24 hours; to reclassify saliva from an intimate to a non-intimate sample; to classify a mouth swab as a non-intimate sample; to clarify that hair samples, other than pubic hair, can include hair roots and to provide that the period for which samples may be retained before being destroyed will be increased from six months to 12 months.</p>
          <p eId="para_174">On the issue of a DNA databank, the Minister believes that we need to make as extensive use as is possible of the DNA profiling technique having regard to the constraints of the Constitution and of the European Convention on Human Rights. He awaits the report of the Law Reform Commission on the matter before bringing forward his proposals.</p>
          <p eId="para_175">I shall now deal with the issue of uncooperative witnesses. They can, depending on the circumstances, be prosecuted for perjury, contempt of court, an offence under section 7 of the Criminal Law Act 1997 or an offence under section 9 of the Offences Against the State (Amendment) Act 1998. The first two offences are common law but the latter two are recent provisions. Section 7 of the 1997 Act created an offence of impeding the apprehension or prosecution of a person who has committed an arrestable offence. The sentence for the offence is related to the substantive offence, the investigation or prosecution of which is being impeded. The maximum penalty ranges from three to ten years.</p>
          <p eId="para_176">Section 9 of the Offences Against the State (Amendment) Act 1998 provides for the offence of withholding information that could prevent the commission of a serious offence or secure the apprehension, prosecution or conviction of a person for a serious offence. It is punishable by imprisonment for up to five years.</p>
          <p eId="para_177">I wish to deal with the protection of witnesses, witness evidence and the protection of jurors. There are provisions in the Criminal Justice Act 1999 aimed at facilitating the participation in criminal proceedings of witnesses who may be in fear or subject to intimidation. Section 9 of the Act provides for the taking of sworn depositions by a District Court judge where he or she is satisfied that it would be in the interests of justice to do so. Either the prosecution or the defence can make such an application. These depositions may be admitted in evidence in certain circumstances. One circumstance is where the deponent does not give evidence at the trial through fear or intimidation. The deposition is taken in the presence of the judge and the witness may be cross-examined and re-examined on behalf of the accused.</p>
          <p eId="para_178">Section 39 of the Act permits any person in criminal proceedings on indictment other than the accused, who is in fear or subject to intimidation, to give evidence through a live television link, with the leave of the court. This also applies in the case of the sworn deposition procedure that I have just outlined. Section 40 makes it an offence for any person, without lawful authority, to try to identify or disclose information about the whereabouts or new identity of a witness who has been relocated under a Garda witness protection programme.</p>
          <p eId="para_179">Section 41 of the 1999 Act also creates a statutory offence for a person to harm or threaten, menace or in any other way intimidate or put in fear another person who is assisting in the investigation by the Garda Síochána of an offence, or is a witness or potential witness or a juror or potential juror in proceedings for an offence, or a member of his or her family, with the intention thereby of causing the investigation or the course of justice to be obstructed, perverted or interfered with. A person found guilty of an offence under the section shall be liable, on summary conviction, to a fine not exceeding €1,500 and/or imprisonment for a term not exceeding 12 months, or, if found guilty on indictment, to a fine and/or imprisonment for a term not exceeding ten years.</p>
          <p eId="para_180">The issue of providing protection for jury members in addition to the provisions just mentioned during trial proceedings, by way of provision for their anonymity, also arises. The Juries Act 1976 makes provision for matters relating to juries, including provisions relating to qualification and liability for service as a juror, and the selection and service of jurors. The prosecution and the defence are given the opportunity to challenge members of the jury prior to such members being sworn in whether on cause shown or without cause.</p>
          <p eId="para_181">There are obvious difficulties if anonymity is to be given to jury members as it could serve to limit the right of the defence to challenge, with or without cause, members of the jury. For example, in the UK a judge, in exceptional circumstances, may order that the names of the jurors be withheld and that they be balloted by number. The defence is entitled to inspect the panel from which the jury is drawn, as is the case here. The problem is likely to be more acute in cases where the court is sitting in regional areas where there is the increased likelihood that the members of the jury may be known to the accused. It is possible under our law to have cases transferred from regional areas to Dublin. It happened recently when it proved difficult to empanel a jury. Section 32 of the Court and Court Officers Act 1995 makes provision for the transfer of trials in criminal cases by Circuit Court judges. Where a person has been sent for trial to the Circuit Court sitting outside the Dublin circuit, the judge may, on the application of the prosecutor or the accused, transfer the trial to the Circuit Court sitting in the Dublin circuit if satisfied that it would be manifestly unjust not to do so.</p>
          <p eId="para_182">The issue of admissibility of prior witness statements will be central to the committee's examination. It is what use a court can make of a prior witness statement when the witness subsequently refuses to testify at trial or recants on the statement previously made.</p>
          <p eId="para_183">In Irish courts a previous statement made to gardaí cannot be admitted in evidence as proof of any fact contained in it. The fact that a witness may have previously said something different can be used to attack the credibility of the witness but the assertions in the earlier statement cannot constitute proof of those assertions. The basis of this approach is that the Constitution guarantees the right to a trial in due process. However, due process requires that the defence has a right to be presented with evidence in court by a witness who can be cross-examined and whose demeanour and credibility can be assessed by the court. The requirement that the defence must, at some stage during the proceedings, have the right to challenge and question a witness is echoed in the rulings of the European Court of Human Rights on the rights that derive from the Convention on Human Rights.</p>
          <p eId="para_184">Aspects of the rule have been relaxed. For example, statements by witnesses who have died or, as I mentioned, by the admission as evidence at a trial of sworn depositions where the witness does not give evidence through fear or intimidation.</p>
          <p eId="para_185">Other jurisdictions have gone further. The UK has provided in its Criminal Justice Act 1988 that a statement by a witness to a police officer can be admitted in evidence as proof of its contents if the person who made the statement does not give oral evidence at trial through fear. Other jurisdictions have also taken a flexible approach to the admission of statements made out of court. Such provisions may not meet our constitutional requirements for due process. The Minister is interested in the approach of the Canadian Supreme Court that allows for the admission of prior statements, subject to certain safeguards to protect against the dangers that the traditional hearsay rule seeks to guard against.</p>
          <p eId="para_186">The Supreme Court of Canada said in its judgment in the case of R <i>v</i>. KGB that a prior statement can be admitted if it would otherwise be admissible as the witness’s oral evidence and if the judge is satisfied that indicia of reliability are present and genuine. The indicia are as follows: that a warning must have been given to the witness of the necessity to tell the truth and of the consequence of not doing so; that the statement was made on oath or solemn affirmation; and that it was video recorded or that other substitute indicia are established.</p>
          <p eId="para_187">The judge must also be satisfied that the statement was made voluntarily and that there are no other factors that would tend to bring the administration of justice into disrepute. In coming to this conclusion the court was careful to ensure, in particular, that the witness could be subject to contemporaneous cross-examination from the defence and that the jury would have the opportunity to examine, not just the words of the witness, but also his or her demeanour. The court was satisfied that these concerns could be adequately dealt with by the witness being available for cross-examination in court on the previous statement and that a video recording of the original statement may be available. The Minister has already announced that he has initiated a study of the Canadian approach and will deal with it in his paper.</p>
          <p eId="para_188">The Minister will also deal with prosecution appeals. While there are broad defence rights of appeal in Irish law there exists only a very limited prosecution right of appeal.</p>
          <p eId="para_189">In May 2002 the Law Reform Commission issued a consultation paper on the subject. It stated that it strongly believes that Irish law should move from a near token system of prosecution appeals to one in which prosecution appeals would represent a real and substantial element in the criminal process. It further sets out five possible options for reform ranging from a narrow without prejudice model to a comprehensive with prejudice model. It will issue a report making its final recommendations in due course.</p>
          <p eId="para_190">In the meantime the DPP has raised the need to extend the provisions of the 1967 Act to make it possible for him to appeal, without prejudice, a decision of a court on a point of law even if the point does not arise from a judge-directed acquittal. The criminal justice Bill contains a number of prosecution appeal provisions that incorporate the specific proposal made by the DPP.</p>
          <p eId="para_191">The provisions come within the narrow without prejudice model provisionally recommended by the Law Reform Commission. The Minister will consider whether, and to what extent, we can go further in the area of prosecution appeals. As soon as the commission's final report is available he will examine it with a view to ascertaining what, if any, further legislative provisions are required.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_192">I thank Mr. Ó hUiginn for his informative and useful contribution.</p>
          <p eId="para_193">The following statement seems to adopt a wide approach:</p>
          <p eId="para_194">The UK has provided . . . that a statement by a witness to a police officer can be admitted in evidence as proof of its contents if the person who made the statement does not give oral evidence at trial through fear.</p>
          <p eId="para_195">Can the same approach be adopted in Ireland?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_100">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_196">The essential issue in Ireland is the constitutional provisions on due process. For example, the case re Haughey established that an accused must be in a position to confront the accuser, or any witness giving evidence against them, and cross-examine them on their statement. The issue also arose in the context of the Canadian decision. The statement would have been video recorded initially but in court a person could be confronted.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_101">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_197">Could the witness's demeanour, etc. be taken into account?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_198">Yes, and they could be questioned.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_103">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_199">Does the witness not have to be present in the UK system, even though a person recants their claims? Juries can impute certain things from demeanour, etc.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_200">In England if a witness is not present because of fear their statement is admitted in court.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_105">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_201">Will the Minister present us with this type of document?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_202">He will expand on some of these issues. I tried to present the committee with the factual situation regarding the current provisions in law that protects witnesses and jurors.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_107">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_203">That is part of it. The assistant secretary mentioned new issues such as creating the offence of being a member of a criminal gang. He also touched on issues on which the Minister shall make proposals.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_108">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_204">The Minister will go into more detail about the difficulties pertaining to the latter issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_109">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_205">Substantial powers of protection for witnesses already exist. If a witness is not prepared, through fear or intimidation, to give a testimony a deposition can be taken and presented in court.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_110">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_206">Yes. Even at that stage a deposition can be made through video link. There are two choices for giving depositions. First, a witness may be present in court, give evidence and be cross-examined or use a video link in another room. In that situation the witness would be available for cross-examination on behalf of the accused.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_111">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_207">Is that if the judge allows it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_112">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_208">The judge must allow it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_113">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_209">The prosecution can also request it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_114">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_210">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_115">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_211">For example, in the case that gave rise to all of these meetings, many witnesses were not prepared to proceed and recanted their testimony. Would the prosecution not have known that prior to the witnesses appearing in court? Why did the prosecution not seek to get a deposition instead if it already knew the outcome resulted from fear? Is this just a provision that it not used in practice?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_116">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_212">No, it does happen because it was discussed in another context in the Fennelly report. That report discussed whether the deposition should be taken in the District Court or the court of trial. The fact that the matter was discussed in the Fennelly report, by reference to depositions that had already occurred, suggests that it is used by the prosecution. I cannot answer the Deputy's question on whether it was considered for a particular case or why it was not done. The committee shall meet the DPP.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_117">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_213">He may not talk about the issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_118">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_214">I presume that he will not talk about the case. However, he may talk about the general issue of when they might consider doing it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_119">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_215">The UK and Canada were given as examples. Are other jurisdictions being looked at? Will we be able to draw on information from other countries?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_120">
          <from>Ms Valerie Fallon</from>
          <p eId="para_216">Yes, we are looking at other jurisdictions. We looked at Canada because the Minister was particularly interested in the provision and it seemed to address the issue of giving the defence an opportunity to cross-examine witnesses. There are provisions in other jurisdictions but we have not been able to look at them in the time available. We will try to do so as part of a study of what is possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_121">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_217">Canada does not have a legislative provision but it is a development of common law and is a reversal of a traditional view of the hearsay rule. The Canadian case was also mentioned in a recent case before the Court of Criminal Appeal. As it was not related to a point at issue in the trial the Judiciary expressed no view as to whether it would be acceptable. I can let the committee have a copy of the case. The courts are aware of it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_122">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_218">If you would, please.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_123">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_219">The British provision of giving a statement to a police officer has constitutional problems. Do they relate to questioning in the same circumstances? Are statements videotaped in Britain? Is the Minister thinking about the Canadian proposal and will he shift the hearsay rule from common law to statute here?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_124">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_220">I shall answer the last question first. The Minister cannot direct the courts on how to deal with the hearsay rule. The only way he could introduce the provision is through legislation.</p>
          <p eId="para_221">The Deputy asked whether the British have an equivalent provision to what is contained in the 1999 Act. I do not know the answer. We will do some research and we will forward it to the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_125">
          <from>Deputy Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_222">Why is one provision questionable constitutionally?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Mr. Ó hUiginn</from>
          <p eId="para_223">It is a question of being able to cross-examine a witness on their statement. We attempted to set down the current extensive provisions. The one area that is not covered in law is the Canadian situation. The committee shall probably return to the issue later.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanArdagh" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_127">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_224">We have had a very useful debate.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">The joint committee adjourned at 11.40 a.m. until 9.30 a.m. on Friday, 28 November 2003.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
