<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2008-04-30/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2008-04-30/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2008-04-30" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/30/select_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2008-04-30/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2008-04-30/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2008-04-30" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2008-04-30/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_justice_equality_defence_and_womens_rights/2008-04-30/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None" showAs="Vol. None" eId="#vol_None"/>
          <oir:numberReference href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None/no/None" showAs="No. None" eId="#no_None"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="withdrawn" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Withdrawn" showAs="Withdrawn"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCEvent eId="bill.2008.2.dail.3" href="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2008/2/dail/3" showAs="Immigration, Residence and Protection Bill 2008: Dáil Committee Stage"/>
        <TLCEvent eId="bill.2008.2.dail.3.amd_19" href="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2008/2/dail/3/amd_19" showAs="Immigration, Residence and Protection Bill 2008: Dáil Committee Stage - Amendment No. 19"/>
        <TLCEvent eId="bill.2008.2.dail.3.amd_19.withdrawn" href="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2008/2/dail/3/amd_19/withdrawn" showAs="Immigration, Residence and Protection Bill 2008: Dáil Committee Stage - Amendment No. 19 (Withdrawn)"/>
        <TLCEvent eId="bill.2008.2.dail.3.amd_20" href="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2008/2/dail/3/amd_20" showAs="Immigration, Residence and Protection Bill 2008: Dáil Committee Stage - Amendment No. 20"/>
        <TLCEvent eId="bill.2008.2.dail.3.amd_20.withdrawn" href="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2008/2/dail/3/amd_20/withdrawn" showAs="Immigration, Residence and Protection Bill 2008: Dáil Committee Stage - Amendment No. 20 (Withdrawn)"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AengusOSnodaighSF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aengus-Ó-Snodaigh.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Aengus Ó Snodaigh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BobbyAylward" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Bobby-Aylward.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Bobby Aylward"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BrianLenihan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Brian-Lenihan.D.1996-04-02" showAs="Brian Lenihan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BrianOShea" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Brian-O'Shea.S.1987-04-25" showAs="Brian O'Shea"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CharlesFlanagan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Charles-Flanagan.D.1987-03-10" showAs="Charles Flanagan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DenisNaughten" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Denis-Naughten.S.1997-01-28" showAs="Denis Naughten"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FinianMcGrath" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Finian-McGrath.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Finian McGrath"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PatRabbitte" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pat-Rabbitte.D.1989-06-29" showAs="Pat Rabbitte"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PeterPowerFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Peter-Power.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Peter Power"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanConnick" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Connick.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Seán Connick"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ThomasByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Thomas-Byrne.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Thomas Byrne"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chair" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chair" showAs="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chairman" showAs="Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister/justice__equality__law_reform" showAs="Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>ROGHCHOISTE UM DHLÍ AGUS CEART, COMHIONANNAS, COSAINT AGUS CEARTA NA mBAN</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>SELECT COMMITTEE ON JUSTICE, EQUALITY, DEFENCE AND WOMEN'S RIGHTS</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2008-04-30">Dé Céadaoin, 30 Aibreán 2008</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2008-04-30">Wednesday, 30 April 2008</docDate>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Select Committee met at 2.40 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#BobbyAylward">Deputy Bobby Aylward,+</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#FinianMcGrath">Deputy Finian McGrath,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#ThomasByrne">Deputy Thomas Byrne,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#DenisNaughten">Deputy Denis Naughten,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#SeanConnick">Deputy Seán Connick,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#BrianOShea">Deputy Brian O’Shea,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#CharlesFlanagan">Deputy Charles Flanagan,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#PatRabbitte">Deputy Pat Rabbitte.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#BrianLenihan">Deputy Brian Lenihan, <i>(Minister</i>
                                    </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <i>for Justice, Equality and Law</i>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11"><i>Reform)</i>,</p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">+In the absence of Deputy Seán Connick, for part of meeting.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_4">In attendance: Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#PeterPowerFF">DEPUTY PETER POWER IN THE CHAIR.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Intoxicating Liquor - Public Order Bill 2008: Discussion with Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform.</heading>
        <speech by="#PeterPowerFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_12">I welcome the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, Deputy Brian Lenihan, and his officials.  The purpose of the meeting is to allow the Minister an opportunity to brief the select committee on his proposals in regard to a Bill published last week entitled the Intoxicating Liquor-Public Order Bill 2008.  Is it agreed to have a short briefing on the Bill before returning to our consideration of the Immigration, Residence and Protection Bill 2008, to conclude at 4.45 p.m.?  Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Deputy Brian Lenihan)</from>
          <p eId="para_13">I thank members of the select committee for facilitating me on this issue.  In my recent public statements on this matter I asked Opposition parties to consider the early enactment of this legislation before the summer recess.  I am anxious to give members as much information as I can at this stage on these legislative proposals.</p>
          <p eId="para_14">I established an alcohol advisory group in January, with Dr. Gordon Holmes as chairman.  Dr. Holmes had chaired a previous Government advisory group on this subject and expressed to me his concern that previous commissions which had examined the intoxicating liquor legislation did not have a mandate of sufficient clarity to examine the harmful aspects of alcohol consumption as a factor which would influence the formulation of the intoxicating liquor code.</p>
          <p eId="para_15">I requested Dr. Holmes to examine key aspects of the law governing the sale and consumption of alcohol, focusing on three issues as follows: the increase in the number of supermarkets, convenience stores and petrol stations with off-licences and the manner and conditions of sale of alcohol products in such outlets, including below unit cost selling and special promotions; the increasing number of special exemption orders permitting longer opening hours being obtained by licensed premises; and the use, adequacy and effectiveness of existing sanctions and penalties, especially those directed towards combating excessive and under-age alcohol consumption.</p>
          <p eId="para_16">The group engaged in a public consultation process and received approximately 200 submissions.  Its report was presented to me at the end of March and I published it alongside the legislative proposals.  The group made 31 recommendations, not all of which are being implemented in the Bill because the Government legislation programme provides for a comprehensive sale of alcohol Bill to be published this year.  The larger Bill will modernise and streamline all the laws relating to the sale and consumption of alcohol by repealing the Licensing Acts 1833 to 2004, as well as the Registration of Clubs Acts 1904 to 2004, and replacing them with updated, consolidated, codified and streamlined provisions.  This will give us an opportunity to examine all the relevant issues in a comprehensive manner.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">I was so concerned by the reports I had received from the Garda Síochána and the general situation, of which most members are well aware, that I decided we needed short and immediate legislation to deal with the grosser abuses that have developed in the licensing code.  The general scheme in the draft Bill is, by and large, based on recommendations made by the alcohol advisory group.  The strategy underpinning the draft legislation is one which tackles the increased visibility and availability of alcohol through retail outlets with off-licences, while tightening the conditions under which premises with on-licences qualify for special exemption orders permitting them to remain open beyond normal licensing hours.  The Bill specifically provides for improved enforcement and penalties, as well as strengthening public order provisions.</p>
          <p eId="para_18">Regarding the sale of alcohol, applicants for a wine retailer's off-licence will be required to produce a District Court certificate to the Revenue Commissioners.  At present, such off-licences can be acquired by simple application to the Revenue Commissioners.  Under the legislation, the wine retailer's off-licence will become the same as any other off-licence and require District Court sanction.  In addition, the grounds on which objection may be made to the grant of District Court certificates for spirit, beer and wine off-licences will be extended to include the suitability of licensed premises for the needs of local residents and the adequacy of the existing number of licensed premises in the neighbourhood.  This is a substantial curtailment of the availability of such licences.</p>
          <p eId="para_19">Off-sales of alcohol shall be permitted only between the hours of 10.30 a.m. and 10 p.m. - noon until 10 p.m. on Sundays - in the case of off-licences and mixed trading premises.  Test purchasing of alcohol by persons under the age of 18 years, subject to necessary safeguards, will be introduced to ensure the strict application of the law on the sale of alcohol to minors in retail outlets.</p>
          <p eId="para_20">With regard to extended trading hours, the grant of special exemption orders to nightclubs shall be made subject to compliance with fire safety standards.  This is a serious omission in the current legislation and one we should not wait to remedy.  The District Court will not grant a special exemption order for any premises unless satisfied that the special occasion will be conducted in a manner that will not cause undue inconvenience or nuisance to persons residing in the locality or create an undue threat to public order or safety.  The granting of special exemption orders in respect of special events to which members of the public are admitted shall be made conditional on the premises having an adequate and fully operational CCTV system.  It is important to note that while many nightclubs have CCTV systems, not all licensed premises which obtain special exemption orders have them in operation.  They should.</p>
          <p eId="para_21">The trading hours applicable to premises with theatre licences are to be made subject to the time limit provisions applicable to premises with on-licences.  Statutory provisions that permit early opening for premises located in the vicinity of fairs and markets are to be repealed.  The early morning pubs will cease to exist.</p>
          <p eId="para_22">On sanctions, a minimum closure period of two days should apply in the case of temporary closure orders for a first offence.  Fines for the sale of alcohol to under-age persons and for permitting drunkenness and disorderly conduct on licensed premises shall be increased.  The Garda Síochána will be permitted to seize any bottle or container in the possession of a person who appears to be under the age of 18 years and which a garda suspects, with reasonable cause, contains alcohol that is being consumed, or intended to be consumed, by a person under 18 years in a place other than a private residence.</p>
          <p eId="para_23">The legislation will provide that alcohol products must be displayed and sold in supermarkets and convenience stores in a specified area structurally separated from the rest of the premises.  Where separation is not possible, alcohol products must be displayed and sold from behind a counter.  Certain retail interests will state this imposes a great burden on them but there is a variable commencement section in the legislation.  Immediate measures can be taken while the provision is phased in over a period of years.  It is essential that we move in this direction.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">On special alcohol promotion and discount sales, reduced price promotions and sales of alcohol are to be prohibited.  Detailed regulations will be required to give effect to this provision.</p>
          <p eId="para_25">The Garda Síochána will be permitted to seize bottles or containers containing alcohol where there is a reasonable apprehension of public disorder and require a person to leave the place concerned in a peaceable and orderly manner.  Fines for public order offences are to be increased.</p>
          <p eId="para_26">I hope to have a draft from the Attorney General by the end of this week.  As soon as it is approved by the Government, I will circulate it to the members, after which we can resume discussions on the matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterPowerFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_27">Members will not want to engage in a Second Stage debate but if they want to make some comments, I would be more than happy to facilitate them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DenisNaughten" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Denis Naughten</from>
          <p eId="para_28">I want to make a few brief comments on the advisory group report and the heads published by the Minister.  They are positive and welcome.  Alcohol abuse is a growing problem but neither the recommendations nor the proposed legislation will address it adequately.  There is a clear link between the abuse and availability of alcohol and public disorder.  Between 2003 and 2007 there was a 57% increase in the number of public disorder offences.  During the same period there was a dramatic increase in the number of outlets for the purchase of alcohol.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">I welcome the proposal to limit the opening hours of off-licences and the new powers to be given to the Garda to seize alcohol in public places.  I hope the Garda will be effective in this regard.  I doubt that the restrictions on retail outlets will have a significant impact but I hope I am proven wrong in this regard.  Given that we have so many retailers selling alcohol, the provision will only scratch the surface.</p>
          <p eId="para_30">We can talk all we like about legislation and recommendations but if we do not enforce them, they are of no use.  Unless sufficient resources are provided for the Garda, local authorities or other public bodies to ensure the legislation is enforced, we will have great difficulty and return to square one.</p>
          <p eId="para_31">Let me flag one anomaly in the legislation that I hope can be addressed when the final version of the Bill is published.  Head No. 14, to which the Minister referred in respect of restrictions on the promotion of cheap alcohol, seems to contain a loophole regarding supermarket loyalty cards.  The legislation, as proposed, only addresses transactions at the point of sale.  The loyalty cards offer a recoupment, at a future date, to purchasers of alcohol.  Before Christmas, a number of retail outlets marketed the sale of alcohol on the basis that, in the months of January, February and March, one would receive vouchers therefor.  This discriminates in favour of the major retailers rather than some of the smaller ones, which many believe are more responsible.  The Minister might consider this in the Bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatRabbitte" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Deputy Pat Rabbitte</from>
          <p eId="para_32">I, too, want to be positive, but do so with no great conviction in respect of this Bill.  It is a modest measure and the Minister makes no further claims for it beyond its being so.  I hope sincerely that it will work.  The Opposition will facilitate the Bill's early passage, as the Minister has requested.</p>
          <p eId="para_33">My lack of conviction stems from the nature of the factors that give rise to the abuse and misuse of alcohol in society generally and by young people, in particular.  The Minister's initiative is based on the presumption that if one reduces the number of outlets, restructures those in existence and prohibits below-cost selling and special deals, it will somehow change the habits of the youth.  I am sceptical about this.</p>
          <p eId="para_34">I am not entirely persuaded of the merits of the trading hours provision.  If one is leaving a pub and going to a party, which does not arise in the case of those of us with grey hairs but does in the case of a very large proportion of the population, one needs to get a bottle of wine.  If in this case the off-licence is closed, one must buy the wine in the pub.  Pubs that do not arrange to sell it will now do so and, therefore, not having a level playing pitch for pubs and off-licences will not make any difference.</p>
          <p eId="para_35">It is obviously the case that off-licences can set up all over the place at present, which is not acceptable.  Some of the measures the Minister proposes ought to be desirable in regulating the sale of alcohol.  I am not quibbling with this and it is one reason I am minded to support the Bill.  Regulation is desirable in itself but I am doubtful about the proposition that it will prevent the youth from embracing alcohol to the extent that some of them embrace it at present.</p>
          <p eId="para_36">Like Deputy Naughten, I have particular reservations about the heads as published.  For example, the Minister set out the physical lay out of supermarkets which will be entitled to sell alcohol.  Premises must be restructured, the alcohol must be sold in a separate area with separate access and behind a counter.  Today's modern sophisticated citizen who wants to buy a bottle of wine is being invited to go into a supermarket, approach the counter and ask for a bottle of their best red.  One will not be able to browse the various wines on offer.  I do not believe the youth of Ireland are drunk out of their heads at weekends because they drink wine.  They drink beer and odd commodities of which I do not know the name.  I do not believe they closely examine, say, Burgundies and say they will have that.  Nor will they be going around with a better claret due to this Bill.</p>
          <p eId="para_37">The Minister clearly feels galvanised into being seen to do something because of the extent of the problem with youth binge-drinking in particular.  The drinking habit adults give youth is more to blame for it than what time, say, one can buy a bottle of wine or closing the early morning openings.  It is news to me that the early morning houses, particularly as there are so few left in Dublin, greatly contribute to the disorder problem or the abuse of alcohol.  There is a tradition as to why they exist.  Perhaps the May Ball in Trinity College Dublin ends up in one of them once a year.  One has to put up with the Ross O'Carroll-Kellys wherever one ends up in the evening.</p>
          <p eId="para_38">I wish the Minister luck with this Bill.  His hand is being forced and he must be seen to do something.  It is a modest measure which we will not hold it up.  It is positive regulation which will be introduced.  I am not convinced, however, that the visibility of drink in a growing number of outlets is a contributory factor to the problem.  It is much more complex than that.  I look forward to the larger control of alcohol Bill being published.  I hope the Minister is correct that this modest measure will make some improvements.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_39">Along with other Members, I welcome this Bill as a first step in tackling the binge-drinking culture in society.  There has been a drink culture for many years but it has changed in recent years.  This may be due to our increased affluence, parents being too busy, the influence of the mass media or, as Deputy Rabbitte said, the in-your-face availability of alcohol.  I hope the Bill's attempt to limit the number of off-licences stands the test of the diktats of the EU internal market.  It should be in the interests of public health and the common good to ensure a limited number of outlets where alcohol is available and restrictions in opening hours.</p>
          <p eId="para_40">Youth is often referred to by politicians and the media when discussing binge-drinking.  Many of those involved in anti-social behaviour or public order offences are very hairy youths and are more in their 30s or 40s.  It is not 17 year olds who are falling around the streets drunk off their heads in Dublin city centre on weekend nights.  Although not addressed by the Bill, there is an association of the drug culture with the drink culture.</p>
          <p eId="para_41">I am glad some of the problems identified in the past several years are being addressed.  For example, the anomaly whereby the city council must give permission to the Garda to enter public parks to confiscate drink has been finally addressed.  However, there is existing legislation to deal with other issues.  I am concerned at the rise in dial-a-drink services where one orders drinks to one's house.  Off-licences and vintners are passing their licences to the delivery person.  In reality, the delivery person is selling alcohol at the doorstep because there is an exchange of cash.  In a reply to a parliamentary question on the matter, the Minister stated legislation is in place to cover this area.  Vintners, off-licence owners, the supermarkets and the Garda Commissioner must be informed of this aspect of the law to address the delivery of drink to young people at home.</p>
          <p eId="para_42">There are several increases in fines but these must be examined again if we are serious about tackling some of the offences that dominate the headlines.  Some of the fines are low.  For example, the maximum fine for wilful obstruction is €400; the duty of the licensee to preserve order is subject to a fine of €5,000.  Perhaps a higher maximum penalty might make some licence-holders take greater steps to prevent public disorder.  I hope we will be able to make it a better Bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CharlesFlanagan" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Deputy Charles Flanagan</from>
          <p eId="para_43">I welcome the fact that the legislation has been published and that the Minister has honoured his commitment that it would be, at the earliest opportunity.  I would reiterate what has been said about facilitating the passing of the legislation.  Notwithstanding the fact, as I am sure the Minister will accept, that this is far from the full story in terms of dealing with a most important public order issue - and even more importantly a public health issue - I was somewhat disappointed he did not address the issue of the proliferation of licensed premises.</p>
          <p eId="para_44">There is no attempt or effort on the part of the Government to reduce the fairly staggering figure of some 4,300 outlets from which alcohol is readily available.  That is effectively one premises for every 750 people in the country, and to my mind is very high and might have been addressed.  The Minister, in the draft legislation, intimates an intention to deal with public order difficulties, which I welcome, and of course the issue of under age drinking.  However, I wonder about enforcement and the fact there were a mere 14 prosecutions for the whole of last year against licensed premises, including off-licences, on-licences and restaurants, for alleged under age drinking.  We have a problem in that there appears to be a difficulty regarding enforcement - there have been a mere 96 prosecutions in the last five years.  That is an issue which must be urgently addressed.</p>
          <p eId="para_45">I also regret that the Minister has not made any specific reference to the need to have a mandatory identity card scheme.  There can be all the voluntary codes and schemes in the world, but they will not deal with the problem in an effective manner.</p>
          <p eId="para_46">I urge the Minister to accept that a criminal justice response to alcohol-associated problems is perhaps only part of the solution.  He should impress on his Cabinet colleagues and the incoming Taoiseach the need to establish a Cabinet sub-committee, involving himself, as Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, as well as the Minister for Health and Children and the Minister for Education and Science, to ensure we can have a multifaceted approach to what is a real public health issue.  The reason we are dealing yet again with legislation of this type is the fact that alcohol is a controlled substance.  The reason we have controls is because of the abuse and the related dangers.  I hope we can look beyond the justice area.  I regard this as a welcome measure, but I question how comprehensive it is in the context of the very serious difficulties associated with binge drinking and the cultural attitude towards alcohol.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianOShea" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Brian O’Shea</from>
          <p eId="para_47">Obviously this is to be welcomed and there is, of course, good will on this side of the House to see it through quickly, as the Minister desires.  The issue raised by Deputy Rabbitte is the one I have heard most about since the report of the Government advisory group was discussed into the media.  That is, if alcohol cannot be acquired in off-licences and other outlets after 10 p.m., what is to stop people buying carry-outs from licensed premises?</p>
          <p eId="para_48">Another phenomenon that is very worrying is the tendency for adults to drink very heavily over the weekend in private houses.  What is emerging in some instances is very serious violence, even death.  I know that interfering in private homes, etc., can give rise to enormous problems, but there have been a number of deaths and serious assaults arising from this type of activity.  It is an area we need to focus on.</p>
          <p eId="para_49">There are very few prosecutions as regards adults buying alcohol for minors and it is an underlying problem that is there all the time.  There is usually an adult around somewhere to buy alcohol for younger people who are under age and want drink.  One of the issues Dr. Gordon Holmes raised when he met the committee, was the difficulty in arriving at the basic unit cost of particular beverages.  Has any progress been made in this regard?  I am speaking in the context of below-cost selling and how one might arrive at the actual cost.  I shall leave it at that, and I wish the Minister well with the Bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanConnick" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Deputy Seán Connick</from>
          <p eId="para_50">I congratulate the Minister and his officials on their publication of the draft legislation.  Like other members, I have been reflecting on some of the Bill's recommendations.  It is down to enforcement, an area in which we have been slack, in terms of the regulation of opening and closing hours.  Let us be honest, we have all been in pubs at 2.30 a.m. or 3.30 a.m. which should have been closed at 11.30 p.m.  This is part of the problem.  I recall being in a pub in the UK some years ago and the Irish tried to carry their glasses onto the street as we were put out at the proper closing time.  It all boils down to the fact that we seem to have a lax attitude towards enforcement.</p>
          <p eId="para_51">I welcome some of the recommendations.  I am not sure how effective they will be in reducing the amount of alcohol being consumed.  I bow to the superior knowledge of my colleague, Deputy Rabbitte, in terms of the wine glut.  When a person is so "trolleyed" at 3 a.m. or 4 a.m. the chances are he or she will drink any type of alcohol.  I am most concerned that we should follow through in terms of enforcement.  I have mentioned before that we need forceful policing in terms of zero tolerance.</p>
          <p eId="para_52">I have a real problem with the fact a person who visits a nightclub and then wants to go elsewhere for something to eat should be able to do so in a safe environment.  Normally, some 800 people could emerge from a nightclub, and only 12 people will cause trouble.  However, these 12 are affecting the lives of the other 788.  The right of the majority must be upheld, and on that basis the Minister must follow through in terms of enforcement.  That is the key to everything.  After that, it is down to disposable income, and very little can be done about that.  People have a good deal of money now and they can spend it where they choose.  Unfortunately, many of them choose to spend it on alcohol.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterPowerFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_53">I thank the Deputy.  As the Minister knows, the committee had a detailed engagement with Dr. Holmes.  For the benefit of the committee, I know from speaking to Dr. Holmes, upon the publication of the Bill, that a number of the suggestions put to him by members here found their way into the report by way of concrete recommendations.  I am glad we had some involvement in it.</p>
          <p eId="para_54">One theme that arose in our discussions, which does not involve the Minister's Department, might nonetheless be conveyed to his Cabinet colleagues.  The proliferation of off-licences, everybody agreed, was a major issue.  The Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform can only have a limited role in that regard, in terms of applicants having to apply to the District Court for a certificate - and that is to be welcomed.  However, there would not be off-licences if the owners did not get planning permission for them from local authorities.  It is a major issue that local authorities are giving planning permissions for off-licences without any regard to the social consequences for particular areas, and that is a very real issue.  It is, perhaps, something the Minister might convey to his Cabinet colleagues.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_11" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_55">I thank all the members of the committee for the broad welcome they have given this measure.  As Deputy Naughten rightly said, this Bill would not solve all the problems, and I never said it would.  To tackle the problem of alcohol misuse in our country requires a multitude of initiatives which must be taken by many Departments.  In so far as the responsibility lies with my Department, I would not accept Deputy Rabbitte's characterisation of this as a modest measure.  It is actually a fundamental change of direction in the manner in which we have approached the formulation of our intoxicating liquor code.  The trend in recent decades has been to liberalise the law in this area, to accept the argument that alcohol is a normal product in a marketplace.  I do not accept that proposition and I believe the reason an intoxicating liquor code exists is because it is a substance which can give rise to misuse and which must be controlled.  To be misguided by notions of competitiveness and market forces in this area will not help us resolve the problems that exist.  That has been my point of departure in the formulation of this Bill.</p>
          <p eId="para_56">It is a modest measure in another sense, as it is a short Bill; it does not contain multiple provisions.  I am a firm believer in such a Bill.  I have tried to isolate the areas of gross legislative misuse and deal with them in a short, simple measure.  I have also tried to focus on items which would command substantial public support and not entangle us in the competing claims of the various vested interests involved.  We will have to adjudicate on those competing claims when we look at the comprehensive legislation on the sale of alcohol.</p>
          <p eId="para_57">Deputy Naughten raised the point about the supermarket loyalty cards.  That issue is being addressed in the drafting of the measure.  It will be dealt with in the Bill when it is published.  I understand Deputy Rabbitte's conviction that the Bill might not lead to a radical change in culture, but it will start the process of addressing that change.  Both Deputy Rabbitte and Deputy O'Shea were under a misapprehension about the question of sales after 10 p.m., although Deputy O'Shea fairly said he was repeating what he had heard in his constituency about the proposal.  The current position is that an on-licence gives a person full power to sell off-licence.  Therefore, a publican with an on-licence can also operate an off-licence, or can sell alcohol products that are taken off the premises.  However, the restriction of 10 p.m. will apply to all premises, so a public house will not be able to sell alcohol for removal off the premises after that time, in the same way that a retailer with an off-licence cannot do so.  Under this Bill, a person cannot purchase a bottle of wine at 11 p.m. to take home.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatRabbitte" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy Pat Rabbitte</from>
          <p eId="para_58">If that can be enforced in pubs across Ireland, then I believe in the tooth fairy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_13" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_59">With respect, on-licensed traders have been quite compliant with the legislation.  Deputy Connick referred to the fact that he has often been in a public house in the early hours of the morning, but he should note that a great number of special exemption orders have been given to standard public houses in recent years which permit them to stay open until 2.30 a.m.  That is entirely lawful trading under current arrangements.</p>
          <p eId="para_60">Deputy Rabbitte also raised the issue of pubs with early opening hours.  We are now prohibiting sales in off-licences from 7.30 a.m. until 10.30 a.m.  Public houses are not in operation before those hours.  By extinguishing the right to sell in the early morning pubs, we are creating a level playing field between the off-licensed outlets and the licensed premises, as the earliest time one will be able to acquire a drink is 10.30 a.m.  Were we to do otherwise, the ban on off-licensed premises selling drink before 10.30 a.m. could be circumvented by the early morning pubs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatRabbitte" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Pat Rabbitte</from>
          <p eId="para_61">The proposition that the housewife in Castleknock who cannot get access to her off-licence at 9.30 a.m. will immediately head down the docks to find an early morning pub is the view of a particular bureaucratic mind.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_15" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_62">We must secure equal treatment between the various actors involved.  Deputy Rabbitte also touched on physical separations between the buyer and the seller.  The buyer will of course be able to browse among the different bottles of claret if there is a specified area in the establishment.  Most establishments which deal in wine have a specified area exclusively devoted to the sale of wine.  There is no requirement in this Bill that all sales should be from behind the counter.  What is envisaged in the larger establishments is that all sales should be separate from any other trading.  Where there is a mixed trading context, there must be a separation for the sale of alcohol.  In smaller trading outlets such as petrol stations, there will be a requirement to sell behind the counter because of the small size of the establishment concerned.</p>
          <p eId="para_63">This separation will impose a considerable burden on the retail sector, and for that reason it will take a number of years to implement it fully.  In return for the deferral of that implementation, I will expect immediate measures from supermarkets towards segregation.  An example would be to have drinks available on a particular aisle that has a turnstile at either end.  It would be a very substantial burden to require every establishment immediately to have a shop within a shop.  That will happen in the medium term and that will be the culture in which drink will be sold in this country.  If we do not treat it with respect in the manner in which it is being sold outside licensed premises, then we will continue to have serious problems.</p>
          <p eId="para_64">Deputy Ó Snodaigh raised the question of the EU directive.  We will have to notify the EU of any regulations we draw up that confer powers under this Bill.  Deputy Flanagan raised the issue of the proliferation of licences.  There is a degree of misapprehension about this.  The supermarkets are buying full public house licences and using them as the basis for their off-licence business.  They find it more onerous to go to court and acquire a new off-licence, which they would need to sell alcohol other than wine.  They buy the licence for a six figure sum, and it is then extinguished, generally in a rural area.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatRabbitte" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Pat Rabbitte</from>
          <p eId="para_65">Does that give them permission to sell alcohol at more than one location?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_17" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_66">No.  Given the volume of sales that can occur in supermarkets, it is a valuable franchise for them.  The proliferation does not happen because the small rural pub has its licence extinguished and the licence is then transferred to an urban retail outlet.  That is what has been happening in recent years.</p>
          <p eId="para_67">The other element of proliferation is related to the wine licences.  A retailer can currently apply to the Revenue Commissioners to get one but this Bill will oblige him or her to go to court.  That is a very substantial restriction on the proliferation of wine licenses, because it will not be worth the candle to go to court for the great number of small retailers simply to get a wine retailer's off-licence.  We are also subjecting the off-licence application in the District Court to all the rigours of objection which a full on-licence would require.  That is a change and will allow substantial public objection to further off-licences.  Therefore, I do not agree with the argument that this Bill does not address the proliferation of licences.</p>
          <p eId="para_68">Deputy Flanagan also raised the question of the mandatory national identity card scheme.  There is a Garda card for younger persons, but if we want a national identity card, we will have to provide some form of national identification for every citizen.  That is a major project and I do not see us agreeing on it and enacting the necessary legislation for it between now and the summer recess.  It is a debate that should take place, but I do not believe it can arise under this Bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CharlesFlanagan" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Deputy Charles Flanagan</from>
          <p eId="para_69">Is the Minister favourably disposed to it in the medium term?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_19" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_70">It is something that is worth examining.</p>
          <p eId="para_71">I agree with Deputy O'Shea that there is a very heavy amount of consumption taking place in some private homes at weekends, which is a very serious phenomenon.  In some Garda reports it has led to many public order difficulties and even homicides have been attributed to this activity.</p>
          <p eId="para_72">I did not respond to Deputy Ó Snodaigh's remarks on retailers offering a "dial a can" service.  This is illegal under existing legislation, which brings us to the question of enforcement.  One of the measures in this Bill that will be helpful in this regard is the power afforded to the Minister to draw up regulations to prohibit promotions by off-licences, which will encompass any promotions of a "dial a can" variety.  Lack of information about the existence of such a facility will go a long way to eradicating it.  The "dial a can" issue also raises difficult questions of EU law.  As Deputy Rabbitte will be quick to remind me, there is nothing to stop a person purchasing a crate of wine from France and having another person bring it into this State.  I confess I have done the same myself.</p>
          <p eId="para_73">All speakers referred to enforcement and I agree it is key.  Deputies Charles Flanagan and Connick pointed to the low number of prosecutions.  I am confident it will be possible to enforce this legislation.  An issue I have raised with the Garda Commissioner is an important provision in the Criminal Justice Act 2006.  Section 184 of that Bill provides for the imposition of fixed penalties for persons who are drunk and disorderly.  These fixed penalties can be administered in a Garda station, not generally.  It is important that we bring this provision into operation in tandem with the new legislation, and I have communicated that view to the Garda Commissioner.  It is two years since the enactment of the Criminal Justice Act.  This provision will be of major assistance to the Garda in enforcing the law in this area.</p>
          <p eId="para_74">Deputy Flanagan raised the issue of the length of time it can take to secure a prosecution.  The powers of seizure being given to the Garda under this new legislation, if brought into operation in parallel with powers to impose fixed penalties on persons who are drunk and disorderly, will go a long way towards effective enforcement of the legislation.  We will have a further opportunity to discuss all of this.  I thank members for their time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterPowerFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_75">Will the Minister clarify a point?  He mentioned on a previous occasion that he would refer either the heads and general scheme of the Bill or the full Bill to the committee.  Is that for the purpose of allowing us to engage in a wider consultation process if minded to do so?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_21" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_76">It is for the committee to decide how to conduct its business.  The heads of the Bill are there and the committee can engage in consultation on those if it so wishes.  When drafting of the Bill is completed, I will take Second Stage in one of the Houses and proceed accordingly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterPowerFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_77">I thank the Minister.  We will recommence our Committee Stage consideration of the Immigration, Residence and Protection Bill 2008 after a brief suspension to facilitate the departmental officials.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">Sitting suspended at 3.40 p.m. and resumed at 3.45 p.m.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3" refersTo="#bill.2008.2.dail.3">
        <heading>Immigration, Residence and Protection Bill 2008: Committee Stage (Resumed).</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_7">SECTION 4.</summary>
        <speech by="#PeterPowerFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_78">Amendments Nos. 19, 96, 234 and 237 are related and may be discussed together.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatRabbitte" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Deputy Pat Rabbitte</from>
          <p eId="para_79">I move amendment No. 19:<entity refersTo="#bill.2008.2.dail.3.amd_19" name="amendment"/>
                    </p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_80">In page 13, between lines 6 and 7, to insert the following subsection:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_81">"(2) Where a foreign national applies for and is refused a permission referred to in <i>subsection (1)</i>, he or she may appeal that refusal (other than a refusal of a protection decision which may be appealed under <i>Part 7</i>) in accordance with regulations made by the Minister, which regulations shall provide for a visibly independent appeals process to review the decision at first instance.”.</p>
          <p eId="para_82">We have made spectacular progress in reaching section 4 of the Bill, which relates to foreign nationals being in the State lawfully or unlawfully.  Amendment No. 19 proposes to insert a new subsection which requires that the Minister make regulations to provide for a visibly independent appeals process to review in the first instance a decision to refuse permission to a foreign national to remain in the State.  Applications for protection are dealt with separately under Part 7.  The requirement here is to publish regulations that would set down this visibly independent appeals process.  I have not sought to introduce a detailed amendment that would be prescriptive in terms of how that appeals mechanism should function, the categories that might be excluded, the restrictions that might apply to a particular category and so on.  Rather, the Minister would be required to promulgate regulations under which such a visibly independent appeals process would apply, which is important.</p>
          <p eId="para_83">The Minister, or at least the Government, also considered it to be important.  I go nowhere without my copy of the programme for Government in order to consult it regularly and find inspiration.  In the section headed "Immigration", the Government made a commitment to "ensure a visibly independent appeals process".  In those circumstances, I would have thought the Minister should be able to take on board what is a reasonable amendment.  I also have to hand the policy platform of another party in the coalition Government, namely, the Green Party, which states it will "introduce a visibly independent appeals process for Immigration decisions, based on the principle of fair and prompt treatment of applicants".</p>
          <p eId="para_84">As my amendment is based on the policy aspiration of the Government, I hope it will feel enabled to include it in the Bill and it is important to so do.  I repeat that I am not trying to be prescriptive.  I will leave it to the Minister to introduce the regulations and will allow him to tussle with the detail of what should be included therein.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DenisNaughten" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Deputy Denis Naughten</from>
          <p eId="para_85">I support amendment No. 19 tabled by Deputy Rabbitte.  It constitutes the basic minimum that must be included in the legislation under discussion, both because the programme for Government states the Government is committed to it and because the Minister made clear on Second Stage that it was his intention to introduce, at some future date, an independent appeals process.</p>
          <p eId="para_86">This is not a detailed amendment.  I tabled a detailed amendment on such a proposal for a later stage that, sadly, has been ruled out of order because it would involve a cost to the Exchequer.  While I believe details on how such an appeals system would work should be incorporated in primary legislation, at a minimum, amendment No. 19 should be adopted in this Bill.  It is of critical importance to so do because we must ensure the existence of a clear, transparent and unambiguous immigration system.  This is not in place at present and the enactment of the Bill as it stands will not facilitate such a system being in place.</p>
          <p eId="para_87">As a basic requirement, an appeal mechanism must be placed on the Statute Book.  The Minister's colleague, the Minister of State with responsibility for integration, also believes that such a system must be put in place.  It is imperative to provide people with a clear avenue to appeal a decision of the Department and that it is seen to be independent.  The Minister suggested something along the lines of the social welfare appeals office and this is his opportunity to facilitate such a development.  He should either accept this amendment or table his own amendment on Report Stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_88">Amendment No. 234, which is also being discussed, was tied with an amendment that was ruled out of order yesterday on the grounds of cost to the Exchequer and which pertained to the appeals tribunal issue.  I ask the Minister to give consideration to such amendments that will be ruled out of order on the grounds of imposing costs on the Exchequer.  While one does not necessarily wish to cause the Government undue expense, the amendments are reasonable.  I refer in particular to the amendment pertaining to the appeals tribunal.  The Minister should consider them and perhaps he could introduce an amendment of his own in respect of an appeals tribunal along these lines on Report Stage.  Such a mechanism has been raised at this level and allows for amendments to be tabled by the Minister on Report Stage, as members cannot table amendments on Report Stage that are likely to incur a charge to the Exchequer.  The only person who can do so is the Minister himself with the agreement of the Minister for Finance.  Were such an amendment to be put in place, it would save the Exchequer money in the long term.</p>
          <p eId="para_89">As for amendment No. 236, this Bill only allows five working days for people to apply for a review of a decision to refuse residency renewal.  I believe this is an unreasonably short timeframe, especially given the possibility that a person will be obliged to supply documentary evidence--</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform (Deputy Brian Lenihan)</from>
          <p eId="para_90">Is this amendment not being discussed separately?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterPowerFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_91">The revised grouping list indicates this amendment will be dealt with separately.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_92">The amendment is included on the list appearing on the monitors.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterPowerFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_93">The Deputy is correct to state the amendment is appearing on the screen. However, I indicated that amendments Nos. 19, 96, 234 and 237 will be discussed together.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_94">That is not a problem.  I was out of the room when the Chairman indicated this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterPowerFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_95">That grouping appears on the revised list.  It is a mistake on the screen.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_96">This is not a problem and the committee will come back to it.</p>
          <p eId="para_97">That concludes my contribution.  As amendment No. 234 is related to amendment No. 17, which was ruled out of order, it probably should be withdrawn or not discussed further.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_34" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_98">While I oppose the amendments, I agree with much of the spirit of what was said by those members who tabled the amendments under discussion.  The Bill will put in place an independent appeals process for protecting applicants who are refused protection either as refugees or as persons eligible for subsidiary protection in the State.  It replaces the current Refugee Appeals Tribunal with the protection review tribunal, which has an expanded jurisdiction to consider appeals against a refusal to grant subsidiary protection.</p>
          <p eId="para_99">Later in this debate, members will have an opportunity to examine in detail the provisions relating to the new protection review tribunal.  Without wishing to anticipate that debate, I wish to advise members that I am examining the provisions relating to the protection review tribunal.  I wish to signal now that I will bring forward additional proposals on Report Stage dealing with the make-up and structure of the tribunal.</p>
          <p eId="para_100">It is important to note that in respect of asylum cases, one should distinguish between the type of decision being made in a protection case and the issues that arise in respect of an immigration permission.  Protection matters are governed by our international obligations and are determined by reference to well-established international standards.  This is as it must be, given the issues involved.  On the other hand, immigration decisions in respect of non-EU states are made at the discretion of the Government.  The Supreme Court recognised this clearly in respect of the Bode case last December, when it made it clear it is both the right and the duty of the Government to safeguard the external boundaries of the State and that the Government has responsibilities in this area deriving from the Constitution.</p>
          <p eId="para_101">Clearly, the State can set out how it is proposed to exercise its discretion in legislation.  Fundamentally, however, immigration is not a right but a facility granted by the State.  A visa to visit Ireland is an act of hospitality by the Irish State.  Attempting to have, for example, a tribunal or independent body to adjudicate on decisions, which necessarily must be taken by the Government and the Administration, is not the way to go in respect of this particular legislation.  In the Supreme Court, Mrs. Justice Denham referred to the granting of permission to remain in the State as a gift.  This constitutes the thinking and analysis of the Supreme Court in this regard.  Were one to set up a tribunal and allow appeals, there would be appeals in every case.  As members are aware, that has been the experience in refugee applications.  The determinations of the office are always appealed to the Refugee Appeals Tribunal.  If one establishes an immigration appeals tribunal, there will be universal appeals to it against all adverse decisions.  This is the reality on which Deputies should focus their minds when considering this legislation.</p>
          <p eId="para_102">Built into the Bill are a number of review processes for the different types of decision that arise at various stages of the immigration process.  For example, section 17 deals with a visa review application, section 40 contains a review mechanism for the non-renewal of a residence permission, and sections 44 and 45 contain processes for making representations as to why permissions should not be revoked.</p>
          <p eId="para_103">In addition, section 100 sets out the process for the revocation of a protection declaration.  Lest there be any confusion on the matter, it is important to clarify the meaning of "independent" in this context and in the context of the commitment contained in the programme for Government.  It means independent of the original decision maker and does not relate to the capacity to exercise a discretion parallel to that of the Minister or the Government.  An independent appeal of an immigration decision must operate within the same framework as that facing the original decision maker.  These guidelines will be set down in regulations, administrative schemes and directions.  Those conducting the appeal cannot substitute their opinions as to who should be permitted to come to Ireland or to reside here for those of the Government or the Minister.</p>
          <p eId="para_104">In this context, I am anxious to ensure during the lifetime of the Government that we implement the commitment in the agreed programme for Government, to which Deputy Rabbitte referred fairly, to ensure a visibly independent appeals process in immigration matters.  I assure the committee that the commitment will be fully met within the Government's lifetime.</p>
          <p eId="para_105">Before we commit ourselves to a legislative solution to this matter, I want to ensure that what we are legislating for will work and will have been proven to work well in the interests of the State.  For this reason, I am taking the approach of introducing systems of independent reviews of immigration matters on an administrative basis at first.  As such, I have indicated my intention to appoint on an administrative basis a person to act as chief review officer with the function of ensuring consistent and high-quality decision making among those who deal with visa reviews under the legislation.  This way of introducing independence may prove satisfactory and, if so, can be implemented throughout the immigration process before being placed on a statutory footing.  However, I am in no rush to create another happy hunting ground for lawyers in this legislation.</p>
          <p eId="para_106">It is worth the effort to do what the Department of Social and Family Affairs did, namely, establish a visibly independent appeals system within the Department, to have a chief appeals officer and to initiate the system on an administrative basis rather than a legislative one.  By trial and error, we can ratify the system in robust legislation.  By taking this incremental approach, I am satisfied that I will fulfil the Government's commitment to provide independent reviews on immigration matters and to do so in a manner that will prove efficient, lasting and in the public interest.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatRabbitte" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Deputy Pat Rabbitte</from>
          <p eId="para_107">The Minister's intervention was interesting, but it did not address amendment No. 19 or related amendments.  He drew our attention to the fact that he has made provision for an appeals mechanism in respect of the protection of applicants, which we accept.  I welcome the fact that he will introduce changes to the operation of the Refugee Appeals Tribunal or, as it will be called, the protection review tribunal, but it is a separate issue from the gravamen of this amendment on immigration.  The Minister repeated his comments on Second Stage, when he stated:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_108">Another commitment in the agreed programme for Government is for an independent appeals process.  I wish to signal my intention to introduce an appeals mechanism along the lines of the system used in the Department of Social and Family Affairs.  This will operate on an administrative basis at first and, once developed, may be put on a statutory footing.</p>
          <p eId="para_109">Much consideration went into the crafting of that paragraph.  How would it be possible to have an administrative system of appeal to a statutory decision?  I am unsure as to how that could operate.</p>
          <p eId="para_110">I am sure the Minister understands the larger issue better than me.  Leaving aside the idea that the purpose of the programme for Government was a certain amount of flummery and puffing, the Minister separated the matter clearly in that a chapter in the programme entitled "Asylum, Immigration and Integration", addresses those issues separately.  Under the immigration heading, there is a commitment to ensure "a visibly independent appeal process".  The Minister quoted Mr. Justice Keane, Mrs. Justice Denham and so on and, on Second Stage, I referred to the Laurentiu case.  It is worth reading into the record a paragraph from Mr. Justice Keane's judgment, in which he stated:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_111">It cannot be too strongly emphasised that no issue arises in this case as to whether the sovereign power of the State to deport aliens is executive or legislative in its nature: it is clearly a power of an executive nature, since it can be exercised by the executive even in the absence of legislation.  But that is not to say that its exercise cannot be controlled by legislation and today is invariably so controlled: any other view would be inconsistent with the exclusive law making power vested in the Oireachtas.  The Oireachtas may properly decide as a matter of policy to impose specific restrictions on the manner in which the executive power in question is to be exercised: what they cannot do, in my judgment, is to assign their policy making role to a specified person or body, such as a Minister.</p>
          <p eId="para_112">Mr. Justice Keane's statement rebuts the Minister's statement more effectively than I can.  Apart from the provisions of the struck down Aliens Act 1935, Mr. Justice Keane accepted that, as the Minister argues, the sovereign State enjoys the power to expel and deport aliens.  However, he stated that the right to expel or deport aliens inheres in the State by virtue of its nature, not because it has been confirmed on an organ of the State by statute.</p>
          <p eId="para_113">Mr. Justice Keane went on to make plain that the effect of legislation was to permit the Minister by regulation to decide what class of aliens might be deported.  My amendment is consistent with this opinion of the then Chief Justice, as I am asking the Minister to make such regulations, thereby allowing him to decide which categories of aliens might be deported.  We will know which when they are published.  Section 54 addresses access to justice, but we will jump that bridge when we come to it.  That a person might be deported does not mean he or she does not have a right of access to justice.  However, I am bringing the argument on.</p>
          <p eId="para_114">As far as this argument is concerned, I am seeking to give expression in the Bill to the commitment in the programme for Government that it would ensure a visibly independent appeals process.  Rather than enumerating conditions in a detailed amendment, I have chosen to be more feasible and, according to the Supreme Court, constitutionally consistent by requiring the Minister to make the regulations and to stipulate whatever he believes he should stipulate.  However, it is not meeting his own commitment in the programme for Government to say that he will draw my attention to the arrangements for protection applicants and that he wants to signal now that there will be changes to that.  I welcome all that but that is not the issue here.  I cannot accept that the Minister's response to this amendment is a reasonable one.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DenisNaughten" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Deputy Denis Naughten</from>
          <p eId="para_115">I support the point Deputy Rabbitte has made.  It is fundamentally important to the integrity of this legislation that we have a visibly independent appeals process which is enshrined through this amendment in the legislation.  It still facilitates the Minister in bringing forward secondary legislation to flesh out this proposal and that legislation can be amended at any stage if the Minister believes changes are required.</p>
          <p eId="para_116">There is a considerable difference between what the Minister is proposing and what is in place in the social welfare appeals office.  That office publishes an annual report and makes its decisions based on entitlements that are guaranteed either in primary or secondary legislation.  The difficulty with much of what is dealt with in the area of immigration is--</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_37" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_117">We are not talking about entitlements here, we are talking about a gift.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DenisNaughten" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Deputy Denis Naughten</from>
          <p eId="para_118">The Minister should allow me to finish.  The difficulty with this legislation is that we do not know under what criteria decisions are made.  The Minister says it is a gift and as such, there should not be any criteria.  However, I believe that a basic set of criteria should be laid down against which people are benchmarked to determine if they are entitled to immigrant status and to enter the country and reside here.  That is not in place and it is not envisaged that it will be in place in the future.  It is partly covered in secondary legislation and in other regulations the Minister may draft.  In that sense, it makes it very difficult to see how a chief review officer can be seen to be independent on the basis of the fact that the decision is a gift and not on the interpretation of primary or secondary legislation that has been laid before the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_39" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_119">Deputy Rabbitte should note that I made it clear that my intention is to implement the commitment in the programme for Government in the lifetime of this Administration and to start implementing it on an administrative basis.  If we were to accept the amendments proposed to this section, we would infringe the very Supreme Court decision Deputy Rabbitte referred to, namely, the Laurentiu case, where the Supreme Court said that the powers conferred on the Minister cannot be delegated in a vague and general way but require specifics.  We cannot simply provide in this legislation that there should be a visibly independent appeals system.  That invites the suggestion that too much power is delegated.</p>
          <p eId="para_120">On the constitutional point and the authority referred to by Deputy Rabbitte, the up-to-date and binding authority in this matter is the decision of the Supreme Court in Bode (A Minor) <i>v.</i> the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform.  That decision was handed down on 20 December 2007.  It is an authoritative judgment of the Supreme Court on a fundamental point concerning our immigration practice.  As Deputy Rabbitte and other Deputies are aware, the State decided on foot of the amendment to the Constitution that took place in 2004 to come to an arrangement for those who had children born in Ireland prior to 1 January 2005 who were thereby Irish citizens.  An arrangement was drawn up by the Minister on an administrative basis and upheld by the Supreme Court when challenged in judicial review proceedings.</p>
          <p eId="para_121">In her judgment in the Supreme Court, Ms Justice Denham expressly addressed issues relating to the executive power of the State and said that in this case, one of the fundamental powers of a state arises for consideration in every state, of whatever model.  The State has the power to control the entry, residency and exit of foreign nationals.  This power is an aspect of the executive power to protect the integrity of the State.  It has long been recognised that in Ireland this executive power is exercised by the Minister on behalf of the State.</p>
          <p eId="para_122">The Supreme Court also quoted earlier remarks of Judge Costello in which he stated the following:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_123">In relation to the permission to remain in the State, it seems to me that the State, through its Ministry for Justice, must have very wide powers in the interests of the common good to control aliens, their entry into the State, their departure and their activities within the State.</p>
          <p eId="para_124">The special role of the State in the control of foreign nationals was also described by Judge Gannon in a 1986 case when he said the following:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_125">That it is in the interests of the common good of a State that it should have control of the entry of aliens, their departure and their activities and duration of stay within the State is and has been recognised universally and from earliest times.  There are fundamental rights of the State itself as well as fundamental rights of the individual citizen, and the protection of the former may involve restrictions in circumstances of necessity on the latter. The integrity of the State constituted as it is for the collective body of its citizens within the national territory must be defended and vindicated by the organs of the State.</p>
          <p eId="para_126">Mrs. Justice Denham affirmed and adopted that description and went on to say:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_127">While steps taken by a State are often restrictive of the movement of foreign nationals, the State may also exercise its powers so as to take actions in a particular situation where it has been determined that the common good is served by giving benefits of residency to a category of foreign nationals - as a gift, in effect.  The inherent power of the State includes the power to establish an <i>ex gratia</i> scheme of this nature.  Such an arrangement is distinct from circumstances where legal rights of individuals may fall to be considered and determined.</p>
          <p eId="para_128">That judgment gives ample powers to the Minister to proceed by way of an administrative scheme to establish an appeals system. While I would like to see that system incorporated in legislation in time, it would be far wiser from the point of view of the State and the public interest to proceed by trial and error in the establishment of an appeals process rather than legislate for an extensive appeals process at this stage with uncertain consequences and indeterminate results. That is how I propose to proceed on the matter and I have indicated that I intend to establish, on an administrative basis, a chief review officer to ensure consistency is an integral part of decisions on immigration matters and that independent reviews of decisions take place. There is nothing to inhibit the Minister doing that under the Constitution or under the Bill as proposed before the committee. Incidentally, Mrs. Justice Denham recognised the inherent powers of the Minister. It is not a question of conferring powers on the Minister</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatRabbitte" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Deputy Pat Rabbitte</from>
          <p eId="para_129">I have not heard anyone assert that the sovereign State does not have the right to deport aliens, to use the term that was used in the past.  Nobody is arguing that.  What we are arguing, and the courts have commented on this, is that the principles and policy ought to be set out in primary legislation.  In many cases here we have not done that because we have opted for a framework that maintains that it is in order for the Minister to make regulations, from time to time, as he or she sees fit.  However, because the power to which the Minister refers inheres in the State, it does not mean to say that where we decide to legislate that, we then do not submit ourselves to the courts.  No one is disputing the fundamental right of the State to deport aliens but where we legislate, that legislation can be quoted before the courts and the courts can then make whatever decisions they choose.  I repeat what Mr. Justice Keane said, "that is not to say that [the power's] exercise cannot be controlled by legislation" and today it is invariably so controlled.  I am still not entirely clear about the Minister's position.  He seems to be making a commitment to a system, on an administrative basis, similar that which exists in the Department of Social and Family Affairs to be the review mechanism in this situation.</p>
          <p eId="para_130">I ask the Minister whether it is feasible to maintain such a review system on an administrative basis when appeals are made on a statutory foundation.  Mr. Justice Keane stated: "The right to expel or deport aliens inheres in the State by virtue of its nature and not because it has been conferred on particular organs of the State by statute".  The Minister accuses me of not having regard to the Denham judgment in the Bode case which states we cannot proceed in a vague and general way, but that is what I am trying to prevent.  By incorporating the amendment in the Bill, the Minister would be required to introduce regulations that would be particular and specific rather than vague and general.</p>
          <p eId="para_131">I do not want to make a political football of the matter but the Minister has sidestepped the commitment that the programme for Government makes in this regard.  Is it not worth at least rebutting me or claiming the provision was put together late at night and that he did not mean it?  Was it because there may have been a few immigrant votes to be gained?  I ask him to give me some reason rather than leave me hanging and arguing that I am trying to implement the commitment in the programme for Government but for some reason he is resisting.  That could have a terrible effect on a legislator's health.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_41" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_132">I am sorry to impact on the Deputy's health.  Of course, I am committed to the independent appeals process set out in the programme for Government.  I am saying I propose to introduce it initially on an administrative basis, as I am perfectly entitled to do under the authority of the Supreme Court decision.  Deputy Naughten used the word "entitlement".  I have made the point that the Supreme Court characterised the capacity of the State to admit a foreign national as a gift, not an entitlement.  That is at the heart of this discussion because the State is entitled to make decisions and exercise discretion in this area.  That is the opinion of the Supreme Court which also agrees that the Minister can draw up an administrative scheme to confer gifts.</p>
          <p eId="para_133">Clearly, if the legislation provides for various determinations that can be made by the Minister, there is no reason it cannot be supplemented with a review mechanism.  As that mechanism is tried and tested in the years ahead and as a chief officer is appointed to ensure consistency in the review processes and that cases are treated in a like manner, the most essential element of justice, it can be incorporated into legislation.</p>
          <p eId="para_134">The amendment would not add anything to the Bill, as it stands, because its implementation would require extensive statutory instruments.  I do not think we are in a position to take such a route at this stage.  We will have to see how the appeals work in practice.  The Legal Aid Board was established on an administrative basis but is now operating under statutory regulation.  The powers of the board and deciding officers are set out in legislation.  It makes sense to introduce the independent review mechanism in the same way because it would allow us to learn by trial and error through a form of scheme which has been upheld by the Supreme Court and which permits the Minister to vary elements as a more perfect system is devised.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatRabbitte" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Deputy Pat Rabbitte</from>
          <p eId="para_135">We are presented with the Bill; therefore, there is little point in saying we should prepare it differently.  Certain issues are important such as access to justice and an independent appeals process.  We are at an important juncture in the Bill.  I am prepared to withdraw the amendment on the clear understanding that I will resubmit it on Report Stage, by which time I hope the respective arguments advanced by the Minister and me will have been subjected to some analysis in the public domain.  I have serious reservations about the Minister's proposals.  At this stage, we should have sufficient experience of immigration to be able to publish regulations that meet the concerns of many.  The issue is not that they are trying to challenge the State's right to deport.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_43" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_136">I never said it was.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatRabbitte" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Deputy Pat Rabbitte</from>
          <p eId="para_137">To facilitate progress, I will re-enter my amendment on Report Stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8" title="decision" refersTo="#withdrawn">Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.<entity refersTo="#bill.2008.2.dail.3.amd_19.withdrawn" name="amendment"/>
                </summary>
        <speech by="#PeterPowerFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_138">Amendments Nos. 20 and 305<i>a</i> are related and may be discussed together.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatRabbitte" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Deputy Pat Rabbitte</from>
          <p eId="para_139">I move amendment No. 20:<entity refersTo="#bill.2008.2.dail.3.amd_20" name="amendment"/>
                    </p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_140">In page 13, between lines 6 and 7, to insert the following subsection:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_141">"(2) (<i>a</i>) Where a foreign national is sentenced on indictment to a term of imprisonment of 12 months or more, any permission he or she enjoys under this Act to be present in the State shall thereupon stand revoked.</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_142">(<i>b</i>) Where a person referred to in <i>paragraph (b)</i> of the definition of “foreign national” in <i>section 2</i> is sentenced on indictment to a term of imprisonment of 12 months or more, he or she shall, notwithstanding that definition, be deemed to be a foreign national for the purposes of this Act, any permission he or she enjoys under this Act to be present in the State shall thereupon stand revoked; but before an immigration officer or member of the Garda Siochána removes the person from the State under <i>section 54</i> he or she shall have regard to Article 28 of Directive 2004/38/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council.</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_143">(<i>c</i>) Where a foreign national is sentenced on indictment to a term of imprisonment of 12 months or more, any protection declaration he or she enjoys under <i>Part 7</i> shall thereupon stand revoked, and <i>section 100(11)</i> shall apply to such revocation <i>mutatis mutandis</i>; but before an immigration officer or member of the Garda Siochána removes the person from the State under section 54 he or she shall comply with Article 32(3) of the United Nations Convention relating to the Status of Refugees.”.</p>
          <p eId="para_144">We have tabled a record number of 707 amendments, designed to improve the Bill from the philosophical standpoint we have been articulating.  There is more than a nuance of difference between this side of the House and the Minister.  That is not to say, however, we want an open door system or to facilitate the entry into this jurisdiction of persons who will not obey our laws.  Amendment No. 20, structured according to the circumstances of leave to remain or residence in paragraph (<i>a</i>), the right to establishment of EU nationals in paragraph (<i>b</i>) and asylum and protection applicants in paragraph (<i>c</i>), would make the legislation consistent with Article 8 of the European Convention on Human Rights, which is why the amendments require that no action be taken unless, for example, Article 28 of the European directive or the UN convention relating to the status of refugees is observed. The principle of <i>refoulement</i> would still apply but it is reasonable where we grant such permission that beneficiaries should be expected to comply with the law of the land. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DenisNaughten" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Deputy Denis Naughten</from>
          <p eId="para_145">I will speak to my amendment No. 305<i>a</i> which has a similar objective to Deputy Rabbitte’s amendment.  Where somebody has been convicted on indictment of a criminal offence he or she shall either leave or be removed from the State in accordance with the provisions of this Act and again the refoulement condition is placed on this.  This would apply only to somebody who has received a custodial sentence after having served that sentence.  The Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform has deported non-Irish citizens after serving a prison term.  From January 2001 to the end of February this year 130 individuals have been deported and we want to see that put on a statutory footing.  It is important we set down clear rules that somebody involved in serious criminal activity here is not wanted here and shall be deported.  We have had several examples recently of individuals who have been involved in very gruesome activities in this jurisdiction and I hope they are deported after they serve their prison sentence.  The Minister talks about the issue of the gift in the earlier amendment we are dealing with.  If it is a gift, it is important such a gift can be withdrawn if somebody blatantly disregards the law of the land here.  I ask the Minister to give serious consideration to the amendments before him.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_48" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_146">I understand why these amendments were tabled.  They address a very important issue, but that issue is already addressed in the legislation.  I agree with the fundamental point made by Deputies Rabbitte and Naughten that where a person to whom the hospitality of permission to be present in the State has been extended abuses that hospitality by committing an offence, the question of that person's continued stay in the State must arise and be dealt with.  I agree with that proposition.  We begin from that same point but the question is how we implement that in the legislation.</p>
          <p eId="para_147">Deputy Rabbitte's amendment has certain simplicity about it.  It provides for the automatic revocation of permission to remain on conviction of specified offences.  However if one examines the legislation it deals with this issue depending on the nature of the permission granted.  Because of the nature of the permission involved, different considerations necessarily apply on revocation.  I refer Deputies to section 43(1)(<i>b</i>) which permits the Minister to revoke an entry permission, a residence permission or a qualified long-term residence permission granted to a foreign national if he is satisfied at (<i>b</i>) that “the foreign national has served or is serving a term of imprisonment imposed in the State”.  That allows the State to impose a term of imprisonment and the Minister, in the course of this term, to deport the foreign national concerned.  By and large that is the practice of the Department in these matters.  If somebody commits a criminal offence the Irish courts are entitled to punish that offender, but the Minister is also entitled to consider the removal of that offender from the State.  That position remains under Section 43(1)(<i>b</i>).</p>
          <p eId="para_148">Section 43(2)(<i>a</i>)(iii) enables a Minister to revoke a long-term resident’s permission granted to a foreign national if the Minister is satisfied that the foreign national, “having been by a final judgement convicted of a particularly serious crime, constitutes a danger to the community of the State”.  Again, I am open to persuasion on the wording of that.  It may be too rigorous and in light of what has been proposed by the other speakers I will have a look at it, although there are certain EU obligations in this area on third country nationals.  Section 43(1)(<i>d</i>) refers to “danger to the security of the State” and 43(2)(<i>b</i>) relates to “an actual and serious threat to public security, public policy or public order”.  All of that is written into the revocation provisions.  When we come to those provisions we can explore it further.  Provision is also made in section 99 for the revocation of a protection declaration and the question of a particularly serious crime constituting a danger to the community of the State is legislated for in that context.  That is the scheme envisaged in the legislation for the protection of national security and the exercise of discretion in cases where criminality has been displayed.  I am satisfied that it addresses the concerns raised by the Deputies save in one respect.</p>
          <p eId="para_149">Paragraph (<i>b</i>) of Deputy Rabbitte’s amendment appears to relate to EU nationals who, by virtue of the definition of foreign national in section 2, are excluded from most of the provisions of this Bill.  The reason for that is that the right of the EU national to reside in the State is not governed by the Immigration, Residence and Protection Bill but by the free movement regulations, SI 656 of 2006.  Those free movement regulations govern entry into the State, presence in the State and removal from the State of EU nationals and those regulations were drawn up under the relevant EU free movement directive.  This Bill does not and cannot address matters where we are under obligations by virtue of our membership of the EU.  Regulation No. 20 of the EU free movement regulations provides, among other things, that the Minister may by order require a person to whom the regulations apply to leave the State where, in the opinion of the Minister, the conduct or activity of the person is such that it would be contrary to public policy or would endanger public security or health to permit the person to remain in the State.  Under EU law I have to deport EU nationals from the State and I cannot introduce in this legislation measures which would infringe our European obligations.</p>
          <p eId="para_150">Deputy Naughten's amendment goes further by seeking to apply itself to all who are not Irish citizens and ignores our European obligations.  On that ground alone I cannot agree to it.  In general I agree I should have the power to consider the termination of the residence permission of a foreign national where there has been a serious conviction but I must have a power to consider the matter and follow a process which will arrive at a decision in a fair way.  Were I to accept the suggestions in these amendments I would have no consideration to give in the matter irrespective of the circumstances.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatRabbitte" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Deputy Pat Rabbitte</from>
          <p eId="para_151">Do we have any figures on this?  The Minister says there is an existing practice.  In any of the recent years how many persons to whom the Bill applies and who have been convicted on indictment of a serious offence have been returned to their country of origin?  This is not the place for legal tutorials, but I have difficulty understanding the refoulement.  If there is a prohibition on a person's being returned to his or her country of origin for fear of abuse, torture or whatever, I would have thought such a person in the first instance would have had a right to asylum in the country in which he or she sought refuge.  I have never been able to get my head around why we are so protective of the concept of refoulement.  By definition it seems to me that if a person has grounds to fear returning to Rwanda, Angola or wherever, he or she would have been entitled to asylum or refuge here in the first place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DenisNaughten" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Deputy Denis Naughten</from>
          <p eId="para_152">Does the Minister have those figures to hand?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_51" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_153">I have a reply given to Deputy Jim O'Keeffe from November 2006.  I thought it was a more recent parliamentary question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DenisNaughten" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Deputy Denis Naughten</from>
          <p eId="para_154">I have those.  Deputy O'Keeffe's reply is dated 1 April, and it seems to only deal with non-EU citizens.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_53" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_155">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DenisNaughten" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Deputy Denis Naughten</from>
          <p eId="para_156">Will the Minister give an indication of whether anyone has been deported under regulation 20 of the European Communities (Free Movement of Persons) (No.2) Regulations 2006?  I am glad to see these figures are available and I had drafted the amendment before the figures became available.  I hope that similar treatment is given to EU citizens, subject to the conditions of the European Communities regulations.  Will the Minister give us an indication of that?</p>
          <p eId="para_157">It is important for the interests of Irish citizens and the vast majority of migrants who come here, some of whom do so to establish livelihoods.  Others wish to come here for a number of years to return income home before going back to their country of origin.  They want nothing to do with individuals who come here and get involved in criminal activity.</p>
          <p eId="para_158">I was surprised when I came across recent figures in the prisons report showing the number of non-Irish citizens in Irish prisons.  The figure of 30% seems to be extremely high.  I hope that all things being equal, and the Minister taking into consideration the points he must have to review each case on the basis of its merits, these particular individuals will be shown the door after they have served their sentence.</p>
          <p eId="para_159">Will the Minister give us an idea of the figures for EU citizens?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_55" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_160">My understanding is that the relevant regulations are very difficult to apply to other EU nationals who have committed offences in this jurisdiction.  That has been the experience of several EU jurisdictions.  I can speak from my own direct knowledge since appointment as Minister that I sent the necessary notices under the regulations to the group of Roma Travellers who last summer encamped on the M50 near Ballymun.  That was the legal basis upon which I invited them to leave the State.  They voluntarily left the State afterwards.</p>
          <p eId="para_161">Apart from that, I have not as a Minister had occasion to exercise this particular power.  I am advised that it is a very difficult power to exercise in the context in which the Deputy has referred to it.  I have raised the issue with my counterparts, the EU justice Ministers, to see how we can address the matter.</p>
          <p eId="para_162">It is a growing and difficult issue given the substantial enlargement of the EU to 27 states.  It is inevitable that more such offenders will present themselves.  The rationale is that the Irish offender in Germany, France or Spain, for example, would be in exactly the same position as offenders here.  I would not single out offenders here by country of origin.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DenisNaughten" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Denis Naughten</from>
          <p eId="para_163">What type of response has the Minister received to date from his colleagues?  Are they prepared to consider changes in these regulations?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianLenihan" eId="spk_57" as="#Minister_for_Justice,_Equality_and_Law_Reform">
          <from>Deputy Brian Lenihan</from>
          <p eId="para_164">The concern is shared and these issues have been raised but we are not yet at the stage of a full review of the regulations.  I am anxious to have them reviewed.  The difficulty is that the directive lays down the template or framework within which our regulations must be drawn up.  We cannot legislate for this by statute.</p>
          <p eId="para_165">One question I am prepared to revisit and have asked to have looked at in the context of this legislation, is whether we can implement the issue raised by the Deputy in a more robust way in this Bill by way of amendment while complying with our obligations under the primary directive.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterPowerFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_166">I thank the members.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_9" title="decision" refersTo="#withdrawn">Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.<b>	</b>
                    <entity refersTo="#bill.2008.2.dail.3.amd_20.withdrawn" name="amendment"/>
                </summary>
        <summary eId="sum_10">Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_11">The select committee adjourned at 4.45 p.m. until 10 a.m. on Thursday, 1 May 2008.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
