<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_foreign_affairs/2010-02-11/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_foreign_affairs/2010-02-11/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2010-02-11" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/30/joint_committee_on_foreign_affairs"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_foreign_affairs/2010-02-11/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_foreign_affairs/2010-02-11/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2010-02-11" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_foreign_affairs/2010-02-11/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_foreign_affairs/2010-02-11/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None" eId="#vol_None" showAs="Vol. None"/>
          <oir:numberReference href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None/no/None" eId="#no_None" showAs="No. None"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AengusOSnodaighSF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aengus-Ó-Snodaigh.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Aengus Ó Snodaigh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DavidNorris" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/David-PB-Norris.S.1987-04-25" showAs="David Norris"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FrankFahey" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Frank-Fahey.D.1982-03-09" showAs="Frank Fahey"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="IvorCallely" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ivor-Callely.D.1989-06-29" showAs="Ivor Callely"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MJNolan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/M-J-Nolan.S.1982-05-13" showAs="M. J. Nolan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MarkDaly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mark-Daly.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Mark Daly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelDHiggins" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-D-Higgins.S.1973-06-01" showAs="Michael D. Higgins"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chair" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chair" showAs="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chairman" showAs="Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>COMHCHOISTE UM GHNÓTHAÍ EACHTRACHA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>JOINT COMMITTEE ON FOREIGN AFFAIRS (Sub-Committee on Human Rights)</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2010-02-11">Déardaoin, 11 Feabhra 2010</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2010-02-11">Thursday, 11 February 2010</docDate>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Sub-Committee met at 11.30 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#FrankFahey">Deputy Frank Fahey,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#MarkDaly">Senator Mark Daly,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelDHiggins">Deputy Michael D. Higgins,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#DavidNorris">Senator David Norris.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#MJNolan">Deputy M. J. Nolan.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">In attendance: Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#IvorCallely">SENATOR IVOR CALLELY IN THE CHAIR.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Business of Joint Committee. </heading>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_6">The minutes of the meeting of 16 December have been circulated.  As there are no matters arising, are they agreed?  Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Human Rights Situation in Gaza: Discussion. </heading>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_7">I remind members and those in the Gallery to ensure their mobile phones and BlackBerrys are switched off completely for the duration of the meeting, as they cause interference, even on silent mode, with the recording equipment in the committee room.</p>
          <p eId="para_8">We have been discussing human rights in Gaza and we are joined by Mr. Khalil Shaheen, director of economic, social and cultural rights unit with the Palestinian Centre for Human Rights.  We welcome him to the meeting.  We are also joined by Ms Louise O'Connor from Front Line.</p>
          <p eId="para_9">Mr. Shaheen and Ms O'Connor will be aware that there is widespread interest and concern among the Irish public regarding the situation in the Middle East and, in particular the humanitarian and human rights situation in the West Bank and in Gaza.  I welcome this opportunity to hear from Mr. Shaheen at first hand of the human rights environment in Gaza today.  We are aware that the Minister for Foreign Minister, Deputy Martin, recently sought to visit Gaza to assess development work being funded by the Irish Government but, regrettably, he was denied permission to do so by Israel.  We, therefore, appreciate this opportunity to meet Mr. Shaheen.  I understand he had some difficulty in leaving Gaza and was held in detention for a number of days before being released to travel to Ireland.  I do not know whether the common denominator is Ireland or the individual but Mr. Shaheen might cover that point.</p>
          <p eId="para_10">Mr. Shaheen might comment on the impacts of the various authorities and entities controlling and working in Gaza, including Israel, Hamas, Fatah, UNRWA and others are having on his work as a human rights defender.</p>
          <p eId="para_11">The witnesses and those in the public gallery will note that there are a small number of members present, this is because we are a sub-committee of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs.  Other activities, including the Order of Business in both Houses delayed the commencement of the meeting.  I assure everybody that the proceedings of this meeting are recorded and relayed to every Member's office and all Members will also receive the "blacks" or the transcript of this discussion.  All Members will be able to follow, either by monitor or later by transcript, what is discussed at today's meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_12">I acknowledge the briefing documents received today from the Israeli Embassy, which have been circulated.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidNorris" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Senator David Norris</from>
          <p eId="para_13">Is that this document detailing the list of children killed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_14">That is correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidNorris" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Senator David Norris</from>
          <p eId="para_15">It should be headlined; we should know from where it comes.  The Chairman has let us know that now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_16">We only received it this morning.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidNorris" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Senator David Norris</from>
          <p eId="para_17">I understand that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_18">The Senator will appreciate that within an hour or so of receiving it this meeting was to take place and it was more important to circulate it.  We are happy to give that clarification.  In future, if time permits, we will ask the Clerk to try to cover that properly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidNorris" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Senator David Norris</from>
          <p eId="para_19">When I saw it I wondered from where it had come because it is obviously part of a propaganda exercise.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelDHiggins" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy Michael D. Higgins</from>
          <p eId="para_20">That is certainly true.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_21">I invite Mr. Shaheen to make his presentation.  I ask him to be as brief as possible.  The normal format of the meeting is that following a presentation we have a question and answer session.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Mr. Khalil Shaheen</from>
          <p eId="para_22">I thank the Chairman.  It is a pleasure to be here with the committee and, hopefully, this is a great opportunity for the people of Gaza and Palestinian people to have a voice.  The people there are still struggling for their rights to self-determination and to have an independent and democratic state.</p>
          <p eId="para_23">It is well documented that the situation in Gaza, especially in the Palestinian occupied territories in the Gaza Strip, has escalated and deteriorated.  It is now one year on from the Cast Lead military operation that took place over 23 days, following which an ongoing total siege, closure and blockade was imposed on Gaza.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">I will briefly outline the impact of the ongoing and escalating situation.  Israeli occupation forces killed more than 1,400 Palestinians, the majority of whom were civilians — 82 civilians, 326 children and 100 women and wounded 5,300 others.  The forces directly targeted and attacked private homes and civilian institutions, including hospitals and schools.  Civilian workshops and factories were directly targeted and agricultural land was razed, destroying farms, fields and irrigation systems that formed the basis of farmers' livelihoods.  Reconstruction has been impossible due to the ongoing 980 days of illegal closure.</p>
          <p eId="para_25">The victims of Operation Cast Lead numbered 1,419 in total, of whom 1,167 were civilians.  In terms of house destruction in the Gaza Strip, 1,920 houses were totally destroyed in north Gaza, 1,601 houses were destroyed in Gaza city, 653 houses were destroyed in middle Gaza, 397 houses were destroyed in Khan Younis in south Gaza and 785 houses were destroyed in Rafah.  With regard to economic establishments affected by Operation Cast Lead, 178 establishments were completely destroyed and 108 were partially destroyed.  The total number of establishments operating prior to the offensive was 390.  In terms of the razing of agricultural land and the uprooting of all agricultural facilities, 2,084 dunums were destroyed in north Gaza, almost 3,000 dunums were destroyed in Gaza city, 860 dunums were destroyed in middle Gaza, 507 dunums were destroyed in Khan Younis and 357 dunums were destroyed in Rafah.</p>
          <p eId="para_26">It is well known that Israel controls five border crossings, namely: Erez, where there is passenger traffic; Nahal Oz; Karni, which is a conveyor belt for grains; and Sufa and Karm Abu Salem/Kerem Shalom, both of which are a crossing for humanitarian goods.  Israel has subjected the Gaza Strip to a closure policy since 1991.  However, its current most extreme form has been applied continuously since 14 June 2007, following the Hamas takeover.  Today, the Gaza Strip has been completely cut off from the outside world for almost three years.  Only 40 goods items are allowed to enter Gaza by the Israeli Government, but they are insufficient to meet the needs of the 1.5 million people trapped inside the Gaza Strip.  This illegal decision has been endorsed by the Israeli high court of justice.  Only 49.48% of Gaza's fuel needs are imported, but this figure has dropped significantly in the past three months.  There are electricity power cuts for over 70 hours a week.  Only one tonne of cooking gas enters Gaza per day compared to a total capacity of 400 tonnes.  Poverty levels are deteriorating with 80% of Gaza's population living below the poverty line.  Some 42% of the population are unemployed, while in some areas the level is over 55%.  Some 18.6% of households report a decrease in income since the Israeli offensive.  In June 2006, some 65,000 workers were employed in the industrial sector, but just prior to Operation Cast Lead the figure was only 35,000.  Following Operation Cast Lead only 1,878 were still working.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">We have a particular problem with humanitarian supplies, including food and medication.  Some of the photographs are well known which show the targeting of civilian hospitals and the resultant injuries.  Medical institutions and personnel were also attacked.  It is well known that eight medical personnel were killed on duty, while 15 hospitals were damaged in Israeli attacks.  Some 43 primary health care facilities were damaged or destroyed, as well as two ambulance stations.  There is a shortage of medication in Gaza and just last week the Minister of Health declared that 135 different items were lacking.  Patients who require external medical treatment are stuck in Gaza as a result of the blockade.  Almost 300 patients have passed away because they were denied access to Palestinian or Israeli hospitals, their travel plans were delayed and there is a lack of medication.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">Only 10% of Gaza's water is potable.  Some 90% of water supplies are unsafe to drink due to high levels of chloride and nitrates, which are associated with causing birth defects.  Total direct losses incurred by the water and sanitation sector are estimated at $6 million during the offensive.  Water wells were partially damaged or completely destroyed in northern Gaza, and approximately 10,000 displaced Palestinians still have no access to clean water one year after the war.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">An average of 85.3% of the Gaza Strip's population are connected to the public sewerage network, but in Khan Younis only 38.4% are connected, while 60.4% of the population depend on temporary services.  Gaza is currently pumping 80,000 cubic metres of unfiltered sewage directly into the sea.</p>
          <p eId="para_30">Despite all these deteriorating circumstances and mass violations of the Palestinians' civil, political, economic, social and cultural rights, they are still struggling to defend themselves.  They believe in bringing peace and justice for these victims, and in having victory for all of these victims.  It is time to end impunity.  Following the UN fact-finding mission, the Goldstone report on Operation Cast Lead had clear recommendations on the implementation of accountability for all war criminals who must be brought to justice.  This is the main hope for the Gaza people.  They believe that Europe, and especially the Irish Government and people, can help to play an important future role in implementing international humanitarian law, including the Geneva convention, as well as acting to protect civilians.  It is a great opportunity for everyone who still believes in peace, justice and the protection of human rights.  Respect for human rights must be ensured in all circumstances.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_31">I thank Mr. Shaheen for his presentation, which is greatly appreciated.  I also appreciate the documentation he has circulated.  We have also been circulated with a press release from the Israeli Embassy, but it is perhaps best not to add fuel to what has already been circulated.  However, I do wish to draw members' attention to documents circulated under item D.  I will place the press release on the agenda for our next meeting when we can have a structured contribution on its content.  For the record, it is important to draw members' attention to the Council's conclusions on the Middle East process in the annex, dated 8 December 2009, which is item 4 in the briefing.  I will read out the relevant lines which refer to the Council's grave concern about the situation in Gaza:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_32">The Council urges the full implementation of UNSCR 1860 and the full respect of international humanitarian law.  In this context, the continued policy of closure is unacceptable and politically counter-productive.  It has devastated the private sector economy and damaged the national environment, notably water and other natural resources [which is what Mr. Shaheen referred to].  The EU reiterates its call for an immediate, sustained and unconditional opening of crossings for the flow of humanitarian aid, commercial goods and persons to and from Gaza.  In this context, the Council calls for the full implementation of the agreement on movement and access.  While extremists stand to gain from the current situation, the civil population — half of which are under 18 — suffers.  Fully recognising Israel's legitimate security needs, the Council continues to call for a complete stop to all violence and armed struggle in Gaza.  The Council calls on those holding the abducted Israeli soldier, Gilad Shalit, to release him without delay.</p>
          <p eId="para_33">The Council's conclusion goes on, but I think it is important to add a bit of balance in light of what has been circulated.  I open the debate to the floor, and Deputy Michael D. Higgins and Senator Norris are offering.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelDHiggins" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Michael D. Higgins</from>
          <p eId="para_34">I welcome Mr. Khalil Shaheen and Ms Louise O'Connor.</p>
          <p eId="para_35">With the Chairman of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs, Deputy Woods, I and others, in a joint delegation of the Joint Committee on European Affairs and the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs, visited Gaza in July of last year.  I visited Israel earlier in the spring, but we were not able to get into Gaza.  I had been to Gaza previously, just two weeks after the Israeli withdrawal and several times through the 1980s.</p>
          <p eId="para_36">My first point relates to the work of this committee.  We are not here as a kind of clearing house where people fire information into us.  The Sub-Committee on Human Rights must at some stage make a recommendation to the Oireachtas joint committee on actions we want taken, and I think there is a consensus around some of these actions.  This is an important point to me.  Otherwise, we would be just a clearing house for statements.</p>
          <p eId="para_37">It is not a matter of balance.  First, one must draw a moral conclusion on the humanitarian tragedy that has been described to us in Gaza, as it affects children, women and men.  Do you accept it as a humanitarian tragedy and that what is taking place is a form of collective punishment, or do you say that those, because they have certain representatives among them who at different levels may or may not be guilty of releasing rockets, are changed as people who are entitled to basic humanitarian protection?  There is no equivocation in that, and you could get chart loads of paper in from each side.  There is no balance in that.</p>
          <p eId="para_38">This raises a question on some of the fundamentals of human rights and I am very interested in what Mr. Khalil Shaheen has to say on it.  I am not clear, as I listen to this presentation, and others, on whether people accept the independence of human rights as a perspective.  This is a crucial issue, one about which Deputy Callely, as Chairman, and we, as a human rights sub-committee, had better make up our minds.  If one does accept it as independent, then one should be able to act on the human rights clause.</p>
          <p eId="para_39">For example, the people in Gaza I mentioned are entitled to have their human rights protected, the families in Sderot that we visited are entitled to their human rights although there is a question of proportion that arises on the scale of the loss of life, and the people who are threatened by Hamas within Gaza are entitled to have their human rights respected.  In addition, the prisoners in Israeli jails are entitled to have their human rights respected, but so also are the prisoners being held by the Palestinian Authority.</p>
          <p eId="para_40">One matter about which I am getting rather weary is that when one speaks at this committee, where we have switched off our mobile phones and we have all respected privilege, we get a barrage of abuse on the basis that we are on one side or whatever.  Some of us have a long record in human rights and we are at the end of the road in taking shovel-fulls of propaganda.</p>
          <p eId="para_41">If one believes also in human rights, as I stated, that apply separately, over and above every issue we have listed, then one will say that they mean something in the articles in the agreement of the EU, both with Israel and with the Palestinian Authority.</p>
          <p eId="para_42">Mr. Khalil Shaheen made reference to the Council's conclusion, item No. 4 in the briefing.  We all want all of these measures mentioned in item No. 4 in the briefing, but we also want the agreement before it has deepened, and also that it be tested as to whether, in fact, the parties are in compliance with the human rights standards that are basic to the treaty.</p>
          <p eId="para_43">Immediately I say this, I can predict the response, that because we look for human rights compliance in the treaty, we are automatically assumed not to be able to be fair.  Those who feel that what they need really is a continual blow of wind in one ear and out the other, must occasionally ask themselves where they stand and if they arrive at a conclusion.</p>
          <p eId="para_44">We arrived at conclusions, and the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs published a report on its visit to Gaza.  We also held several discussions since.  What is in the Goldstone report, for example, identified not a general threat on human welfare but an immediate threat in terms of sanitation and environment that would affect everyone, particularly through contaminated water.</p>
          <p eId="para_45">I cannot see how a person can use the words human rights if they say, "Well, it is their own fault."  That is what has been said.  We looked at houses that were incomplete, and could have been roofed.  We listened to presentations by persons whose character was absolutely attacked repeatedly: Mr. John Ging and Colonel Desmond Travers.  Colonel Travers, on the Goldstone report, drew attention in a fair and balance way to what no one disputes, namely the immediate need for work on the environment.  Mr. Ging, in a balanced way, brought us from one UNRWA project to another.</p>
          <p eId="para_46">Summarising what I have said about Gaza and what I have heard, it is wearying if one must be reminded of the degree of the humanitarian tragedy that is present, but what is less ready is the acceptance by the international political community that what is taking place is politically scandalous in every respect of international law.</p>
          <p eId="para_47">I do not agree with the briefing document we received, that things are looking up on the fundamental matters.  Sadly, I had hoped that Senator Mitchell would have achieved very much more.  I had no expectation at all of anything from Mr. Tony Blair's presence in the region.  On east Jerusalem, while we were there an eviction took place.  On settlements, they are extending.  On movement, it is contracting.</p>
          <p eId="para_48">Years ago, when Senator Norris and I were in Israel, we met maybe 20 or 30 voluntary organisations in Israel interested in human rights.  I go in and out, as an adjunct professor of the Irish Centre for Human Rights and I see what is coming in.  It is interesting that, unless one is signing up for the propaganda, if one takes an internationally recognised body of human rights the work that comes from Beth Salem, a human rights institution in Israel itself, is excellent and fair.  However, it too is regularly blackened by the propaganda machine.  Members of this sub-committee, the joint committee and the Dáil must now make up their minds on whether they want to reach conclusions on these matters.</p>
          <p eId="para_49">There are different versions of what we will hear about people who have tried to break the siege, as it is, from one side or the other, and there are issues that arise for the Egyptian Government or whatever.  At the end of the day the fact is what happens in the so-called Quartet process is that when the United States blows hot and cold on this particular issue — the game being played at present, incidentally, is to get to the last two years of the US presidency when nothing can be attempted and nothing will be achieved — the vacuum that is created is not filled by the European Union.  The European Union has been ready to deepen the agreement without doing as it should, as the Joint Committee on European Affairs asked it to do, namely to be scrupulously fair, take a period of three months, decide whether the agreement is being complied with in terms of human rights, take all the human rights information — I condemn the outrage of a child killed in Sderot in the same way as I would in Gaza, and have — and the facts, examine them, and then decide whether, in fact, instead of deepening the treaty one should cancel it, which is where the evidence tends at present.  I am happy to have somebody else decide that independently over a period of three months and report to the General Council, and to have Ireland give a lead, campaign for it, etc.</p>
          <p eId="para_50">At the same time, if one is to do this, if one is to make the human rights argument, one must be able to criticise the person who releases a rocket from Gaza in the direction of Sderot.  One must be able to demand that you visit not only Palestinian prisoners in Israeli jails, but also Palestinians in Palestinian jails in the West Bank where — I say this as a human rights activist — the mistreatment learned in another prison is being visited upon inmates.  That is the work the committee needs to do.  Others may require it but I certainly do not need a new deluge of paper in which a high moral windy position is adopted.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidNorris" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Senator David Norris</from>
          <p eId="para_51">I welcome Mr. Shaheen from the Palestinian Centre for Human Rights and Ms O'Connor from Front Line.  The latter is a remarkable organisation.</p>
          <p eId="para_52">On the press release and other material circulated, how does Mr. Shaheen respond to this type of thing?  There has been an attempt on the part of the Israeli Embassy in its press statement to undermine this meeting.  The press statement also contains a list of the names of Israeli children who have been killed.  I accept that deaths are tragic and that everyone present deplores the use of suicide bombers, etc.  When we visited the region, I managed to obtain from the late Yasser Arafat a statement in which he condemned such behaviour.  How does Mr. Shaheen respond to this tit for tat argument to the effect that "they started it" or "we started it"?  It is a complete irrelevancy.  In saying that, however, I do not mean that the human tragedy on both sides is irrelevant.</p>
          <p eId="para_53">On the subject of the press release and the statement to the effect that the sub-committee has not invited representatives from the Israeli Embassy to come before it, the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs invited the Israeli ambassador to appear before it on a number of occasions but I understand we have yet to receive a response to these invitations.  In such circumstances, I do not know what those at the Israeli Embassy are squawking about.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_54">The Senator will be aware that we invited the Israeli ambassador to come before the sub-committee and that he declined.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidNorris" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Senator David Norris</from>
          <p eId="para_55">In that event, it is an extraordinary impertinence to issue this statement and imply that our deliberations are one-sided and that we are not prepared to invite the Israeli ambassador to come before us.  We did not invite Colonel Richard Kemp to come before us.  I am glad because I am an extremely busy and professional politician and do not need to hear a lot of utter rubbish.  I read what this person had said to the United Nations committee and it was just drivel, completely unrelated to reality.  The man has never been in Gaza and knows nothing whatever about it.  I cannot waste my time on somebody who is a committed and blinkered supporter of Israel and refuses to face the facts.  It would add nothing to our deliberations if we were to invite a British army colonel, acting as a propaganda spokesperson for the Israelis, to come before us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_56">The Senator is correct.  The Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs invited the Israeli ambassador to come before it.  I will not say the ambassador declined the invitation but he made an offer to the effect that Colonel Kemp would appear in his stead.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Senator Mark Daly</from>
          <p eId="para_57">The ambassador pointed out that he was not available.  We were trying to identify a date on which he would be available but it appeared that he was completely booked up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidNorris" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Senator David Norris</from>
          <p eId="para_58">He did not appear; therefore, he has no cause for grievance.</p>
          <p eId="para_59">The Israelis also complain about the use by the Palestinian Centre for Human Rights of the phrase "occupation forces" and state this shows extraordinary bias.  I regard them as occupation forces, as do many human rights organisations within Israel whose members are Jewish Israelis.  Under the terms of international law, they are occupation forces.  Not using the term, therefore, would be more indicative of bias.</p>
          <p eId="para_60">On the use of the term "war crimes", there may be a degree of tendentiousness about it but there is no doubt that Mr. Goldstone who is Jewish, a very distinguished person and cannot really be seen as anti-Semitic found <i>prima facie</i> evidence of war crimes.  Therefore, that establishes that fact.  I do not believe using these phrases is necessarily an indication of bias, although it might be.</p>
          <p eId="para_61">Like Deputy Higgins, I am fed up being deluged with paper, particularly that which contains a lot of blather and hypocrisy.  That is exactly what the document from the Council of the European Union constitutes.  The Council virtually accepts that there have been infringements.  It states there have been infringements of international law.  If there have been such infringements and if there have also been infringements of human rights law, why, in the name of God, is the Council not even monitoring the human rights protocols attached to the Euro-Med treaty?</p>
          <p eId="para_62">I wish to make a formal proposal — I hope it will be seconded and that unanimous agreement will be reached on it — to the effect that we should write to the Minister for Foreign Affairs to ask him to actively pursue this issue.  What is happening makes a complete nonsense of the concept of human rights.  If words to the effect that "we will examine the financial aspects of this treaty if human rights are infringed" are included in a treaty and if there is a review to discover whether such an infringement has taken place, action must be taken.  Another part of the European apparatus and the United Nations have clearly indicated that human rights violations have taken place.  I am not stating these have all been perpetrated by one side.  If there is anything other than hypocrisy in our approach and that of the European Union to human rights, it is imperative that the human rights protocols attaching to the Euromed treaty be monitored at the very least.  There would have been a quick end to the war if the European Union had signalled that it was going to operate these protocols and place an embargo on the 85% of Israeli agricultural product exported to the Union.  The difficulty is that there are many guilty consciences in countries such as Germany which obliterated 6 million Jewish people during the Second World War.  That is an appalling reproach to Europe as a whole.  This country did not do much to save its honour because we refused to take in any Jews.  Our guilty consciences about what happened to the European Jews during the Second World War should not be salved at the expense of people who were not associated with the Holocaust, namely, the Palestinian Arabs.</p>
          <p eId="para_63">I agree with Deputy Higgins on the remarkable work done by Israeli groups such as B'Tselem and Ta'ayush Rabbis for Human Rights and individuals such as the 29 Israeli air force personnel who refused to bomb the territories because they, unlike their government, were aware of the United Nations conventions and Yehuda Shaul from Breaking the Silence, an orthodox observant Jew who because of his beliefs could not even answer the telephone in his hotel which meant I had to call in person to see him and who had to leave the door to his room open.  Displaying immense moral courage, he wrote down the infringements he had witnessed and encouraged other good, patriotic Israeli soldiers to state their country was being destroyed morally from the inside by this blasphemy, against everything Judaism stands for.  I honour and salute these people.</p>
          <p eId="para_64">I wish to ask a couple of specific questions.  Does Mr. Shaheen possess information on the medical condition of the children?  I have a house in Cyprus and watched live streamed reports on al-Jazeera.  What was happening was appalling.  What is the medical condition of the children?  I refer not only to those who have been injured and have continuing medical difficulties but also to those who suffered as a result of the bombardment, the confinement relating thereto, the restrictions imposed on them, particularly in the context of their diet, and the trauma they experienced.  When UN sanctions were imposed in Iraq — an action that was completely and utterly wrong — it was women and children who suffered.  Information on their levels of nourishment and development indicated that children in Iraq were quite restricted when compared to their counterparts elsewhere and in the context of their nourishment and developmental levels prior to the imposition of sanctions.  What is the position on malnourishment and diseases?  The sewage problem is absolutely appalling.  It is horrifying that a civilised, intelligent and educated people have been deliberately placed in such appalling living conditions.  What is the position on education?</p>
          <p eId="para_65">The Irish people are extremely concerned about this matter.  Citizens in this country always supported Israel.  The feeling among many people, particularly republicans, was that the Israeli struggle for independence paralleled the Irish experience.  I did not always agree with that, but I think we taught them some nasty tricks, like car-bombing.  Feelings have now shifted towards considerable sympathy for the Palestinians.  This is not anti-Semitism, but comes even from people who strongly supported Israel, but who now, because of the atrocious misbehaviour of a series of Administrations, have come out against their actions.</p>
          <p eId="para_66">I will finish on that.  However, I would like a response with regard to the medical condition of the children.  I would also like to put my proposal formally and ask whether someone is willing to second it.  Will the committee deal with this matter?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelDHiggins" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Deputy Michael D. Higgins</from>
          <p eId="para_67">I second that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Senator Mark Daly</from>
          <p eId="para_68">I support Senator Norris with regard to the Euro-Med agreement.  Today's presentation has provided us with information and before Christmas Colonel Travers spoke to us, not only about the attack in Gaza but also the consequences of the attack in terms of the destruction of the agricultural infrastructure and people being unable to make a living due to the contamination of water and soil.  The press release we received in the documentation is propaganda and is deeply inaccurate, like all propaganda.  The Israeli ambassador was invited to come before the committee, but he deflected the invitation spuriously by asking that a mercenary, Colonel Richard Kemp, come in his place and try and persuade us that he knew all about the operation in Gaza, even though he had never been there.  That was a pathetic attempt to insult us.  We had invited the ambassador, but he did not have the courtesy to come before us and explain his side of the story.  We wanted to hear both sides of the story.  If the press release sent out by the Israeli Embassy is not rebutted by us, people will read it as true.  It does not present the true facts, but is inaccurate.</p>
          <p eId="para_69">It is right to call an occupation force an "occupation force" if it is one.  If it walks like a duck and quacks like a duck, I suppose it is a duck.  Therefore, if a force is in someone else's country, I presume it is an occupation force.  The whole world knows that to be the case.  The Israeli press release goes on about the figures and the number of Israeli people who were killed or injured, 82% of whom were civilians, which is akin to Joseph Stalin saying one person's death is a tragedy, but the death of 1 million is a statistic.  We are talking about human beings.  The press release gives us a list of the Israeli children killed.  Each of these is a tragedy for the parents.  It is a tragedy also for all the children who were orphaned.  However, as a human rights committee, we cannot let the Israeli statement go unrebutted.  We must put the facts out there.  We must also put those questions to the Israeli ambassador when he responds to our invitation to come here.  Every time this committee meets, we will invite him and each time we get the response that he is unavailable, we will write to him again, so that never again can he say he was not asked to give his side of the story.</p>
          <p eId="para_70">If the Israeli Embassy wants to send in a member of the Israeli defence forces — which we asked for if the ambassador was not available — we will accept a presentation from that person.  I am sure Colonel Travers would also be delighted to come in again to put across his side of the story.  The Israeli press release will be printed in tomorrow's newspapers as fact.  If we, as a human rights committee, do no rebut it, we will have failed to put across the true facts.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_71">I would be happy to take a proposal from Senator Daly to formally invite the Israeli ambassador to the committee and we could let the Senator know the outcome of that at our next meeting.  I will work with the secretariat of the committee for the record to word an appropriate motion to issue an ongoing, recurring invitation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidNorris" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Senator David Norris</from>
          <p eId="para_72">That would be very useful.  May I make an additional suggestion?  Due to the situation raised by Senator Daly and the immediacy of the press release, would it be possible for this sub-committee to put together and issue a short press release countering the Israeli press release?  I propose we should consider doing that because otherwise the damage will be done in the press, although the majority of the Irish people are well aware of the true situation.  It is terribly sad that the antics of the Israeli Government and its embassy here have so alienated the Irish people.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Senator Mark Daly</from>
          <p eId="para_73">I agree with Senator Norris that we should act immediately.  As soon as the Israeli press release is issued, it should be rebutted.  I would like to put on record my great admiration for two Irish men, Colonel John Travers and John Ging, who are doing extremely important work in difficult circumstances.  I am aware it was suggested by an Israeli supporting body in the newspapers yesterday that Colonel Travers was anti-Semitic, but a more decent man could not be found.  I suggest that when we write to the Israeli ambassador we should ask him whether he can propose any human rights organisation in Israel, the West Bank or Gaza upon whose figures we could rely.  Apparently, there is none — not the European Union, the UN nor any other organisation — other than Israel itself.  The Israelis have put the question to us as to why Israel did not attack Gaza when it pulled out and Hamas won the elections.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidNorris" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Senator David Norris</from>
          <p eId="para_74">The Israelis apparently do have a source of information.  It is called the Center for Middle Eastern Studies, but it is in America.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Senator Mark Daly</from>
          <p eId="para_75">As a politician, I am sure Senator Norris will appreciate that it was not the analysis of threats against Israel that kept it from attacking Gaza then, but the fact there was an impending election in Israel.  That is probably the main reason and the wish of the incumbents to remain in power and keep out Netanyahu, neither of which happened.  I hope the Chairman and secretariat will draft a press release rebutting the Israeli one.  Perhaps it could be circulated to committee members for agreement.  We should also ask the ambassador to come in and put his side of the story.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_76">It is important that I reiterate some of the points made by Senator Daly.  To be fair to the Israeli ambassador, when he was invited before the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs, there was a time constraint and he indicated he could not accept the invitation in that timeframe.  He offered instead to send the retired former British colonel, Richard Kemp, to put the Israeli side.  I appreciate that the Senator's proposal ——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Senator Mark Daly</from>
          <p eId="para_77">The Chairman should tell him this committee is available all year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_78">To clarify for the record, we have a proposal from Senator Daly to invite the Israeli ambassador to appear at our sub-committee at a time suitable to him to discuss the humanitarian and human rights situation that prevails in Gaza.  We will issue that open-ended invitation to him and assess his reply at our next meeting.  Is that agreed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelDHiggins" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Deputy Michael D. Higgins</from>
          <p eId="para_79">Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidNorris" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Senator David Norris</from>
          <p eId="para_80">Absolutely.  Would the Chairman put my proposal also?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_81">Is the proposal put forward by Senator Norris, with regard to human rights non-compliance and the Euro-Med agreement agreed?  Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelDHiggins" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Deputy Michael D. Higgins</from>
          <p eId="para_82">Please excuse me, but I must go to a meeting on Travellers' rights.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_83">I thank Deputy Higgins for his contribution.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_84">Not being a member of the sub-committee, it is not for me to put forward suggestions as to who else to invite.  However, I think the committee should seriously consider inviting the Egyptian ambassador also, given the ongoing humanitarian problems in Gaza and the inability to get humanitarian aid through the various border crossings between Egypt and Palestine and between Israel and Palestine.  If the Israeli ambassador turns up, he will deal with the blockage from their end, but it would be a useful exercise by this committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_85">I apologise to Mr Khalil Shaheen that I was not here for his presentation but I was listening in my office.  I thank him for the PowerPoint document which I believe contains the main points of the presentation.</p>
          <p eId="para_86">When I was in Gaza in November 2008, our group visited a number of places and I know that since then the situation has worsened.  One of the areas we visited was an agricultural farm which was trying to encourage workers back to produce goods for the European market, such as flowers and strawberries.  The programme was funded by the United Nations.  I watched in horror last year as some of those fields were bombed.  What is the current situation with regard to agricultural production?  We are aware that the product is not getting to market and this is a problem when the programme's aim is to encourage farming.  We also visited the major sewerage works in Gaza City.  They are incomplete and are dependent on simple materials which we take for granted in Ireland and in most of the world, such as concrete and cement, to complete a project which was funded by the European Union and the United Nations.  This project would have dealt with the sewage problem in much of Gaza City and also the situation whereby tens of thousands of tonnes of raw sewage is being pumped into the Mediterranean, one of the most important waterways in the world.  This is causing destruction to both the Palestinian and Israeli coastlines and further afield.  Has Mr. Shaheen any updated information on the sewage situation in Gaza?</p>
          <p eId="para_87">We also visited the power plant where we met the chief executive officer who explained that its operating fuel is paid for by the European Union but the fuel supply is restricted by Israel — even though it is paid for by the EU — as it is transported across Israeli territory by pipeline.  A power cut hit the city of Gaza when I was leaving and the image stayed with me, that of all the lights going out as we waved goodbye to the city.  Electricity is essential for sanitation, water purification, the operation of hospitals and everything else in a modern society.  The power plant was working on temporary generators because the original power station had been bombed and the new equipment was sitting at the border.  Has this situation changed or is the plant still awaiting delivery of the equipment to give it the capability to make electricity available for everyone?</p>
          <p eId="para_88">The situation was bad enough before I visited Gaza City.  There were no supplies of concrete or cement to complete some of the dwellings that had been bombed or destroyed previously and people were living in overcrowded conditions as they could not build homes.  Without the normal basic building materials, how are the people in the city able to cope and rebuild houses and schools which have been destroyed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Mr. Khalil Shaheen</from>
          <p eId="para_89">I thank the committee.  As a human rights defender and as a Palestinian, my mandate is very clear.  I always condemn all violations against human rights, whether involving the killing of civilians, women and children.  We are looking for respect for human rights and fundamental human rights for all people, whether they be Palestinians, Brazilians, Israelis, Muslims, Christians, Jewish or whatever.</p>
          <p eId="para_90">I will try to brief the committee on the internal conflict and the reconciliation that is very important.  During recent weeks, real and serious efforts at reconciliation were started.  We hope this reconciliation can be achieved.  Hamas is willing to sign the Egyptian initiative to hold preconditional elections.  We hope to have our democratic elections in May or June 2010.  These will only be local authority elections.</p>
          <p eId="para_91">It is clear the international community is granting immunity to Israel and this is the main obstacle we are still suffering as Palestinians.  There are more than 450 UN resolutions regarding the Israeli-Palestinian conflict.  I refer to the recommendations of the Goldstone report, the UN fact-finding mission.  I hope this committee can play a very important role at a political level to bring justice and peace for these victims.</p>
          <p eId="para_92">One of the important questions is the impact on medical treatment for children.  We have a sophisticated health system but we are still suffering.  Seven months ago, Mr. Netanyahu promised President Sarkozy he would allow 300 tonnes of cement to be brought in to rebuild the main hospital in Gaza City, Al-Quds Hospital, but up to now they have not allowed it.  This is similar to what is happening now regarding the building of houses for the 20,000 people who are homeless.  A total of 55,000 people are living in partly demolished houses and 16,000 apartments have no glass in their windows.  Total and additional sanctions have been applied during the past three years and there has been a total ban on the importation of building materials to Gaza.</p>
          <p eId="para_93">Senator Norris asked me about the impact on children.  Just recently during the past five weeks Gaza community mental health programme, which delivers mental health services in Gaza and is one of the most important non-governmental organisations, published research regarding the mental health impact on children in Gaza, indicating that at least 85% of Gazan children are traumatised.  Despite all these types of psycho-social support projects which were delivered after Operation Cast Lead, it is still a mess for these children.  They need follow-up and different types of psycho-social support.</p>
          <p eId="para_94">It is also the same for farms, especially flower farms and strawberry products.  Gazan farmers were proud that they could return to export their products.  Despite the mass destruction — it was like cleansing of their lands, water supplies irrigation works and everything — they replanted their farms.  The main obstacle is that they are not allowed to export their products.  Last year, two months after Operation Cast Lead, the Israeli occupation forces only allowed 5 million of 60 million flowers to be exported to EU countries.  Some 55 million flowers ended up as food for animals.  Their daily life and access have been destroyed.  They are under daily pressure from those who are shooting randomly, especially farmers who are based in the border areas.</p>
          <p eId="para_95">Regarding education, four of the Gazan main universities had real problems.  The Islamic University of Gaza lost one of the most important buildings, the engineering college.  It was totally destroyed along with all its equipment.  At Al-Azhar University in northern Gaza, the college of agriculture was destroyed.  Some 158 different educational installations have been destroyed or partially destroyed.  As a result of that most of the governmental schools are without windows.  They replace windows with plastic just to protect the students.</p>
          <p eId="para_96">Regarding sewerage, electricity and power plants, there is a shortage of materials and spare parts.  For example, the generator is working for 24 hours a day.  For three months it has needed repair, but we do not have the spare parts.  It is very common to have electrical power cuts ten times for one hour each time in the main hospital in Gaza City.  This requires the resetting of the monitors of patients in the intensive care unit.  It is the same for chemical treatment materials needed in the filtration process of sewage.  As a result, they have no more solutions.  The only solution is pumping the sewage directly to the sea.  We believe it is risky for the environment and everything.  In 2007, one of these sewage treatment plants was flooded and five people were killed, 75 people were injured and 27 houses were totally destroyed.  That was because the Israeli occupation forces did not allow the international bank to access an alternative pipeline east of Gaza and access to this is still totally denied.</p>
          <p eId="para_97">One of the members said he was there in November 2008.  It was a shame the Israeli supreme court of justice decided on the limitation on fuel supplies to the Gazans.  These limitations mean electricity power plants are only supplied with one fifth of their daily needs.  Some 68% of the Gaza Strip's electricity consumption is imported from Israel.  Power plants in Gaza produce only approximately 18% to 19% of our needs with the balance imported from Egypt.  I believe the occupation power and occupation authorities have to meet their legal obligations regarding international humanitarian law and international human rights law.  This is a form of collective punishment as declared by the UN special rapporteur to the occupied Palestinian Territories, Professor Richard Falk.  His reports declared that such siege and closure is regarded as a form of collective punishment and is considered as war against humanity.  Rather than the international community just waiting and publishing such reports, let us have real action just to implement international law to ensure respect for human rights.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_98">I thank Mr. Shaheen for his presentation and the very detailed response he gave to the various issues raised.  I congratulate him and encourage him to continue to do the good work.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Mr. Khalil Shaheen</from>
          <p eId="para_99">It is a pleasure again to be here and meet members of the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_100">I thank him for presenting his message and relaying it in such a candid fashion.  I am also pleased to welcome Ms O'Connor from Front Line.  It is good to see Front Line lending its solidarity to this work.</p>
          <p eId="para_101">We have been criticised again in the press release that I circulated today.  This sub-committee, the Department of Foreign Affairs and the Irish Parliament as a whole have been criticised for being too one-sided in our approach to the situation in Israel and Palestine.  As the Chairman of this sub-committee, I have to set aside all political considerations.  Mr. Shaheen said that a number of things will have to happen in terms of human rights and the humanitarian situation.  He mentioned that 20,000 people are homeless and 50,000 people are in inappropriate accommodation.  He also referred to the hospital in Gaza, the pipeline, the electricity supply and the water and sanitation services.  It is clear to everybody involved where the balance of injustice lies.  The Palestinian people in Gaza have been left in a state of abject poverty and powerlessness.  I am trying to be as fair as possible when I say that is not the case for the citizens of Israel who, thankfully, live in a prosperous and democratic state.</p>
          <p eId="para_102">I should mention that diplomats from the Nigerian, Palestinian, Israeli, Ethiopian, Moroccan, South African, Egyptian, Malaysian, German and Romanian delegations in Ireland are in the public gallery, along with a representative of the Irish Red Cross.  They are all very welcome.  Their presence demonstrates the level of interest in today's discussion.  It is appropriate that the chief concern of the sub-committee should be for those who are, in the words of the United Nations Office for the Co-ordination of Humanitarian Affairs, living in a "human dignity crisis" in Gaza as a result of Operation Cast Lead.</p>
          <p eId="para_103">I will conclude by saying we have passed two motions unanimously.  Mr. Shaheen is more than welcome to keep in contact with the officials in the committee secretariat, who will brief him on the response to the motions.  I hope the Israeli representatives at this meeting will relate to the Israeli ambassador the sub-committee's genuine and deep desire to hear at first hand the proposals he would like to make in respect of Gaza.  I would like to think such a meeting could happen within ten, 20 or 30 days.  We will try to accommodate the ambassador, regardless of when he considers to be the most appropriate time for him to attend a meeting of the sub-committee.  If the officials in the Israeli Embassy make contact with the secretariat of this sub-committee, or with my own office, we will try to agree a date as quickly as possible.</p>
          <p eId="para_104">I thank Ms O'Connor again for her attendance.  I wish her well with Front Line's three-day conference.  I understand there has been great interest in the conference.  I congratulate Front Line again in that regard.  I thank everyone who has attended today's meeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Senator Mark Daly</from>
          <p eId="para_105">Perhaps Deputy Ó Snodaigh's suggestion that we should invite representatives of the Egyptian Government to address the sub-committee can be discussed when other members are present.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvorCallely" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_106">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">The sub-committee went into private session at 12.55 p.m. and adjourned at 1 p.m. until 11.30 a.m. on Thursday, 6 May 2010.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
