<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_affairs/2005-02-02/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_affairs/2005-02-02/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2005-02-02" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/29/joint_committee_on_european_affairs"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_affairs/2005-02-02/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_affairs/2005-02-02/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2005-02-02" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_affairs/2005-02-02/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_affairs/2005-02-02/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference showAs="Vol. None" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None" eId="#vol_None"/>
          <oir:numberReference showAs="No. 110" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None/no/110" eId="#no_110"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AengusOSnodaighSF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aengus-Ó-Snodaigh.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Aengus Ó Snodaigh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AnnOrmonde" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ann-Ormonde.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Ann Ormonde"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BarryAndrewsFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Barry-Andrews.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Barry Andrews"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BernardAllen" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Bernard-Allen.D.1981-06-30" showAs="Bernard Allen"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DanWallace" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Dan-Wallace.D.1982-12-14" showAs="Dan Wallace"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DerekMcDowell" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Derek-McDowell.D.1992-12-14" showAs="Derek McDowell"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FergalQuinn" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Feargal-Quinn.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Feargal Quinn"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnDardis" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Dardis.S.1989-10-01" showAs="John Dardis"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnDeasyFG" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Deasy.D.2002-06-06" showAs="John Deasy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnnyBrady" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Johnny-Brady.D.1997-06-26" showAs="Johnny Brady"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaeSextonPD" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mae-Sexton.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Mae Sexton"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NoelTracey" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Noel-Treacy.D.1982-07-20" showAs="Noel Treacy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulBradford" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Bradford.S.1987-04-25" showAs="Paul Bradford"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RuairiQuinn" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ruairí-Quinn.S.1976-07-01" showAs="Ruairí Quinn"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chair" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chair" showAs="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chairman" showAs="Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/foreign_affairs" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM GHNÓTHAÍ EORPACHA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>JOINT COMMITTEE ON EUROPEAN AFFAIRS</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2005-02-02">Dé Céadaoin, 2 Feabhra 2005</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2005-02-02">Wednesday, 2 February 2005</docDate>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 2 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#BernardAllen">
                Deputy B. Allen,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulBradford">
                Senator P. Bradford,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#BarryAndrewsFF">
                Deputy B. Andrews,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#JohnDardis">
                Senator J. Dardis,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#AengusOSnodaighSF">
                Deputy A. Ó Snodaigh,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#DerekMcDowell">
                Senator D. McDowell,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#RuairiQuinn">
                Deputy R. Quinn,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#AnnOrmonde">
                Senator A. Ormonde,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#MaeSextonPD">
                Deputy M. Sexton,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#FergalQuinn">
                Senator F. Quinn.
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#DanWallace">
                Deputy. D. Wallace,
              </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#JohnDeasyFG">
   DEPUTY J. DEASY IN THE CHAIR.
  </person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>EU Constitution: Ministerial Presentation</heading>
        <speech by="#BernardAllen" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Deputy Allen</from>
          <p eId="para_12">This meeting will clash with questions to the Minister for Foreign Affairs at 2.30 p.m. and, naturally, I will have to absent myself then.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_13">I thank the Deputy. Since that is the case, if the Minister of State, Deputy Treacy, does not mind, I will allow Deputy Allen to speak on the first item on the agenda. He has 20 minutes in which to do so. We will wait until people have arrived, however.</p>
          <p eId="para_14">I have received apologies from Senator Lydon, Jim Higgins, MEP and Avril Doyle, MEP. The first item on the agenda comes is a survey that was taken last week on Irish people's awareness of the upcoming EU constitutional treaty. Some of the figures that came from that survey were worrying. It showed that the electorate was the least aware in Europe of the elements of the EU constitution. Some other countries had a far higher awareness of its detail. For that reason, I put this on the agenda and that is why the Minister has come here today. I thank him for coming at such short notice.</p>
          <p eId="para_15">I heard Deputy Quinn in the House today refer to European issues and he commented on this, as did Deputy Allen. It was interesting that people brought it up during the statements on the European Council. In particular, Deputy Gormley stated that there was not enough awareness. He tried to get hold of the most recent edition of the EU constitution, but he had difficulty in finding a copy. It is pertinent to what we will be talking about today. A number of organisations will be given the task of informing the public on what is in the EU constitution before we vote on its ratification. These bodies include the Institute of European Affairs, the Referendum Commission, the European Commission, the European Parliament, the Department of Foreign Affairs and the European Movement, of which Deputy Quinn is chairman.</p>
          <p eId="para_16">Considering what will happen this year, it seems that this committee will have a role to play. We will act as a clearing house for those organisations whose job it is to provide the information on the EU constitutional treaty for the Irish electorate. We also have a role as politicians in getting the message out to the public. This has to be done through political debate such as committee hearings here. There is a range of things we could do within the committee to heighten the awareness of what is in the EU constitution.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">The next few months will be very interesting in view of the upcoming French referendum in April or May. Spain will hold its referendum on 20 February. Hungary and Lithuania have held referendums. It is still indeterminate as to how this matter will be dealt with in France, even though the Socialist Party has decided to support it. There is a solid majority in Holland in favour of the referendum, but it is still not clear how it will go there. The issue of Turkey crops up again and again. I agree with what Deputy Quinn said today. There seems to be an underlying racist tendency involved. One Dutch politician claimed that if we voted against this, it would prevent Turkey's input into legislation. That is not much of a reason to vote against it. As a committee, it is incumbent on us to deal with the organisations involved in the EU constitution.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BernardAllen" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Deputy Allen</from>
          <p eId="para_18">I would like to make one or two points before I leave. I am sorry that I have to leave, but I have questions to deal with in the Chamber. I was taken aback when I heard that 45% of people never heard of the constitution, even though we held the EU Presidency when it was agreed. We are in 22nd place out of 25 countries in the league of awareness of the constitution. In football terms, that puts us in the relegation zone. We asked the Minister when the referendum would be held here, but he did not know.</p>
          <p eId="para_19">There has been no consultation with those Opposition parties that are in favour of the constitution on how we could inform the public on this issue. Other countries are putting their plans in place. We have to hold a referendum, but we are not in a good position. Where there is lack of information and ignorance, the fear is that people can be exploited. It is about time we got our act together. We must ensure that the mistakes prior to the first Nice referendum are not repeated. Over the next few weeks, I hope that the Government will make decisions, speak to those Opposition parties in favour of the constitution and start educating people. The lack of awareness is a major problem to which we have to face up and it should start now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RuairiQuinn" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Quinn</from>
          <p eId="para_20">When the delegates assembled in Philadelphia, the Scots-Irish in the backwoods of Pennsylvania and other parts of the world were not immediately informed on what was happening downtown, yet they came to learn how to use the American constitution, just like Irish citizens in this republic after the referendum was passed by a minority of the total population. It was not long before Irish citizens, given a new tool of democratic effectiveness, learned how to use it. Immediate awareness is an issue about which I would be concerned, as is the Deputy. In time, people will come to learn how to use what we are talking about if it is ratified by democratic vote.</p>
          <p eId="para_21">I thank the Chairman for allowing me to upset the normal rule of things and to speak in advance of the Minister. I ask the Minister to consider two things. I support the call of my colleague, Proinsias De Rossa MEP, that a copy of the complete constitution be sent to every household. That includes the protocols and I will elaborate on why they should be part of it. A copy should also be sent to every school and made available to every library. The network and the infrastructure was assessed before, but a full comprehensive document is required. There will be references in the debate to some of the protocols that are attached to the constitution, asserting that those protocols contain elements within it which oblige people to do something or not to do something. If they are not part of the document, the conspiracy theory allegations will prevail.</p>
          <p eId="para_22">However, I still recommend it be done.</p>
          <p eId="para_23">Whatever about the date of the referendum, which I accept is a decision for the Government of the day, in light of the parliamentary timetable and the unusual coming together of the St. Patrick's Day holiday and Holy Week the Minister should seriously consider holding the debate on the referendum legislation before St. Patrick's Day, without specifying the date. Before the documentation is sent to all households and before 17 March, the Houses, the Members of which are well informed, should have this debate. Provision is not made for this in the legislative programme circulated. I would be open to the suggestion, if it would facilitate parliamentary passage, that the Bill should commence in the Seanad because there is a backlog of legislation and we are always told the Senators are more reflective and less partisan on such matters. However, we need to decide this.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">I suggest that we get the documentation in place in order that it is sent to people's houses between Easter and June and we can state the Oireachtas has decided there will be a referendum on this matter and endorsed the provisions of the Government, but that the date of the referendum has yet to be decided.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelTracey" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Deputy Treacy)</from>
          <p eId="para_25">It is always good to attend the committee and hear what my colleagues have to say. I thank you, Chairman, for putting this item on the agenda and for providing the opportunity to attend.</p>
          <p eId="para_26">All of us involved in explaining the European constitution to the people and working for its ratification were concerned by the findings of the Eurobarometer poll to which you, Chairman, and Deputies Allen and Quinn referred, and to which colleagues referred in today's Dáil debate on the European Council report of December. It revealed disappointing levels of awareness and understanding across the Union. From an Irish perspective, the figures were poor in spite of a number of factors which one might have expected would work in the other direction, and which have been alluded to by the committee. One would have expected the good ongoing work of the National Forum on Europe and organisations like the Institute of European Affairs — to which I pay tribute for their significant contribution in providing information about Europe on a consistent and professional basis — and the extent of media coverage of the negotiations on the constitution during our Presidency to have ingrained the importance of the constitution and informed our citizens much better than the poll suggests. However, the only practical response is to acknowledge the difficulty and the need to do much more.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">We know from the two Nice referenda that the most important factor in stimulating public awareness and interest is active political debate, as covered by television, radio and the newspapers. The Government is determined to play a leadership role in the political campaign and we know that, as previously, other pro-European Union political parties in the House will also take an active part. The role of the social partners and other civil society organisations was particularly important in the second Nice referendum. I welcome the recent unanimous decision of IBEC to support the constitution and look forward to working with it and others to ensure its ratification in this country.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">As the committee is aware, no date has yet been set for the referendum, and I agree with Deputy Quinn that this is a matter for Government. The Government is keeping all relevant factors under careful review and will come to a decision on this issue at the appropriate moment. We are determined adequate time and space will be provided for public debate and an energetic and participative campaign.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">Proprietary work on the wording of an amendment to Bunreacht na hÉireann to allow for Ireland's ratification of the European constitution is proceeding well. I hope it will be possible, as on previous occasions, to reach a broad positive consensus within the Oireachtas. On that point and Deputy Quinn's point, we are anxious to move this matter forward as quickly as possible. However, we are constrained by the Constitution in that we must initiate in the Dáil the debate on any referendum on the Constitution before it goes to the Seanad.</p>
          <p eId="para_30">The reality is that most people will focus on the European constitution only when it becomes a live issue. However, it is also important to ensure that factual information is made widely available. Last autumn, the Government published an initial guide to the European constitution and a short leaflet. These were widely distributed to libraries, educational institutions, public offices and various other areas. Their availability was also advertised in all national newspapers and we received a good and pleasing response seeking these documents. The documents and the text of the constitution have been on the Department's website since last October and are available and accessible to everybody. The National Forum on Europe has also published a good summary of the constitution and a DVD for schools. It has a full programme of meetings scheduled for the period ahead in Dublin and provincial locations throughout the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_31">Work is under way on the preparation of a comprehensive White Paper on the European constitution which will explain its provisions in detail. However, while such a document is significant by definition, it is not aimed at a wide audience. The Government will therefore prepare summary information material for nationwide distribution as it did before the second Nice referendum. We have yet to decide when these materials will be published but we are committed to ensuring they are produced as quickly as possible and distributed across the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_32">I emphasise the work being undertaken by the European Commission and Parliament, which have been very positive in their efforts. Their information material and especially the website they have jointly developed are of a very high standard. In addition, the Commission office here will make available a satisfactory supply of copies of the constitution for distribution to interested members of the public. I understand a first batch of the printed version will arrive in the next few days.</p>
          <p eId="para_33">In response to Deputy Gormley, responsibility by practice, precedent and tradition for the printing of European constitutional documents has always rested with the European Parliament and Council through their publications office. They are handling the printing and as soon as copies are printed, as I am sure Deputy Gormley is aware, they will be available for everybody. A limited number will be available in the next few days and a large number as the month progresses. We must consider the practicality of ensuring that documentation is sent to every household. It is a huge document and we must consider the appropriateness of sending all of the documentation or an abridged version to every household.</p>
          <p eId="para_34">Of particular significance is the work of the Referendum Commission which under law has the twofold duty of developing public understanding of the issues and encouraging voter turnout, which is important. During the Nice referendum, the commission spent a little over €4 million, much of which was expended on television, radio and cinema advertising and on the production and circulation of two short information leaflets. In its report the Referendum Commission acknowledged that on the last occasion it had been established with sufficient time to do its work properly, although I accept that previously it had difficulties with the timespan available to it. We are anxious to accommodate it with the maximum time possible.</p>
          <p eId="para_35">The Referendum Commission can legally be established only after the referendum Bill has been published. I acknowledge Deputy Quinn's point and will raise the issue with the Taoiseach and my Cabinet colleagues to make sure the legislation is published as quickly as possible. The Government is acutely mindful of the need to ensure the commission has the time and resources it requires.</p>
          <p eId="para_36">We have for some time been working hard on the wording of the legislation. Since I took up my new position, at the highest levels of Government and across the two Departments with which I am involved, I and my Government colleagues have been working on this matter on a weekly basis. The wording is important and it is critical we get it legally correct. As soon as the wording becomes available, we will have discussions with the leaders of the Opposition parties and, through the Taoiseach, the Minister for Foreign Affairs and myself, we hope to reach common ground on that. It will then be printed and published and we will have the debate thereafter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_37">The Minister referred to the Referendum Commission. Members are aware it will have a significant budget. Deputy Quinn made a valid point with regard to the timing. The commission complained following previous referenda that it did not have enough time to deal with the issues. Therefore, the sooner the text is printed the better. The National Forum on Europe will have a full programme of hearings as times goes on.</p>
          <p eId="para_38">Following an approach to the Institute of European Affairs, Mr. Alan Dukes has agreed to come to next week's meeting which will be chaired by Deputy Andrews. This represents the beginning of discussions with the bodies and groups dealing with the referendum on the EU constitution. Professor Richard Sinnott from UCD, who has extensive involvement in this area, has also agreed to come before the committee. He is particularly interested in the public awareness aspect in terms of how best to get the message out regarding the content of the constitution. His views will be relevant over the coming months.</p>
          <p eId="para_39">Everyone understands where we are coming from on this issue. I appreciate the Minister of State's remarks and the committee will get back to him over the next few weeks. Every member understands that the Department is in the initial stages of formulating its information campaign. Once the committee has heard from relevant bodies and individuals, we may ask the Minister of State to come before the committee once again to give us a more definitive framework in terms of the Government's intentions over the next six months in regard to such issues as what information should be mailed to every household. I appreciate the Minister must be somewhat vague at this time as not all the decisions have been made. The purpose of today's meeting is to begin that process from our standpoint.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_40">I apologise if I am forced to leave the meeting early to deal with a priority question I have tabled to the Minister for Foreign Affairs. When the Treaty of Nice was under discussion, the full text, which was complex and referred to a number of other treaties, was not circulated. In this case, however, there is a comparatively simpler document. I agree with Deputy Quinn it should be circulated to every voter to ensure there is a proper and informed debate.</p>
          <p eId="para_41">Because it is a complex issue, when politicians or other interested bodies are discussing it in the media the public should have a reference document that can be consulted to check the veracity of any such public utterances. Although it is the responsibility of the European Parliament and Council to publish this document, the Government or the Houses of the Oireachtas should try to ensure that not only a summary but the full text of the treaty is distributed to every household. Specific funding should be made available for this undertaking if it is not within the remit of the funding for the Referendum Commission.</p>
          <p eId="para_42">Are fora available for NGOs and other groups which are campaigning on the constitution to circulate their material? It should be not only the Government that has the means to circulate a White Paper or other information on the issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelTracey" eId="spk_8" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Treacy</from>
          <p eId="para_43">I appreciate what Deputy Ó Snodaigh has said and am delighted members are anxious there should be no inhibitions, difficulties or impediments in the way of the Government in ensuring that the necessary resources are provided to distribute the constitution text to every household. A final decision has yet to be made on what information will be communicated to every household.</p>
          <p eId="para_44">Public funds can be spent only on the communication of factual information and no funds are available to other organisations from the Exchequer. This applies to the conduct of any referendum campaign. The Government's job is to ensure that official documentation, which is formulated on the basis of decisions by the Oireachtas, is circulated to the public. That is as far as we can go in terms of the utilisation of resources in this area.</p>
          <p eId="para_45">We are anxious to ensure full participation in the debate and that there is strong, vigorous and positive discussion, taking into account the historic traditions of our involvement in the EU since we joined in 1973 and bearing in mind the opportunities being created for a greater union into the future. The public must fully understand that we need to regularise and singularise the existing structures, treaties and systems that have served the EU so well. The EU is now a much larger entity and we must ensure there is a more official and structural operation that makes it simpler for citizens to access information while also retaining significant power for the domestic Parliaments of all member states.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_46">We can have that debate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelTracey" eId="spk_10" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Treacy</from>
          <p eId="para_47">We can do so. However, the important issue is to get the message across.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_48">Is the Referendum Commission called when the Bill is published or when it is passed? There is a difference here because one could publish a Bill in the morning. For example, the Referendum Commission has not been called in instances where Opposition parties have published referendum amendments in the past.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelTracey" eId="spk_12" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Treacy</from>
          <p eId="para_49">Once a Bill is published and lodged with Dáil Éireann, the Minister is legally in a position to make an order establishing the commission.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_50">Is it true that the earlier the Government publishes the Bill, the earlier the commission can begin its work in encouraging and facilitating debate among the public?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelTracey" eId="spk_14" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Treacy</from>
          <p eId="para_51">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_52">Members of the commission have made the point in the past that a difficulty for them in undertaking their work is that Bills have not been published on time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_53">I agree.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelTracey" eId="spk_17" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Treacy</from>
          <p eId="para_54">The commission was positive in this regard in its last report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_55">Yes, the report observed that this was the first time the commission was given sufficient time to undertake its work.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnnOrmonde" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Senator Ormonde</from>
          <p eId="para_56">I welcome the opportunity to have this debate. Most of the relevant issues have been discussed. Following the result of the first referendum on the Treaty of Nice, we cannot afford to make the same mistakes in this referendum. I note what the Minister has said about taking a leadership role and I have no doubt we will involve the social partners, education institutions and public offices.</p>
          <p eId="para_57">It is important that the message sent to every household is kept simple. If we use any gobbledegook, the information will not be read. This is an important aspect of the information campaign for any referendum and especially so in this case. The public must understand the issue on which it is voting. It has happened in the past that too many "wordy" words have been used in the information literature.</p>
          <p eId="para_58">The Minister of Sate observed that the Bill will only come to the Seanad after it has been debated in the Dáil. However, I have always maintained that the Seanad could be used as a forum for creating public awareness on issues such as this. I will ask in the Seanad that a debate be initiated by highlighting the imminence of this process and that statements be made. Seanad Éireann should be used as a forum to create a link between us and the public. I will raise this point again with the Minister of Sate.</p>
          <p eId="para_59">I welcome the fact that a summary information leaflet will be compiled and sent to interested members of the public initially. The quicker this is done, the sooner we can start the ball rolling. It may be early days but we should start immediately so that by the time the referendum campaign begins, everybody is well acquainted with the issues.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_60">Does the Minister of State have anything to say on "wordy" words?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelTracey" eId="spk_21" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Treacy</from>
          <p eId="para_61">I do. I agree with Senator Ormonde this is an important element of the difficulty in generating discussion on EU issues. Many people seem to believe that the issues are too complicated and tend to shy away from such discussion to a degree. The old maxim of keeping it simple is relevant in this regard. We must provide information that is clearly focused and easily understood, which functions as a tool to allow people to inform themselves, their families and their communities so that everybody can participate in a decision that is critical to the future of our country and of the EU.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_62">Senator Ormonde made a good point to which the Minister of State has given his reply. History will teach us a number of lessons when it comes to these referendums. In many cases, our approach has been a failure in terms of trying to get across even a basic message to the public with regard to Europe and these referendums. Our point is well made. There is little point in sending out a book of this size. As others said, we are talking about a lengthy document. Perhaps we could come up with some alternative method with regard to educating the public before we next meet. People like Richard Sinnott will come before the committee and I am sure they will give us ideas on how to do that.</p>
          <p eId="para_63">The message from the poll published last week was that Irish people are in the dark, generally speaking, about what is contained in the constitutional treaty. Are there methods to inform them other than sending out a booklet to every household? We have to be ready to engage different methods to get the message across.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelTracey" eId="spk_23" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Treacy</from>
          <p eId="para_64">I have listened to the requests made today. Everybody has a desire that all our citizens are informed as quickly and in as great detail as possible but our difficulty is to balance the requirement of getting the entire document to every household, which is a major technical but worthy task operation, against the requirement to inform the people and ensure that when they get the document they will read it. That is the challenge and we have to make the decision on that. There is no doubt about what Professor Sinnott and all the people involved in that area have said over the years, particularly since the last referendum. The one clear way to inform the people is through communication by way of television, radio and public debate. That is where people get the most information, participate to the greatest extent and are armed to make a decision based on what they hear from those who take part in a debate on these issues. That is the clear message — television, radio and public debate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DanWallace" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Deputy D. Wallace</from>
          <p eId="para_65">I welcome the Minister of State and thank him for coming before the committee at short notice. Deputy Allen and Senator Quinn expressed their concerns but the response from the Minister of State dealt with some of the anxieties felt by all of us. This process has already begun and we, as a committee, have an important role to play in it. Speaking at a function last Friday night in Cork, the Taoiseach briefly referred to the forthcoming referendum on the European constitution. He alerted the people that much information would be available on the European constitution. That is not just a matter for the Chairman or members of this committee, it is for everybody. The more simplistic we make the presentation, the better for everybody.</p>
          <p eId="para_66">We all received material from the National Forum on Europe yesterday regarding the EU referendum in which there is a summary of the European constitution. That process is starting now and the points made by the Minister here are important because the dialogue must continue. It will be up to us to do that, not just in this forum because the issue is wider than that. I thank the Minister of State for coming before the committee today because it is helpful to us, and we will move forward from here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelTracey" eId="spk_25" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Treacy</from>
          <p eId="para_67">I thank Deputy Wallace for his comments. The Taoiseach is committed to this process. We all have a duty to use every opportunity when discussing issues in a public forum, whether in public meetings or whatever, or outside this House, to alert people to the importance of the constitution and the fact that Europe has been very good for our country. We should ask them to study the constitution and be aware of its importance. That will allow them make a balanced, positive decision on the referendum.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FergalQuinn" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Senator Quinn</from>
          <p eId="para_68">I support what Senator Ormonde said about the simplicity aspect. Deputy Wallace referred to the document issued by the National Forum for Europe, Summary of a Constitution for Europe. I am not aware if other members do this but when I read the letters to the editor section of a newspaper, unless I have plenty of time, I tend to ignore the long letters. I read the short, snappy ones. I would be reluctant, therefore, to encourage loading every home with the full constitution because I do not believe it will be read. This document is much easier to read, and perhaps we should produce something even more simple.</p>
          <p eId="para_69">To take the example of the sin bin in rugby, when somebody misbehaved playing rugby in the past the referee was reluctant to send off the player because that was the end of the match for that person, but with the introduction of the sin bin, the referee is happy to send off the player because it will be for only ten minutes. The easier it is to have something understood, the simpler it is. Something similar happened with the alcohol Bill. In the past, the only power the judge had in the event that somebody misbehaved was to take away the pub owner's licence, thereby closing the pub. Now a judge can close a pub for a few hours or days, and that sanction is much more readily used. The comparison may not be understood, but selling Europe to our citizens — we have talked about bringing it closer to our citizens — is much more easily done in simple words.</p>
          <p eId="para_70">I was talking to the Minister for Foreign Affairs about the marvellous new road to Dundalk and he told me there is huge appreciation for the road, although I believe the thanks might go to the Government party rather than to Europe. We should ensure we draw attention to the benefits of Europe. The road improvements throughout the country were brought about by Europe. The low cost air travel would not have come about except for a united Europe. The benefit of price comparisons, particularly recently with petrol, would not have come about without a euro currency. If we remind people of the benefits they get from Europe we are much more likely to get them to admit they appreciate them and will support the referendum. In that respect, the simpler we can make the case for the constitution, the better.</p>
          <p eId="para_71">I do not know how we should handle the Referendum Commission, which must strike a balance between the pros and cons of the argument. As the Minister of State said, it is up to us, as citizens, to use every opportunity to highlight the benefits of Europe to our citizens. That way we are much more likely to get support for the referendum and not have a repeat of what happened in the first Nice referendum where, due to complacency, it was lost and we had to work much harder to ensure the second referendum was passed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelTracey" eId="spk_27" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Treacy</from>
          <p eId="para_72">I am impressed by what Senator Quinn said because he has been a master of communication to a wide consumer base. The complexity of retail business has been brought down to a fine art. We must examine the complexity of the European constitution, and keeping the message simple is very important. I will take on board what members said today. The advice of this committee is very important and we value it. I hope that, together, we can reach a conclusion on the final package and that we can have maximum participation from all our citizens as quickly as possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BarryAndrewsFF" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Deputy Andrews</from>
          <p eId="para_73">I record that I got lost on a few occasions in Superquinn in Blackrock.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_74">That is the point, they want you to get lost.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BarryAndrewsFF" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Deputy Andrews</from>
          <p eId="para_75">One is drawn down to the dairy section at the far end, even though that is the only item one wants. It is very clever.</p>
          <p eId="para_76">On the one hand the McKenna judgment requires the Government to spend evenly on the "Yes" and the "No" arguments, yet people are critical of the confusion these complex treaties cause. We are all talking about simplicity but the McKenna judgment feeds into confusion because we are used to an adversarial style of politics where the Government party argues one aspect and the Opposition parties argue another. That system was suspended on only one occasion by Alan Dukes, with his famous Tallaght strategy. Irish people do not understand the "on the one hand-on the other hand" type argument put forward by the Referendum Commission. They think it is mumbo-jumbo.</p>
          <p eId="para_77">We managed to pass a large number of European treaties, including the Amsterdam and Maastricht treaties and the Single European Act, without the need for any of that. Arguably, we are a little over-cautious since the first Nice referendum. The mistake was that we did not take the first Nice referendum seriously enough. The electorate has become much more sophisticated. I agree with Senator Quinn in that I do not see any point in that. I wonder if anyone will read it<b>,</b> much less understand it. With complex legal instruments such as this one, people rely to a large extent on others to form their opinion, and that is where we step in.</p>
          <p eId="para_78">Senator Ormonde's point on the role of the Seanad is interesting. The Finnish Parliament does not have a second house. It has a grand committee which is solely responsible for European affairs and it reviews and scrutinises European legislation. There is an argument for enhancing the role of the Seanad in terms of this debate and elevating its role to bring simplicity to this matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelTracey" eId="spk_31" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Treacy</from>
          <p eId="para_79">Deputy Andrews has made a number of valuable points. The McKenna judgment is now the law of the land. Arising from that, it can be said that the putting of the two sides of an argument before the people can create confusion. The consensus of the committee on this issue is obvious. The documentation we publish on this matter should be simple, clear, concise, focused and attractive for people to peruse, study and become informed to help them make up their minds on what they be believe is best in terms of the common good for the future of the country. We take on board what has been said here. We are mindful that we must do so against the legal constraints in place. We will do our utmost to make the documentation as simple as possible and to ensure it is available to everybody.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_80">For the information of members who came in late, we propose to invite in those organisations dealing with the EU constitution to ask them exactly what they propose to do in terms of informing the public about it. We will ask the Department of Foreign Affairs and the Minister to come in again at a later date<b>,</b> as well as people like Richard Sinnott who has agreed to come here on 2 March to give us some suggestions as to how to raise public awareness about the EU constitution.</p>
          <p eId="para_81">The message today is to ensure we bring simplicity to this matter. That is what we are all talking about. We are all politicians in our right. None of us is surprised or shocked that people would be in the dark as to what is in the EU constitution. None of us expects the entire electorate to be fully knowledgeable or aware of the detail of the protocols involved in this by the time the process is finished. One can only do one's best, but we have had some failures in the past.</p>
          <p eId="para_82">I disagree with Deputy Andrews that there may be an over-reaction to this matter in comparison with what has happened in the past. I heard him and others speak on the floor of the Dáil earlier about a neo-liberal agenda, militarisation, the subjugation of Irish law in the context of the constitution on which we may vote. I have heard some misinformation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BarryAndrewsFF" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Deputy Andrews</from>
          <p eId="para_83">The Referendum Commission has to present this argument.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_84">It is not the only body dealing with it. I understand the Deputy's point. I heard what was said on this matter on the floor of the Dáil today and I have a concern in that we, and the Department, should be involved in this matter at this point. What I heard today concerns me in that we need to begin this process immediately. I thank the Minister of State for his contribution.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelTracey" eId="spk_35" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Foreign_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Treacy</from>
          <p eId="para_85">I thank the Chairman and colleagues.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_86">We will suspend briefly.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_4">Sitting suspended at 2.54 p.m. and resumed at 2.56 p.m.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Lisbon Strategy: Presentation.</heading>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_87">The second item on the agenda is a discussion with representatives of Community Platform on strengthening the social dimension of the Lisbon strategy. As members will probably remember, we asked Orla O'Connor, Robin Hanan and Eric Conroy to come back to the committee not to make an argument about why this was important but on how they thought we could help in pushing forward the social dimension of the Lisbon strategy.</p>
          <p eId="para_88">Before the presentation, I draw your attention to the fact that while members of this committee have absolute privilege the same privilege does not extend to you. Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that members should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official by name in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_89">Mr. Hanan might refresh us on the issues and introduce his colleagues.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Mr. Robin Hanan</from>
          <p eId="para_90">We represent Community Platform, an alliance of 26 national organisations working against poverty and inequality in Ireland. In our submission we list the names of the organisations. I am from the European Anti-Poverty Network Ireland and my colleagues, who were present at our last meeting with you, are Orla O'Connor from the National Women's Council of Ireland and Eric Conroy from the Irish National Organisation of the Unemployed.</p>
          <p eId="para_91">To recap, we want to avoid repeating everything we said the last time because even though a number of members were not able to attend because of other commitments, I am sure they do not want us to repeat everything that was said the last time. At the last presentation we make a submission which laid out our concerns about the European Union's Lisbon strategy, particularly that the social cohesion and social inclusion dimensions of the Lisbon strategy seemed to be stalled and that in the mid-term review of the strategy, which is going on at present five years into the strategy, most of the discussion seemed to centre on one of the four pillars of the strategy, that of competitiveness.</p>
          <p eId="para_92">The original Lisbon strategy was seen as an economic and social strategic plan for the European Union which was designed to prepare the EU to compete more effectively in a more globalised world through drawing on its traditional strengths of social cohesion, social inclusion, a relatively strong tradition of welfare and social rights, employment rights and so on. We were concerned that much of the debate about the mid-term review of the Lisbon strategy, which will come to a head at the spring Council, concentrated very much on only aspect of that strategy, that of competitiveness.</p>
          <p eId="para_93">At the last session, we outlined a number of proposals we made in terms of strengthening the social inclusion aspect of the strategy, which I will not go into because they are on record. If members wish we can recirculate them or go into more detail about those aspects of strengthening the social cohesion and social inclusion side.</p>
          <p eId="para_94">At the last meeting, there was some discussion about the possibility of the committee taking an initiative to follow up the report which it did last summer about the competitiveness aspects of the Lisbon strategy. We thank the committee for inviting us back to discuss this in more detail. The paper we circulated before this meeting lays out a number of proposals on some of the areas which we believe it would be useful for the committee to take up or to produce some thinking on to fill out the picture which was partly sketched in the report last summer and to look at some of the social inclusion and social cohesion aspects of the strategy.</p>
          <p eId="para_95">We make the proposals under three main headings. One is strengthening the social inclusion strategy. The second is making the employment strategy work for inclusion or ensuring that the employment strategy which forms part of the Lisbon Agenda works to include people in the labour market. Rather than simply being seen as a way of increasing the number of jobs in its own right it should also provide paths to employment for people who are furthest from the labour market and quality employment. The third heading is mainstreaming gender equality in the Lisbon Agenda.</p>
          <p eId="para_96">Our first question is the question which was left hanging at the last meeting, that is, what way the committee is involved in making an input into the mid-term review of the Lisbon strategy and how we can contribute to that. We have made a proposal in that regard. There is a strong emphasis at European Union level on the importance of national parliaments having an input into the Lisbon strategy and that is being handled in different ways in different countries. There was some discussion at the last meeting about the committee producing its own report on the social inclusion and social cohesion aspects of Lisbon in terms of a few specific proposals and our paper is oriented around ideas on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FergalQuinn" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Senator Quinn</from>
          <p eId="para_97">I have considered the document carefully and I am impressed by the objectives and what the group is trying to achieve. We are familiar with the adage that if one gives a man a fish, one feeds him for a day but if one teaches him to fish, one feeds him for life. My concern is that sometimes the steps we take are solutions that solve the immediate problem but do not solve the long-term problem. I am particularly concerned about the link between poverty and unemployment. We must find a solution for that core of people. Ireland has the lowest unemployment figure in Europe but the same core group of people remains unemployed.</p>
          <p eId="para_98">I was involved for five years with the new leaving certificate applied. This identified that those who lost out at school tended to do so early in their education. They were at the back of the class and were the pupils who did not keep up with the rest. This could have happened at five, ten or 15 years of age. They then lost confidence and because of that, their performance went lower and lower and the differences between them and the high achievers were such that they never improved. These were identified as the people who became the core unemployed group. They were not only unemployed but probably unemployable.</p>
          <p eId="para_99">With the leaving certificate applied one could identify the ability of somebody to achieve something. There is an old saying to the effect that nobody is good at everything but everybody is good at something. It might well be the case that a youngster at the back of a class who was not good at mathematics or literature was brilliant at gardening or something else. If one could find that youngster's ability and build on it, the confidence grew.</p>
          <p eId="para_100">My concern is that the emphasis does not seem to be on getting to the fundamental long-term solution. The danger is that we solve the problem by propping up those who have fallen out of the system rather than getting at the core solution which is to ensure that they never get to the bottom in the first place. I have learned in business over the years that if one manages to find somebody's ability and concentrate on that, they blossom and gain in confidence and suddenly become good at other things as well. If, when people fail in one area, one can identify what they are good at, they gain in confidence doing that. They are then recognised by their colleagues and gain in confidence elsewhere.</p>
          <p eId="para_101">I am concentrating on the area of employment because I am not sure that we have a solution in that area. I fear that in Ireland, because we see employment and high income employment coming from highly skilled people, we are quite correctly pumping more money into technology and science education but the danger is that we will leave behind the core group I mentioned. These are the socially excluded. Can the group comment on whether we could do more in Europe, particularly under the Lisbon Agenda which includes a reference to it? We do not seem to be getting close to a solution.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Mr. Eric Conroy</from>
          <p eId="para_102">I welcome the Senator's remarks. He made some good points. They are taken on board in the national employment action plan and the European employment strategy, which are part of the employment strategy in the Lisbon Agenda. They all work together. With regard to the issue of early school leaving, there is a major correlation between it and long-term unemployment. I gather Ireland is doing a little better but Europe is not doing well in terms of 90% achievement of completion. That is a key issue and we want to see implementation of the references to education in the employment guidelines and the national employment action plan and as part of the wider Lisbon Agenda.</p>
          <p eId="para_103">There are also issues such as inter-generational unemployment. People at the margins, despite the Celtic tiger economy, did not get the jobs. Their parents are unemployed too. There are unemployment blackspots. The business of getting and working the social capital to get a job is not there. Programmes such as community employment, jobs initiative and social economy are most important. They have been reduced in recent years and we have been given a black mark by Europe for our performance in ALMPs, active labour market programmes. There was some movement last year but more is required in terms of active measures to get people ready for jobs.</p>
          <p eId="para_104">The Senator mentioned high tech jobs. That is an important issue arising from the Tánaiste, Deputy Harney's, report. We welcome the move to high tech jobs but it should not create a two tier society. We want jobs across all social groups. Not everybody can aspire to be a professor or to graduate from a university. There should be jobs at all levels and I cannot see any reason that there should not be.</p>
          <p eId="para_105">Throughout the country many jobs are being lost. Many jobs are centred in the services area in Dublin and the mid-east but we must not forget about the jobs lost in Kerry, Donegal and outlying areas. The Lisbon Agenda refers to regional disparities in unemployment. We must spread employment creation through all regions so everybody is converging towards the employment goals in the agenda.</p>
          <p eId="para_106">I welcome the Senator's comments. Hopefully, we can implement the social side of the Lisbon Agenda.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DerekMcDowell" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Senator McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_107">I welcome the delegation. There is a real difficulty with the Lisbon Agenda. It was a political agreement at the time which was a compromise between people of different political views in Europe. The pillar type arrangement was an attempt to balance those views.</p>
          <p eId="para_108">I will outline where the difficulty arises. Most governments in Europe, which are largely Christian democratic in hue, see the poverty and the social inclusion targets as the end result but they see competitiveness and the employment strategies as the way to get there. Frankly, at times there is a disconnect between the two. If poverty is reduced by doing things that Europe wants to do anyway, such as increasing competitiveness, well and good.</p>
          <p eId="para_109">There is a problem because we do not have an integrated labour market. The type of labour market interventions that might be made in Germany, with its employment and social structure, will be completely different from what might be appropriate in Ireland, which has virtually full employment and where people who are unemployed have particular difficulties which must be addressed by specific direct intervention.</p>
          <p eId="para_110">I am being sceptical but I wonder if there is any real value beyond saying that it would be nice to reduce poverty by pretending that there is a genuine social inclusion agenda as part of Lisbon because, frankly, I am not persuaded that there is. I would like to think there was and that it was attainable but I am a little sceptical of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Mr. Hanan</from>
          <p eId="para_111">What the Senator said is largely correct. On the last occasion we talked about the difference between the way the EU approaches market and employment issues compared with the way it approaches issues such as social inclusion. What was, and what is, important about the Lisbon Agenda is that it set in process a whole series of co-ordination mechanisms between governments to achieve social inclusion objectives, that is, the same objectives in different ways. The open method of co-ordination, the fact that it centred around the aim of making a decisive impact on poverty by 2010 and the fact countries must report on a two yearly basis on what they are doing against a very comprehensive set of objectives agreed at European level is important.</p>
          <p eId="para_112">What the Lisbon Agenda gave the social inclusion process was a very strong political drive, that is, the fact it was named at European level as being one of the main priorities. It gave it the mechanism for monitoring, comparing and learning. The term "name and shame" is one people in the Commission like to use. It also means looking in a fairly comprehensive way at the way different countries deal with issues such homelessness, drug abuse, access to employment, disability rights and so on. However, that is only an instrument governments need to use. Since we are looking at a very broad, open method of co-ordination, the success or failure of the social inclusion strategy depends entirely on how much political drive there is behind it at government level.</p>
          <p eId="para_113">Our worry is that the Lisbon Agenda seems to be a symptom of simply withdrawing from that whole process. There was a commitment five years ago to take social inclusion seriously. That is from where the fairly detailed objectives and all these co-ordination mechanisms come. It is a signal and amounts to withdrawing the resources from making that happen. We believe the type of competitiveness outlined in the Lisbon strategy was a compromise between different approaches but it was also a fairly coherent vision. There was a vision of working from Europe's strength compared with the US, for example, or some of the other big markets, with a relatively cohesive economy, a relatively highly trained workforce and a relatively involved inclusive society and using that as a strength to build on rather than simply undercutting costs.</p>
          <p eId="para_114">One of the things which has come out very clearly in the past number of years is that while there are more jobs available, there are also a lot more poor quality jobs. The EU Commission's statistics show that three quarters of people who it describes as experiencing poverty are in jobs. As described, there is the problem in this country of a large group of people who cannot access work because of various barriers, whether training or physical barriers in the case of disabled people or whether it is as a result of the type of barriers about which the Senator spoke in terms of building up personal supports needed to get back to work. There are also a large number of people going back to work but it has not taken them out of poverty. The work is simply not well enough paid, secure enough and of good enough quality to break that cycle of poverty.</p>
          <p eId="para_115">It is true that when we talk about the Lisbon strategy we are partly talking about symbols; about political commitments made at European level by all 25 governments and not just those of a particular political hue. The fact that governments seem to be pulling back from that and are looking at another way of handling the competitiveness issue is very worrying in terms of the impact it will have on people's lives. It is also a very specific set of mechanisms. In the employment area, they have a little more legal weight behind them with the treaty. The new draft treaty on the EU constitution has a couple of provisions which should give the same sort of legal weight to the social inclusion strategy but again only if they are used by governments.</p>
          <p eId="para_116">I think the Senator is right about the difference between aspiration in the social inclusion area and legislation in some of the other areas, for example, industrial policy. The mid-term review of the Lisbon Agenda is one of the most important places where the European Union talks about where it is going. That is why we were very keen for this debate, whether in the media or at this committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulBradford" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Senator Bradford</from>
          <p eId="para_117">As we had an interesting discussion at our last meeting, I do not want to rehearse what was said. Senator McDowell gave an overview of the political background to most of the economic decisions being taken at European level. It now appears that regardless of who wins elections in Europe, there is a fairly narrow degree of economic difference and limited change from one administration to the next <i>vis-à-vis</i> economic policy. Does Mr. Hanan believe the broader Lisbon Agenda or strategy can be implemented within the terms of that fairly narrow political discourse and the sort of economic agendas set by governments from Ballyferriter to Berlin, perhaps of different colours but with the same politics? Is this project possible?</p>
          <p eId="para_118">In the domestic sphere, we have had partnership agreements in recent decades and much of this is happening. It might be coming from Europe but it is already happening. On the broader aspirations which I know all of you would passionately advocate, can they happen politically within present government confines and configurations?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Mr. Hanan</from>
          <p eId="para_119">There are two questions. One is can it happen realistically and economically and the other is will it happen politically. We would argue that in both cases the answer must be "Yes". Economically, we still hold by the basic thinking behind the original Lisbon strategy which is that the European Union's strengths come from a particular niche in terms of a particularly cohesive society and a level of stability in our economies. I do not think anyone realistically believes Europe will undercut China in terms of labour prices or less protected workforces. Nor do I think there is any real drive for us to go out and compete in that type of marketplace in terms of labour costs. The only way we can compete is in terms of added value.</p>
          <p eId="para_120">One of the things the Lisbon Agenda identified is that there is relatively low participation in the workforce. For one reason or another, many people are not able to participate, or see no advantage in terms of their lives in taking part, in the labour force. If we continue to see the levels of child poverty we have seen in this country, one is automatically ruling out a future generation of workers or of people who can contribute to society in a many different ways. That, in itself, must undermine our competitiveness. If the new Lisbon goal sets out an aspiration to have a more highly trained workforce and a much greater involvement by that workforce but does nothing about the quality of pre-school education or about the poverty which drives people out of effectively taking part in education from quite a young age, the package will not hold together. That is the competitiveness side.</p>
          <p eId="para_121">The strategy laid out is a realistic one and is one which the Commission and the governments bought into at the time. Whether it will happen politically is probably a question we should put back to this committee representing the Oireachtas and the political parties. There is a strong commitment from Ireland. Ireland has taken some very important initiatives at European level, for example, in the past year around the new EU constitution. Previously, in starting up the EU social inclusion strategy, Ireland played an important role contributing to that. Going back to the 1970s and the first poverty programmes, Ireland has taken quite a strong leadership role in terms of setting a political agenda for a more inclusive Europe. We cannot predict the outcomes of these types of discussions in Parliaments throughout Europe but we believe it is a necessary project economically and politically. If one looks at the European barometer polls when they ask people in the 25 EU member states what is the main issue the EU needs to tackle, poverty and social inclusion come at the top of the list.</p>
          <p eId="para_122">Europe cannot just continue to be about completing the Internal Market and becoming more competitive, particularly if this undermines people's lives. The answer is that in economic terms it is viable and that in political terms we regard it as being necessary, particularly from the point of view of the type of organisations we are trying to represent, the people affected by inequality with whom we work, society and the European project itself.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DerekMcDowell" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Senator McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_123">I respectfully disagree with Senator Bradford about whether there is political difference. There is a broad level of political difference which is hugely important. Any objective observer considering the past eight to ten years of the Irish boom would say that our primary mechanism — it is arguably the only such mechanism — for tackling poverty has been the employment strategy. To be fair, this has been very successful in that it has reduced the number of people in consistent poverty to quite an extent. It has also done a little, though not very much, in terms of reducing relative poverty. The difficulty is that we are left with a hard core in respect of which direct intervention is required.</p>
          <p eId="para_124">There are many people currently in poverty, particularly those who do not have jobs, who are disconnected from or have a loose connection with the labour market. As Mr. Hanan stated, these people may be disabled, they may be lone parents, they may have health problems or they may be drug addicts or ex-offenders. From working with the Northside Partnership in Coolock, I am aware that people in the categories I have outlined comprise a significant percentage of those who do not have jobs. In my opinion, the difficulty these people face in entering the labour market, in so far as they can or want to, is not being addressed at present by the employment strategy or by other measures the Government has taken. We have used one trick which has been important and successful but which has failed to address the residual level of poverty. To that extent, I disagree with Senator Bradford's assertion that there is not a broad range of political choices available.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Ms Orla O’Connor</from>
          <p eId="para_125">The Senator is right when he states that the policy has been that the route out of poverty is to get a job. Obviously, however, a certain number of people are disconnected from that. In addition, that policy has produced gross inequalities which have given rise to current statistics for relative poverty which are the highest in Europe. I accept that I said this at the previous meeting but there is also an issue of sustainability. How sustainable is the policy in light of the inequalities that are arising? Such inequalities are particularly relevant to women who have re-entered the workforce. They have experienced difficulties in terms of child care, part-time work and social welfare. It is not sustainable to continue to proceed as we are at present. There are serious issues in terms of work-life balances and employment policies. In conjunction with considering consistent poverty and the people who are completely disconnected from the labour force, there is also the issue of gross inequalities for people who are in employment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DerekMcDowell" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Senator McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_126">I could not agree more. Making available universal services to people, whether they are in the labour market or not, is crucial. We have done very little work on that. We do not have social supports in place in a number of areas, one of which is that of pre-school. Even within the social security system, we do not have the broadness we require to ensure that people who fall through the net do not get lost. I agree with Ms O'Connor. We have done well because we have had an economic boom. However, we are not geared up to deal very well with recession. If there were a recession, the results could be quite catastrophic for many people.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Ms O’Connor</from>
          <p eId="para_127">It would be useful from our perspective, in terms of the direction the committee is going to take in respect of the mid-term review and how it intends to engage with it, to know if the committee will be producing a report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_128">We are initially proposing to include this in our work programme which is being formulated at present. We are then going to write to each Department asking them to give weight to it. The third option we can take is to issue a statement which could be laid before the Houses as a report. Our guests' statement could be included as an appendix to that. We can agree on the first two quite readily. However, I would rather wait until entering private session to discuss the laying of the report before the Houses and appending our guests' statement to it. I do not have a difficulty with proceeding in this way but I want to obtain members' views. Those are my suggestions as to how we proceed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Mr. Conroy</from>
          <p eId="para_129">What sort of timescale will be applied? The spring Council will take place in March or early April and it is now February. As this is the only time of the year that Heads of Government address the mid-term review, we are looking for maximum impact. We have not seen the report from the Commission which will inform the meeting of the plenary on social partnership. The latter will discuss the Lisbon Agenda. It should, therefore, all come together in terms of a maximum impact on the second half of the decade. The input should influence those at the highest level in the coming months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_130">As far as members are concerned, we can do that immediately. I will communicate, if the committee decides to take that course of action, with our guests as regards the laying of the report before the Houses at a later date.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DerekMcDowell" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Senator McDowell</from>
          <p eId="para_131">I wish to ask a final question. A number of years ago the Government decided to ask individual Departments to poverty-proof measures then intended to take. Do our guests believe this made a difference or was it merely gesture politics?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Mr. Hanan</from>
          <p eId="para_132">One could say it made a small difference but not as much as could have been the case. Poverty-proofing has been in place for seven years since the introduction of the first national anti-poverty strategy. It took a number of years, for example, for poverty statements to emerge with the budget. In the main areas of Government policy, poverty-proofing is seen more as an add-on to rather than a central part of thinking. When major new initiatives are introduced, Departments are required to include a poverty-proofing statement in the memorandum for Government. It is possible that such statements make a slight difference to memorandums but, effectively, there is no major change. A great deal of work is being done behind the scenes by the Combat Poverty Agency and the Office of Social Inclusion to train people in Government Departments and co-ordinate the implementation of poverty-proofing.</p>
          <p eId="para_133">Poverty-proofing has made a difference around the margins. We are of the opinion, however, that it has not changed any major or substantial new policies. It is not just about ensuring that poverty is addressed more strongly, it is also meant to try to prevent policies from moving backwards. We could name a number of policies in recent years which have increased poverty and social exclusion such as, for example, direct provision for asylum seekers and the removal of the right to work — which had been granted for one year — from asylum seekers. In our view, the latter clearly increases rather than reduces poverty and there was no sign that the policy was poverty-proofed. The changes in the community employment schemes have come and gone. There has been much inconsistency in respect of some measures in this regard which, in the short-term, have either improved or disimproved the situation. There is very little indication that the thinking behind them employed a poverty-proofing approach.</p>
          <p eId="para_134">Poverty-proofing is a mechanism that can be used but people need to buy into it. The change of thinking that occurred in this country in the 1980s in terms of the national deficit and reorganising the public finances was a form of proofing which obliged every official to take it into account in every decision they made. One can say that most decisions taken by Government are largely international investment confidence-proofed. I do not believe poverty-proofing has taken off in the same way.</p>
          <p eId="para_135">One of the issues we highlight in respect of poverty-proofing is that it is largely a system which relies on individual officials to make assessments of the impact of their proposals. It would be useful if an outside body such as the Oireachtas — although it would probably not be the role of this committee to do so — agreed to examine poverty-proofing statements to discover the impact of particular proposals. I refer here to considering the impact of the budget on increases or reductions in poverty, the impact of employment actions plans, etc. Part of the problem is it has not been part of public debate and it has been simply a check box exercise.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_136">I thank the delegation for its submission and for attending.</p>
          <p eId="para_137">The joint committee went into private session at 3.30 p.m. and adjourned at 3.45 p.m. <i>sine die</i>.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
