<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2018-06-12/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2018-06-12/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2018-06-12" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/32/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2018-06-12/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2018-06-12/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2018-06-12" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2018-06-12/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2018-06-12/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-03-05" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AliceMaryHiggins" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Alice-Mary-Higgins.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Alice-Mary Higgins"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BernardJDurkan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Bernard-Durkan.D.1981-06-30" showAs="Bernard Durkan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CatherineMartin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Catherine-Martin.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Catherine Martin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FionaOLoughlin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Fiona-O'Loughlin.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Fiona O'Loughlin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="HildegardeNaughton" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Hildegarde-Naughton.S.2013-07-19" showAs="Hildegarde Naughton"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JanOSullivan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jan-O'Sullivan.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Jan O'Sullivan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnBrady" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Brady.D.2016-10-03" showAs="John Brady"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnCurranFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Curran.D.2002-06-06" showAs="John Curran"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="KathleenFunchion" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Kathleen-Funchion.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Kathleen Funchion"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MariaByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Maria-Byrne.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Maria Byrne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulMurphy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Murphy.D.2014-10-10" showAs="Paul Murphy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="StephenDonnelly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Stephen-Donnelly.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Stephen Donnelly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ThomasByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Thomas-Byrne.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Thomas Byrne"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Co-Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/office/co-chairman" showAs="Co-Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM OIDEACHUS AGUS SCILEANNA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Education and Skills</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2018-06-12">Dé Máirt, 12 Meitheamh 2018</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2018-06-12">Tuesday, 12 June 2018</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 12:00 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 12:00 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#JohnBrady">John Brady</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#AliceMaryHiggins">Alice-Mary Higgins.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#JoanCollins">Joan Collins</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#StephenDonnelly">Stephen Donnelly</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#BernardJDurkan">Bernard J. Durkan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#FionaOLoughlin">Fiona O'Loughlin</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#BridSmith">Bríd Smith.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#JohnCurranFF">Teachta / Deputy John Curran sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
        <summary eId="sum_5">The attendance list is a composite list of members of the Joint Committee on Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Joint Committee on Education and Skills and Joint Committee on Health. Committee Chairs are styled as Co-Chairman.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Joint Meeting of the Joint Committee on Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Joint Committee on Education and Skills and Joint Committee on Health<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T12:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Supports for People with Disabilities: Discussion (Resumed)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T12:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T12:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_10">Deputy O'Loughlin, who chairs the Joint Committee on Education and Skills is <i>en route</i>. She is a little late but she will be here shortly. We have received apologies from Senator John Dolan, Deputy Margaret Murphy O'Mahony, Deputy Michael Harty, Deputy Hildegarde Naughton, Senator Paul Gavan and Senator Lynn Ruane.</p>
          <p eId="para_11"> The witnesses are all welcome to the meeting of the Joint Committee on Employment Affairs and Social Protection, the Joint Committee on Education and Skills and the Joint Committee on Health. This is the third meeting of this configuration of three committees. We are continuing our discussion on the necessity to improve the supports available for people with disabilities intending to transition from education or training into employment. The three joint committees first met the Disability Federation of Ireland and Inclusion Ireland on 3 May. We subsequently heard contributions from individuals of their lived experiences at our last meeting on 29 May. Today's meeting will focus on the input from departmental representations. I hope that our combined efforts and consideration will enable us to make some real proposals that will improve the outcomes for people with disabilities. The content of the previous meetings has been circulated to the Departments and, therefore, officials will know the issues we have examined.</p>
          <p eId="para_12"> I welcome the attendance of colleagues today. Specifically, I welcome Ms Simonetta Ryan and Mr. John Bohan from the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Mr. Jim Mulkerrins and Mr. Phil O’Flaherty from the Department of Education and Skills and Ms Patsy Carr and Mr. Dave O'Connor from the Department of Health. They are all welcome. I will ask them to make your opening statements presently and then committee members will have a number of questions.</p>
          <p eId="para_13"> I wish to draw the witnesses' attention to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee. However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence. Witnesses are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_14"> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_15"> There is no particular order for the speakers. The first person I will ask to make an opening statement is Ms Ryan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from> Ms Simonetta Ryan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T12:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_16">I am assistant secretary in the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection with responsibility for disability policy and the administration of the disability allowance scheme.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">I am joined today by my colleagues, John Bohan and Danny Harty, also from the Department. I thank the committee for this invitation to discuss supports provided by the Department for people with disabilities, particularly in respect of employment.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> I will focus on three key areas as follows: working with other Government agencies and services to ensure good cross-governmental functioning to secure better employment outcomes; providing a range of income and employment supports and services to address the needs of people with disabilities; and engaging with people with disabilities to advise them of these supports and to guide them where appropriate to employment or to other services.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> Before I say something about each of these, I would like first to recall some of the main statistics of relevance to this area. According to Census 2016, there are almost 645,000 people living with a disability in Ireland. In April 2016, there were 130,000 people with a disability at work of which 122,000 were in the working age population range. People with disabilities, however, are still only half as likely to be in employment as others of working age. Census 2016 figures show that the employment rate for people with disabilities of working age is 37% compared with a rate of 73% for people of working age without a disability.</p>
          <p eId="para_20"> We know that many people with disabilities want to work. In our survey of 2015, 35% of people not then working said they wanted to work part time, while 8% said they wanted to work full time. Young people with disabilities are likely to start out with lower employment rates and the gap widens with age as people leave employment.</p>
          <p eId="para_21"> The data tell us that to improve employment rates we need a twofold approach: early engagement with young people with disabilities and a focus on retention of those already established in the workforce. For young people, the potential benefits are greatest in the crucial years following school to young adulthood when otherwise their disability threatens to keep them out of the workforce. For older people, the advantages of early engagement can also apply to those who acquire disabilities later in life and who may need retraining and other supports to stay in the workforce.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> The comprehensive employment strategy was adopted by Government in October 2015 having been developed in consultation with Departments, State agencies, the National Disability Authority, NDA, and disability stakeholders. The ten-year strategy is a cross-governmental one co-ordinated by the Department of Justice and Equality and provides a roadmap to ensure that people with a disability who are able to and want to work are supported and enabled to do so. The Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection is engaged in delivering 33 actions through the comprehensive employment strategy. Progress to date includes the publication in April 2017 of the Make Work Pay report. This was an interdepartmental report with independent external participation and chaired by Professor Frances Ruane. We have either implemented or made significant progress on some of the recommendations and I will return to some of these later.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> The Department has worked jointly on the pilot project to integrate employment and mental health support which was developed with Genio and departmental funding and in partnership with the HSE mental health division, EmployAbility companies and Mental Health Reform. A central objective of this project was to improve integration between public mental health and supported employment services at national and local levels. There has been joint working, supported by the National Disability Authority, NDA, with the Department of Health and the Department of Education and Skills, on action 5.1 which focuses on transition points for people with disabilities. The group has produced a report agreed by Government, to be published shortly, outlining the policy approach and an implementation plan.</p>
          <p eId="para_24"> More generally, the Department participates in the comprehensive employment strategy implementation group chaired independently by Mr. Fergus Finlay who produces an annual report. We provide a range of income and employment supports. The primary income supports for people with disabilities are disability allowance, invalidity pension and partial capacity benefit. Disability allowance is a means-tested payment for people who are aged between 16 and 66. To qualify a person must be substantially restricted in undertaking suitable employment. Disability allowance is structured so that a person who wishes to do so may take up employment and still retain all, or a significant portion of, his or her payment, thereby ensuring that work is seen to pay. The first €120 of weekly earnings is disregarded in the means test for the payment while weekly earnings between €120 and €350 are assessed at 50%. A single person earning more than €420 a week can retain the minimum amount of disability allowance and continue to qualify for the free travel pass.</p>
          <p eId="para_25">A number of contributors to the joint committees mentioned that uncertainty around the retention of benefits, including the medical card, represents a barrier to people with disabilities exploring their work options. The Make Work Pay report made a number of recommendations, including that the requirement that work be of a rehabilitative nature for the disability allowance earnings disregard should be dispensed with. This would mean that a report from a doctor would no longer be required before commencing work and that the focus is on capacity rather than incapacity. Legislation is required to give effect to this change and is included in the Social Welfare Bill 2017. Currently, 10% of disability allowance recipients - about 13,000 people - avail of the disability allowance earnings disregard.</p>
          <p eId="para_26"> Other recent changes to the income supports to make them easier to retain if employment is taken up include the extension of entitlement to a travel pass to five years after commencing full-time employment or exceeding the appropriate income threshold, which exceeds the three years recommended in the Make Work Pay report; a fast-track return to disability allowance if employment does not work out; a clear statement that disability allowance payments will not be stopped or reviewed on the basis of an enquiry about work at an Intreo centre; and the introduction of an online benefit of work estimator to assist people with disabilities in assessing the impact of taking up work on their disability payment. Since the launch of the Make Work Pay report, just over 800 disability allowance recipients have entered full-time employment and ceased claiming the allowance.</p>
          <p eId="para_27"> Invalidity pension<b>
						</b>is an income support payment paid to people who are permanently incapable of work because of illness or disability. It is based on a claimant's social insurance contributions and is not means tested. While invalidity pension is generally paid to pension age, where a person with a disability wishes to return to work, he or she may apply for partial capacity benefit. Partial capacity benefit was introduced in February 2012 and is designed for people who are in receipt of long-term social insurance invalidity, illness or disability income support payments who have some capacity for work.</p>
          <p eId="para_28"> As well as providing these income supports, the Department also provides a range of supports specifically intended to improve employment outcomes for persons with a disability. The EmployAbility service, for example,<b>
						</b>is a nationwide employment service funded by the Department and dedicated to improving employment outcomes for jobseekers with a disability. There are 23 limited companies, each with a specific geographical remit. The Ability programme<b>
						</b>is the new pre-activation programme for young people. The focus of the programme will be on projects aimed at young people who have disabilities and who are aged between 15 and 29 and it is designed to assist in their transition from school to further education and employment. This will be undertaken using person-centred, case management approaches that support participants to identify and follow progression pathways based on both their needs and their potential. We also provide a range of grants under the reasonable accommodation fund and the disability awareness training support scheme to assist employers in the private sector to take appropriate measures to enable a person with a disability or impairment to have access to employment.</p>
          <p eId="para_29"> The Department also funds two significant disability projects directed at participants in third level education. The Willing Able Mentoring programme, WAM, builds the experience and confidence of graduates with disabilities and employers through the method of a mentored work placement programme which is paid for by the employer programme. Get AHEAD is a training programme and forum for students and graduates with disabilities to discuss their experiences of education and employment.</p>
          <p eId="para_30"> On engaging with persons with disabilities through the public employment service, the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, DEASP, network of 62 Intreo centres provides a gateway for people with disabilities who wish to explore their work options and they may voluntarily look for an appointment with a case officer to discuss their work ambitions and develop a personal plan to progress their goals. We recognise that our engagement with people with disabilities will require developing our employees' skills in engaging with them. In November 2016, a certificate in professional practice in employability services provided through the National College of Ireland was introduced for DEASP staff. There is good coverage of disability issues, including a guest lecturer who is a specialist in the area, and contributions from two staff development unit case officer trainers specialising in DEASP supports for people with disabilities.</p>
          <p eId="para_31"> As I mentioned earlier, the publication of the Make Work Pay report in April 2017 marked an important step in the identification of specific actions that are intended to secure better employment outcomes for people with disability. The report made many recommendations, including that disability allowance payments and other schemes should be reconfigured for new entrants aged 18 and over to ensure that their work ambitions could be explored systematically at an early age. This is referred to as the principle of early engagement.</p>
          <p eId="para_32"> Following the publication of the report and the recognition that some of the recommendations may be controversial, the then Minister indicated that the Government wanted to consult persons with disabilities and their families on some of the recommendations. We engaged an experienced facilitator to ensure the consultation process was as wide-ranging as possible and included representation from a wide range of stakeholders. The information documents were designed to allow people with disabilities and their families to provide an input to the process. We made considerable efforts to ensure that the materials were fully accessible. The documents were also produced in a range of accessible formats such as easy read, Braille, audio, video captioned and Irish Sign Language.</p>
          <p eId="para_33"> The Minister, Deputy Regina Doherty, and Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath, launched the consultation process in Richmond Barracks, Inchicore, Dublin 8, on 7 March 2018. Regional seminars were held in Cork, Dublin, Sligo and Limerick during March and April this year. The findings of the consultation process are being consolidated and a report will be prepared for the Minister and Minister of State on the outcome of the consultation process when it is finalised to inform the next steps in the implementation of the Make Work Pay report. </p>
          <p eId="para_34"> In conclusion, I hope this presentation demonstrates that while many supports and services are in place to assist people with a disability to fulfil their employment ambitions, the Department is very active in addressing the objectives of the comprehensive employment strategy in trying to improve the employment rates of people with a disability. The multifaceted nature of the barriers faced by persons with a disability calls for a similarly multifaceted approach and the Department is pursuing a range of actions across a number of areas to achieve this. The fall in unemployment and the transformation of the Intreo service provide an opportunity to make significant progress in this area.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_3">
          <from> Mr. Jim Mulkerrins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T12:25:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">I thank the Co-Chairman and members. I am principal officer in the special education section of the Department of Education and Skills. I am joined by Phil O'Flaherty, who is the principal officer for further education and training in the Department. I apologise for the late delivery of our remarks; I was out of the country late last week which contributed to the delay.</p>
          <p eId="para_36"> I thank the joint committees for the invitation to today's meeting. We are aware of the joint hearings of 3 and 29 May and will try to address the matters highlighted during those meetings. Our  statement today will primarily address the provisions made for supporting children with special educational needs to support participation in further studies, training or employment, the supports available in the further education sector to facilitate access to further education and the transition from further education to employment and career guidance for those with a special educational need.  The Department's policy for supporting children with special educational needs aims to ensure that all children with special educational needs have access to an education appropriate to their needs, preferably in school settings through the primary and post-primary school network as well as in special class or special school settings. Such placements facilitate access to individualised education programmes which may draw from a range of appropriate educational interventions, delivered by fully qualified professional teachers with the support of special needs assistants and the appropriate school curriculum. Funding for special education provision in 2018 will amount to some €1.75 billion, an increase of about 43% since 2011. That is equivalent to about 18.7% of the gross overall current allocation for education and training.  To support pupils and parents in the transition from education, the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, has published guidelines for parents, students and schools covering the transitions between all stages of education, including the transition from primary to post-primary and post-school education and training options for people with disabilities. These guidelines provide students and their families with valuable information on the extensive range of post-school options and supports available and guidance to inform individual choice. The guidelines cover further education and training, higher education and rehabilitative training and adult day services. The publications are available on the NCSE's website. All schools were informed when they were published. I can arrange to have copies sent to the committee clerk for distribution. </p>
          <p eId="para_37"> The Department recognises the importance of planning for transitions throughout a child's education and at present all schools are required to develop education plans for all children identified with special educational needs and additional care support needs. The Department's inspectorate's advice is that the majority of schools are now using some form of individual education planning for children with special educational needs, which is welcomed by the Department. </p>
          <p eId="para_38">Educational plans should be differentiated in line with pupils' needs. A student's support plan should include clear, measurable learning targets and specify the resources and interventions that will be used to address student needs in line with the continuum of support process. Individualised support plans for students should be developed through a collaborative process involving relevant teachers, parents and guardians, the pupils themselves and outside professionals, as necessary. The individualised planning process should include regular reviews of learning targets as part of an ongoing cycle of assessment, target setting, intervention and review.</p>
          <p eId="para_39"> Members may know that the comprehensive review of the special needs assistant, SNA, scheme was published by the NCSE on 30 May. It has found that while the scheme is greatly valued by parents, students and schools and works well in meeting the care needs of younger students it is less effective for some older primary and post-primary students, as over-reliance on SNA support has been found to result in some students experiencing alienation and stigma. It also found that there can be an overdependence on SNA support, leaving some young people inadequately prepared for life in post-school settings, and it is seen as a blunt instrument to deal with the wide range and variety of needs, ages, developmental stages and school settings. The Department is now developing proposals to implement the review's recommendations in consultation with other key Departments and agencies.</p>
          <p eId="para_40"> Turning to further education, a major focus of the further education and training strategy is to deliver skills for the economy and support active inclusion of all citizens. These twin goals are closely connected and both point to the importance of assisting people with disabilities to access employment.</p>
          <p eId="para_41"> Overall in 2017, more than 17,000 people with a disability were enrolled in a wide range of mainstream further education and training, FET, programmes. Details on all FET programmes are available on the FET courses website. Learners on FET programmes have access to appropriate guidance services. Some programmes also provide income support by enabling learners to retain their entitlements under schemes provided by the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection and have provision for meal and travel allowances. The Higher Education Authority fund for students with disabilities also funds services and support for students with a disability in post-leaving certificate colleges.</p>
          <p eId="para_42"> SOLAS and the Department meet regularly with the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection to discuss issues relating to the training and upskilling of unemployed people and those on other payments. Protocols are in place between Intreo offices and education and training boards, ETBs, to deal with issues relating to the planning of training and the management of referrals. This provides a good opportunity for the Department, SOLAS and the ETBs to assist the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection as it looks to extend the employment services and supports for people with disabilities.</p>
          <p eId="para_43"> SOLAS, through the education and training boards, also provides specific funding of almost €47 million per annum for dedicated education and training for people with disabilities through specialist training providers. More than 3,500 learners benefitted from this provision in 2017. Generally, this provision is accessed by people who need more intensive support. Features of the programme include longer duration, adapted equipment and transport arrangements.</p>
          <p eId="para_44"> SOLAS regularly commissions follow-up surveys to establish what happens to participants, primarily in terms of outcomes, after they leave the FET training delivered by ETBs. The most recent follow-up survey was conducted in 2017 and it surveyed those who exited ETB training in the period from January to March 2016. Within this survey, a customised survey to gain feedback from participants with a disability who participated in specialist training programmes, STPs, was conducted. The findings included outcomes indicating that 26% were in employment, 4% were on Government schemes and 15% were engaged in further study. There are plans to extend the approach to monitoring outcomes in order that we can also get a better picture of how people with disabilities on mainstream programmes do after completing their courses.</p>
          <p eId="para_45"> SOLAS engages with ETBs each year to discuss funding priorities, taking account of local need and labour market data. This year, SOLAS has required ETBs to set out how they are addressing barriers to accessing FET. This is done in the light of the 2017 SOLAS report on barriers for vulnerable groups accessing FET. A fuller picture of initiatives in place at ETB level will emerge from this process and provide a basis for determining future supports.</p>
          <p eId="para_46"> The Department recognises that there are still access difficulties in some FET settings. Until now, the scope available to address these difficulties has been limited as no specific capital budget was allocated for FET. Enhanced allocations of capital funds for the sector over the period of the national development plan will give greater capacity to address these issues.</p>
          <p eId="para_47"> Turning to apprenticeships, the Department noted that many contributors to the previous joint committee hearings spoke about the potential of apprenticeship to provide access for people with disabilities to the labour market. A total of 371 current apprentices, out of a total population of almost 13,500, report as having a disability.</p>
          <p eId="para_48">The review will look at the quality of information available to students and adults on career guidance, the sources of this information and how the system is organised to support students and adults in this area. Opportunities have been provided for all relevant stakeholders to contribute to the review. More than 100 written submissions have been received, including a significant number of submissions from special schools. Drawing on the results of the consultation process and further consideration by the steering group, the specific role and objectives of career guidance in supporting students in special schools will be assessed further.</p>
          <p eId="para_49"> Related to the area of career guidance, some stakeholders have spoken about work experience. The Action Plan for Education 2018 includes an action to commence a review of work experience at post-primary level with a view to increasing access to, and the quality of, work experience for students. This review is at the early planning stages with a steering group to be established which will then define terms of reference and a project plan for the review.</p>
          <p eId="para_50"> While noting the broadly complimentary remarks made in a previous hearing concerning access to higher education for persons with disabilities, it may be helpful to provide some information on the higher education sector. Student support services in higher education institutions usually include an equity of access office, dedicated disability services and a career guidance support service. The central role of disability officers is to provide supports and services to students with disabilities to assist them in accessing higher education and successfully completing, as well as to ensure compliance with the legal requirement to provide reasonable accommodations as appropriate. A key ambition of the National Access Plan for Equity of Access to Higher Education 2015-2019 is to achieve the implementation of more inclusive practices and integrated approaches which contribute to the realisation of a student body which reflects the diversity and social mix of the population.</p>
          <p eId="para_51"> Perhaps the most important measure of how well access to higher education is facilitated is to note that the proportion of higher education entrants indicating they have a disability has increased from 6% in 2012 to 10.3% in 2016. The challenge, of course, is to maintain and build on these numbers.</p>
          <p eId="para_52"> The Department is represented on the working group of the comprehensive employment strategy for people with disabilities strategic priority action 5.1, which is led by the National Disability Authority. It focuses on transition points for people with disabilities. The group has produced a report agreed by the Government, to be published shortly, outlining the policy approach and an implementation plan.</p>
          <p eId="para_53"> Significant progress has been made in supporting learners with disabilities across the range of school levels and into further and higher education. The comprehensive employment strategy framework will also help us advance the cross-departmental co-operation which may be necessary in some areas. It gives us visibility and access to colleagues in other Departments. I thank the committee for the invitation today to present to it.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">As part of a review on "Pathways to Participation in Apprenticeship", which is due to be completed at the end of June 2018, research is being undertaken on barriers to participation by people from diverse groups, including those with a disability. Alongside this research, SOLAS is conducting café dialogue sessions to further inform recommendations for the review. Attendees at the sessions have included individuals from organisations representing people with disabilities. It is expected that the expansion of apprenticeship into new sectors, giving access to a much broader range of job opportunities and occupation types, will also assist in enabling people with disabilities access this valuable pathway to employment. As members know, the Disability Act 2005 places an obligation on public bodies, including our own Departments, to ensure that at least 3% of their workforces are people with disabilities.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_7"> I turn to career guidance for those with a special educational need. Guidance in schools refers to a range of learning experiences provided in a developmental sequence that assist students to develop self-management skills which will lead to effective choices and decisions about their lives. It encompasses the three separate but interlinked areas of personal and social development, educational guidance and career guidance. For all children in mainstream post-primary schools, including those with special educational needs in mainstream or special classes, the support of the guidance counsellor is available where it has been provided to the school. There is no other additional or separate guidance support for children with special educational needs and there is currently no policy to support an alternative or separate guidance provision for children with special educational needs in mainstream post-primary. That is in keeping, I suppose, with the policy of inclusion which the Department supports.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_8"> In mainstream post-primary schools, it is common practice for the school guidance counsellor and the special educational needs, SEN, co-ordinator to work very closely in liaising with parents and the feeder primary schools, analysing psychometric assessments, identifying and supporting the needs of students with special educational needs, advising students and their parents on the most suitable subject choices and programme options, and facilitating students to secure appropriate work experience as part of the transition year, leaving certificate applied and leaving certificate vocational programmes. The SEN and guidance teams collaborate in facilitating students to apply for supports such as the reasonable accommodation for certificate examinations, RACE, scheme, the disability access route to education, DARE, scheme and other access routes into further and higher education and employment.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_9"> A key role of the guidance counsellor is to develop close links with employers, access officers in colleges, SOLAS training and apprenticeship schemes and other organisations, such as the National Learning Network, with a view to maximising the opportunities for students with special educational needs and other disabilities to access further education, training and jobs. The National Learning Network offers 70 different training programmes, including vocational and rehabilitative courses, to up to 5,000 students annually, many of whom have a disability and wish to up-skill, gain employment and live more independent lives. The programmes are funded through the Education and Training Boards and the Health Service Executive. The courses are free and individualised and offer a variety of awards including QQI levels 1 to 6, ECDL and City and Guilds. Of those students who completed a training programme last year, 90% went on to further education and training.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_10"> For students in special schools<b>, </b>the position is somewhat different. Special schools are substantially different from mainstream schools and these students typically have very different needs. </summary>
        <summary eId="sum_11">In all cases, the classroom teacher and other school staff are more intimately aware of the abilities and strengths of all students than would be the case in mainstream schools. That is partly because of the average pupil-teacher ratio of less than 5:1 and the special needs assistant ratio of 3:1 in the majority of special schools. Special school staff typically have extensive engagement with parents, HSE multi-disciplinary teams and the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, which involves planning for the child's future, including options for further education, training, employment or other placement options subject to the child's abilities, including the young person's transition to adult services when the child reaches the age of 18 years. Students who transfer to adult service settings can continue to participate in educational programmes through further adult educational programmes or in adult settings which are allocated resources towards educational provision.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_12"> The National Skills Strategy 2025 and the Action Plan for Education 2016-2019 provide for a career guidance review that will include recommendations on changes to improve the existing career guidance tools and career information for post-primary, further education, higher education students and adults currently in place across the education and training system in Ireland. The purpose of the review is to ensure that we are providing high quality, relevant career guidance information to students from post–primary level up to further and higher education. The review will look at the quality of information available to students and adults in relation to career guidance, the sources of this information and how the system is organised to support students and adults in this area.</summary>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T12:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">I thank Mr. Jim Mulkerrins for his presentation. I invite Ms Patsy Carr to make her opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_5">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T12:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">I thank the committee for the opportunity to outline the policy context in which the Department of Health, through the HSE, provides services for people with disabilities, including employment supports.</p>
          <p eId="para_56"> Disability services are provided to enable each individual with a disability to achieve his or her full potential and live as independently as possible. Services are provided in a variety of community and residential settings in partnership with service users, their families and carers, along with a range of statutory, non-statutory, voluntary and community groups. Services, in the main, are provided either directly by the HSE or through a range of voluntary service providers. Voluntary agencies provide the majority of services in partnership with and on behalf of the HSE. The range of specialist disability services provided to people with disabilities includes residential; respite; day services and rehabilitative training; assisted living services, namely home support and personal assistant services; early intervention and school-aged services through progressing disability services for children and young people 0-18 years; multidisciplinary supports; aids and appliances; neuro-rehabilitation services; financial allowances; and miscellaneous support services.</p>
          <p eId="para_57"> Disability services were allocated €1.78 billion in 2018. This funding is providing specialist disability services to 36,000 persons across all nine CHO, community healthcare organisation, areas, ensuring that services are delivered in line with nationally agreed policy for persons with a disability, while, at the same time, endeavouring to maximise value. A wide range of disability services is provided to those with physical, sensory, intellectual disability or autism or both.</p>
          <p eId="para_58">Over 60% of the resources available are allocated to provide a range of residential services to approximately 8,400 people with a disability. A further 20% is targeted at the provision of more than18,000 day places and supports to nearly 25,000 people. The remaining 20% provides respite care services to just over 5,700 people, over 4 million personal assistant and home support hours for 2,500 people, as well as multi-disciplinary teams and other community services and supports to children.</p>
          <p eId="para_59"> Last month, I met the Joint Committee on Public Petitions on the HSE-funded personal assistant service. I am also aware that personal assistants, PAs, have been discussed in this forum. The term "personal assistance user" refers to a person with a disability choosing a personal assistant of his or her choice to aid him or her in everyday tasks. The 2004 Health Act does not mandate the HSE to provide PA services. It is, rather, an ancillary service. However, the Department of Health and the HSE are committed to protecting the level of personal assistant services available to persons with disabilities. From 2013, the HSE has consistently, year on year, increased the number of hours of PA service delivered to persons with a disability. Last year, 1.5 million hours were provide to approximately 2,500 people at a cost of €42 million.</p>
          <p eId="para_60"> Day services are a key component of support services that enable service users to live within the community. Currently, day services are transitioning to a new approach outlined in the policy, New Directions. This policy is underpinned by the values of person-centredness, community inclusion, active citizenship and quality. There are approximately 25,000 people availing of day services and there is an annual intake of approximately 1,000 additional young people who require such a service on leaving school.</p>
          <p eId="para_61"> Within the New Directions service approach, people in receipt of a HSE-funded day service are offered a choice of 12 supports. These include support for making choices and plans; support for inclusion in one's local community; support for accessing education and formal learning; support for maximising independence; and, support for accessing vocational training and work opportunities.</p>
          <p eId="para_62"> The first support referred to is support for making choices and plans. This sets the foundation for each individual's service. A person-centred plan is formulated for each individual and within that context, if a person has ambition to progress to employment, a plan is developed to support the person to achieve this target. The plan may incorporate a range of all of the 12 supports.</p>
          <p eId="para_63"> The range of supports and the timeframe involved in supporting a person to achieve his or her goal will depend on the needs and abilities of each individual. One of the key supports for people who express a wish to progress to employment is support for accessing vocational training and work opportunities. Within this support, depending on a person's social and work-related skills, preparation for the world of work commences. This support will include work experience placements which can act as a transition for people into employment.</p>
          <p eId="para_64"> The rehabilitative training programme, which is also provided within the framework of New Directions, acts as a foundation programme for people with disabilities. Work-related social skills are also a key focus of this programme together with work experience placements and trialling of vocational training programmes. There are rehabilitative training programme places available throughout the country. Rehabilitative training places are managed at CHO level and are often reallocated or moved within the CHO area to meet demand. They include all ages and disabilities, including mental health.</p>
          <p eId="para_65"> Since 2016, all HSE CHOs are allocated the funding required to meet the needs of all school leavers in their area. All school leavers in 2017 received the quantum of day service requested and a similar outcome is envisaged for this year's school leavers.</p>
          <p eId="para_66"> The HSE is allocating €12.5 million in 2018, that is, €25 million in a full year, to provide appropriate services and supports to young people with disabilities and autism who will require continuing health-funded supports on leaving school or rehabilitative - life skills - training this year. As part of the annual school leaver day service process, each service user seeking a day service is individually profiled to ensure that he or she receives the level of support required.</p>
          <p eId="para_67"> The Department and the HSE works closely with the National Disability Authority and are grateful for its support in ensuring that the right supports are provided at the right time to support each school leaver to maximise his or her potential.</p>
          <p eId="para_68"> Earlier, I spoke about day services and employment supports. The range of supports offered can include work experience, therapeutic work following a clinical recommendation, employment in the open labour market and supported employment. Supported employment can include the national employability programme, which my colleague, Ms Simonetta Ryan, from the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, spoke about, or service provider supported employment initiatives.</p>
          <p eId="para_69">In the absence of appropriate supported employment programmes being available to people with disabilities in recent years the HSE has funded some providers to provide this element of employment. This support will continue for those who are availing of it while a more responsive arrangement is developed as part of the comprehensive employment strategy.</p>
          <p eId="para_70"> The Department of Health and the HSE are collaborating with the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection and the Department of Education and Skills as part of the comprehensive employment strategy 2015-2024. This initiative is led and co-ordinated by the Department of Justice and Equality, which has a co-ordinating role for disability matters. With the assistance of the National Disability Authority, the Departments are exploring the development of a pilot project to test the policy approach for a comprehensive supported employment programme. Such a programme could be implemented over 2018 to 2020 and focus on a specific target group. This will provide learning for any future scaling of such an approach.</p>
          <p eId="para_71"> The 2017 report of the Make Work Pay group made two principal recommendations regarding medical cards to address a barrier to employment for people with disabilities. The Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, has committed to deliver on the recommendation to raise the medical card earnings disregard from its current level of €120 per week for people on disability allowance or on partial capacity benefit associated with invalidity pension. The Department has collaborated with colleagues in the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection and is working with the HSE on the operational aspects to enable implementation of this recommendation as quickly as possible.</p>
          <p eId="para_72"> A second recommendation made by the group sought to amend the medical card guidelines requiring that employment must be of a rehabilitative nature for the associated income to be disregarded when being assessed for a medical card. I am pleased to say that the guidelines were amended and the disregard has applied since April 2017.</p>
          <p eId="para_73"> Disability is not a health issue or an education issue or an employment issue. It is, however, an equality issue and Government has had a whole-of-government approach to disability for a number of years. The Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath, has responsibility for disability issues in the Department of Justice and Equality, the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, and the Department of Health. The Department of Justice and Equality is the lead Department for policy co-ordination for all disability and equality issues. The Department of Health works on a cross-sectoral collaborative basis with colleagues in Departments on national policies for adults and children with a disability. For instance, an interdepartmental cross-sectoral group at assistant secretary level meets regularly to ensure a co-ordinated approach to policy development across the Departments of Health, Education and Skills, Children and Youth Affairs, and Employment Affairs and Social Protection. We know that more people with a disability have more complex needs. Government is responding by providing the supports that people with disabilities need to live the full and independent lives that we all take for granted.</p>
          <p eId="para_74"> I thank the committee for inviting me here today. I am glad to have the opportunity to meet in such a collaborative forum and I am happy to take any health related questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">The first comment I wish to make relates to the three presentations. I thank the witnesses for the time they have taken. They obviously listened to the issues raised at the previous meetings and have tried to address them. That was the purpose of the exercise rather than having a general discussion. I thank the witnesses sincerely for taking the time to address those issues.</p>
          <p eId="para_76"> I was taken by the fact that a great deal is happening. If we read all the material submitted, we could sit here and say that we are doing a great job. All that has to be balanced, however, by the lived experiences of the people who attended the committee some weeks ago. I am not suggesting the services are not in place but the challenges those people have found along the way need to be considered. That was one of the reasons for the exercise rather than simply talking to advocates. The idea was to include the individuals themselves. I thank the witnesses sincerely for the presentations and for the way they went about addressing the questions.</p>
          <p eId="para_77"> The next session will allow colleagues to ask questions. I propose to allow each member up to ten minutes to direct questions because three different Departments are represented at the meeting. I will start with Deputy Brady. He has ten minutes initially. He can stop and start but I ask him, please, to be specific in who he addresses his questions to because I am conscious that we have representatives from three different Departments.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnBrady" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Deputy John Brady<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">I want to make a general comment and pick up on a particular paragraph in the presentation given by Ms Carr because it cuts to the chase and to why we are here. Ms Carr said that disability is not a health issue or an education issue or an employment issue but an equality issue. She said Government has taken a whole-of-government approach to disability for a number of years.</p>
          <p eId="para_79">At our two previous sessions, the Disability Federation of Ireland, DFI, indicated that the current activation measures are not impacting on the employment rates of people with disabilities in post-recession Ireland. That view is echoed by numerous other organisations that deal specifically with people with disabilities. There are serious question marks over how successfully the measures are impacting on the ground.</p>
          <p eId="para_80"> To home in on one area, much has been said about the comprehensive employment strategy which has been in place for two years. The strategy has not had any impact on the employment levels of people with disabilities. That view is borne out by statistics that are available for everybody to see and have been referred to in a couple of presentations. It has also been echoed by the DFI and other organisations. The Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection has responsibility for 33 actions in the comprehensive employment strategy, most of which were to be delivered in 2016. How many of those specific actions have been implemented? I can state categorically that few of them have been implemented, even though the target date for implementation was 2016. Will Ms Ryan indicate how many of the 33 actions in the strategy have been implemented by the Department?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_8">
          <from> Ms Simonetta Ryan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T12:55:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">We have done a considerable amount of work to advance the 33 actions. I understand, as I have read the previous presentations to the committee, that people are frustrated because they do not see enough action on the ground. What I tried to show in my presentation was that there is a great deal being done but this is a complex area and it is difficult to show where things are happening immediately or quickly. The most obvious action to point out is the large amount of work done on the Make Work Pay report, consulting people with a disability to try to come up with the best way to take matters forward. In terms of some of the other steps we have taken, I will ask one of my colleagues to contribute. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_9">
          <from> Mr. John Bohan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T12:55:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">I am in charge of the disability policy unit. I will revert to the Deputy with more details on the individual actions. There are 22 actions specific to the Department and those on which we have made good progress are those relating to the previous disability activation project, DACT, programme, co-funded by the European Union. In the past month or so, we have built on DACT by introducing a mainstream programme known as the Ability programme which implemented the findings of the review of the DACT programme. The review included a number of recommendations, including several on systematic engagement with people with disabilities. That recommendation also featured in the Making Work Pay report. For the past year, my colleagues and I have been engaging with disability groups, parents and stakeholders on how this recommendation could be implemented in practice, particularly how the principle of early engagement with young people might be systematised in Intreo services. We have made some progress on that.</p>
          <p eId="para_83"> The report also recommended the introduction of a ready reckoner, a benefits of work estimator. The Department implemented this recommendation in the past month. We have made good progress on some of the actions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnBrady" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy John Brady<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T12:55:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">I am sorry to cut across Mr. Bohan but I am conscious that my time is limited. Given that there were 33 recommendations, I do not expect the witnesses to rattle them all off. I ask them to furnish the joint committees with a progress report on all of them because there is legitimate concern that they have not been implemented, despite the report setting a timeframe for doing so of 2016.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_11">
          <from> Mr. John Bohan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T12:55:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">We can send two documents. We can send a note that goes through the actions that specifically related to the Department and also send a copy of the annual report by the chair of the implementation group, Mr. Fergus Finlay, who does an annual review of progress in implementing the strategy. </p>
          <p eId="para_86">That might give the Deputy a good sense of the situation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnBrady" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy John Brady<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">I have another specific question. Some employment projects are doing fantastic work. WALK is one such programme. Year after year, it lobbies committees to try to get funding to ensure it can continue, which is ludicrous. It provides tangible benefits for people with disabilities. If we are serious about putting in place measures which work and benefit those with disabilities why is that the case? Projects such as WALK should be rolled out across the State. Maybe I could get a specific answer to that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_13">
          <from> Mr. John Bohan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">WALK was one of the successful applicants for the ability programme. Its funding is secure for a three-year period.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnBrady" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy John Brady<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">That has to be welcomed. I was not aware of that. It is long overdue. WALK has done Trojan work over many years.</p>
          <p eId="para_90"> I am seriously concerned about social enterprises which do fantastic work. A number are closing and there seems to be confusion about who has responsibility for them. The HSE is not funding staff to support projects. Who has responsibility for social enterprises operating across the State? The buck seems to be passed between different Departments and ultimately the HSE is not providing funding. It is a general question which covers a couple of different Departments. I ask Ms Carr to address the role of the HSE.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_15">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">I am not familiar with the project to which the Deputy referred. Social partnerships are part of the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AliceMaryHiggins" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Senator Alice-Mary Higgins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">The Deputy might be referring to the schemes Ms Carr mentioned that the HSE had funded in the absence of other schemes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_17">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">My presentation referred to individual care providers who have run programmes within their own organisation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnBrady" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Deputy John Brady<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">Okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_19">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">I will look into it in case I am wrong.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnBrady" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy John Brady<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">I have two other specific questions covering two different areas. A lot of evidence has been given about the barriers which have been put in place for people with disabilities in terms of entering or re-entering the workforce. One has been touched on. There has been some welcome progress in terms of people being able to keep the free travel pass for five years. I do not think the scheme goes far enough, even though I acknowledge it exceeds the recommendation of three years.</p>
          <p eId="para_97"> Another issue is medical cards. I note the response that the Minister is working on the issue and the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection is currently working with the HSE on the operational aspects to enable implementation of the recommendation. What is the current status of the project? This has been going on for quite a while. It was suggested at a previous committee meeting that specific legislation is required to allow changes to be made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_21">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">In respect of one aspect of the Deputy's question, as I said the rehabilitative training scheme has been in place since 2017. The income disregard piece has almost been finalised.</p>
          <p eId="para_99">Discussions are ongoing with the HSE on finalising it, but the Department also wants to be consistent with what is done in the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection. I think that is what requires legislation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:05:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">We may come back to the Deputy in a moment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnBrady" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Deputy John Brady<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:05:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">To clarify, is specific legislation required?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_24">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:05:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">Not for the medical card piece, but we need to be consistent.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnBrady" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Deputy John Brady<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:05:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">In relation to the income disregard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_26">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:05:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">Yes, but we need to be consistent with what is in place in the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection. My understanding is legislation is required to change the income disregard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnBrady" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Deputy John Brady<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:05:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">Is work ongoing on the legislation required or what stage is it at?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_28">
          <from> Mr. John Bohan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:05:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">I am not sure if that is the case. I think the income disregard in the area of social protection works in a different way. It starts at €120 but extends over a range to €350. The medical card scheme cannot operate in the same way because one cannot taper the withdrawal of a medical card. The Department of Health has been considering various options. It would like to align the income disregard in some way with that in the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, but it cannot mirror it. Therefore, it is looking at options in order to be able to do so. We have been engaged in discussions with the primary care reimbursement service, PCRS, of the Department of Health, the section that manages the issue. We have given it information on the number of people in receipt of disability allowance to allow it to do so. I am not fully sure whether there is a need for the Department of Health to change the legislation, but I do not think we need to change ours to allow it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_29">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:05:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">I am sorry if I misinterpreted the question, but I do not think we need to change our legislation. We have to develop a policy, but the Minister wants it to be consistent with what applies in the area of social protection. As Mr. Bohan pointed out, the Department of Health has more flexibility. As far as I am aware, it has more to do with a medical card for a family. For an individual, there is one arrangement. If the medical card is for a family, the arrangement is different. The Department is in the process of agreeing to it and working it out with the HSE, but as far as I know, it is expected that it will be sorted out in a matter of months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#StephenDonnelly" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Deputy Stephen S. Donnelly<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:05:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">I thank all of the delegates for their work and statements. I count 22 pages of statements. Clearly, there is a lot of activity, but I could not find a single sentence identifying existing problems. It is unbalanced. I appreciate that this is a political arena and that it is not really up to civil servants to come and hang out to dry the Government of the day on what is not working, but the report is not balanced. It talks about a lot of activity, but there is no critical analysis of what is working, or rather what is not working, where additional resources are required, where enabling legislation is required or anything else. That is very disappointing because there is very little we can do with the information supplied. The statements outline where we are at, but they do not really tell the Oireachtas what the Departments need and how we, as legislators, could help, particularly in the run-up to the next budget when there may be a little money to spend. I am disappointed with the information supplied from that perspective, but that is not to take from what is, undoubtedly, a lot of work that is ongoing across the Departments.</p>
          <p eId="para_109"> What strikes me about the three presentations - the Chairman also alluded to it - is the disconnect between all of this activity and what is actually happening on the ground for people with a disability. I will direct my first question at the HSE. </p>
          <p eId="para_110"> I spent about half of Friday in the National Rehabilitation Hospital trying to help a young man to get out of it. He was injured a year and a half ago and is paraplegic as a result of the injury. He was discharged from the hospital last September. I engaged with the HSE. The family also engaged with it. The young man in question was told that he would have to move back to Sligo to the intensive care unit to live out his days, which obviously is completely ridiculous. He was told this because people were screaming at the National Rehabilitation Hospital for the bed he had. He wants to lead his life and go back to work, but it took me and his family having his case highlighted on "Prime Time" and me raising it in the Dáil to even get a response from the HSE.</p>
          <p eId="para_111">I wrote multiple emails. I, as a Member of Parliament and as Fianna Fáil's health spokesperson, could not even get a response to my emails. That is the reality. The reality is that it is now June. He was discharged last September but he is still there. To be fair, at the table last Friday were people from stepdown facilities, senior clinicians and people from the HSE who have been trying very hard. The reality is that he was discharged almost a year ago. He is in the wrong setting and his bed is needed by about 50 other people. That is the reality.</p>
          <p eId="para_112"> Can I ask the HSE how it can possibly be, with all this activity going on and all this emphasis on and work and money aimed at helping people with disability lead as full a life as they can, that someone can be discharged from the National Rehabilitation Hospital, NRH, last September and still be meeting me, his clinicians and members of the HSE last Friday? How is that still a reality today?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_31">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">I am not from the HSE.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#StephenDonnelly" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Deputy Stephen S. Donnelly<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">The Department of Health. I beg your pardon.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_33">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">I am not familiar with the case the Deputy is talking about. We are all aware that there are 110 beds in the National Rehabilitation Hospital and obviously that is not enough for the needs around the country. As the Deputy rightly pointed out, there are a lot of people in beds there who could have their care provided, and would prefer to have their care provided, in their own community. There are an awful lot of people in acute hospital beds all around the country waiting for those specific beds.</p>
          <p eId="para_116"> There is a new rehabilitation strategy and the desire is to move some of the services to the community but we do not have the staff. The programme is expensive and we do not have an allocation for it. Every year the HSE makes a case to the Department for funding and we negotiate with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, but no matter how much money we get for the disability services, we have had years of no funding. Quite frankly, since the economic downturn, there has not been investment in disability services, and not just in neuro-rehab. We have huge waiting lists for residential care and respite care and, unfortunately, it is a case of loaves and fishes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#StephenDonnelly" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Deputy Stephen S. Donnelly<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">I thank Ms Carr. Her answer is that there is not enough money. In this case, moving this gentleman into a stepdown facility out of the NRH, which is obviously a high skill and expensive place for someone to be, would be cheaper. Given any envelope of money, why is it that we are keeping people unnecessarily in a high-cost, high-care environment, and not changing the mix of the money we have to put people in a clinically more suitable situation and provide a cheaper solution? Why is that not happening?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_35">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">Without getting into the specifics of it, the bed he is occupying in the NRH is already funded. It costs extra money to provide the funding for him to go into the community. It is not always cheaper. I do not know the level of that man's needs but he could require 24 hour care at home. This is not cheap but would give him the quality of life that he requires and deserves. It is about having additional funding but it is also about having the additional teams to work on the ground in the various settings around the country. That all takes planning and funding.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#StephenDonnelly" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Deputy Stephen S. Donnelly<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">I thank Ms Carr. I wanted to raise this again because that is the reality. We can have all the plans, the work and the decent gestures we want, but if the reality is that we have a quadriplegic man, fully capable of going back to work and fully capable of leading quite an independent life with the right supports, who was discharged almost a year ago from the NRH, then something is badly broken in terms our spectrum of care for people with disabilities.</p>
          <p eId="para_120"> I have a similar question for the Department of Education and Skills on assessment. There has been a lot of talk about the need for assessment and the need for transition. Certainly in Wicklow, and I imagine in most if not in every other constituency, one of the most frustrating conversations one has as a Deputy when canvassing is to meet the parents of children with disabilities who are waiting for years for assessment.</p>
          <p eId="para_121">I am not even talking about getting the supports; I mean for assessment. I met a mother whose daughter has serious spinal issues who has been waiting a year for an assessment for a wheelchair because the curvature of the wheelchair that she has is wrong. She is in pain and cannot use the wheelchair. She sits on the ground for most of the time. She is not waiting a year for a wheelchair; she is waiting a year for someone to assess the wheelchair requirement. In the meantime the HSE will not fix wheelchairs and throws them into a big skip.</p>
          <p eId="para_122"> I talk to parents who are waiting literally years for speech and language assessment for their children. We all know that early assessment is incredibly invaluable. How is that happening? Is anything being done to get the assessments and the supports in place for young children with various disabilities, be they physical, learning or intellectual disability. It seems that things are moving in the wrong direction and that this is a profoundly stupid, dangerous, damaging and unnecessary thing for us a State to be doing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_37">
          <from> Mr. Jim Mulkerrins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:15:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">There are three separate questions there and I will have to bounce some of this back to Ms Carr because the main provider of assessments is the HSE. However, we have a National Educational Psychological Service. Its function is not to provide assessments but to upskill and support schools and to ensure that they are supporting children within the schools as well as they possibly can. We are conscious of the long delays that have been there for assessments historically and we have been engaging with our colleagues in the Department of Health, the HSE and the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, in a cross-sectoral format on a very regular basis about this. Back as far as 2012, we engaged with the National Disability Authority, NDA, and it was telling us at the time that assessments just for educational supports were costing the equivalent of in excess of 75 whole-time equivalent psychologists across the State. We took the view that that was wasteful because it is better that our therapists and practitioners are providing services rather than assessing for services. We were proactive about this and the committee will be aware that we introduced a new resource teacher allocation model in September 2017, which removed the need for an assessment in order that resources would be provided. In the past, a child had to have an assessed disability before additional teaching hours were provided but that is no longer the case.</p>
          <p eId="para_124"> The special needs assistant, SNA, review I mentioned in my presentation contains similar recommendations. Hopefully, if these recommendations are accepted and implemented by Government in the future, it will no longer be necessary for children to have an assessment of need before they can access SNA-type support. I am conscious that that review also had a number of other recommendations which primarily all blend together to ensure that in future children will get the right support from the right person and at the right time. In order that that would happen the over-reliance of the assessment of need process will be discontinued or rolled down. We know, of course, that children will continue to need assessment for clinical reasons and perhaps to guide the professionals and practitioners in understanding the levels of support and the types of needs that children have.</p>
          <p eId="para_125"> On speech and language therapy, we are very conscious, that while the Department of Education and Skills is not currently the provider of speech and language therapy services, there is a commitment in A Programme for a Partnership Government to develop an in-school approach and language support service to ensure that children can get access when and as they need support. To that end, from this September, in collaboration with our colleagues in the Department of Health and the Department of Children and Youth Affairs, we will roll out a pilot project across CHO 7, involving 76 schools, including a number of special schools, and 76 preschools, where therapy services will be delivered in school in line with the continuum of support service - a high level of support for the higher level of need; a middle level of support for the middle level of need and a whole school approach to children to try to identify and deal with needs as they first arise in order to try to prevent them from getting worse, so to speak.</p>
          <p eId="para_126"> That pilot is being rolled out in on a collaborative basis. We work on a very regular basis with our colleagues in the Department of Health to ensure that the need for clinical governance and clinical support for therapists currently being recruited for this particular pilot will be available. The HSE will do the recruitment process for us and the NCSE will manage the programme for us. This heralds a new era of enhanced co-operation and collaboration between our Departments to ensure that children get access to supports without having to wait years for assessments.</p>
          <p eId="para_127">The National Council for Special Education, NCSE, will manage the programme. This heralds a new era of enhanced co-operation and collaboration between our Departments to ensure children get access to supports without having to wait for years for assessments. I accept this will take some time. The pilot will run from September to the end of the school year and then we will work towards delivering a nationwide project, assuming that the evaluation of the pilot tells us it is positive.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_38">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">Deputy Donnelly mentioned an assessment for a wheelchair. I understand that is done in the primary care setting in the HSE. While a quantum of service is funded, it is only a quantum and I do not know what the situation is in the case the Deputy has raised. I know that primary care does the assessments and, based on funding available, provides the wheelchairs to individuals on a priority basis.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#StephenDonnelly" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Deputy Stephen S. Donnelly<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">It struck me as extraordinary, when I spoke to this mother, that she was waiting for over a year for an assessment. Is the Department aware that we have young girls with curved spines who are no longer able to sit in their own wheelchairs, sitting on the floor, waiting for a year for an assessment for a new wheelchair? Is the Department aware that is the level of the crisis?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_40">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">Not to pass the buck, but I work on the disability side, which is primary care, as I said. If the Deputy wants to give us the details, I can have it looked into.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AliceMaryHiggins" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Senator Alice-Mary Higgins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">I am following up on some of the issues which have been highlighted already, including the huge level of unpaid administrative work. It came across very strongly in the testimonies of the many individuals who have navigated the system. A huge level of unpaid administrative work is undertaken by individuals to access not just equality but their rights and entitlements and to navigate the system. Something that came across very strongly was that the huge level of administrative and bureaucratic work that individuals have to undertake - sometimes in a supported capacity, since they may be lucky enough to have strong advocates, or they may not - seems to begin again at each new chapter in their lives. There is a question of transition points. A key reason we have all these Departments in together is those problems of transition points. I will not ask for all of the points in the comprehensive employment strategy to be discussed. I am sure we are due to receive a report on that. It would have been wonderful if one that was mentioned was ready in time for these hearings since it relates strongly to them. It is priority action 5.1, which focuses on transition points for persons with a disability. While I am a little concerned that the other Departments did not mention it, it is mentioned in the statement from the Department of Education and Skills that it will be published shortly. It will be relevant for us to know when that report on transition points will be coming through. It is key. I expected that it would be the focus of a lot-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">Will we see if there is an answer to that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AliceMaryHiggins" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Senator Alice-Mary Higgins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_133">I will make a couple of points and then there can be general answers. Maybe the witnesses can give that date. Is there a date?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_44">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">It is with the Minister of State with responsibility for equality, which is Deputy Finian McGrath, but it is in his capacity as Minister of State with responsibility for equality.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AliceMaryHiggins" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Senator Alice-Mary Higgins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">Is it expected before the summer recess or do we not know?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_46">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">We do not know.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">For clarity, the report is complete and with the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AliceMaryHiggins" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Senator Alice-Mary Higgins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">Perfect. That was a key question. I will give input regarding a couple of points that really struck me on that issue of transition points from the testimony of others. Special needs assistants were mentioned. People may have had special needs assistance in our higher education institutions or post-primary institutions and then find themselves wishing to transition into employment but the educational supports that they had were tied to their educational chapter. There are people who may have managed to navigate and, for example, receive a degree but in that period immediately afterwards, when it is so important for translating into employment, they are almost entering a brand new system cold, starting the negotiations again and trying to get support again, rather than having a period of overlap which allows them to transition into employment. That was one example. Those transitions are a key concern. I welcome that there is a fast-track for those who may seek to leave disability allowance and return to it. It is positive that that may happen a number of times.</p>
          <p eId="para_139">I have a couple of concerns on the social protection system. One is the fact that people can become invisible in terms of their disability at a number of points. For example, if somebody transitions into full-time employment the fact he or she is a person with disability can become invisible. We have talked about the level of income disregard on medical cards. There are many situations when we talk about making work pay and the cost of disability where people may well need quite extensive medical supports over the course of a lifetime that are not going to go away and are not going to be fundable. We heard from people who felt they had to go back on disability allowance because of that cost and the fear they would lose their entitlement to the medical card and who would have preferred not to be getting disability allowance and the medical card but simply getting the medical card. However, they had to transition back to get both again.</p>
          <p eId="para_140"> The other concern I have is where people get to pension age and they disappear as somebody with a disability in terms of the visibility of that issue. There were a lot of concerns on the question of the invalidity pension. The transition to partial capacity benefit was mentioned. Partial capacity benefit is an interesting one because the recognition of partial capacity is not as well recognised for those on a disability allowance, although they have the disregard. Given that we know some people are working, using the income disregard while on disability allowance, and others are seeking to work, and perhaps Ms Ryan might answer this question, are there quality part-time educational and employment options that recognise that people may be available and seeking work on a part-time basis?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:25:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">Would the Senator like answers to some of those-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AliceMaryHiggins" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Senator Alice-Mary Higgins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:25:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">Yes. I have one last set of questions which I will come to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:25:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">I call Ms Ryan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_52">
          <from> Ms Simonetta Ryan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:25:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">There are a lot of different things going on there. We have the two different schemes - invalidity pension and disability allowance. They are different schemes and have different conditionality. One is based on contributions and the other is means-tested and the payment rates are slightly different. It always becomes complicated if one tries to merge two schemes because it does not lend itself to it. We are doing a lot on the ground with people and are developing our services to engage with people. If the committee would like it, we can talk a little about what we are doing. We recognise also that we have a lot more to do and that is what hopefully will come from the work we have done on the Make Work Pay and the article 5.1 group. Part of that is to look at how one helps people who need more supports and what are the options as one goes forward. All these things, to some extent, have to be iterative, because one has to try different ways of working to see what is going to work.</p>
          <p eId="para_145"> The Senator talked about the full-time or part-time option. As regards part-time, we have the part-time capacity benefit for people on illness pension. That is a good scheme. Given that disability allowance, DA, is different, the way it is dealt with in DA is through the disregards. There is an option for people on DA to work and to still retain quite a lot of benefits for quite a long time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AliceMaryHiggins" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Senator Alice-Mary Higgins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:25:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">I am talking education and part-time options and not simply the entitlement to same. I refer to things like quality part-time educational options. For example, the CE scheme is one of the few schemes that is part-time. Perhaps this is too micro in detail but that is not available to people on certain schemes. The question is about quality part-time options.</p>
          <p eId="para_147"> Another key issue that relates to this is the concern around the invisible, that is, those who have a disability but because disability allowance is means-tested may not be on disability allowance and, moving away from the payments, their access to the educational, the training and the employment supports. That is what I was talking about in terms of there being suitable good quality options. Are they available to people, regardless what payment scheme they are on, and to those who may not be on a payment scheme but who may have a disability?</p>
          <p eId="para_148"> The other witnesses might answer my question on what we heard about the iterative process because there is a real concern here. Disability is one of the issues that has not landed suddenly; it is one of the most known issues. We know it is a long-term fact of society and yet it seems there is a huge reliance on pilot schemes.</p>
          <p eId="para_149">JobPath, for example, scaled up very quickly and yet we have had a litany of excellent practice schemes which seem to have come and gone. WALK PEER was mentioned as was the three-year funding. Is it national? Is it available everywhere? There is the Care project and the Inclusive Learning Project at Maynooth University, about which we heard great things but then the funding stopped. There is also the Career Pathways, a transition to employment scheme in Trinity College. There is a litany of excellent good-practice schemes. However, what seems to happen is that the pilots are put in place but then the scale-up does not happen. I am very concerned about a new project, namely, the pilot project testing the policy approach for a comprehensive supported employment programme. This is just another example, which will be a pilot from 2018 to 2020, and will provide learning for any future scaling of such an approach. How do the Departments plan to move from pilots to national implementation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">I thank the Senator. Who would like to answer?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AliceMaryHiggins" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Senator Alice-Mary Higgins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">I have one tiny final point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">We will come back to the Senator if we have the time. I call Ms Ryan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Ms Simonetta Ryan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">I will try to answer some of those points. On the question of the part-time education options, to be honest I do not have specific answers on that, but we are developing the capacity of our case officers to work with people with a disability. People can come talk in to us about activation and engage with us, whether they are on a scheme or whether they are these invisible people. Part of that may be about awareness and people realising that is something they can do. We have put a lot of work into our case officers. I always accept that we have more to do because this is a complex client group; it is not homogenous. We accept that.</p>
          <p eId="para_154"> Side by side with that we have pilots. There is one running in the midlands at the moment. It is not that we are just doing pilots. We use the 62 Intreo services around the country to provide access for people. However, we have to look at how can we do it better and how we can target particular situations and circumstances, working with our colleagues, whether in health, education or elsewhere. That is where the pilots can help us. They help also people with disabilities and their families to input into what is working and what is not. It is slow and I accept that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AliceMaryHiggins" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Senator Alice-Mary Higgins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">What might be-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">Senator, please. There is quite a bit to do yet. I want to hear the comments from the other witnesses. I will come back to the Senator if I have an opportunity. I call Ms Carr.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_60">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">We work regularly on working groups with our colleagues in a number of Departments on the Make Work Pay and on the comprehensive employment strategy because from the specialist disability service side, we are working with people from a particular cohort. We want to get them into a day services that meet their needs and that are changing and evolving with their needs. Now we have people with disabilities living longer. I appreciate what the Senator said about pilots and that they should not end but sometimes what is required changes. We work collectively on that and the Department of Education and Skills would be involved as well in ensuring that people are trained to meet their needs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">Does Mr. Mulkerrins wish to come in here?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_62">
          <from> Mr. Jim Mulkerrins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">I will pass that on to my colleague, Mr. Phil O'Flaherty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_63">
          <from> Mr. Phil O'Flaherty<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">There are a probably a couple of points to be made. Ms Ryan raised the issue of the role of the Intreo offices. As members are probably aware, there was some major reconfiguration of further education and training and the employment service whereby training, delivered by FÁS in the past, moved to newly-created education and training boards, the former vocational education committees, that also delivered vocational education.</p>
          <p eId="para_161"> There are protocols in place locally with all the Intreo offices and the education and training boards. That is giving Intreo offices a much greater visibility as to the full range of education and training offerings that are out there where previously most of the referrals would have been to the training side because the employment and training side were together in FÁS at one point. That includes quite a lot of part-time provision - for example, the back to education initiative and a range of programmes at various levels, including in areas like literacy, numeracy, digital skills and basic skills.</p>
          <p eId="para_162"> More broadly, in further education, training and, indeed, higher education, there is a major push to increase the range of flexible options available. Members will be aware of the Springboard programme, for example. Springboard was previously heavily pushed towards people who were unemployed, were on jobseeker's assistance or benefit but now it has been opened up much more broadly and provides good options, including for people in employment, which may include people with disability. There has been a considerable push and some funding through the higher education funding mechanisms, through the Higher Education Authority, and also in further education, through SOLAS, on technology-enhanced learning, with blended approaches. That is through both the use of technology in classrooms, which is something that can be very important to people with disabilities, and also online, with blended approaches which deliver greater flexibility. It is reasonable to say that those protocols have been in place for two years for Intreo offices and ourselves.</p>
          <p eId="para_163"> Our Department, SOLAS and the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection regularly meet on a tripartite basis to review how that is working locally. As the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection broadens its focus more clearly beyond people who are unemployed - and some capacity maybe has freed up in Intreo services - our Department also needs to look at how we can support the broader range of clients that are likely to come our way. That is a focus of our discussions too.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BernardJDurkan" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Deputy Bernard J. Durkan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:35:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">My apologies for being absent for quite a long time. I had to attend another meeting. It is very difficult when two meetings are being held at the same time.</p>
          <p eId="para_165"> I welcome our guests. I have a couple of quick comments. Something that has become obvious to me and, I am sure, everybody in public life is that families that are affected by disability spend much of the time waiting for something to happen, waiting for services to kick in or waiting for attention. It has become a burden to them with the anxiety that is attached. Can the Departments do anything to try to eliminate that? For example, why should children with special needs of an acute nature have to wait indefinitely for urgent surgical procedures? These families have to wait a long time and they do not know when an outcome will be forthcoming</p>
          <p eId="para_166"> The burden on families has to be experienced by means having close contact with the families. These people will readily relate the facts. The mother of a teenager who has a serious disability recently informed me that she has been at it for 20 years, day and night and on call all the time. She said that some things are well done and some are not; that sometimes provision was made and sometimes it was not. Certain families have more than one member with a disability and that increases the burden. I would like the service providers to bear that in mind when they refer to waiting.</p>
          <p eId="para_167"> In the context of the disability allowance versus the invalidity pension, the former is insurance-based but there was a tradition whereby a person, a year from coming off a disability allowance, particularly when coming off a domiciliary care allowance, automatically qualified for an invalidity pension. This does not happen any more. That is a huge disadvantage to people who may have a limited income and who may find themselves in a difficult position. Any extra money is a huge advantage to them.</p>
          <p eId="para_168">That needs to be looked at again.</p>
          <p eId="para_169"> This is important and I do not want an answer to it. It is a comment. Some people can overcome disability to a huge extent, whether a physical disability or a sensory disability. Others cannot. Others may find the disability so overpowering, whether inherited or a disability following an accident, that they find themselves at a huge physical and psychological disadvantage and feel unable to cope, and feel very pressurised, as I saw at a recent case where it was suggested that an amputee should seek employment. It was an appalling decision. I cannot understand how an official or anybody could stand over a decision like that. The simple reason was the unfortunate person was at a very severe physical disadvantage to start with and, to overcome that physical disability mentally, in itself, was a huge issue for him. To suggest to the person concerned that he should be looking for a job and there was no reason he should not get a job is crazy.</p>
          <p eId="para_170"> The Intreo people have been referred to. The jury is still out on that for me. They have done some interesting and useful work but they have also gone off on a tangent on some occasions where a little more thought could have gone into what eventually became a decision and a burden on the people affected by that decision. I am not asking for answers. I am making a comment. I have serious concerns about the things I have mentioned because I have daily contact with people who are affected in that way.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">I will come back to the Deputy in a moment. I want to be fair to the witnesses we had here a couple of weeks ago. I will make a couple of comments and they can be referred to specifically. I reflected on it before I came in. Something the witnesses all said collectively was that they felt lucky about where they have got to. Despite all the programmes and policies we have in place, they all felt lucky to have worked through the system and for their entitlements. They all came by different pathways but there was an element of luck. That was the way they felt about it and, in that way, there is something wrong with the system in that there are not clearer, more identifiable pathways onto which those people or their advocates can see them. They all referred to it as luck. I was very taken with it. The witnesses have quite rightly explained a significant range of programmes that are available but the people who are to avail of them do not see it as easily as that. Information and education are issues.</p>
          <p eId="para_172"> I will address a couple of specifics that the individuals referred to, in no particular order. One lady spoke about what she was able to do because she had a personal assistant. She was a little bit older and had the personal assistant for some time, but she made the point that if she was a younger person, she would not have access in the same way that she does. She recognised the old system versus the new system and was quite specific in it. We had one person who spoke about special needs assistants and their support in primary, secondary and third level. There was no continuity of support. There was a significant drop-off in second level and they were quite impressed with the level of support they got in third level.</p>
          <p eId="para_173"> We heard about the special schools and the fact that, in many of them, there is no pathway either to do the leaving certificate or applied leaving certificate, and what that means for those people in the future. Mr. Mulkerrins alluded to the fact that careers guidance in those special schools is not done in the normal way, as it would be done in a regular school. These were highlighted. Everyone expressed concern about the loss of the medical card or the travel pass. They all said to us in different ways that, while they might have a job, they still have their disability and the associated costs that go with it.</p>
          <p eId="para_174">While they might have a job, the people concerned still have disabilities and face associated costs. We need to look at more than just means testing. One of the delegates is visually impaired. Some of the equipment covered by the medical card scheme is relatively expensive and she faced a huge personal burden. When the transition is considered in the round, people with disabilities face additional costs in getting to work. There is a feeling of nervousness and vulnerability in losing the medical card and free travel. </p>
          <p eId="para_175"> There was much talk about the disability allowance and illness benefit. I understand there are approximately 2,500 in receipt of partial capacity benefit. It was rightly set out that the person was assessed. My experience of partial capacity benefit is that many persons who are availing of it and have re-entered the workforce do not have a regular weekly salary because many do not work full time. The partial capacity benefit does not recognise whether a person has worked in a given week. Such persons are on a reduced payment, in comparison to the previous benefit of which they availed. We should look at the benefit specifically for those who are beginning to go back to work where the nature of the work is part time or casual or for a few hours a week. That is the stepping stone for them, but partial capacity benefit is only for a set amount, irrespective of what a person earns in a given week. I suggest a system be put in place to provides the full benefit if a person has not worked in a given week for a specified period of time. For many, it is a transition. </p>
          <p eId="para_176"> My colleagues will speak briefly about this issue, but they are the main points. I am taken by the reports and the actions proposed for the future, but I emphasise that the delegates who were here a couple of weeks ago all said they were lucky. They had all transitioned and were making progress in their lives. However, there was a feeling there was no clear stepping stone or that another person could follow exactly what they had done. There was a feeling those who had transitioned had met the right person at the right time or had been on the right programme at the right time. I was taken when I heard the delegates say that they had got lucky.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AliceMaryHiggins" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Senator Alice-Mary Higgins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:45:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_177">I was struck by what was said about technology in assisted learning. Perhaps the delegates might tell us more about the reasonable accommodation aspect that was mentioned, either now or in writing later. There were some strong recommendations for an overhaul in that area, particularly in the use of technology and in terms of how important it is. This applies not only to the provision of reasonable accommodation for those in work but also to the provision of reasonable accommodation in applying for work. One of the people who spoke mentioned the obstacles faced in merely applying for work. The update on that aspect was important.</p>
          <p eId="para_178"> In terms of SNAs and personal assistants, the question of autonomy and choice arose, as well as questions about the hours and quality of support available. Personalised budgets were discussed, as was the idea of providing a role for the individual in question in choosing the person who would be his or her personal assistant.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_67">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy Fiona O'Loughlin)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:45:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">I sincerely apologise for not being here earlier. I will look back at the contributions made. I have had the opportunity to read the reports. What I have read is very informative, but the lived experience of the people who have appeared in front of the committee is key. There are programmes, but access and information are the big problems. I mentioned during the last session that we needed representatives of possible and potential employers at a meeting such as this because I believe we need to work with prospective employers on perceived barriers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:45:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">I will afford the delegates an opportunity to make some concluding remarks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_69">
          <from> Ms Simonetta Ryan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">I note from the comments of the Chair that people feel lucky. It has been very helpful for us to read the testimonies of the people who have appeared before the committee. The feeling is that there should be access and information for those people now and in the future so that they are not relying on luck. That is the direction in which we are going. I do not believe we can answer Senator Higgins today on her point about employment and the reviews of reasonable accommodation, so we will revert to her in writing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">Will the witness discuss the partial capacity benefit question?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_71">
          <from> Ms Simonetta Ryan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">I will have to revert to the committee on that point as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_72">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">On the medical card issue that was raised, I am confident that it will be sorted out in the next couple of months and that the HSE and the Department will come to an agreement on what the disregard will be raised to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">To clarify, the issue in terms of the disregard is that there was a range for the other payments. I believe the problem is in trying to work out the level of disregard. Is that the technical issue that is holding it up?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">It is at €120 at the minute, and the level it can be raised to is being considered.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_75">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">That is the case in the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, but it can vary between €120 and €350.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_76">
          <from> Ms Patsy Carr<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">That is the problem that arises where a medical card is given out for a family. The level of the disregard can have knock-on consequences for a family. We do not want anyone to lose out as a result of something that is intended to improve matters for someone else. This matter needs to be investigated further, but I am confident that it is going to happen in the next couple of months.</p>
          <p eId="para_189"> We all agree with Deputy Durkan on his point about families waiting for services and assessments for whom this is particularly traumatic, especially those with children with special needs who are then going for acute services. I was only made aware recently that there are disability liaison nurses in the major acute hospitals, so those processes for a child with a disability requiring acute services can be streamlined. That is a positive.</p>
          <p eId="para_190"> No one disputes the huge burden families face. This year, as part of the Estimates for 2018, the Government allowed an extra €10 million to provide extra respite services. It is a drop in the ocean, but it helps provide an extra respite house in each community healthcare organisation, CHO, area. This is having a positive impact throughout the country, and we would hope to build on that next year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_77">
          <from> Mr. Jim Mulkerrins<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">I will make three points, if I may. The first is a general point that I imagine reflects all of our views. The Department of Education and Skills accepts that while it has provision and policies for support in place, individual experiences may not necessarily reflect that. We are aware that individual experiences are less than satisfactory, and it makes it all the more important that we have opportunities to come to committees to hear about individual experiences. We also hear about such experiences through parliamentary questions and representations as well. We are very conscious of it, and it affords us an opportunity to try to modify our arrangements to make the individual experiences better.</p>
          <p eId="para_192"> On the second point, I read some of the presentations that were made at earlier meetings about special needs assistants, SNAs, the experiences of one particular person at primary, secondary and third level, and the drop-off in the service that person experienced at second level. I was somewhat surprised by that individual example, because if I recall the case correctly the drop-off occurred during leaving certificate year. I was surprised to hear that because we operate a policy, between ourselves and the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, that when an SNA allocation is reviewed, unless there was absolute clarity that the individual need had diminished substantially, there would be no removal of that level of support in the final year. I suspect that was an individual example of something falling through the gaps.</p>
          <p eId="para_193"> I am not sure when this happened, but I would make the point that between 2001 and 2010, the number of SNAs in the system grew by approximately 1,000 every year. There was a period of cooling off between 2010 and 2013, largely because of the economic downturn, I suspect. However, we continued to make additional provision. By the end of this year there will be 15,000 SNAs in the system. A person attending school ten years ago may not have had the same level of access to SNA support as one would get now. We recognise that the levels of need have not changed greatly in the intervening years. The levels of assessed understanding of what those needs are has changed very substantially.</p>
          <p eId="para_194">All of those needs existed in pupil populations ten, 20 and 30 years ago. We just were not supporting them the way we should have done, or in the way we now understand we needed to do. </p>
          <p eId="para_195"> Two points were raised about special schools, the first was about pathways to leaving certificate and applied leaving certificate. The committee knows that we have introduced levels 1 and 2 and there have been significant improvements in terms of accreditation for pupils. It is important that students' performance and abilities are recognised. In respect of the leaving certificate and applied leaving certificate there is a discussion between us and the National Council for Special Education which takes the lead in providing us with policy advice, having conducted research and consultation in the sector, about how we need to consider provision for special schools in the future. There is a discussion about getting the balance right. We recognise that there will always be children who will require the supports of special schools but who will have the capacity to go on and do leaving cert and applied leaving cert. That, unfortunately, is not the case for the majority. The issue is what the appropriate provision would be for pupils who are attending special schools but have aspirations to go on and do leaving cert applied and the ordinary leaving cert. It is a matter of getting the balance between where provision should be made, whether children should be provided with greater levels of access, even part-time, perhaps in the mainstream or access to a special class with transition to mainstream for appropriate subjects and whether the needs are such that they require special schools. That is a challenge we face and we hope to be able to improve our consideration of that over the coming year. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCurranFF" as="#Co-Chairman" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Co-Chairman (Deputy John Curran)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T13:55:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_196">That concludes today's meeting. On behalf of the committee I thank Mr. Harty, Ms Ryan, Mr. Bohan, Ms Carr, Mr. O'Connor, Mr. Mulkerrins and Mr. O'Flaherty for their attendance today, their presentations, opening statements and responses to the questions asked. One or two pieces of correspondence will flow from today's meeting and we look forward to receiving those.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_13"> The joint committee adjourned at 1.55 p.m. until 4 p.m. on Tuesday, 12 June 2018.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_14">This is the attendance list for the second meeting of the joint committee at 4 p.m. on 12 June 2018.</summary>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <p eId="para_197">Deputy Thomas ByrneDeputy Kathleen FunchionDeputy Catherine MartinDeputy Hildegarde NaughtonDeputy Jan O'Sullivan </p>
            </td>
            <td>
              <p eId="para_198">Senator Maria ByrneSenator Paul Daly* </p>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <summary eId="sum_15">* In éagmais / In the absence of Senator Robbie Gallagher.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_16">I láthair / In attendance: Deputy Paul Murphy.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_17"> Teachta / Deputy Fiona O'Loughlin sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Business of Joint Committee<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_79">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">We did not have a quorum at 3.30 p.m. so commence now in public session. I remind members to turn off their mobile phones when attending committee meetings.</p>
          <p eId="para_200"> I thank Senator Paul Daly for attending as a substitute for Senator Robbie Gallagher. Apologies have been received from Senators Robbie Gallagher, Paul Gavan and Lynn Ruane.</p>
          <p eId="para_201"> I suggest we not deal with private session matters now but go straight into public session in deference to our witnesses, who, in fairness, have given of their time to be here and have been waiting 40 minutes to come in. I will suspend the meeting for two minutes to allow them to take their seats.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_18">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 4.11 p.m. and resumed at 4.14 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_5">
        <heading>Review of Relationships and Sexuality Education: Discussion (Resumed)<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:10:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_80">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">As I mentioned earlier, we will skip Nos. 1 to 4, inclusive, in deference to those who have been waiting for us. I ask members to stay behind when we have finished with our witnesses to take them. I apologise to the the witnesses for having delayed them. I have been Chairman of this committee for only two years but I believe this rarely happens, and we hope it will not happen again. We normally have good attendance at the committee. I thank the members who attended and Senator Paul Daly for stepping in.</p>
          <p eId="para_203"> The purpose of this part of the meeting is to resume the committee's review of relationships and sexuality education, RSE. This is the third of three sessions. We are gathering evidence on RSE in Ireland. We have gathered compelling evidence regarding what is happening and not happening in our education system in this regard, acknowledging that it has been 20 years since a programme was put in place and, with the advent of social media, etc., that many concerns are not being addressed. There is also a lack of consistency in how RSE is taught in our schools and at third level. We are also cognisant that the responsibility should not just fall on schools or educational organisations, and there is also a responsibility on parents and communities. It is a question of how we can all work together and make recommendations in this regard. We want to improve the curriculum to give our young people the skills they need, particularly in the areas of consent and contraception.</p>
          <p eId="para_204"> Our witnesses will provide a good variety of opinions, views and experience that will certainly help to influence the report we intend to compile and issue after all these engagements. I welcome Dr. Clíona Saidléar, executive director of Rape Crisis Network Ireland; Mr. Niall Behan, chief executive of the Irish Family Planning Association; Ms Jane Donnelly, human rights officer, Atheist Ireland; Dr. Aoife Neary, lecturer in sociology of education at University of Limerick, UL; Dr. Debbie Ging, associate professor of media studies at Dublin City University, DCU; Dr. Aidan Seery, senior tutor with the school of education at Trinity College Dublin; Ms Sarah Haslam, who is the training, learning and development manager with Foróige; and Ms Orla McGowan, programme manager for education, HSE. I acknowledge that Mr. Michael Nugent, Ms Avril Hickey and Ms Helen Deely are in the Public Gallery.</p>
          <p eId="para_205"> The format of this part of the meeting is that I will invite the witnesses to make brief opening statements, three minutes maximum, which will be followed by an engagement with the members of the committee. As we have a significant number of witnesses, which is important in their sharing the different views and experience they have, I ask them to respect the three-minute rule in so far as possible.</p>
          <p eId="para_206"> I draw the attention of the witnesses to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, they are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to this committee. However, if they are directed by the Chair to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to do so, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence. I must direct them also that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given, and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable. I also advise them that the opening statements they make to the committee may be available on the committee's website after this meeting, as will the submissions they kindly forwarded.</p>
          <p eId="para_207"> I remind members of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_208"> I call Dr. Clíona Saidléar to make her opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_81">
          <from> Dr. Clíona Saidléar<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">I thank the Chairman and members of the committee. We are delighted to be here. We have been engaged on this issue for some time and we have been convinced that it needs Government-level engagement and intervention. Rape Crisis Network Ireland is a specialist information and resource centre on sexual violence. We are owned and governed by our member rape crisis centres and we develop policies, responses, reactions and strategies in this area.</p>
          <p eId="para_210"> The focus on sexual health education is often drawn to this issue based on public debate arising out of sexual violence crimes and our sense that we could do more to prevent them. We rightly ask questions about the messages about sex and sexual relationships to which our children are exposed in our culture and the messages they receive from the sources we hope set standards of behaviour that are safe, supportive and empowering, such as from parents, schools and trusted authorities.</p>
          <p eId="para_211">The questions include how should we support everyday respectful, safe and healthy sexual behaviour and whether we have fully engaged our institutions and structures to ensure our children and young people share in and contribute to evolving positive values on sexual behaviour and expectations? Curriculum content is one aspect to address, but it is vital we understand that excellence here will be ineffective in the absence of a holistic response which ensures the institutional context and care responses also support positive sexually healthy relationships. I really want to focus on matters relating to that area but I am also happy to talk about curriculum content.</p>
          <p eId="para_212"> Historically the State has been resistant and ambiguous towards sexual autonomy and liberation. This has resulted in silences, paralysis and gaps, not least in sexual education in the schools system. We suggest that the ambiguity with which we have treated sex education has been baked into our institutions and bureaucratic structures and it is our view that those need to be addressed if we are to serve our children adequately in this matter. Rather than one location that holds the strategic lead on this matter there are currently four Departments and at least six strategies and policies that have a role in shaping sexual health education. Each of these strategies has a role in ensuring children and young people have access to the education and supports they need to prepare them to make healthy decisions about their sex lives. It is doubtful to us that there is any one statutory location that has the full picture or oversight in the area of sexual health education, which risks leaving the Department of Education and Skills with a lack of insight into the capacities and resources it has to hand and clarity of objective in curriculum and policy development and implementation. For example members may find it surprising to hear that the relationship and sexuality education, RSE is under review at the moment. Rape Crisis Network Ireland, RCNI, submitted seven modules to the RSE review in 2015. However, this is not happening within the Department of Education and Skills and the National Council for Curriculum and Advancement, NCAA. Instead, it is happening in the HSE under the crisis pregnancy programme, within the B4UDecide programme. The HSE, of course, is working in partnership with the Department of Education and Skills. </p>
          <p eId="para_213"> We would bring to members' attention another difficulty in the multitude of overseeing bodies. When looking across the national strategies which the Department of Education and Skills is subject to in various manners it is clear that actions in the area of sexual health education consent, harm and violence prevention use the word "prevention" to mean different things. It has become standardised internationally to differentiate between primary and secondary prevention, not least because the two require very different capacities and activities. Primary prevention is a whole of population approach that seeks, through generalised intervention, to stop the issue from arising in the first place. Secondary intervention seeks to respond to harm, to identify it early and respond. This distinction is not consistently embedded across Government activities in this area. It is our experience that these failures to distinguish uniformly across Government creates gaps and inefficiencies at best and actions that nullify the effectiveness of each other at worst. An example is the Department of Education and Skills's action plan on bullying, which establishes whole-of-school guidance on bullying prevention, that is, primary prevention. It is an excellent resource but it seems to have abandoned addressing sexual harassment, although it continued to address cybersexual harassment, on the basis that sexual crime is dealt with by Children First. However, Children First is almost entirely about secondary prevention activities, not about primary prevention. This leaves schools with no national primary prevention action plan outside of curriculum content regarding sexual harassment, notwithstanding some excellent generalised whole-of-school school ethos and values programmes. Instead, we find ourselves waiting for children to be at risk of harm before we intervene under Children First. </p>
          <p eId="para_214"> Clarity and agreement at all policy levels as to what level of prevention they are engaging in is essential. We are asking for a joined-up approach. We need a national strategy. Failing that, consideration should be given to a sort of national review of the policy landscape in this area. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_82">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">I ask that everyone present ensures that his or her phone is turned to flight mode or turned off, because they interfere with the recording and cause difficulty for the parliamentary reporters.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_83">
          <from> Mr. Niall Behan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">I thank the committee for the opportunity to address it this afternoon. The Irish Family Planning Association, IFPA, welcomes the review of relationship and sexuality education undertaken by the joint committee. The IFPA is probably best known for its medical clinics and counselling centres but over many years we have been delivering sexuality education to young people, parents, teachers, youth workers and carers, among other groups. We currently provide a range of programmes, mainly to parenting groups through our Speakeasy programme, which is funded by the crisis pregnancy programme of the HSE. The other programmes we have run have generally been funded through once-off initiatives. They have been short-term projects with which we have been able to do some innovative things but we have always faced difficulties in our attempts to mainstream those projects. We have learned a lot from those projects.</p>
          <p eId="para_217"> As a reproductive healthcare provider we see in our clinics and counselling centres the impact of poor quality sexuality education at first hand. We see it every day. We see it in our pregnancy counselling centres with unintended pregnancies, in our clinics with sexually transmitted infections, and in our training workshops in the lack of understanding of the issues involved. The profound gender inequality present in the issues we see really sticks out for us. Women and girls largely bear the burden of inadequate sexuality education and are exposed to some of the risks I have mentioned already. For these reasons we are deeply concerned about the public health impact of inadequate, inconsistent and poor quality sexuality education, particularly in schools in Ireland. </p>
          <p eId="para_218"> As a reproductive healthcare providers we see in our clinics and counselling centres the impact of poor quality sexuality education first hand. We see it every day in our pregnancy counselling centres with unintended pregnancies, in our clinics with sexually transmitted infections, and in our training workshops with a lack of understanding of the issues involved. The profound gender inequality in the issues we see really sticks out for us. Women and girls largely bear the burden of inadequate sexuality education, and are exposed to some of the risks I have mentioned already. For these reasons we are deeply concerned about the public health impact of inadequate, inconsistent and poor quality sexuality education, particularly in schools in Ireland. </p>
          <p eId="para_219"> We have identified four areas for the committee that we believe should be focused on. The first area is the RSE curriculum and the need to broaden it. There seems to be a consensus that high-quality, comprehensive sexuality education facilitates the development of accurate and age-appropriate knowledge and attitudes and promotes positive values. It is seen as a good thing. It respects human rights, gender equality and diversity, and provides an important opportunity to reach young people with accurate information before they become sexually active, as well as offering a structured environment in which to learn. Real education only really happens if it is genuinely comprehensive, and we have some concerns that the RSE programme is not genuinely comprehensive. We believe the content of the RSE curriculum must be revised to reflect international best practice, particularly in terms of contraceptive use, sexually transmitted infections, information around abortion, sexuality orientation, pornography, consent, psycho-sexual issues and gender equality. </p>
          <p eId="para_220"> The second area that could be focused on is the status of sexuality education. It is very low at the moment; it does not have the status other subjects have. In many schools it is not a priority. Too often we see RSE as a subject to be left to the newest member of staff, and is usually squeezed in at the end of the school year. For some schools it is a box-ticking exercise, while for others it really is delivered properly. We believe there is a need for specialist knowledge and skills in RSE for teachers. The reason for its low status is that it is not considered as a criterion for recruitment or promotion. Many teachers would avoid the subject if possible. Teachers have already spoken about the discomfort they experience around the teaching of RSE. </p>
          <p eId="para_221"> The third area that could be improved is around capacity building for teachers and parents. Finally, we believe the Department of Education and Skills must take the lead in making sure that the RSE programme is monitored and evaluated properly and that quality assurance is integrated into the structures. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_84">
          <from> Ms Jane Donnelly<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">I thank the members of the committee for asking me to speak today. I want to make four main recommendations on behalf of Atheist Ireland. Our first recommendation is that the recent referendum changes everything. As legislators, members can no longer assume that even most Roman Catholic parents want Catholic sex education for their children. Also, even if most parents in a particular area wanted Catholic sex education in the only local publicly funded school, that is still not a reason to deny the rights of the rest of the school community to objective sex education. We have moved beyond the time for fine-tuning the religious discrimination and privilege in our schools. We now need to move towards a secular, human rights-based school system that treats everybody equally.</p>
          <p eId="para_223"> Our second recommendation is that Atheist Ireland supports: mandatory provision of sexual and reproductive health education for adolescent girls and boys, as recommended by the UN Committee on the Rights of the Child in 2016; a single consistent curriculum for relationships and sexuality education across all schools, as recommended by the Ombudsman for Children in 2016; and scientifically objective, standardised, age-appropriate education on sexual and reproductive health and rights, as recommended by the UN Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women in 2017. The Minister for Education and Skills recently acknowledged in the Dáil that young people have the right to get such factual information about sexual matters.</p>
          <p eId="para_224"> Our third recommendation is that having factual content is not enough, if that content is delivered through the religious ethos of a school patron body. The content must be delivered in an objective, critical and pluralistic manner that avoids indoctrination outside of optional religion classes, as recommended by the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission in 2015, while ensuring a neutral studying environment, including in denominational schools outside of optional religious instruction classes, as raised with Ireland by the UN Human Rights Committee in 2014.</p>
          <p eId="para_225"> To do this the law will need to be amended because the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment has no legal power over how the curriculum is delivered by school patron bodies with their own religious ethos. We ask the Oireachtas to amend sections 9(<i>d</i>), 15(2)(<i>b</i>) and 30(2)(<i>b</i>) of the Education Act, which have been identified as problems by the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment in 2017.</p>
          <p eId="para_226"> Our fourth recommendation is that Atheist Ireland supports Solidarity’s Provision of Objective Sex Education Bill, which broadly proposes the approach that we recommend. Our written submission includes more details and I am happy to answer any questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_85">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">I call Dr. Aoife Neary, associate professor of media studies at DCU.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_86">
          <from> Dr. Aoife Neary<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">I am a lecturer in sociology of education at the University of Limerick.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_87">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_229">I beg your pardon. I read out the details for Dr. Ging.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_88">
          <from> Dr. Aoife Neary<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">I am grateful for the opportunity to appear before the committee. For almost a decade, I have been doing research in the area of gender and sexuality in education, funded by several awards from the Irish Research Council. The following is a summary of the changes I proposed in my written submission related to RSE content, teaching methods and structures.</p>
          <p eId="para_231"> On content changes, first, there an urgent need for comprehensive RSE that responds to the lived realities of children and young people’s lives – what Renold and McGeeney call a "living curriculum" that assesses and meets the needs of children and young people at that stage in their lives. Second, there is a necessity to uncover the deep silences that have surrounded lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender identities in RSE. Third, I propose a move from sexuality as isolated and individualised towards critical consideration of sexuality as intersectional and caught up in broader power relations and cultural norms.</p>
          <p eId="para_232"> I propose the following changes to teaching methods. First, we need to move from the overemphasis on risk to creating safe and ethical teaching and learning spaces that facilitate open and frank dialogue among children, parents and school staff. Second, I propose that children and young people be more heavily involved in the co-construction of RSE. Creative, arts-based methods have huge potential here. Third, I suggest a critical approach to RSE that would avoid assumptions about young people or their lives, avoid tokenistic inclusion and be at peace with not having all the answers in advance.</p>
          <p eId="para_233"> Finally, the structural changes I propose are as follows. First, we must take account of how fears around childhood innocence act as a barrier in ways that do not account for the capabilities of children or the wants of parents. To be effective, comprehensive RSE must begin in early years, from as young as three, in partnership with parents.</p>
          <p eId="para_234"> Second, we know that many teachers and principals lack knowledge about and are uncomfortable with RSE. Therefore, a comprehensive system of in-service training as well as new RSE specialist pathways in initial teacher education will be crucial here.</p>
          <p eId="para_235"> Third, uncertainties around religious ethos continue to constrain RSE. There is an urgent need for clarity on how religious-run primary and post-primary schools can meet the RSE needs of all children equally.</p>
          <p eId="para_236"> Fourth, there is a necessity to ensure that there is strong RSE leadership in schools to steer a whole-school, spiral, sustained and meaningful approach to RSE in partnership with relevant local organisations.</p>
          <p eId="para_237"> Finally, on an ongoing basis, RSE should be informed, supported and evaluated by an RSE research, practice and education network that includes representation from key education stakeholders and expertise spanning the various topics encompassed by RSE.</p>
          <p eId="para_238"> I suggest that the recent developments in RSE in Wales and the recommendations made by the expert panel outlined in Renold and McGeeney’s 2017 report should serve as an exemplary signpost for changes to RSE in Ireland. Many of their recommendations are echoed across my written submission.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_89">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">I am sure UL would never have forgiven us if we had transferred Dr. Neary to DCU by mistake. I now call Dr. Ging, who is associate professor of media studies at DCU.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_90">
          <from> Dr. Debbie Ging<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">I am grateful for the opportunity to speak here today. I am also a member of the National Anti-Bullying Research and Resource Centre and of the Institute for Future Media and Journalism, both based at DCU. My research is primarily concerned with issues relating to gender, sexuality and social media. I am particularly interested in the topic of sex and sexuality education as it relates to the Internet and social media, as well as pornography.</p>
          <p eId="para_241"> I was a co-investigator on the Government-commissioned report on the sexualisation and commercialisation of children in Ireland and principal investigator on a recent study about LGBT inclusion in post-primary schools.</p>
          <p eId="para_242"> I will give a summary of my written submission. I draw on existing research and literature in Ireland and elsewhere to identify the key problems have been identified with the Irish RSE curriculum and its delivery. These are as follows. The programme focuses largely on the avoidance of pregnancy and STIs. The programme constructs heterosexual intercourse as the primary definition of sex. The programme is not inclusive of LGBTQ students’ experiences and sexual practices. The programme does not deal sufficiently with consent, although the senior cycle materials do contain a very good section on consent that was certainly progressive for its time. The programme does not explicitly acknowledge sexism and inequality. The programme does not deal with the role of the Internet, social media, mobile phones or pornography. The programme does not start with young people’s lived experiences. As noted by Maycock, Kitching and Morgan in their 2007 review, significant problems have been observed with the delivery of the programme.</p>
          <p eId="para_243"> This last problem is the most significant and the one that presents the biggest challenge to improving RSE in our schools, not just in terms of time and expense but also in terms of impressing upon school boards of management that comprehensive RSE is a human right and not something that can be selectively addressed.</p>
          <p eId="para_244"> The international literature recommends that an overall shift in focus is required toward a rights and gender equality-based, inclusive, holistic, creative, empowering and protective RSE curriculum. This again draws from Renold and McGeeney's research and recommendations in Wales. This should be underpinned by key principles of sexual literacy and sexual citizenship. This is of crucial importance, particularly in the digital context, because it shifts the emphasis away from risk, shame and self-censorship to rights, responsibility and self-empowerment.</p>
          <p eId="para_245"> The 2017 European Network of Ombudspersons for Children position statement on comprehensive relationship and sexuality education, states that all children and young people have the right to high-quality, holistic and inclusive education about sexuality and relationships. A recent synthesis and review of international research on the views of children and young people suggests that high-quality RSE starts early; is adaptable and needs-led; offers a spiral curriculum; collaborates with external providers; is of sufficient duration; is engaging and participatory; and creates a safe, respectful and confidential learning environment.</p>
          <p eId="para_246">To this end, I have suggested that the Irish relationship and sexuality education, RSE, programme should consider adapting the core principles underpinning the recent recommendations made on the future of the sex and relationships education curriculum in Wales. These are rights and gender equity; creative and curious; empowering and transformative; experience-near and co-produced; holistic; inclusive; protective and preventative. My more specific recommendations are for an RSE programme that moves beyond abstinence and pregnancy prevention to embrace issues of consent, negotiation and the dynamic, evolving nature of sexuality. This summarises the points I made in my written submission and I am happy to expand on them and respond to questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_91">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">I thank Dr. Ging. I invite Dr. Aidan Seery, senior tutor in the school of education, Trinity College Dublin.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_92">
          <from> Dr. Aidan Seery<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">For the purposes of clarity, I am the senior tutor in Trinity College Dublin. There is no senior tutor in the school of education.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_93">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">I beg Dr. Seery's pardon. I had that wrong.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_94">
          <from> Dr. Aidan Seery<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">I thank the Chairman and the committee members for the invitation to address the committee today. I am appearing in the place of Ms Patricia Murphy who presented the proposals to the committee. Ms Murphy is currently out of the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_251"> By way of introduction and some explanation of my own credentials, I am the college representative in the partnership project with TCD students' union on sexual consent workshops that have run for the past two years in TCD. I have chaired the steering group for the project since its inception. I have no specific content knowledge but I have, at least, some background.</p>
          <p eId="para_252"> The committee has received a submission from Ms Murphy on the provision of sexual consent workshops and training for personnel in higher education institutions. This proposal is based on our experiences of conducting workshops for the past two years in Trinity College Dublin and, more specifically, in the college accommodation facility of Trinity Hall in Dartry, which houses approximately 1,000 new college entrants each year.</p>
          <p eId="para_253"> As a result of our experiences, the outcome of the immediate evaluation of students and facilitators involved in the project and the institutional reflection and assessment over the past two years, we believe we have gained sufficient knowledge to be useful to the committee in its deliberations and add to the evidential basis for the proposals it will make.</p>
          <p eId="para_254"> In summary, the proposal envisages that annual sexual consent workshops be provided for identified groups in all colleges in the State, with supplementary online materials and videos available for whole college communities. The proposal also suggests that bystander training workshops be provided on how to intervene safely when non-consensual activity is being observed. The proposal envisages that first responder training be provided for specific identified individuals who are likely to be the first persons contacted about instances of non-consensual sexual activities, for example, tutors, students' union representatives, college societies, club presidents and officials.</p>
          <p eId="para_255"> That is a summary of the proposals and I will be pleased to discuss any further points.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_95">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">I thank Dr. Seery. I invite Ms Sarah Haslam who is the training, learning and development manager with Foróige.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_96">
          <from> Ms Sarah Haslam<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">I thank the committee for giving me this opportunity to present on behalf of Foróige on our work in the area of relationships and sexuality education. Non-formal education provided by youth work organisations is distinct from formal education but is complementary to it. We believe youth work in general, especially Foróige, can offer the education system decades of expertise in enabling and equipping young people to develop the skills, confidence and knowledge to develop healthy relationships. It can also offer a comprehensive evidence based relationships and sexuality programme, namely, Foróige’s REAL U programme, which could be delivered in schools through an existing and ever growing network of skilled and trained facilitators.</p>
          <p eId="para_258"> The multitude of strategies, policies and initiatives in recent decades has resulted in a sense of confusion, with Government, schools and many community and voluntary organisations unsure of the best way to meet the needs of our young people to best support them to develop healthy and positive relationships in their lives. This lack of clarity, combined with our extensive experience in non-formal education and feedback from young people about their dissatisfaction with sex education in schools, were the reasons we identified the need to develop this comprehensive programme.</p>
          <p eId="para_259"> The initial design of the REAL U programme was conducted by Foróige’s best practice unit in 2012. The curriculum design process started with an extensive review of national policy and strategy, and of best practice and what works nationally and internationally. Foróige liaised with the expertise of organisations such as the HSE crisis pregnancy programme, the Rape Crisis Network Ireland, BeLonG To and the Marie Keating Foundation to ensure the programme meets the wide-ranging needs of young people, and to ensure it provides a comprehensive and holistic approach to RSE.</p>
          <p eId="para_260"> The REAL U programme is more than just a sex education programme. It is a personal development programme that equips young people with the skills, knowledge and confidence to develop healthy relationships, make responsible decisions on their sexual health and ultimately delay the onset of early sexual activity. The programme is holistic in its approach to RSE and includes modules on gender and sexuality; emotional well-being; understanding boundaries; contraception and sexually transmitted infections, including a practical condom demonstration on correct use; sexual violence and the law; deciphering media messages; and understanding pornography.</p>
          <p eId="para_261"> In 2014, the programme underwent an extensive evaluation by the UNESCO Child and Family Research Centre, National University of Ireland, Galway. Among the key findings from the evaluation were that the programme was effective in engaging young people, responding to their needs and impacting on their knowledge and attitudes in the area of RSE. Young people said they would recommend this programme to other young people because they felt the programme was relevant, insightful and they felt better informed and more aware of the consequences of their actions. The research also identified statistically significant effects on young people's attitude to members of the LGBTI+ community, and 100% of those who trained in facilitating the programme said it was effective in meeting its outcomes.</p>
          <p eId="para_262"> With the support of the HSE crisis pregnancy programme, to date Foróige has trained more than 1,100 professionals from organisations and disciplines, including youth organisations, the HSE, ISPCC, the school completion programme, Tusla, residential care centres, family resource centres and those who work with young people and adults with intellectual disabilities. These trained facilitators of the REAL U programme run the programme with young people and service users nationwide and evaluations of the facilitator training and the programme have been consistently overwhelmingly positive. Foróige’s REAL U programme has been called the gold standard in RSE in Ireland. As such, we currently cannot meet demand for the REAL U facilitator training and the waiting list stands at more than 200.</p>
          <p eId="para_263"> We believe the REAL U programme meets the needs of modern Irish young people. It has been extensively and rigorously tested, evaluated and proven to do so. If we wait for a new programme to be written and teachers to be recruited and trained, we will fail a large number of young people by further delaying their needs being met. In recent months, we received a tenfold increase in the number of school teachers contacting us about the programme. We currently cannot meet this need. The REAL U programme offers everything the Government announced it wishes to have as part of the reform of the RSE curriculum. The programme is ready to go and ready to be rolled out in schools. While it has been written for young people rather than schools, we are willing to meet the Department of Education and Skills to discuss how the programme can be adapted for the school context. We recommend that the Government invest in large-scale training of youth services and community organisations to deliver the REAL U programme in all schools while the schools ready themselves to deliver it.</p>
          <p eId="para_264"> Foróige's REAL U programme is the gold standard in RSE. Young people, now and in future, deserve to have access to the programme. We are ready and willing to work together to make that a reality.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_97">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">I thank Ms Haslam. Our final stakeholder this afternoon is Ms Orla McGowan, programme manager with the Health Service Executive.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_98">
          <from> Ms Orla McGowan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">I thank the committee for the opportunity to address it today. The Health Service Executive welcomes the review of RSE being undertaken by the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment, NCCA. I have worked in this area for 12 years and I and my colleague have made a detailed written submission to the committee. I will outline the main points of the submission and our thoughts on the review of RSE. I will also respond to any questions committee members may have.</p>
          <p eId="para_267"> RSE is a strategic focus of the HSE sexual health and crisis pregnancy programme. As outlined in our submission, we have commissioned a range of research studies and developed a range of resource materials and training for parents, teachers and youth workers in partnership with a number of different organisations, including the Department of Education and Skills, the Professional Development Service for Teachers, the National Youth Council of Ireland, Foróige, Tusla, the National Parents Council and the Irish Family Planning Association.</p>
          <p eId="para_268">Overall, the evidence indicates that young people are more likely to receive sex education now than in the past and they are more likely to say that it was helpful to them. Young people who felt that they had good quality relationships and sexuality education were more likely to use contraception at first sex. Contraceptive use among young people in Ireland is very high, with approximately 80% of young people reporting use of contraception, and there as been a decline of 66% in the number of births to teenagers since 2001, and a 75% decline in the numbers of teenagers accessing abortion services since 2001.</p>
          <p eId="para_269"> While these findings are positive, we acknowledge that there is more to relationships in sexuality education than preventing crisis pregnancy. Sexuality education should emphasise the importance of supporting young people to understand themselves and develop healthy relationships with others. Students should be facilitated to explore and question how our society understands gender, power and sexual expression in an age-appropriate way. Several research reports have indicated that teachers find relationships and sexuality education, RSE, challenging to teach and require more professional development to improve their confidence and competence levels. It is our view that any revised curriculum on its own will not be sufficient to change practice unless it is supported by a comprehensive and potentially accredited continuing professional development, CPD, programme for teachers in social, personal and health education, SPHE, and RSE.</p>
          <p eId="para_270"> SPHE is the only subject at post-primary level where there is no accredited professional qualification and this contributes to the lack of status of the subject in some schools. We note and welcome that the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment, NCCA, review will include advice on implementation of the curriculum in schools. </p>
          <p eId="para_271"> Another barrier to consider is that while RSE is taught within the context of SPHE from primary level to junior cycle, SPHE is still optional at senior cycle. This means that schools are required to teach six classes of RSE per year at senior cycle, but are not required to teach it within the context of SPHE. This makes RSE more difficult to timetable and more difficult to teach because the teachers might not have the opportunity to build up a relationship with the class on other health education topics before addressing RSE. Surveys and inspection reports by the Department of Education and Skills have consistently found that RSE implementation decreases significantly in senior cycle. This is a concern because 16 to 18 year olds may be starting romantic relationships and dealing with break ups during their senior cycle years.</p>
          <p eId="para_272"> The committee may be interested to know that ourselves and the Department of Education and Skills have commissioned Dublin City University, DCU, to undertake a piece of research on RSE in post-primary schools to develop a more nuanced understanding of how the RSE programme is implemented. Students, parents and teachers have been interviewed. The findings are due at the end of the year and I understand they will contribute to the NCCA review. I thank the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_99">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_273">I thank Ms McGowan. I wish to clarify that the process we are undertaking is separate from the NCCA review and we will be making our own independent findings and recommendations to the Minister and to the Department. We are interested in any extra papers or research the witnesses feel would be useful to our committee. We go to all the members for questions and comments and we will give the witnesses the opportunity to come back in. If there is any further information the witnesses would like to send on to us following the meeting, send this on to the clerk, Mr. Guidon, and he will ensure that all the members receive same. That will certainly add to the report when we have the opportunity to sit down and review it.</p>
          <p eId="para_274"> I thank all the witnesses for their experiences, wisdom and thoughts. There are some very clear lines of agreement among everybody in terms of the gaps of knowledge and the capacity building we need among our teachers and among the community at large. There were some very practical suggestions, which I believe will be very helpful.</p>
          <p eId="para_275"> I will now ask the members for their questions. Deputy Thomas Byrne is going to another committee meeting at 5 p.m.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_100">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">Yes, and I apologise for that in advance. I am aware the Chairman is due to go to it as well but I will give her apologies.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_101">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_277">Yes, give my apologies.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_278">I found many of the contributions fascinating and I have a number of quick questions. A huge range of information and food for thought was provided. Dr. Seery outlined the sexual consent workshops in Trinity College. Is there a similar programme in the University of Limerick and DCU?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_103">
          <from> Dr. Debbie Ging<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">Does it exist in the University of Limerick?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_105">
          <from> Dr. Aoife Neary<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_281">Not that I am aware of.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_282">Students have told me it is a fantastic resource.</p>
          <p eId="para_283"> Many people raise similar issues. It is the general experience that teachers, for whatever reason, are uncomfortable teaching this subject. They do not like it, they are not trained and there is not enough time in the day. The Irish Family Planning Association and Foróige, among others, deliver their own modules or their own support. Would an answer to this be to provide funding to outside groups, such as these groups, subject to being suitably quality controlled, to provide more of what they already do? We have teachers who do not like doing this and who do not feel equipped. The NCCA, with all due respect to it, takes forever to deal with this and it does not react quickly to changes, etc. The curriculum that is there is 20 years old. The NCCA has to deal with leaving certificate and junior certificate reform, etc. Would that be a way to do this? I am sure the witnesses will say they would be delighted. Perhaps some of those who are not involved in Foróige or the Family Planning Association might give their views on that? Would that be something that could help in the short term?</p>
          <p eId="para_284"> I would like to ask Dr. Ging about phones. I have a bee in my bonnet about phones and want to ban them, or smart phones at any rate, in schools up to junior certificate level. Will she expand on where she thinks mobile phones come into this particular curriculum because she mentioned it? The current programme does not deal with mobile phones. Could she give a brief outline? I do not need detailed answers. I already got "Yes" and "No" answers to my first questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_107">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_285">Would Dr. Ging like to take that particular question?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_108">
          <from> Dr. Debbie Ging<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_286">Mobile phones are just part of the general gamut of technologies so my concerns would be more about content rather than whether or not schools decide to ban them. I have not given that a huge amount of thought. It is more about how they are being used in terms of sexting and the policy of the school or the RSE programme is with regard to sexting. That opens up a whole other range of questions about sexual rights as opposed to blocking or censorship that need to be explored there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_109">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_287">The Irish Family Planning Association and Foróige would be only too delighted if we gave them extra funding but it would be interesting to hear other views on that point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_110">
          <from> Dr. Debbie Ging<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_288">One of the issues that has to be taken into account on outsourcing and working with external agencies is that a key recommendation in all the international research is a whole-of-school approach. It is really important that any kind of outsourcing would not work against that. A whole-of-school approach requires that everybody in the school is cognisant of the RSE approach, is familiar with the programme and is familiar with the principles at the core of the programme. There is a danger that it is threatened if teachers feel they are off the hook and that they do not need to engage. A whole-of-school approach requires everybody to be on board with those principles.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_111">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_289">I thank Dr. Ging. I will let Dr. Neary to come in on this. There will be an opportunity to respond to many other questions but as Deputy Byrne must go, I wanted to give him the opportunity to ask his questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_112">
          <from> Dr. Clíona Saidléar<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_290">On Deputy Byrne's first question on consent workshops at third level, we commissioned a piece of research with NUIG on consent, young adults, alcohol, in particular, and behaviours around that. Out of that arose a set of programmes called Smart Consent. These have been rolled out from NUIG and they are in Trinity College as well. UCC is also very active in this area and we are part of a network called the Respect network which is an all-Ireland network of NGOs, the institutions and academics in this area. What we are looking at is the whole-of-school approach for the university.</p>
          <p eId="para_291">We are looking at curriculum content and delivery in respect of prevention. We are also looking at the policy of how the institution responds and how it creates a zero tolerance campus which is a safe place to learn. The third aspect, then, is relevant support for those who have been hurt. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_113">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_292">Does that include institutes of technology as well?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_114">
          <from> Dr. Clíona Saidléar<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_293">It is an ever expanding network.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_115">
          <from> Dr. Aoife Neary<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_294">I echo the point on outsourcing and the whole school approach. The Pound <i>et al</i> study that reviewed best practice internationally in ten countries over a 25-year period cautioned against over-reliance on external organisations. The tendency was for it, potentially, to result in one-off sessions which are problematic.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_116">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_295">I thank Dr. Neary. I am going to some of the questions and then I am going to let in Ms Haslam and Ms McGowan. I call Deputy O'Sullivan and then Deputy Naughton.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MariaByrne" eId="spk_117">
          <from>Senator Maria Byrne<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_296">Apologies but we have to go because of two committee meetings clashing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_118">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_297">I thank Senator Byrne.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_119">
          <from>Deputy Jan O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_298">I thank the witnesses for their presentations. As the Chair said, there are some common threads. One is that the curriculum needs to be broadened and made more accurate, according to what some people have said. The other issue arising is the delivery of the curriculum, the status of teachers and the need to upskill. I think it was Ms McGowan who said there is no accredited qualification for teachers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_120">
          <from> Ms Orla McGowan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_299">That is correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JanOSullivan" eId="spk_121">
          <from>Deputy Jan O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_300">That is clearly a deficit that we need to address. The real crux, though, is who delivers it. We have just had the issue of whether it should be external people. The three people here who deliver from the outside have good, positive, objective programmes. We do not, however, want to leave out schools. It needs to be inclusive because part of the problem is that it is very good in some schools - whether it is delivered from outside sources or internally - but not good at all in other schools. The committee wants to ensure that whatever is proposed is comprehensive and includes good, objective, well delivered programmes to all schools.</p>
          <p eId="para_301"> That brings me to the question of ethos. We did not have many references to ethos in the presentations today, with the exception of Ms Donnelly and Dr. Neary. We did in previous sessions. One of the problems, currently, is that much sex education is presented through the prism of the school's ethos. I do not know who would like to answer this but should that change fundamentally? Should we say that there is an objective curriculum, it is factually based and it is presented the same way in all schools irrespective of patronage etc? That is one of the crux issues. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HildegardeNaughton" eId="spk_122">
          <from>Deputy Hildegarde Naughton<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_302">I will follow on with regard to the teaching of factual information on sexual education and relationships. I take the point that a huge part of it is about our relationships with one another, as well as the biology of it. I come from a teaching background and many teachers are uncomfortable with it, as are many adults who are not teachers. It can be a difficult topic for parents to discuss with their own children. Proper training in teacher training colleges, leadership within the school and an open dialogue among staff makes it much easier for teachers. Continuous professional development, CPD, courses are critical. They exist for every other subject and this should not be excluded.</p>
          <p eId="para_303"> I was struck by Rape Crisis Network Ireland's explanation that four Departments and at least six strategies and policies have a role in shaping sexual health education. Notwithstanding all the consultation alluded to - with young people involved in the structure, as well as all the different key agencies - should the lead be taken by one Department? I refer to making sure that we have a comprehensive curriculum for RSE. How can we also get around the teaching of factual sex education despite the ethos of the school? Religion could be a separate class - where the ethos of the school, whatever it is, could be taught - but sex education would involve the facts and giving young people all the information they need on all of the issues. I open that up to anyone who wants to deal with it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_123">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_304">I thank Deputy Naughton. I call Ms Haslam first and then Ms McGowan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_124">
          <from> Ms Sarah Haslam<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_305">I will address Deputy Thomas Byrne's comments at the start on reviewing and updating the curriculum. Our RSE programme was developed in 2012. We have already had to update it and it is going to need another update. That is how quickly things are changing and that is how behind I think we are. As for the comment on whether we all would love more funding, of course we all would. That is not, however, why we are here and not what we are advocating for. We are advocating for quality, comprehensive, holistic relationship and sexuality education for young people. It is already happening in the youth work sector and has been for years. We have had the resources to be able to base the work we are doing on evidence and allow others access to it and not just those within Foróige. They say, repeatedly, that it is quality education.</p>
          <p eId="para_306"> Teachers have a role to play. It is a partnership. RSE education does not just begin and finish in schools. A bank of professionals is already doing this who can go into schools and do it now - should that investment be there - while teachers are getting themselves ready. It should not be a case where a teacher or non-teacher is shoved into doing this. It is correct to say that this is not for everybody. The teachers who are willing to do it, however - those who have come to us and said that they are willing, ready and able - should be resourced and supported. </p>
          <p eId="para_307"> It is a different type of learning. It is negotiated learning - while there are facts, young people also have to be allowed the opportunity to learn for themselves and to develop a skill set around positive relationships. I think it is really about a partnership approach and not just a case of us seeking funding. While my CEO would tell me that I should be saying it, the expertise and resources exist. The investment should be in sharing that among the informal and the formal sector. The members were correct in what they said on ethos. It should be an objective programme. All young people within schools should have access to the same programme, the same quality of education and the same quality of teaching or facilitation. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_125">
          <from> Ms Orla McGowan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_308">I would also like to respond to the question of outsiders doing RSE training. It is important to note that the Professional Development Service for Teachers, PDST, an agency funded by the Department of Education and Skills, already does RSE training for teachers. I understand that several hundred teachers are trained each year at primary and post-primary level. We have worked with it on the development of two different resources specifically for schools. Those are the Talking Relationships, Understanding Sexuality Teaching Resource, TRUST, for the senior cycle and B4UDecide for junior cycle. B4UDecide is being updated at present. It is important to acknowledge that there is already a support service doing this work and training many teachers. That is not the big problem.</p>
          <p eId="para_309"> The problem is that there is a revolving door of teachers attending training because the teachers are moved. They might teach SPHE one year, then it is changed and they are not teaching SPHE the following year. Teachers are not being given the opportunity to build on professional experience and to develop professionally in this area. In an ideal world, teachers would go to ten days of training and that would be accredited. Those teachers would build up professional expertise and then would be a resource within the school. That would make it less likely that the principal will move them on or chop and change the team. I understand that there are issues with contracts and changes are needed on occasion. The main point, however, is that the issue is not that we do not have people who can train in RSE. We do have people who can do that - the pedagogues here are doing it - but it is just one day and not being built upon year on year. As I mentioned in my opening statement, the answer is an accredited programme in SPHE and RSE. </p>
          <p eId="para_310">When we are at that stage we would, as always, be working in partnership with the people who have expertise in this area, in addition to the Professional Development Service for Teachers, PDST.</p>
          <p eId="para_311"> In response to the question on ethos, a research study was conducted a number of years ago by Paula Mayock, Karl Kitching and Mark Morgan on RSE implementation at post-primary level involving nine schools. One school was picked out as an excellent example of RSE delivery. It was a single-sex boys' Catholic school, which shows that it is possible to have good RSE taught in schools that have a Catholic ethos. I am not saying it happens all of the time but it would be wrong not to acknowledge that many teachers and principals are teaching comprehensive RSE even though they are in Catholic schools.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_126">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_312">Ms Jane Donnelly is next.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_127">
          <from> Ms Jane Donnelly<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_313">I would like to respond to the ethos issue. All children have a right to objective sex education. Article 42.3.2°. of the Constitution requires that children receive "a certain minimum education" including moral, intellectual and social. Sexual education fits in under the social heading. The Constitution does not say anything about religious or Catholic sex education. One could say that the State is failing in its duty to provide objective sex education to most pupils because in most schools the sex education provided is Catholic.</p>
          <p eId="para_314"> Furthermore, the Catholic Church has issued guidelines on RSE. Most schools do not tell parents that the sex education provided to pupils is Catholic. Catholic sex education is being integrated into the State's RSE curriculum. The church in its guidelines states that because RSE is an integral part of both the religious education curriculum and the SPHE curriculum, schools are not required to ask parents to sign a permission slip to allow their child to attend lessons in the sensitive area of sex education. Minority, non-religious and Catholic parents who do not want their children to receive Catholic sex education are not being told that this is happening. They do not know that their children are getting Catholic sex education which is integrated into the State course.</p>
          <p eId="para_315"> There are two issues at play here. The first is the fact that children have a right to objective sex education and we believe that the State is failing in its duty to provide same. The second is the fact that parents do not know that they can opt out of Catholic sex education for their children, which is what is being taught in schools.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_128">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_316">Mr. Niall Behan is next.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_129">
          <from> Mr. Niall Behan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_317">I wish to respond to two questions, the first of which was on the role of outside facilitators. We agree with what a number of speakers have said on the matter of a whole-school approach and that RSE should be based in schools. That said, our role could be around complementing that process, helping with resources or with particular aspects of delivering the programme. Problems arise when the outside facilitators become the deliverers of the whole RSE programme and it becomes a box-ticking exercise.</p>
          <p eId="para_318"> The question of ethos can be quite complex. Ethos ties into the teachers' discomfort with the content of programme. There is a worry about the ethos of the school and about whether, for example, a teacher should be talking about contraception. That is part of what gives the RSE programme its low status. The UK authorities tried to improve the status of RSE a number of years ago by making involvement in it a requirement for promotion to school principal. That brought more teachers into the RSE programme there and encouraged them to stick with it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_130">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_319">Our next contributor is Dr. Aoife Neary.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_131">
          <from> Dr. Aoife Neary<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_320">There are two central issues with religious ethos, the first being clarity. There is a need for clarity around exactly how a comprehensive RSE programme can happen in religious-run primary and post-primary schools. I also agree that access to comprehensive RSE is a human right for children.</p>
          <p eId="para_321"> The other issue, which draws on research by Mary Lou Rasmussen in the Australian context, is the fact that we cannot divorce religion from sexuality. There are many children who are religious, who have religious affiliations or cultural affiliations intermingled with religion and RSE needs to address those issues. There is a requirement for a space where there is open and healthy conversation around providing all of the facts - the comprehensive RSE programme - while also acknowledging the tensions between religion and sexuality. Obviously, it will require very experienced teachers who have the ability to create a safe, ethical, open and respectful space in RSE classrooms for that to happen. It does a disservice to people who are religious to talk about sexuality as somehow separate from that because sexuality is core to humanness.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_132">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_322">I will go back to members now. Deputy Funchion is first.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KathleenFunchion" eId="spk_133">
          <from>Deputy Kathleen Funchion<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_323">I thank the Chair. I acknowledge the work done by the Rape Crisis Network Ireland, RCNI. I have dealt with many people who have used the services of rape crisis centres which has made a very positive impact on their lives.</p>
          <p eId="para_324"> I agree with a lot of what Dr. Neary and Dr. Ging have said about the need for more inclusion of children and young people themselves. Often we do not realise the extent to which young people are clued in. I also agree that parents should be included more. They are included in almost every other aspects of their child's education. They receive emails, texts and so on about what is going on generally, but when it comes to RSE, it is often a question of a brief mention or a booklet being given at a parent-teacher meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_325"> The key questions for me are around what is being delivered in schools, how it is being delivered and who is overseeing the delivery of RSE. It is the lack of oversight that has led to the delivery of RSE being so <i>ad hoc</i>. Some schools and teachers are very good while others are very uncomfortable and not so good. While I take on board the points made about avoiding outsourcing, which I would not generally favour, perhaps there is a role for a combined approach involving, for example, teachers and the Irish Family Planning Association. Perhaps we need to think about providing some external support for teachers so that it is not just them in the classroom, because clearly for some, it is an uncomfortable topic. What needs to be done so that RSE delivery is not so uncomfortable for teachers? What can we do to ensure that they do not shy away from it? The teachers who are good at it are comfortable with it and we need to ensure that this is the case for all teachers.</p>
          <p eId="para_326"> I agree that RSE must be delivered by schools. While RSE also requires the involvement of parents and families, it must be provided at school and in every class. At the moment, it only seems to be provided to older classes, and for some children, unfortunately, that is too late. What would the witnesses do if they had the opportunity to engage directly with teachers? What changes would they make?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_134">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_327">Deputy Catherine Martin is next. I explained to the witnesses that the Deputy was unable to attend for the earlier part of this meeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_135">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_328">Yes, I had to chair a meeting. I thank the Chairman for explaining that to our guests. I read the written submissions in advance of the meeting and managed to catch the end of Ms McGowan's presentation. What I found quite striking was the fact that SPHE is the only post-primary subject for which there is no professional, accredited qualification. That is quite shocking and it certainly explains why teachers would feel uncomfortable. It seems unfair to both students and teachers alike and it also goes some way to explaining the difficulties around RSE timetabling. It has become a difficulty for principals, in truth. They are faced with trying to squash it in and selecting a poor, unfortunate teacher to teach it. That is the way it is treated in schools, which is shocking given its importance for our children.</p>
          <p eId="para_329">It is appalling. On the issue of ethos, I do not know how to reconcile the delivery of relationships and sexuality education in line with the ethos of the school with a circular being issued to schools instructing them to ensure RSE is objective and does not withhold or censor. There is a little confusion for school management.</p>
          <p eId="para_330"> My question for Dr. Debbie Ging relates to the research that has been done. She said the Department of Education and Skills and HSE have commissioned the survey. Is the survey related purely to the experience of the teachers, parents and students with how RSE is taught in schools or has it been widened to ascertain young people's thoughts, experiences, knowledge and what they feel is needed with regard to relationships, sexuality and consent?</p>
          <p eId="para_331"> A question for all the witnesses relates to age appropriate material. How do we determine what is age appropriate so that we get the age right and do not deliver RSE too early or late? How is that ascertained or determined? Do some schools have an RSE policy in place while others do not? How does that work? Why do some schools have a policy while others do not? After a whole-school evaluation of management, leadership and learning, or MLL as it is known, has been completed, do inspectors comment on the merits of the school's RSE policy or ask why it does not have an RSE policy in place? Has the Department highlighted this in any way? Do we know what the position is regarding feedback from inspections? It seems bizarre not to have a policy on RSE.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_136">
          <from> Ms Orla McGowan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_332">I thank Deputy Martin for her comments and questions. On the status of social, personal and health education, SPHE, in schools, the Deputy is right that it is sometimes a headache for principals with regard to timetabling. The well-being curriculum that is coming on track in junior cycle will increase the status of SPHE and RSE in schools. It will take a few years for that to embed. With this RSE review, there are positive things on the horizon.</p>
          <p eId="para_333"> With regard to ethos, I agree that the current approach does not make much sense. It is not clear how a teacher will be able to teach about inclusivity and respect for diversity, and at the same time adhere to a Catholic ethos. I might not have made that point clear earlier but ethos should not come into relationships and sexuality education.</p>
          <p eId="para_334"> With regard to the Deputy's questions on RSE policy, all schools are required by the Department to have an RSE policy. The most recent study, the Lifeskills Survey 2015, showed that approximately 90% of schools have a policy, 8% are working on one and 2% have no policy in place. It is one of the areas the inspectorate will examine when carrying out inspections on RSE.</p>
          <p eId="para_335"> The Deputy also asked about the research study. She may have been referring to the study we commissioned. It is a study of the views of students, principals, teachers and parents about RSE delivery in their school. We designed it like that because we were hearing so many mixed reports about RSE in schools. On the one hand, we had large numbers of teachers attending training and we had developed new resources that were evaluating really well. However, on the other hand, young people were still saying they were not getting RSE. We want to find out what is going on and why teachers think they are providing RSE whereas young people say they are not getting it. What is missing? We hope the report will shed some light on that issue for us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_137">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_336">Does the study focus solely on the delivery of RSE without ascertaining the experience or knowledge of relationships or sexuality among young people?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_138">
          <from> Ms Orla McGowan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_337">No. It asks a general question and is open-ended, rather than structured. As it is open-ended, young people can talk about whatever they think needs to be included.</p>
          <p eId="para_338"> I will come back to Deputy Funchion's questions about what is being delivered. The teaching relationships, understanding sexuality teaching, TRUST, resource at senior cycle is being delivered. Approximately 70% of schools are using this approach, which was developed in 2009 and requires an update. This is the resource the Professional Development Service for Teachers, PDST, currently uses in its training in RSE. At junior cycle, it is B4UDecide, which is supported by a website, <i>b4udecide.ie</i>, and approximately 66% of schools report that they use B4UDecide. We have not yet developed materials at primary level. We have the "Busy Bodies" booklet which is for fifth and sixth class, with a DVD to accompany it, and we have recently published guidance for parents on talking to their young child about relationships, sexuality and growing up, with a little booklet for younger children called "Tom's Power Flower" that goes into the very basics of the human body and how babies are made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_139">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_339">I thank Ms McGowan. If she has electronic copies of those, it might be useful to send them to members. That would be appreciated.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_140">
          <from> Ms Orla McGowan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_340">Yes, I can do that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_141">
          <from> Ms Sarah Haslam<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_341">I will reply to Deputies Funchion and Martin. The first comment was about parents. Relationships and sexuality education does not start and end in school. Parents should be supported in this. In our experience, before we start any of our programmes, we arrange an information night for parents where they are given many of the resources. When they leave those meetings, they have comprehensive knowledge of what we will cover in our programme and they are supported throughout the programme. They should be able to have these conversations at home. They know they are started and developed by us but they can continue to have them at home. Parents need to be supported and involved in this.</p>
          <p eId="para_342"> With regard to the comment on teachers and teachers being unsure or unwilling, when teachers come to us and want to use our programme, it is striking that they have heard, believe and know that this is a comprehensive programme that has been tried and tested. They feel confident with that. If I am given a curriculum that is really good, that everybody else says is really good and has gone through rigorous testing and evaluation, that will support me. Another response that we receive from teachers is that they want to receive ongoing feedback from us. We have a training department. In addition to providing training, we also offer continuous support through newsletters, telephone calls and other types of support. That is really important. There is an issue if there is no continuing professional development, CPD, or adequate training. What is required is training plus follow-up and continued support.</p>
          <p eId="para_343"> On age appropriate content, the programme that we have is for young people aged 12 to 18 years. It is divided into core modules, of which there are six, and every participant in the programme does the core modules. We train our facilitators to be able to identify particular needs as the programme starts and finishes. They choose a number of elective modules based on the needs, the age and the awareness of the young people in question. This approach, where we have a core programme and a number of elective modules that can be facilitated afterwards, ensures that core learning, development and outcomes are achieved for all young people who participate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_142">
          <from> Dr. Debbie Ging<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_344">I think Ms McGowan answered Deputy Martin's question. I am not leading the research. My colleague, Dr. Mel Duffy, in the school of nursing, is leading it. It brings up a really important question about research. We are seeing that much of the research on delivery of the programme is piecemeal and out of date. Having bits and pieces of research, regardless of their quality or importance, is not sufficiently comprehensive. A starting point would be to commission national level, large-scale research that addresses young people's perceptions and experiences of RSE, their needs, where they are and what they are doing sexually, and what their perceptions of the programme are.</p>
          <p eId="para_345">Otherwise I do not think we are ever going to get to what is age appropriate or what is actually going on. How do we start with a student-led programme unless we actually know what is happening on some sort of reliable, representative scale? That is probably a better starting point than trying to join up a lot of different pieces of research. It is small funding; it is very good research but the funding and therefore the scale is not adequate.</p>
          <p eId="para_346"> In response to Deputy Funchion's question as to what teachers should do, one of the recommendations made by the Welsh RSE review was to make it mandatory to appoint an RSE lead in every school in the country. That recommendation has now been adopted. If there are external bodies, that person can act as a liaison with them and he or she is also ultimately responsible for the ethos within the school. That would be a core development.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_143">
          <from> Dr. Clíona Saidléar<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_347">I want to pull together some threads, starting with Deputy Funchion's question about teachers. What is coming through is that there is something about the specialisation and professionalisation of this role in terms of sexual health. We know from our work that there are transferable and generalisable, mainstreamable tools that we can give teachers. However, as Ms Haslam has said, we renew and review the content of that curriculum very regularly. We talk about ethos and objective in very particular ways in this debate but one thing we really need to grapple with is that once we get beyond a certain basic level of facts, we are dealing with culture. We are engaging with and asking questions of culture and therefore we have to keep up to date with that, in terms of being led by the children's needs and their lived realities. To do that, we need someone in place who has a specialisation and is supported within a structure. I am inclining more towards the Department of Education and Skills having a set of professionals in this area who have standing, status and support and who are able to carry out that continual review because they are all the time upskilling and learning from the children they are engaging with. We really have to be aware that we are dealing with culture here and with equipping and upskilling children to get through the ever-changing challenges they are facing.</p>
          <p eId="para_348"> The rape crisis centres were mentioned. In terms of infrastructure, there is no funding stream for the 16 rape crisis centres around the country to draw on to do the primary prevention work in schools. A lot of them find ways to do it but they do not have any funding. Rape Crisis Network Ireland has no funding to do this work or this thinking. The bank of personnel and the resources must be there. There must be some part of government that is watchful, mindful and responsible for this and that has cross-departmental, whole-of-government capacity and authority. In the absence of these things, I wonder about what falls through the cracks. We end up developing a set of tools that go out of date and nobody is keeping an eye on the situation.</p>
          <p eId="para_349"> On the question of uncomfortableness around this issue, sexual violence prevention has had a hard time getting onto the sexual health agenda and curriculum. One of the reasons, which we address head on, for example in the REAL U programme, is that there is confusion about role. We have to ask ourselves why we do not have a sexual harassment policy for our schools. It is a glaring gap that nobody is asking about. There are lots of reasons for this, one of which is that we move into the criminal sphere very quickly when we talk about sexual violence. That is why I emphasised primary and secondary prevention. If we are to build up a bank of professionals around primary prevention, this educational piece, we will need to be very clear to them that they are not investigators, that the child protection and children first aspects of the responsibility of the schools happens elsewhere and they are not going to be doing that work as well. We need to distinguish those two roles very clearly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_144">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_350">I invite Ms Jane Donnelly to respond and then I will go back to the remaining questioners.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_145">
          <from> Ms Jane Donnelly<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_351">The circular letter on sex education from the Department is contradictory. I have noted that. It is very disappointing that something like that would come from the Department of Education and Skills. While the schools' policies on sex education are not all published, parents have sometimes sent them to us and we seek them out. Sometimes they are clear that Catholic sex education is being taught and that is fine, we know what that is. Other times they quote from the Department's circular letter and talk about objective sex education yet go on in the policy to talk about Catholic sex education. If what is coming from the Department is contradictory and the school's policy is also contradictory, how do we expect parents to understand that?</p>
          <p eId="para_352"> Policy needs to be clear. What are our children being taught with regards to sex education in school? Even in the Education Act, ethos is not defined. As to what does that mean, it means different things to different people and different schools. Parents do not know what to expect. We are getting contradictory messages from the Department of Education and Skills. The policies are not clear. We need facts. We need to know what our children are being taught and that is all we are asking. If needs be we can opt our children out of the classes. If they are religious-run sex education classes, there needs to be a process to say we are opting them out. What they do when they opt out is another thing but we need practical and clear information.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMurphy" eId="spk_146">
          <from>Deputy Paul Murphy<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_353">The presentations gave a rich picture of the problems that exist in RSE. There seems to unanimous agreement that they are there. Mr. Niall Behan raised a really important point about the gender aspect of the impact of inadequate sex education, which falls disproportionately on women. Would he or other witnesses expand on this gendered impact element? Other anecdotal evidence suggests there is a gendered difference in how sex education is delivered. Boys get one form of sex education that, anecdotally, seems to be less in terms of fewer minutes per year or whatever, and which includes very little in terms of consent. Young women probably get more minutes although it is still completely inadequate in terms of time and the gatekeeper model, whereby it is their role not to have improper or unsafe sex, is put on them in particular.</p>
          <p eId="para_354"> Dr. Aoife Neary raised a really interesting point about the idea of childhood innocence, which is something we hear about a lot around this topic, particularly when we get into the idea of age appropriateness and the idea that sex education can start from as young as three. People say we should not be taking away childhood innocence. It reflects the fact that a section of society sees sexuality as something from which young people should be shielded and as a negative as opposed to its being part of humanity and part of who we are. Could Dr. Neary unpack that a little? What does age-appropriate RSE look like for children at three, five and seven years? Could she demystify this and take away the fears that people have about it?</p>
          <p eId="para_355"> We got a really good picture of how religious ethos interacts with the curriculum.</p>
          <p eId="para_356">A curriculum can be the best in the world on paper but something can then happen. There can either be a board of a school or a principal directing that a certain bit will not really be taught and when another bit is taught, account will be taken of the religious ethos of the school, which can cause direct interference or which can interfere indirectly as the perception of religious ethos or pressure leads to teachers shying away from really going there, even if the curriculum exists on paper. That arose when representatives from the teacher unions came before us. The major issue, as touched on by Ms Donnelly, is that there is a legislative basis for the confusion and contradictory messages of the Department of Education and Skills. The legislative basis is the Education Act 1998, with the reference to having regard to the characteristic spirit of the school. It is quite fundamental and I am interested in the opinions of the witnesses on this. We cannot have progressive, modern, sex-positive RSE without dealing with that. One must deal with that by amending the Education Act. I encourage the committee to try to find time to take the next Stage of the Provision of Objective Sex Education Bill 2018, one purpose of which is precisely to do that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_147">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_357">It has been incredibly interesting listening to everybody. Listening to what has been mentioned by Deputy Paul Murphy, the same thought had struck me that in some of the evidence we heard at our second meeting, the lowest amount of sex education was in single-sex male schools. One of the witnesses spoke correctly about the gender issue and the impact on girls and young women. However, if we call males the "perpetrators" in that position, and if they are not getting the appropriate education they are, to a certain extent, victims as well. We need to ensure that both young men and women get the appropriate sex education in the proper way, with clarity and the appropriate facts.</p>
          <p eId="para_358"> Dr. Saidléar and Ms McGowan spoke about B4UDecide, which seems to be a really good resource. They, and particularly Dr. Saidléar, highlighted that there are a significant number of resources and networks that are available for teachers and schools but there seems to be an issue with schools taking that on board. There is a space for co-ordination that absolutely needs to happen. I would imagine there is a role for all of those within a new model of RSE. If much of the work has been done, we do not need to reinvent the wheel but rather ensure it comes together and is coherent.</p>
          <p eId="para_359"> Mr. Seery spoke about the use of student facilitators with appropriate roles, and that is a really good model. Is it something that would be effective at post-primary level in terms of peer support? There is also the issue of choosing young people for it, as it is a very important role in itself. It might be helpful and supportive for younger students, particularly with the idea of gender equality officers. I mentioned at a meeting before how I was struck by a Comhairle na nÓg workshop that I attended. There was a real concern among young people in post-primary school about the lack of support they felt was evident for those who are identifying as lesbian, gay, bisexual or transsexual, LGBT. It is something we could do much with. Foróige's Relationships Explored and Life Uncovered, REAL U, programme has absolutely been noted as a gold standard. It has been mentioned at some of our other meetings as well. Have schools ever asked for Foróige to come in and deliver that? The group has an existing network of trained facilitators and this would be important for us.</p>
          <p eId="para_360"> This is an ongoing debate about internal versus external approaches and there should be a mix of both. When there are experts in the area, as outlined by Dr. Saidléar, we need those people with an incredible wealth of knowledge and experience in dealing with specific situations. We all know that sometimes some young people will open up more or take more from somebody they may not see again. They feel more free about it. Equally, it is vital that there would be a support mechanism within every school. It is the notion of having somebody whose responsibility is to ensure a robust RSE policy is delivered. They should have that adequate training - the ten-day training mentioned by Ms McGowan - and ensure that there is a holistic view in the school. The teacher should have that as an absolute responsibility within middle management. There is an issue relating to inspection or vetting of external people coming to schools. It is important in the context of setting a policy.</p>
          <p eId="para_361"> I could go on for a while but I will not. I will go to Ms Haslam and Dr. Neary first as they indicated a wish to speak at the end of the previous contributions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_148">
          <from> Dr. Aoife Neary<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_362">To respond to Deputy Funchion, who brought up evaluation, it is key and it brings legitimacy. Recommendation No. 9 of the Informing the Future of the Sex and Relationships Education Curriculum in Wales report is the inspection of RSE in a very formal way as part of an inspectorate's work. It should come in tandem with research support and the evaluation aspect of a network that would take in the spiral notion of the curriculum and continuing professional development and training, which should happen in a meaningful way.</p>
          <p eId="para_363"> Deputy Paul Murphy asked about age appropriateness. A number of international studies mention age appropriateness, including Pound <i>et al.</i>, as I mentioned. That was a review of RSE in ten different countries across 25 years that mentions the spiral curriculum needing to happen from early years, which is a significant finding. It would be from age three onwards. Professor Emma Reynold's work in the UK explores how children are not too young in a primary school context to engage with the concepts of RSE, gender and sexuality and so on. In the US context, Ryan <i>et al.</i> and Martino and Cummin-Potvin's work illustrates how primary age children from as young as four can make sense of and question structures of disadvantage and privilege related to gender and sexuality in an age appropriate way, of course, and in partnership with parents. Robinson and Davies have, in an Australian context, work relating to early childhood and caution against this notion of age appropriateness policing us and we should not make assumptions about what is age appropriateness but rather speak with children and young people and find out where they are. It is a notion of the living curriculum. Another aspect is the fear that this might be for parents at this age. The problem with just being educated by parents is that the most vulnerable in our society will not get the same education for RSE. For a fair and equal system, it should be comprehensively across the board and across all primary schools.</p>
          <p eId="para_364"> Renold speaks about consent as something that can be talked about from early years, such as three onwards, and taking in concepts of refusal, language and communication. The three year old might say "I do not like that". We can start with such simple language. Similarly, with LGBT identities, the INTO LGBT teacher group introduced a resource called "Different Families, Same Love", and it again has age-appropriate language usable from four onwards which mentions love, mammy and mammy, mammy and daddy, daddy and daddy, and the variety of family forms, including mammy on her own, daddy on his own and others that could be evident. It makes it very real and possible from early ages and there is nothing to be frightened about.</p>
          <p eId="para_365"> I welcome Deputy Paul Murphy's comment about amending the Education Act 1998. From an LGBT perspective, amending section 37(1) of the Employment Equality Act 1998 would remove chill factor for teachers in respect of being recruited and dismissed. In a study I did on primary schools to explore homophobia and transphobia, we found that teachers are afraid to approach these topics because they are afraid of the reaction of parents and that in some way it is contrary to the ethos of the school. That ambiguity needs to be cleared up and the amendment of the Education Act would be an excellent place to start from that perspective.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_149">
          <from> Ms Sarah Haslam<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_366">I would like to make two points in response to Deputy Paul Murphy, the first of which is about gender. We do not agree with splitting the curriculum in terms of gender. Our curriculum is for all genders and everybody participates in all aspects of it. One of the core modules of this programme relates to gender and sexuality, which we sought advice on from BeLonG To, and we continue to work with it to update that. It is one of the key modules in this programme that has seen significant effects statistically in terms of young people's attitudes towards members of the LGBTI+ community.</p>
          <p eId="para_367"> I echo what Dr. Aoife Neary said on age and taking away innocence. A spiral curriculum is what we would recommend and that key pieces of learning must start early and continue to be repeated and built on as young people age.</p>
          <p eId="para_368"> The Chairman asked if we have been asked about this by teachers. They are beating down our door seeking this curriculum but we face two barriers in that regard. First, we cannot replace the educational curriculum; we cannot come in and replace what is provided. We are seeking to be the named as the curriculum. The second barrier is the cut in our core funding. We had a 33% cut in our core funding of which only 7.5% has been restored. That has impacted on our resources and on young people accessing the programme. This year, we have 200 people waiting on a list to be trained to facilitate this programme.</p>
          <p eId="para_369"> Coming back to what Dr. Saidléar said, if we continue to research, talk and write curricula from the beginning, we are failing our young people now. There are curricula available. We are an example of one that has been tested robustly. It is our job to work with young people and to ensure our curriculum and programmes meet the needs of young people. Young people are constantly inputting into this curriculum, which is the reason we have to continue to update it.</p>
          <p eId="para_370"> There is no point reinventing the wheel. We are calling for this to be the named curriculum and for the Government to invest in, and fund schools, to allow them access the current network of trained and skilled professionals to come into schools and to train teachers who are in a position to cover this curriculum to the standard to which we train them, and be supported by us on an ongoing basis.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_150">
          <from> Ms Orla McGowan<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_371">I would like to respond to Deputy Paul Murphy's question on the area of childhood innocence. We did some research with parents of four to nine year old children on talking to young children about growing up, relationships and sexuality to support us and they raised the issues of giving them too much information, childhood innocence and so on. However, the overwhelming response from parents was that they wanted to do a better job than their own parents in this area. They believed it was important that their children received RSE but they were stuck regarding the language, what they should say, when they should say it, how not to say too much while providing enough information and so on.</p>
          <p eId="para_372"> In terms of the response to that, when a parent asks how they should teach a three year old about RSE, we tell them that they are doing it. Whether they think they are doing it, if they are in a relationship with their children, they are giving them information on how they should feel about their body, what it is to be a boy or a girl and naming their feelings. By the time the children are four they will be asked where babies come from and, therefore, all those areas constitute RSE at the age of three, for example, as Deputy Murphy mentioned.</p>
          <p eId="para_373"> At the age of seven, it is still the same education. The children might get some information in the school curriculum but young people ask questions long before the topic is dealt with in the school. That might be appropriate because children develop at different rates and the primary responsibility for RSE is with parents. Parents are asked these questions constantly. A seven year old might be curious about the different types of love. They might ask, "Who do you love more? Me, Daddy or Granny?" Those are the types of questions they will ask and when parents respond to those questions, they are talking to the children about different types of love. Questions might arise from school. For example, children might ask the reason another student has two mums or two dads, and the parent will answer that. That is RSE. We talk about privacy and nudity in terms of who is and is not allowed see them without clothes. There are also general messages about children having a positive body image.</p>
          <p eId="para_374"> International guidance on age appropriate sexuality education developed by the World Health Organization, WHO, is available but the main point is that parents are doing it anyway. It is just a question of how they are doing it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_151">
          <from> Ms Jane Donnelly<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_375">Regarding Deputy Paul Murphy's question on the ethos, I agree the Education Act needs to be amended but there has not been an amendment to religious discrimination under the Employment Equality Act 1998. Under section 37(1), one can still discriminate on the grounds of religion. That was changed in regard to LGBT but it was not changed in regard to religion. Under their contract, teachers are obliged to uphold the religious ethos of the school. They are in the position, therefore, if they give objective sex education in schools under religious patronage, they are in breach of their employment contract. There is a connection, therefore, with section 37(1) of the Employment Equality Act as well as the various sections in the Education Act to which we have referred.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_152">
          <from> Dr. Clíona Saidléar<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_376">To respond to the gendered question, we can see the gendered impacts but it is more difficult to see how all that plays out before we get to those stark impacts. That is one of the reasons I have spoken on a few occasions about the need for a sexual harassment policy.</p>
          <p eId="para_377"> In the programmes we are involved in, boys and girls are together in the classroom but, as a facilitator and an educator, we are clearly looking at power dynamics and the different expectation that are based on gender. When we commissioned the research, Young people, Alcohol and Sex: What's consent got to do with it?, it surprised us that young people said there is no difference between men and women, boys and girls, they are all empowered now, they can all say "Yes" and "No", and that everything is fantastic. However, when we scratched the surface of that regarding scenarios that were questionable such as sexual violence and sexual consent, in the quick responses on who is the gatekeeper in terms of responsibility and blame, strict gender roles were outlined.</p>
          <p eId="para_378"> Delivering the curriculum in the classroom is one thing but what happens when those children walk out into the corridor? Unless we have a sophisticated understanding of the gendered, sexist and misogynistic world they are stepping into in the corridor, we may have equipped them poorly to engage. If we do not empower them to stand up for themselves and call out, say, the sexual assault they experience as soon as they step out into that corridor, what have we done as institutions to ensure they are in a safe place in terms of the power dynamics going on in that corridor?</p>
          <p eId="para_379">When we have delivered our curriculum, have we also done our homework on the context they step out into? That is why I talk about a sexual harassment action plan for schools, a national policy on how we do that and create safe spaces in the school environment. We have a template, 'Safe and Supportive' that BeLonG To spoke about. It is an excellent piece of work. Why do we not have that for sexual harassment? We would like to think about how this curriculum is enacted in children's lives when they step back into the real world and whether we have empowered them in ways that are unintentionally unsafe because we have not taken care of context outside the classroom.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_153">
          <from> Dr. Aidan Seery<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_380">I am conscious that the experience in TCD provides us with a small knowledge base and I admit that I have no experience of schools or schooling. From the experience of young adults in college, however, and particularly with reference to this debate about the factual or objective on one side of the spectrum, and the ideologically tendentious on the other end because that is probably a more appropriate way to look at that end of the spectrum, the students we have dealt with come from different backgrounds. A total of 25% of them come from international backgrounds and while many have had a religion-based education, but every one of them comes into a consent workshop with a set of attitudes, dispositions and world views. Every one of them has experienced social power relations in their own bodies and they have been formed and shaped by their experiences whether religious, non-religious or whatever.</p>
          <p eId="para_381"> Stepping precariously into the realm of schooling and teachers, without any background, a set of highly skilled professionals who are able to engage with this theme on the basis of dispositions, attitudes and power relations somewhere in the middle of that spectrum between the impossibility of looking at this theme purely factually and objectively on the one hand and with a highly ideological tendentiousness on the other, is required. It will require great skill and careful planning, and a careful curriculum.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_154">
          <from> Dr. Debbie Ging<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_382">Briefly in response to Deputy Murphy's point about gender inequality that has to be core, particularly to any training initiatives. There needs to be an awareness that not only is the programme often delivered differently but also of how the wider school processes of gender socialisation contribute to many of the problems that we are experiencing with regard to certain views on consent, or to the issue of girls feeling more responsible or being trained for particular behaviours that boys are not. As Dr. Saidléar mentioned, these are parts of what many children and parents feel as the norm. How do we advance a progressive curriculum when we are still grappling with problematic gender norms? A whole-school approach is probably the only way to make those incompatibilities work together.</p>
          <p eId="para_383"> With regard to the question on religious ethos, I concur entirely that the Education Act 1998 must be amended.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_155">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2018-06-12T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_384">I thank Dr. Ging. Home-school liaison teachers will play an important role in respect of that balance between home and school.</p>
          <p eId="para_385"> I thank all the witnesses for attending and sharing their wisdom, experience, and huge depth of research and knowledge. It has been useful for me and all the committee members. If there is anything else they would like to send us, bearing in mind the questions and comments, they should please feel free to do so and we will ensure that all the members have the opportunity to read that before we prepare our final report.</p>
          <p eId="para_386"> I would like members to stay on because we did not deal with housekeeping. </p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_19">
          <i>The joint committee went into private session at 6.05 p.m. and adjourned at 6.20 p.m. until 9.30 a.m. on Thursday, 21 June 2018.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
