<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_tourism_culture_arts_sport_and_media/2022-03-09/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_tourism_culture_arts_sport_and_media/2022-03-09/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2022-03-09" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/33/select_committee_on_tourism_culture_arts_sport_and_media"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_tourism_culture_arts_sport_and_media/2022-03-09/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_tourism_culture_arts_sport_and_media/2022-03-09/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2022-03-09" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_tourism_culture_arts_sport_and_media/2022-03-09/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_tourism_culture_arts_sport_and_media/2022-03-09/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2022-03-16" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AlanDillon" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Alan-Dillon.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Alan  Dillon"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CatherineMartin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Catherine-Martin.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Catherine Martin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CiaranCannon" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ciaran-Cannon.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Ciaran Cannon"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ImeldaMunster" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Imelda-Munster.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Imelda Munster"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JackChambers" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jack-Chambers.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Jack Chambers"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnnyMythen" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Johnny-Mythen.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Johnny Mythen"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister/tourism__culture__arts__gaeltacht__sport__media" showAs="Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/tourism__culture__arts__gaeltacht__sport__media" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN ROGHCHOISTE UM THURASÓIREACHT, CULTÚR, EALAÍONA, SPÓRT AGUS NA MEÁIN</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Select Committee on Tourism, Culture, Arts, Sport and Media</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2022-03-09">Dé Céadaoin, 09 Márta 2022</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2022-03-09">Wednesday, 09 March 2022</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Roghchoiste le chéile ag 01:30 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Select Committee met at 01:30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2"/>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#CiaranCannon">Ciarán Cannon</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#JackChambers">Jack Chambers (Minister of State at the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media)</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#CatherineMartin">Catherine Martin (Minister of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media)</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#ImeldaMunster">Imelda Munster</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#JohnnyMythen">Johnny Mythen.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#AlanDillon">Teachta / Deputy Alan Dillon sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Estimates for Public Services 2022<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:30:00+00:00"/></heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Vote 33 - Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media (Revised)<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:30:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_1">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_8">This meeting has been convened to consider the Revised Estimates for public services 2022, Vote 33, programme areas A, B, D and E, which have been referred to this committee by Dáil Éireann. I welcome the Minister, Deputy Catherine Martin, the Minister of State, Deputy Jack Chambers, and their officials to the meeting. As the Minister and Minister of State are present, officials should not speak in public session. I also wish to advise them that the opening statements and any other documents they have submitted to the committee will be published on the committee's website after this meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_9"> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable. I again remind members of the constitutional requirement that they must be physically present in the confines of Leinster House to participate in public meetings. I will not permit a member to attend where he or she is not adhering to the constitutional requirement. Therefore, any members who attempt to attend from outside the precincts will be asked to leave the meeting. I also remind all those joining the meeting online to ensure their mobile phones are on silent or switched off.</p>
          <p eId="para_10"> I invite the Minister to make her presentation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media (Deputy Catherine Martin)<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_11">Fáiltím go mór roimh an deis labhairt leis an gcoiste agus Meastacháin Athbhreithnithe 2022 do mo Roinnse á mbreithniú. Tá €1.2 billiún sa leithdháileadh iomlán do Vóta 33 in 2022, méadú de thart ar 8% ar an bhfigiúr inchomparáide do 2021. Éascóidh an maoiniú méadaithe seo sraith bearta substaintiúla chun na hearnálacha a bhfuil mé féin mar Aire freagrach astu a thacú agus a neartú agus iad ag dul in oiriúint don, agus ag teacht chucu féin ón, dochar nach bhfacthas riamh a d'eascair as paindéim Covid-19. These sectors are both wide-ranging and valuable and were among those most severely impacted by the Covid-19 pandemic. Employing many hundreds of thousands throughout the country, these are the sectors that thrive when people congregate to enjoy their leisure time together. Our cultural institutions and theatres, live performances, tourism destinations, sporting occasions and Gaeltacht communities have all been severely impacted for almost two years. The public health measures necessitated by Covid enabled us to protect the most vulnerable in our society through our collective action but also had such a negative impact on the way we have lived our lives for the past two years, for example, our ability to watch a match, to attend a live performance, to enjoy a weekend away with friends, to participate in the arts as well as the ability of artists, workers and businesses to provide these uniquely valued experiences.</p>
          <p eId="para_12"> As Minister, I am very pleased we are now in a position to enjoy the safe and successful reopening of our society and, with it, our tourism sector, our arts and culture venues and events, and the return of fans to our sports grounds. The 2022 Revised Estimates for my Department have been informed by ongoing engagement with sectoral representatives. The additional funding covers a wide range of initiatives and measures to support the resilience and growth of practitioners, businesses, communities and operations in the sectors overseen by my Department, with all efforts very much focused on both social and economic recovery.</p>
          <p eId="para_13"> I will outline total 2022 funding for the sectors supported by my Department. There is €288.5 million in funding for tourism services in 2022, which is an increase of €67.6 million or 31% on the comparable 2021 allocation<b>. </b>This additional funding includes a €50 million provision for further business continuity support to help drive the sustainable recovery of the sector. A €35 million increase in the tourism marketing fund will support the delivery of a marketing strategy to help restore inbound tourism to Ireland. In addition, €27 million<b>
						</b>is allocated for a range of industry initiatives, including domestic marketing and festivals, investment in digital skills development, and staff retention, and €36.5 million in capital funding for tourism product development – an increase of almost €4 million over the 2021 allocation – for the delivery of enhanced visitor experiences in line with the objectives of the National Development Plan 2021-2030.</p>
          <p eId="para_14"><b>
						</b>Some €371.4 million<b>
						</b>will be allocated to the arts and culture sector, including €25 million to pilot a new basic income guarantee scheme for artists. This measure was the key ask from the arts and culture recovery task force and will bring new life and support to the arts and culture sector. The Arts Council maintains the record €130 million<b>
						</b>funding<b>
						</b>allocated in 2021, allowing it to continue to protect the jobs and livelihoods of artists and assist arts organisations through financial difficulties and empowering it to play a strong role in supporting artists and arts organisations to flourish in the years ahead. Some €50 million is allocated for further supports for the live performance sector following on from the successful operation of a number of schemes in 2021, including the live performance support scheme, LPSS, the music and entertainment business assistance scheme, MEBAS, and the events sector Covid support scheme, ESCSS, thereby supporting a successful return to full-scale performances.</p>
          <p eId="para_15">The 2022 allocation for Screen Ireland is €36.7 million, an increase of more than €6.6 million on the 2021 allocation. The audiovisual industry has been one of the success stories of the past two years and this additional funding will ensure the continued success and growth of this internationally renowned industry into the future. Funding for this programme area includes the following: €4 million to deliver a suite of initiatives proposed by the night-time economy task force; €5 million in additional funding for the national cultural institutions to ensure they continue to provide high-quality services to the public and deliver progress in their ongoing programme of investment; and €5 million to support the 2022 commemorative programme delivering rich and diverse national and local programmes marking the significant centenaries arising in 2022.</p>
          <p eId="para_16"> Funding of €295.7 million will be provided for media and broadcasting in 2022, which includes €5.5 million for the establishment of the new media commission and the appointment of an online safety commissioner to begin work on key issues following the enactment of the Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill in 2022. This allocation also provides for an increase of €4.2 million, the largest ever funding increase for TG4, bringing its annual funding for 2022 up to €44.9 million. This additional funding will allow it to deliver its ambitious post-Covid strategy, focusing on news content and putting audiences centre stage.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> In conclusion, I am satisfied the increased allocation for my Department in 2022 of €1.222 billion will allow for the continuation and enhancement of its very diverse but critical work programmes. As Minister, I intend to do everything possible to continue to support all the sectors for which I have responsibility as we emerge from the shadow of Covid-19, and I look forward to their future growth and successes. I will now hand over to my colleague the Minister of State, Deputy Chambers, to speak about the Revised Estimates for 2022 as they relate to sport.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_3">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_18">I thank the Minister and invite the Minister of State to make his opening remarks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Minister of State at the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media (Deputy Jack Chambers)<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_19">Cuirim fáilte mhór roimh an deis labhairt leis an gcoiste maidir le Meastacháin Athbhreithnithe 2022 mar a bhaineann siad le mo réimse freagrachta maidir le seirbhísí spóirt agus fóillíochta.</p>
          <p eId="para_20"> The 2022 allocation for sports and recreational services amounts to €181.2 million and is clear evidence of Government support for the aims of this programme area by contributing to a healthier and more active society by promoting sports participation and supporting high performance and the provision of sport facilities.</p>
          <p eId="para_21"> In the context of sports facilities, the Minister and I recently had the pleasure of announcing an overall package of €150 million in new capital grants under the latest round of the sports capital and equipment programme. There was a record number of applications for these grants and the Government responded with the most significant level of individual awards ever. The increased allocation of €34.5 million for the sports capital and equipment programme in 2022 reflects this commitment to investment in sport.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> Current funding for Sport Ireland programmes totals €96.21 million in 2022, enabling Sport Ireland to ensure the emergence of a strong and vibrant sport sector post Covid. Measures support the implementation of the high-performance strategy approved by the Government in June last, equality in grant funding for female and male Gaelic players and core grant funding for sporting bodies. The allocation also provides for increased funding for sports measures via the Dormant Accounts Fund and increased funding for initiatives to attract major sporting events to Ireland.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> The overall 2022 allocation represents a significant investment in sport and builds on the extensive support packages provided to address the Covid-19 challenges to national governing bodies and clubs in 2020 and 2021. I believe it will ensure the emergence of a strong and vibrant sports sector post Covid, which will provide opportunities for everyone to engage in sport and physical activity in all our communities.</p>
          <p eId="para_24"> The Minister and I will be happy to take any questions Deputies may have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_5">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_25">I thank the Minister of State.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_26">Will the Minister give us a breakdown of the tourism marketing fund? Is the funding given to Fáilte Ireland to be managed, and does it provide the total figure of the Department’s funding of Tourism Ireland? There is reference to €8.3 million in the Estimates and a portion of the €81.8 million in the tourism marketing fund. How is the fund distributed? It is a sizeable sum.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_7" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_27">It is used to provide funding for overseas tourism marketing. The bulk of the funding forms the State's share of the agreed North-South co-funding of Tourism Ireland's destination marketing of the island of Ireland overseas. Given Tourism Ireland is a North-South body, it also receives funding from the Northern Ireland exchequer for its core overseas marketing. The primary objective of the tourism marketing fund is to increase tourism revenue by attracting more overseas visitors to Ireland. Irish tourism is marketed primarily on an island-of-Ireland basis and the majority of the tourism marketing fund goes toward Tourism Ireland's core funding for all-island overseas marketing activity. A proportion of the non-core tourism marketing fund is allocated for the development of Ireland's specific product and regional marketing by Fáilte Ireland, to be delivered by Tourism Ireland as its overseas agent.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_28">Following on from Deputy Munster's question, is the money given out regionally? Is equality among the regions taken into account?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_9" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_29">The tourism marketing fund is used to pay for Tourism Ireland's destination marketing overseas and for Fáilte Ireland's niche product marketing. Tourism Ireland delivers marketing programmes in 21 markets throughout the world and reaches a global audience of more than 600 million each year. The agency is doing incredible work and I have witnessed that in two missions I have undertaken, to the United States and, recently, to Dubai. The work it is doing to sell our island as a destination at a time when that is so badly needed is incredible, not least because of the time and commitment that is given to it. As an example of where the money goes, targeting market activity includes advertising online, on television, at outdoor sites, in cinemas, newspapers and magazines and through e-marketing, overseas publicity and co-operative marketing with carriers, other partners and promotions. I have heard from the main tour operators to which they are trying to sell Ireland that at a time of absolute devastation in those early days of the pandemic, it was Tourism Ireland that reached out to the tour operators when others did not, and kept that relationship really special and valued. They linked in with them and that is what is being remembered as tourism reopens. That is all down to the incredible work Tourism Ireland does.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_30">I understand all that, but very often the marketing is done in respect of the western and eastern sides of the country, heading up towards the north, whereas other parts are neglected in respect of promotion. My point is we should ensure it is done on an equal basis for each region and for the four provinces.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_11" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_31">Absolutely. Fáilte Ireland is delivering four new regional tourism strategies in 2022, setting out a ten-year vision and a five-year action plan for each region. They will be activated through a series of local destination and experience development plans. By the end of 2022, 27 of them will be live, while by 2025, every part of the country will have a destination development plan. That should address some of the Deputy's concerns. Each plan will be appropriate to a given region's level of tourism maturity.</p>
          <p eId="para_32">The Deputy can look also at the incredible amount of funding provided by Fáilte Ireland last year to develop tourism attractions, for example, in Westport, Donegal, Dublin and Cavan. It was the largest funding ever announced by Fáilte Ireland, which is constantly working on developing new destinations and attractions for tourism and sharing tourism out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_33">When will the regional plans be finished?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_13" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">The four new regional tourism strategies will be delivered in 2022. They will set out a ten-year vision and a five-year action plan for the regions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">There is a reference on page 12 to Housing for All. Perhaps the Minister could please explain it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_15" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_36">Where did Deputy Munster say it is?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_37">It is at the bottom of page 12 of the Revised Estimates. The reference is to the National Tourism Development Authority-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_17" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_38">It is looking at the short-term letting. The National Tourism Development Authority legislation is to be updated to take account of the Housing for All requirements and to limit capital increases. It is looking at how that can help.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">Could the Minister explain the Housing for All requirements in the context of what we are talking about? Exactly what does it mean?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_19" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_40">It is to register Airbnb accommodation. The registration would be welcomed. My departmental officials are linking in with the officials of the Minister, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_41">That is grand. I thank the Minister for providing clarity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_21">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">I have one question for the Minister on the €36.5 million capital allocation for tourism product development. I live close to the Wild Atlantic Way. Does the Minister have a breakdown of the programmes or the infrastructure? I know she spoke previously about the regional strategies. Is the €36.5 million part of the four regional strategies that will be published very soon?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_22" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_43">Fáilte Ireland will develop, support and promote tourism at a regional and county level. The Vice Chairman mentioned one of the four regional tourism experiences. These are the Wild Atlantic Way, Ireland's Ancient East, the Hidden Heartlands and Dublin. Tourism Ireland is promoting the island of Ireland in more than 21 markets. Those four brands resonate with tourists, and they work very well. In terms of Fáilte Ireland-supported capital projects, although restrictions associated with the Covid-19 pandemic may have delayed some openings, some examples of projects that were completed in recent years include the Butler Gallery in Kilkenny, the Blasket Islands viewing platform, which will open shortly, and Carlingford Castle. The work is ongoing. Fáilte Ireland allocated the sum of €1.1 million to the Butler Gallery; €1.7 million was allocated to the Blasket Islands viewing platform; Carlingford Castle got €400,000; Nowth in Meath, where I was last week, received €1.4 million; and the Céide Fields visitor centre in Ballycastle, County Mayo, received a Fáilte Ireland investment of €863,000. Some of the Fáilte Ireland tourism projects due to be opened during 2022 include the Blasket Islands, the Céide Fields, Avondale House, Strokestown Park, Mount Congreve House and Gardens and the Norman Heritage Park. We are constantly building on the regional spread. Much-needed investment is taking place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_23">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_44">I thank the Minister very much for her response. The OPW and Fáilte Ireland have worked on the Céide Fields visitor and exhibition centre. It will be a hugely beneficial project for north Mayo and we welcome it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">I have a quick question which comes under tourism. Will the Minister explain the significant reduction in investment for regional museums, galleries, cultural centres and projects? This will result in a cut of €51 million. Where will the cuts be made?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_25" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">There is a separate line this year for Covid supports under B16. Cultural supports now have their own separate line. It looks like the figure has dropped, but it has not. It is just that we have given a separate line now to the Covid supports. That was well spotted by the Deputy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">I thank the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_27">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_48">We will now continue with questions from Members on programme B, which relates to the arts and culture.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCannon" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Deputy Ciarán Cannon<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_49">I thank the Minister, the Minister of State and their officials for joining us. I also thank each and every one of them for the work they did during the pandemic to support the sector. What lessons can we learn from the engagement, as a result of the experience of supporting a sector that was particularly badly impacted by the pandemic and following the establishment of new links with elements of Irish cultural activity that perhaps the Department had not supported previously? I have in mind the work of the Music and Entertainment Association of Ireland, MEAI. I have heard it repeatedly said that in rushing back to normal, let us decide what parts of normal are worth going back to. Will there be any change in approach in the Department's work or by the Arts Council in how it engages with and supports those who were supported for the first time during the pandemic? Are there any plans to develop those linkages in the future?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_29" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_50">In general terms, the lesson that has been learned by everyone, not just the Department, is the value of the arts. As an artist, Deputy Cannon will appreciate that. We have often spoken about the value of arts and how we treasure it, but it really came to light during Covid. A valuable lesson also is not just about the performers themselves, who of course are incredibly important, but also about the people who make these events happen - those who work backstage on whom the spotlight does not shine. A light was shone on them, and it is my intention to keep that light firmly there.</p>
          <p eId="para_51"> We could not have designed the number of schemes we did without engagement. From the first moment I became Minister, engagement and feedback have been key. Schemes have been adjusted following engagement with those affected. Although we are emerging from Covid, I would not see that as something that should ever stop. It is essential that we continue to engage with the stakeholders through the forum that was set up to assess the recovery and their current needs. Yesterday, we announced another new scheme, which is about helping people with the recovery. That needs to continue. Such engagement is evident also in what we are doing with the basic income. The artists must shape what we do in the Department. As far as I am concerned, the artists must be involved and at the table in any policy initiatives. That is the lesson that has been learned.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCannon" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Deputy Ciarán Cannon<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T13:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">I thank the Minister. The creation of a universal basic income for artists is a truly groundbreaking move on the Minister's part. Everyone, in his or her time as Minister, seeks to do exactly that, in other words, make a significant change that would impact on the lives of people long after he or she has exited the role. I think of the work President Michael D. Higgins did when he was Minister, including the 1% for arts provision, the establishment of TG4 and various other wonderful things. I congratulate the Minister on having the vision and ambition to make this happen. This will be truly groundbreaking if and when - I always use the word "when" - we make it happen. It is important that she gets the support of her Cabinet colleagues and the Government in general in making it happen.</p>
          <p eId="para_53"> I would be grateful for an update on where we are at right now. Since the Minister first mentioned the proposition, an extraordinary number of artists have been in touch with me to ask if they would qualify and how they can make their voice heard right now in terms of being able to access the universal basic income when it becomes a reality. Anything the Minister could say this morning to reassure the artists that this will be as encompassing and broadly supportive as possible would be much appreciated.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_31" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">Engaging with the artists shows how essential that basic income is. This was the number one recommendation that came from the artists themselves through the arts and culture recovery task force. I was absolutely delighted to secure agreement within the Government on that. I secured €25 million in budget 2022 to launch this three-year basic income for arts pilot scheme.</p>
          <p eId="para_55"> The stakeholder engagement has been absolutely core. We had the stakeholder forum in December followed by public consultation. There were well over 1,000 pieces of feedback into that public consultation. As I said, we received a significant number of submissions. That reflects the high level of interest, which the Deputy talked about, in this key policy intervention.</p>
          <p eId="para_56"> The scheme will be open to practising and developing artists and creative arts workers. It will be non-competitive. Therefore, once a person satisfies the eligibility criteria, he or she will be included in a randomised selection process. The eligibility criteria will be published as part of the scheme launch, which I hope to do in the coming weeks. We are nearly there. It was essential that the artists had to feed into this and help to shape it. I expect the launch in the coming weeks. We are now down to the final details of the number of recipients and the rate of payment. We are trying to finalise that right now. Of course, issues around artists with disabilities have been raised so we must give serious consideration to ensuring this is addressed.</p>
          <p eId="para_57"> It is my intention that the basic income for arts will be an unconditional basic regular income to artists and creative arts workers to allow them to focus on what they need to focus on. The recipients can do that when they are in receipt of this grant. It will be groundbreaking. There will be a control group as well and we will be assessing the scheme. Research will be done throughout the programme on its impact on creative output and well-being. It will be a thorough research project for three years.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCannon" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Deputy Ciarán Cannon<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">I thank the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">Could the Minister explain where the €6.6 million in funding for Screen Ireland will go? Of the 40 feature film and television drama projects that received funding from Screen Ireland in 2020, how many were located in counties Dublin and Wicklow versus other regions of the country? Has regional balance been factored into the output targets for 2021 and 2022 to ensure the whole country benefits?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_34" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_60">As I said earlier, the audiovisual industry was one of the success stories of 2021, recording a record level of output in the face of Covid-19. New figures published recently reveal a record-breaking spend of more than €500 million in the Irish economy across film, television, drama, documentary and animation production in Ireland in 2021.</p>
          <p eId="para_61"> The Irish screen production industry is building a reputation for high-quality production across the world. The 2022 allocation for Screen Ireland will amount to €36.743 million comprising €32.15 million in capital funding and €4.593 million in current funding. For screen allocations, there will be pay of €2.2 million and non-pay of €2.275 million with capital funding at €32.15 million.</p>
          <p eId="para_62"> That €6.65 million will allow them to keep indigenous production levels at a pace that is consistent with previous years. That is where that is being targeted. It will enable the encouragement of more regional productions in the Irish language; continue the training academies, which build on the skill set that is needed; introduce a new funding stream to support documentary series; and a provide a further round of State funding to support Irish companies. That money will allow them to invest in IT and marketing and recruit key roles and talent such as a diversity and inclusion manager, a project manager, a development executive, an audience engagement executive, an IT executive and a HR executive. That is where the money will be targeted.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">Why are the output targets for the number of arts organisations to receive funding in 2021 and 2022 both significantly lower than the actual number of organisations that received funding in 2020 despite Arts Council funding going up each year?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_36" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">The Deputy is looking at arts organisations in receipt of funding.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_38" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">One aspect is what we were aiming for, and we actually went above that. The 2020 out-turn target was 1,146 organisations. The 2021 output target was 840 organisations and the 2022 output target is 895. The Department is currently in the process of collating the 2021 out-turns for performance metrics. All 2021 performance information will be available in the 2021 public service performance report, which is due to be published by the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform at the end of this month. That is where we will gather that information.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_39">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">I thank Deputy Mythen and the Minister. I think Deputy Cannon has a supplementary question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCannon" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Deputy Ciarán Cannon<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">I have one supplementary question. In early December, the Minister announced a most welcome €50 million package of support for the live performance sector. Does she have a breakdown at this point of how that has been expended? What is left in the pot? How does she intend to distribute that to those who are still in a very difficult place?</p>
          <p eId="para_69"> We always made the point, and the Minister always agreed with us, that this is not an industry where we can just turn the lights back on like we can in a factory on a Monday morning and it goes right back into full production. It will take quite a length of time to get back to something resembling normal activity and pre-pandemic times.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_41" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">Of the €50 million that was allocated for a suite of supports for the live entertainment industry, €5 million was allocated for the live performance support scheme, LPSS, strand 2. The Deputy might remember that this was to support pantomimes and seasonal musical theatre, which were brought to a halt due to the Covid-19 restrictions in place in December and January. Of that, grants of €2.6 million have been offered and payments of €1.3 million have been made under the scheme to date.</p>
          <p eId="para_71"> Up to €20 million has been allocated under strand 3 of the LPSS to support events that were due to be staged in December and January and were curtailed, cancelled or rescheduled due to the restrictions with live performances at 50% capacity and the closing time of 8 p.m. Grants of €7.7 million have been offered and payments of €1.1 million have been made under the scheme to date.</p>
          <p eId="para_72"> Applications are being assessed on a rolling basis and grantees are advised of the status of their grants as soon as a decision is made. The payments are being made and issued on a rolling basis once grantees have supplied the Department with the required documentation. There is, therefore, ongoing liaison with my officials.</p>
          <p eId="para_73"> There was €4 million allocated for another round of the music and entertainment business assistance scheme to support small music and entertainment businesses that do not operate out of a rateable premises. Some 642 applicants have received funding of €2.8 million. To date, €2.3 million has been awarded and payments of more than €900,000 have been made since the scheme closed on 27 February.</p>
          <p eId="para_74"> There was €5 million allocated for local authorities under the live performance support scheme to support local artists and performances. A further €5 million was allocated to continue the capital support scheme, for example to help venues that might need ventilation upgrades or other Covid-19 adaptations. There was €1 million for the St. Patrick's festival. Yesterday, the live performance restart grant scheme was announced, which is a new scheme for businesses engaged in staging events in the arts and cultural live performance sector.</p>
          <p eId="para_75"> We will continually assess what money goes out but that money will go where it needs to go, which is to the artists. As I said, that is through constant liaison with officials linking in with artists if further information is needed. It will go where it is meant to go, however, which is to support the artists.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCannon" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Deputy Ciarán Cannon<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">I thank the Minister for the additional scheme announced yesterday. I will make one final comment on it. My understanding is that the vast majority of people who succeeded in securing LPSS support will automatically migrate to this scheme and will not have to make a new application. Is that correct?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_43" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">People will have to apply. The scheme is really to support venues, promoters and producers and help them with the costs of reopening and hiring artists and crew to stage live performances in the coming months. It will trickle down.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCannon" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Deputy Ciarán Cannon<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">That is most welcome. We need to look forensically at how best to support the artists and technicians the Minister mentioned earlier, namely, those who switch on the lights and are not seen. It is important that all the work we do through the LPSS and the live performance restart grant scheme, LPRGS, is focused solely on that.</p>
          <p eId="para_79"> Artists cannot survive without venues. The two have a symbiotic relationship. I would argue that some venues are perhaps more interested in selling alcohol than in staging cultural events and view cultural events as a tool or mechanism to earn money elsewhere. These events are not the <i>raison d'être</i> of many of these places. We need to be careful to ensure, as the Minister has been, that the vast majority of the funds her Department disburses reach those who create and genuinely support the creation of art.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_45" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">To that end, all grantees will have to complete evaluation surveys on the exact purposes that for which the grants were applied.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCannon" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Deputy Ciarán Cannon<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">I thank the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">I want to touch on the live performance restart grant scheme announced yesterday. I am sure it will be very much welcomed by the industry. In relation to the eligibility criteria, the Minister stated that those who already receive the funding under the LPSS or the events sector Covid support scheme, ESCSS, will have to reapply. Will they essentially be automatically entitled to the grant without having to provide any further information?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_48" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">I refer to producers, promoters and venues, including nightclubs with an established track record in producing live arts and cultural performances that are advertised as such. Existing grantees, who are fully compliant with their existing service level agreement and drawing down procedures, would be defined as LPSS pilot, LPSS 2021, LPSS 2, LPSS 3 or ESCSS stream A grantees in full compliance.</p>
          <p eId="para_84"> The existing grantees are deemed to have already demonstrated their track record and there will be no need to demonstrate that again. If an applicant is a new entrant, that is, not an existing grantee, the applicant will have to be in a position to demonstrate either a proven track record of at least two years of delivering ticketed events in the arts and culture sector or VAT exclusive turnover generated in the State of at least €100,000 for 2018 and 2019. The business must also be in the State. There are details provided on how they would demonstrate their loss. That would probably answer Deputy Munster's question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">As they are already in the system, they do not have to give further information. Am I right in saying the full amount allocated to the restart grant scheme is €15 million?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_50" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">If all those pre-existing recipients are automatically entitled to draw down a grant based on having previous grants because, as the Minister stated, they have all their ducks in a row, that would amount to €14.39 million. That would only leave €600,000 for new applicants. I am curious as to why a scheme would be designed to provide grants of upwards of €100,000 that totals over €14 million to companies based solely on the fact that they have already benefited from State funding and leave so little then for new applicants.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_52" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">There are three streams to the scheme, namely, stream A, the existing grantees, which are those LPSS 2021 grantees; stream B, the LPSS ESCSS; and then the new entrants. The payment is up to a maximum of €100,000. It is not unusual to have a cap on the funding but, as I stated to Deputy Cannon, if demand exceeds the allocation, we will look at that. I have often stated that I will go back to the Covid contingency fund, which is where we secured an additional €25 million before Christmas. The idea is not to exclude people but to help as many as possible, up to the maximum of €100,000.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">That is fine. My point is that if all the grantees who applied previously receive funding, it would amount to over €14 million of the €15 million fund, leaving slightly over €600,000 for new applicants. It seems this funding is made available solely on the basis that people had already benefited from it, leaving very little funding for new applicants. That is my query.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_54" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">The Deputy is asking a hypothetical question. We do not know whether all the previous recipients will apply. The scheme is open to new entrants.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">We would imagine they would all apply.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_56" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">I have not ring-fenced money for one section only. In everything I do, the Department is reaching as many people as possible. If the hypothetical scenario the Deputy presented emerges, we will reassess the matter. The idea is to get money out to those who need it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">I am flagging the point that only a tiny proportion of the funding will be available for new applicants if all those who applied previously-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_58" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">-----automatically receive funding. There is no reason to suggest they will not apply again. It would be unusual if they did not apply for this round of funding. I am merely pointing out to the Minister that there is very little left over for new applicants.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_60" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">Within the €15 million allocation, I have not ring-fenced a certain amount for a certain group. I have not allocated a specific amount or provided that the majority of the funding will go to a certain group. It is open to everyone to apply for funding.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">I accept that. I am saying that if all those who were entitled to and previously received funding were to get a payment from this scheme, it would amount to €14.39 million, which would only leave a small pot. That is my point. However, the Minister is saying that all of those who received funding apply again, using up €14 million of the fund, and there are new applicants for the remaining €600,000, she will increase funding.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_62" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">I will assess the matter. To reassure the Deputy, there is no absolute entitlement and the scheme is open to everybody.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_99">The Arts Council budget is €130 million compared with An Foras Teanga's budget of €17.2 million. The amount spent on the main State organisation for the arts is seven times higher than the amount spent on the main State organisation for the Irish language. How does the Minister justify this?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">It goes to the Arts Council funding, which I brought up to €130 million in budget 2021. I maintained it in 2022. As I have stated many times, if one looks at what I am doing with Irish language funding, for example, for TG4, it has exceeded all previous levels and has been very well received.</p>
          <p eId="para_101"> Our arts and culture were devastated through Covid. The ability to perform was taken away from artists. Artists who were on the cusp of breaking through had that snatched from them. Artists who spent all their lives at this and for whom the arts is their only way of making a living found that their living was taken from them. It was essential that the Government sent a signal that we treasure our arts. The way to do that was in all the Covid supports I put in place and in bringing funding for the Arts Council up to €130 million.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">Will the Minister attend the Joint Committee on the Irish Language, the Gaeltacht and the Irish-Speaking Community to answer questions on those Estimates that fall under the committee's remit?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_66" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">I believe that the Minister of State, Deputy Chambers, has already discussed with the committee the Revised Estimates in that regard and has expressed that, as the Minister of State with responsibility for the matter, he is willing to attend the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_67">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">I wish to make a contribution on the audiovisual industry, specifically on the section 481 regional film development uplift programme. Without it, we would not have experienced our success to date and enjoyed the economic contribution that film provides. Every country in the world has a film tax credit and ours is no different from many others. The incentive in implementing the uplift programme was to encourage more production outside the major urban centres of Dublin, Wicklow and Cork. Can we do more to incentivise more regional productions? There are additional costs of up to 8% for regional productions, but this critical element of shooting regionally is not factored into the programme. Perhaps the Minister could speak to the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, about trying to increase regional production and enhancing the regional film development uplift.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_68" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">The Vice Chairman has rightly identified that the section 481 tax relief is a vital part of the financial infrastructure of the audiovisual industry, as is the regional film development uplift. We are seven months out from the budget, so I will include this matter in my negotiations. This is a thriving industry and it can do much more. It helps with many other areas. I will be undertaking some trade missions with a view to developing more production in this country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_69">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">I thank the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCannon" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Deputy Ciarán Cannon<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">It is important we clarify a matter because misinformation is perhaps creeping out into the public domain as to how the LPRGS is going to work. If I am a venue owner in Athlone and I secured funding under the LPSS, the maximum grant under which was, as far as I recall, in the order of €100,000 at the time, will the Minister clarify what I was required to do to make the case for that funding? Was I to stage one or a number of performances? Was I to provide definitive proof that those performances took place and who took part in them? With the implementation of the LPRGS, I fully suspect those who are already part of the branch aid system and who have registered their presence on the Department's system will see this as an opportunity to apply again because the bureaucratic burden on them will be much less, and thankfully so. What will they be required to do this time? If the same venue in Athlone succeeded in securing another €100,000, what would it need to have proven to the Minister it had done to support the creation of art and the people involved in that creation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_71" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">Different schemes were developed at different times throughout the pandemic. This scheme is about supporting people and has been designed to give them restart stability to ensure they can plan ahead. All applicants, existing and new, must be able to demonstrate their VAT exclusive turnovers and a proven track record of at least two years of delivering ticketed events in the arts and culture sector. If an applicant is a new entrant, he or she must be in a position to demonstrate that. Existing grantees are deemed to have already demonstrated their track records, so they will not have to do so again.</p>
          <p eId="para_109"> The LPRGS was just announced yesterday. All grantees will have to complete the evaluation survey to demonstrate that the grants are reaching where they need to go. I am happy to forward the committee more information on comparing the schemes and how that comparison might impact on the LPRGS. What we were doing in the thick of Covid compared with what we are doing now to aid in the recovery process are quite different in design.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCannon" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Deputy Ciarán Cannon<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">I thank the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_73">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">We will move on to programme D, sports and recreational services.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCannon" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Deputy Ciarán Cannon<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">I have a short question. I thank the Minister for State for being so proactive in securing this level of funding. I do not need to tell him the impact such funding has on local communities in terms of the provision of sports facilities is phenomenal. Every cent we invest in local communities on the development of sports facilities is leveraged. I am sure some analysis has been done on this, but it leverages other funding through fundraising locally and work that is done voluntarily. It is extraordinary. Time and again, I have stressed the importance of this investment, so I thank the Minister of State for his support in making such a significant investment this year. His predecessor, Deputy Griffin, also did a great deal of good work in this regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_113"> We have always striven to ensure to the application process is as simple and straightforward as possible while acknowledging these are public funds we are dispensing. Regarding invalidated applications, what mechanisms are in place this year for clubs that did not realise they had made a small documentary error? What options are available to them to regain access to the funding stream?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_75" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">I acknowledge the Deputy's input into, and interest in, sports capital. There will be an appeals process, which I hope will be outlined and published in the next week or so. There will be a three-week window in which applicants can make an appeal. It will capture not only invalid applications but a broader range of unsuccessful applications than was the case previously. We have a €6 million fund ring-fenced for it. This will allow for a fair second or additional chance for applicants that missed out for technical reasons or whatever. This process will be open in the next week or so and there will be an opportunity for clubs to appeal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CiaranCannon" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Deputy Ciarán Cannon<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">I thank the Minister of State.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">Will the Minister of State confirm the total figure spent under the sports capital grant programme in 2021?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_78" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">We will revert to the Deputy shortly. That information is here, but we just have to retrieve it. I will get the specific figure. As the Deputy knows, there would have been an underspend under many of the capital subheads. This situation applied across the Government because, due to Covid, there was not the same level of drawdown. We will get the exact figure for the Deputy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_79">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">Is the money that was allocated in February to be annualised? Will that be the amount every year in future?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_80" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">Does the Deputy mean the €150 million package?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_82" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">That was a negotiated package for the last round. There were record levels of demand amounting to almost €200 million. Each round is assessed on its own merits in terms of the funding requirements. We have had increased sports capital allocations in recent years.</p>
          <p eId="para_122">Whenever we have future rounds, we will be able to assess the demand. It is the single largest grassroots allocation and I am committed to trying to continue that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">It was a substantial allocation. Was it done over a couple of years?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_84" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">Yes, if a club in Louth or anywhere else is awarded €120,000, it might draw that down 18 months later, after it has got the planning permission and gone through the process. It is a provisional grant allocation and clubs are able to draw it down pending the completion of the process. There could be another club in the Deputy's area that has gone through all the stages and it could then draw it down this year. We have grant applications going back to 2018 and even earlier where the clubs have not been able to draw down because they have not been able to fulfil the criteria on the provisional grant allocation. They may not have been able to get the land that should have been acquired, for example. Obviously, the timeline is dependent on the club's application. We are ready to enable drawdown when clubs are ready, and there is a process whereby they are being communicated with regarding how they can fulfil their respective drawdown.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">In the case of a couple of years, the allocation was skipped and rolled over. In one year, €30 million was not paid out, so there was €60 million the following year, to incorporate two years. Is the sports capital grant programme going to be annualised? Will it be open to applicants every year from here on and what sort of sum are we looking at annually?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_86" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">As it is capital, it is a multiannual programme and that has been the nature of it for many years. Even so, there is a commitment in the programme for Government to running regular rounds of the sports capital and equipment programme. We answered parliamentary questions on this issue last week in the House. The timeline and sequence will involve, first, concluding the appeals process that I referred to in response to Deputy Cannon and the €6 million allocation in that regard. We will then conduct a review of the sports capital programme from this round, and take learnings and get input from the Oireachtas and the broader public as to how we can strengthen it and ensure every part of our grassroots sports system can apply and be enabled to fulfil their ambition. We expect that to take about two or three months.</p>
          <p eId="para_127"> After that, we will look at a timeline for a further round. There will be a further round, although I cannot give a definitive answer as to when we will open it. It is still my intention and that of the Minister to match the ambition in our sporting system and to invest in it. We will be able to give further details to the committee as we move through the year about when there will be a further round. As it took ten months to assess the applications for both capital equipment, we cannot commit to an annual round where we can assess and pay out in that period. It is a multiannual programme and has been that way for many years. Nevertheless, we appreciate the demand that is there, the ambition in communities and the scale people want, which is why we delivered the €150 million investment this year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_87">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">I thank the Minister of State. He might keep the committee up to date on whether he has made a decision.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_88" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">Absolutely. I appreciate the importance of the matter to members. The spend on sports capital was almost €24 million in 2021, so that will be the approximate figure for the drawdown for last year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_89">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">How does the Minister of State ensure equality in respect of the distribution of grants among the regions? I have spoken to many clubs in my county, Wexford. We would like to have a fair shot at the supports in the same way as the cities.</p>
          <p eId="para_131"> How much of the allocated funding for sports in 2022 will go towards helping people with a disability to participate in sport?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_90" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">In the most recent round, my predecessor, the then Minister of State, Deputy Griffin, brought in a 50:50 split between <i>per capita</i> and the level of demand, which gave a good regional spread. As can be seen in the Deputy's county, Wexford, and in County Kerry, which I visited in recent days, there is a fair regional spread that reflects not only the population dynamics of the country but also the necessity to invest in rural Ireland and our regions. The feedback on that has been positive and it has provided a fair balance.</p>
          <p eId="para_133"> A number of budget lines support people with disabilities. We are working with Sport Ireland on a new diversity and inclusion policy, which will strengthen the overall policy on people with disabilities when it comes to sport. We will focus on Activities for All and channel a good deal of funding supports through that.</p>
          <p eId="para_134"> As for the governing bodies and the core funding they receive, I can give a breakdown but it is complicated. Under subhead D5, there is significant support through Sport Ireland, with goals for the national governing bodies to support people with disabilities. Furthermore, we increased the Dormant Accounts Fund from €10 million to €12 million this year, which directly supports people with disabilities. I am anxious that, with the increase we have secured, we should focus on inclusion and on ensuring everybody in our community can have greater opportunities in sport, and support the grassroots clubs that want to deliver sport for people with disabilities. I am engaged with some of the sporting organisations, such as the Football Association of Ireland, FAI, and the GAA, regarding how we can deliver better sporting opportunities for people with disabilities.</p>
          <p eId="para_135"> On the sports capital and equipment programme, we can send further detail to the committee, with a breakdown in respect of some of the governing bodies, such as Special Olympics Ireland and Irish Wheelchair Association Sport. Moreover, in our new sports action plan, there is a clear focus on people with disabilities. I am conscious we all engage with people in our local areas who have disabilities. I often say that if there are three people in the back of a car, there tends not to be the same level of opportunity for the one who may have a disability, whereas the other two siblings will be able to play any of ten sports on a Saturday morning. In the context of the Football for All events and the significant potential and inclusive nature of events under Activities for All, a clear focus of mine, through additional funding and budget lines we have received this year, will be on people with disabilities and on giving them greater opportunities in sport.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_91">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">In regard to attracting major sporting events to the country, will the Minister of State provide the committee with a breakdown of what is being discussed within the Department and which bodies are involved?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_92" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">One of the major events we are discussing at the moment is Euro 2028. As a Department, we are positively disposed to the idea. We have to conclude the cost-benefit analysis and the ratio that applies in that regard but there is considerable potential from a North-South, east-west perspective. Work is ongoing and we will have to make a final decision before 23 March in respect of submitting an expression of interest.</p>
          <p eId="para_138"> The programme for Government is committed to forming a major events policy. We will soon carry out a consultation in that regard, trying to engage with the public but also with governing bodies as to what opportunities exist to bring major sporting events to Ireland. The Ryder Cup is coming in 2027 and there is significant engagement with the Department on that. From a tourism perspective, too, the Minister is trying to maximise the benefit for Ireland and the region. The Northwestern versus Nebraska game will be held in August of this year. That has substantial tourism potential and will bring many visitors from the US, so it is great to see that type of event back up and running.</p>
          <p eId="para_139">Regarding women's golf, the Irish Open will return in the autumn this year, which is extremely positive and something we are keen to support. It will take place in September 2022 in Dromoland Castle. Those are some of the specific events we are focused on. Ireland has great potential to do more and in the coming years we want to attract major events that provide a return for the country. Return on investment is a key metric. We need to ensure what we invest leverages a return for the economy and broader society.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_93">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_140">Regarding how the national development plan links to our applying to host major sporting events, is there linkage between the various Departments, local authorities and State bodies so that we have a coherent approach in addressing this? It needs a whole-of-government approach and not just be dealt with by the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media. I know the Minister of State is doing fantastic work in developing that policy so that we have something to refer back to when we seek to host these sporting events in the future.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JackChambers" eId="spk_94" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Jack Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">Obviously, having a major events policy formalises that across Government. The national development plan captures, for example, investment in the national sports campus and the potential it offers for hosting major events. For example, the velodrome could host events across multiple disciplines because it is a multi-use facility. Beyond the periphery of the velodrome, which obviously enables cycling, there are big opportunities for badminton and a range of indoor sports.</p>
          <p eId="para_142"> I forgot to mention that the Cricket World Cup 2030 is coming to Ireland and it will obviously present major opportunities. There are good relationships between the major events unit, local authorities and other pillars of government. Unfortunately, we did not get Euro 2020 to come here, but good local structures were established which enabled that collaboration. Obviously, the Department of Justice and the Garda play a key role as do fans and spectators. The major events policy will formalise that. There are good working structures and there has been no impediment, barrier or delay when it comes to enabling the hosting of major events.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_95">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">The final item is programme E, broadcasting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_96">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">Does the Department carry out reviews of An Post collecting the television licence fee? How is the amount given to it decided? I ask the Minister to provide a breakdown of the funding it receives.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_97" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">We engage with An Post all the time. I might be able to come back to the Deputy with the breakdown of funding afterwards, if that is okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_98">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">The Minister said the Department carries out reviews. I ask her to expand on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_99" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">We engage with it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_100">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_148">Yes. Does the Department carry out reviews of the effectiveness of An Post collecting the licence fee?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_101" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">There is an annual service level agreement, SLA, with An Post.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">The Minister will be aware of the level of non-payment and non-collection of fees.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_103" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">Yes, of course. We set up the Future of Media Commission because there is an issue with the funding.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">Did that come up in any of the SLAs or any of the reviews carried out?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_105" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">It comes up all the time. It has been well identified as an issue, not just in the annual SLAs, but more widely. That is why the Future of Media Commission was set up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">Does the Minister have a breakdown of the funding it receives with her?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_107" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">I believe it was €9.8 million in 2021.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_108">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">How much is it for this year?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_109" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">We do not have the figure for 2022. The figure I gave is for 2021.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_110">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">Does the Minister have anything for previous years?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_111" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">In 2020 it was €10 million, in 2019 it was €11.3 million and in 2018 it was €12 million. We can send this to the Deputy. I have the details all the way back to 2010 here. Would the Deputy like me to forward those details to her?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_112">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">Yes, please. It has clearly reduced if it was €9.8 million in 2021.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_113" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">In 2010 it was at €10.9 million. It seems to fluctuate between €11 million and €12 million. In 2020 and 2021 it was between €9.8 million and €10 million. It depends on the licence fee sales.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ImeldaMunster" eId="spk_114">
          <from>Deputy Imelda Munster<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">It depends on the licence fee sales. I would appreciate getting a copy of that breakdown.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_115" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_116">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">I ask about the situation with intellectual property and broadcasting. We provide considerable funding to indigenous companies. For instance, for an animation film which was recently made the intellectual property rights ended up with Netflix which benefited from all the money, whereas the indigenous companies would reinvest that and create jobs in our country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_117" as="#Minister_for_Tourism,_Culture,_Arts,_Gaeltacht,_Sport_and_Media">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">The intellectual property is an issue of copyright which would not lie with my Department. It may be something to raise with the Tánaiste and the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_118">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">I thank the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_119">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Chambers, and the Minister, Deputy Catherine Martin, and their officials. I wish them the very best for the future.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Message to Dáil<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#AlanDillon" eId="spk_120">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2022-03-09T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168"><b>
						</b>In accordance with Standing Order 101, the following message will be sent to the Dáil:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_169">The Select Committee on Tourism, Culture, Arts, Sport and Media has completed its consideration of the following Revised Estimates for public services for the year ending 31 December 2022: Vote 33 - Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5"> The select committee adjourned at 2.49 p.m. <i>sine die</i>.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
