<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_health_and_children/2010-06-15/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_health_and_children/2010-06-15/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2010-06-15" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/30/joint_committee_on_health_and_children"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_health_and_children/2010-06-15/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_health_and_children/2010-06-15/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2010-06-15" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_health_and_children/2010-06-15/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_health_and_children/2010-06-15/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None" eId="#vol_None" showAs="Vol. None"/>
          <oir:numberReference href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None/no/None" eId="#no_None" showAs="No. None"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BernardAllen" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Bernard-Allen.D.1981-06-30" showAs="Bernard Allen"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BeverleyCooperFlynn" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Beverley-Flynn.D.1997-06-26" showAs="Beverley Flynn"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BobbyAylward" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Bobby-Aylward.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Bobby Aylward"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CharlieOConnorFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Charlie-O'Connor.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Charlie O'Connor"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DanNeville" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Dan-Neville.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Dan Neville"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DavidStanton" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/David-Stanton.D.1997-06-26" showAs="David Stanton"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DrJamesReilly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/James-Reilly.D.2007-06-14" showAs="James Reilly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="KathleenLynch" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Kathleen-Lynch.D.1994-11-10" showAs="Kathleen Lynch"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaryMWhite" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mary-M-White.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Mary M. White"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NiallBlaneyIND" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Niall-Blaney.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Niall Blaney"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulConnaughton" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Connaughton.S.1977-10-27" showAs="Paul Connaughton"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PhilPrendergast" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Phil-Prendergast.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Phil Prendergast"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RoryOHanlon" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Rory-O'Hanlon.D.1977-07-05" showAs="Rory O'Hanlon"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanOFearghaillFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Ó-Fearghaíl.S.2000-06-09" showAs="Seán Ó Fearghaíl"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanSherlock" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Sherlock.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Sean Sherlock"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chair" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chair" showAs="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chairman" showAs="Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>COMHCHOISTE UM SHLÁINTE AGUS LEANAÍ</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>JOINT COMMITTEE ON HEALTH AND CHILDREN</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2010-06-15">Dé Máirt, 15 Meitheamh 2010</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2010-06-15">Tuesday, 15 June 2010</docDate>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 3.30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#BernardAllen">Deputy Bernard Allen,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#PhilPrendergast">Senator Phil Prendergast,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#BobbyAylward">Deputy Bobby Aylward,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#MaryMWhite">Senator Mary M. White.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#NiallBlaneyIND">Deputy Niall Blaney,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulConnaughton">Deputy Paul Connaughton,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#BeverleyCooperFlynn">Deputy Beverley Flynn,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#KathleenLynch">Deputy Kathleen Lynch,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#DanNeville">Deputy Dan Neville,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#CharlieOConnorFF">Deputy Charlie O’Connor,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#RoryOHanlon">Deputy Rory O’Hanlon,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#DrJamesReilly">Deputy James Reilly,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">In attendance: Deputies Seán Sherlock and David Stanton, and Senators Michael McCarthy and Brendan Ryan.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#SeanOFearghaillFF">DEPUTY SEÁN Ó FEARGHAÍL IN THE CHAIR.</person>
          </summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">The joint committee met in private session until 3.48 p.m.</summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Health Issues for Carers: Discussion with Carers Association</heading>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_13">We are in public session for our first session with the Carers Association.  I welcome Mr. Frank Goodwin, Mr. Enda Egan, Ms Clare Duffy and Mr. Frank Lahiffe.</p>
          <p eId="para_14">Before we begin I advise you that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, you are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence you are to give this committee. If you are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence in relation to a particular matter and you continue to so do, you are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of your evidence. You are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and you are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, you should not criticise nor make charges against any person(s) or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_15">We shall now hear the presentation followed by a question and answer session with Members.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Mr. Enda Egan</from>
          <p eId="para_16">I thank the committee for having us today during national carers' week.  This is a great opportunity for us to come here on behalf of family carers to voice the main issues that affect carers regarding health issues.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">The members have the document and I shall go very quickly through the first section or introduction.  Most members will be very much aware of the role of family carers and the kinds of statistics that sit behind it so I shall run though this briefly.  There are about 160,000 family carers in Ireland, according to the last census.  As everybody will know, family carers provide very valuable work looking after loved ones in their own homes.  By and large, a carer does not make a choice to provide care.  An actual incident happens to a loved one, to a husband, wife, child with special needs or a person who gets a terminal illness.  Somebody in the family has to make a decision to stay at home and provide that care.  Obviously, this saves the State huge sums of money.</p>
          <p eId="para_18">There are about 40,000 full-time carers in Ireland, people who are doing this job around the clock, 24 hours a day, seven days a week.  They are not in a position to leave unless somebody else comes in to fill in for them because of the level of care required by the person who is being cared for.  According to the 2006 census there are more than 90,000 people who provide care and work in paid employment.  Some 14,000 of those work full-time as well as providing more than 43 hours of care per week.  That is an horrendous load to have on one person.  Statistics wise, there are just over 5,000 young carers in Ireland but I would not know whether these are aged between 15 and 19 years.  The statistics from the 2006 census did not allow us to pick up how many carers there are below the age of 15.  The new census to take place in 2011 will be able to pick that up, which is a strong development.</p>
          <p eId="para_19">It is fair to say that in recent years there have been a number of developments within the social welfare framework that support carers.  The development of the half-rate allowance is obviously very significant and the development of the respite grant and the carer's benefit certainly support many people and are very welcome.  It is of vital importance they are all protected within the forthcoming budget.  We estimate that carers in Ireland save the State approximately €2 billion.  That is by comparison to the lowest point on the home help pay scale.  When one works out the number of hours carers provide and multiply that figure by the lowest point on the home help pay scale, which is just over €14, one comes to a figure of about €2.8 billion.  That is not comparing it to the cost of institutional care which would be very much higher.  That figure of €2.8 billion is a very defensible one.</p>
          <p eId="para_20">I shall move quickly into the priorities for the Carers Association and family carers in terms of health services for this year.  There are about ten of these and I shall try to move through them as quickly as I can.  Respite is probably the most important practical solution intervention that carers require in their own homes to allow them a break.  There are different types of respite.  The traditional model is where the person being cared for goes into institutional respite, to a local day-care unit or nursing home for a period, perhaps a day or two or three weeks.  That is very important.  Another important aspect which carers tend to look for more often is home respite where the person being cared for stays at home and somebody comes in to relieve the carer.  All research carried out in recent years indicates that home respite is where the trend is heading.  Home care packages which were introduced a number of years ago currently run to an investment of approximately €130 million per year by the HSE.  This has been used very wisely by the HSE in terms of providing respite to carers.  The home care package can be used to buy in help to the home which is specifically built around giving the carer a break.  It is also used to provide help to the carer in their caring duties.  We find that is working well where it can be obtained.  There appears to be some anecdotal evidence in certain parts of the country that home care packages are not always put back in place after a person goes into long-term care or perhaps passes away.  It is difficult to be absolutely certain of that but the evidence we have, as a provider of home care packages, would be that in certain parts of the country those packages are not replaced at present.</p>
          <p eId="para_21">Home help is of vital importance to the family, the carer and the person being cared for.  Evidence at present suggests that home help is being reduced and is difficult to get in certain parts of the country, especially in the south.  In Cork, in particular, at the moment it appears it is almost impossible to access the home help service.  On a daily basis we have telephone calls from carers reporting that the number of hours of home help they have been in receipt of are being reduced, very often to a point where the service is ineffective.  We had a situation very recently where somebody who was receiving an hour of home help per week was reduced to 45 minutes.  To be honest, it is very difficult to see how effective 45 minutes of help in a week is to anybody.  This would be a very valuable service if it was held at the appropriate levels one would expect.</p>
          <p eId="para_22">Another worrying trend we see within the home help service is that in certain parts of the country it appears that carers who are in receipt of the carer's allowance are being deterred from accessing home help service and that at local level the HSE is saying that because the person is getting a payment from the State for the work they are doing therefore they should not get the home help service.  The State is very clear that the carer's allowance is not a payment for the work being done but is an income supplement.  The Department and this committee could take on that issue and look into it.  It is a worrying trend and, again, is one of those things which are happening beneath the surface.  It is not really on the radar but the evidence comes back to us that unofficially it is being used in certain parts of the country to deter people from getting the home help service.  It would be very unfortunate if that were the case.  It goes right against policy in this regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_23">Our association, along with the Royal College of Psychiatry and Care Alliance Ireland have carried out a number of studies looking at the health and well-being of the family carer.  There is a lot of evidence to show that carers frequently ignore their own health needs in favour of those being cared for.  Carers tend to be people who give all the time and put themselves last.  This has an adverse effect on their health, their psychological and mental health as well as their physical health.  There is a lot of evidence to suggest that carers' health suffers significantly as a result of providing care.  In this regard it is essential that medical cards are given to family carers on a non-means tested basis.  In other words, if people become full-time carers they should automatically get a medical card which would allow them at least one full medical check in the year.  This is used in other countries where governments state very clearly they value carers and the work they do and recognise the carer's health can be damaged by providing care.  They put this intervention in place which seems to work well.  It would not cost a lot of money and would give a significant signal that the Government is very much in favour of the work carers are doing and recognises what it is they do.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">One of the outcomes in last year's budget was that the drugs payment scheme went from €100 to €120.  In families where care takes place we find that is a significant issue and it needs to be looked at and reviewed.  Obviously, it has a greater impact on families where there are health issues than on those without. Carers are in that predicament.</p>
          <p eId="para_25">Needs assessment is one of the cornerstones that would allow the health services to deal with the issue of caring, carers' health and service provision for family carers.  This is something we do not have in Ireland.  It does take place in UK, which has passed an Act that allows each carer to obtain a needs assessment by right.  It is similar to the needs assessment here for people with disabilities, under which one is entitled to the needs assessment but not automatically to the services.  However, it is a step in the right direction.  We felt it would form an integral part of the carer's strategy, but unfortunately that has not happened.  We will talk about that in a few moments.</p>
          <p eId="para_26">We recently had a conference which dealt with the issue of young carers.  As I said earlier, according to the statistics there are just over 5,000 young carers in Ireland, but we estimate the true figure is a multiple of that.  Children as young as five are involved in providing family care at home, often to a grandparent or a sibling.  It often takes place in situations in which the relationship between parents has broken down; the child lives with one parent or the other, and that parent becomes ill.  There is also much support for parents with alcohol or drug addiction.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">Under Towards 2016 the Government decided to do some research into this area; the work was given to NUI Galway, which has recently published a study on young carers on Ireland.  It is vital that the Government, particularly the Department of Health and Children, deals with this issue.  We call on the Government to establish a specific budget for the area of young carers.  Perhaps through a pilot project, we must consider how to identify young carers.  One of the big issues in the UK and other countries in which carers are dealt with specifically is the identification of young carers.  We will approach the Minister of State with responsibility for children in this regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">To return to the core area of family carers, the fair deal scheme has come more and more to the fore over the last number of months.  There appears to be much confusion among carers about the rules and regulations governing the scheme.  There is a general lack of awareness among older people and certainly among family carers about how the scheme actually operates.  One of the advantages of the old scheme was that one could access what was known as short-term subvention for respite care, which came to about €330 per week.  This is now gone — it no longer exists under the current scheme.  It could still be considered within local HSE budgets but, as everybody is aware, at the moment it is quite difficult to access anything that is not specific.  There is also quite a long waiting period for the processing of applications under the fair deal scheme.  While that is going on, carers are still caring at home.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">As most people here are aware, the Government committed to the formulation of a national carers' strategy in the Towards 2016 agreement.  Quite a lot of work was done on that strategy by an interdepartmental group headed up by the Department of Social Protection.  Unfortunately, in the spring of last year, the Government decided not to publish the strategy.  Since then, despite the amount of work that has gone into it, it has sat on the shelf.  Our position on this is that there is no particular policy pertaining to carers that sets out a roadmap and considers specifically how carers will be served and valued over the next number of years.  This is despite the fact that carers are probably the biggest national resource the country has.  It is a shame.</p>
          <p eId="para_30">We will call on the committee to give us support in calling for the Government to publish the strategy and to state clearly what it would intend to do if it did have the resources.  It should at least put the strategy out there so people can see it is committed to it.  At a later stage, when the economic indicators improve, we can start to work on implementing the strategy.  Since the shelving of the national carers' strategy, the Government has introduced the national drugs strategy and gone ahead with the national positive ageing strategy, which signals that these issues are more important than that of family care.</p>
          <p eId="para_31">As everybody is aware, Ireland has an ageing population; therefore, in the future, there will be more pressure on family carers than ever before.  HSE and Government policy is that people should be cared for in their own homes for as long as possible.  Professor Drumm has consistently stated that community care is the way forward.  Everybody is aware of the various rationalisation programmes taking place in hospitals, with patients being admitted to hospitals much closer to the point of surgery and being discharged much sooner afterwards.  The period spent in hospital is much reduced, as is the period of convalescence, and thus families must pick up the slack.</p>
          <p eId="para_32">The fair deal scheme is probably a fairer scheme than the one that was there previously, and it is a sign of progress.  Having said that, however, it only considers high-level care; people who require medium and low-level care unfortunately cannot get access under the fair deal programme.  What will happen to those people?  Again, they are pushed back on the family.</p>
          <p eId="para_33">The 160,000 carers — we expect this number to be larger in the next census because the question is being changed — are saving the State, conservatively, about €2.8 million per year.  There will be more pressure on them than ever before as the State pushes care back on the family as much as it can.  Families will need to provide care without any extra resources because services are being reduced, and, at the same time, we do not have a strategy.  In view of all this, the future does not look very bright for carers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_34">I thank Mr. Egan for that broad overview of the issues affecting carers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PhilPrendergast" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Senator Phil Prendergast</from>
          <p eId="para_35">I thank Mr. Egan for his presentation.</p>
          <p eId="para_36">Mr. Egan stated that the figure of 5,500 young carers was an underestimate.  Is there any means of setting up links between GPs and public health nurses in order to increase awareness?  Is there any way in which information can be gathered about the number of carers and the role they play?</p>
          <p eId="para_37">The contribution of family carers to the Irish economy was mentioned.  In terms of the interpretation of the reduction in hours that a carer might need, I would have thought, as a nurse, that the needs of the patient would increase rather than decreasing.  What would be the basis for such a decision?</p>
          <p eId="para_38">I heard of a case study of a couple in their fifties in which the husband was suffering from multiple sclerosis.  The man was receiving disability allowance while the wife relied on the carer's allowance; their son, who was unemployed because he was in the construction industry, moved home.  Their household had already suffered due to the withdrawal of the Christmas bonus.  The man was on 11 different prescriptions which needed to be filled every month, costing €127 per week.  Thus, their weekly income was reduced by €26.37, or 4.1%, and their income was reduced overall by 5.7% over the year, equating to €1,900.  These factors appear to have a disproportionate effect on people whose needs assessments were corroborated by their GPs, public health nurses and, probably, public representatives.  We are supposed to provide primary care services.</p>
          <p eId="para_39">Can an estimate be made of the average number of prescriptions written for people in care?  Again, this represents a disproportionate charge on an identified group of people who are already in need.</p>
          <p eId="para_40">Should the HSE provide workshops for carers and carers' associations to give further clarity on the fair deal and how needs are assessed?  Yesterday I dealt with a case involving a lady who had been refused a carer's allowance for her husband because he was deemed as not sufficiently disabled even though he clearly had significant needs.  The house in which they lived was not even amenable to a disabled person's grant because the stairwell was too narrow for a stair lift.  I know this is not unusual because I conduct my clinics by visiting houses rather than sitting somewhere and expecting people to come to me.  What are the main priorities for carers?  I thank the delegates for their presentation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DrJamesReilly" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Deputy James Reilly</from>
          <p eId="para_41">I apologise for being late but I had business in the House.  It is like Jack Charlton advised, keep them under pressure.  I welcome the delegates.</p>
          <p eId="para_42">I am concerned that the fair deal scheme is leading to a lack of respite care.  Many of the patients who are currently catered for in long-term public beds are being transferred under the scheme into private nursing homes, thus consuming the capped funds available for nursing home care with no benefit to patients because the public facilities are being closed.  Does the Carers Association have an opinion of this issue?</p>
          <p eId="para_43">I understand a number of home care provider services are operated on a semi-commercial voluntary basis.  They are not only paid a quantum by the HSE but also levy a charge on their clients.  I do not refer to family members who give care but to agencies.  This paints a false picture of the cost of care for individuals.  While a private provider might charge €18, the HSE pays €15.  Are the delegates aware of the extent of this practice and what is their view of it?  Will they further comment on home care packages.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CharlieOConnorFF" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Deputy Charlie O’Connor</from>
          <p eId="para_44">I would like to associate myself with the warm welcome extended to our friends.  I do not want to single out Mr. Lahiffe in case I get him into trouble but it is good to see him nevertheless.  I acknowledge my relationship with the Carers Association, particularly at local level.  I am in awe of the great work it carries out in my local office, which is in Clondalkin rather than Tallaght, funnily enough.  I pay warm tribute to its work and the way its members keep in touch with me.</p>
          <p eId="para_45">It is important that we hear from the Carers Association and understand the pressure on Government sources.  It needs to battle with everyone else but it deserves our particular support.  All of us have had experience of dealing with the association.  My sister cared for my late father, who died 14 years ago.  It is important that we bring our own experiences to our politics.  At the end of the day, the work of the association keeps people out of hospitals and nursing homes.</p>
          <p eId="para_46">I refer to Tallaght.  I conduct nine clinics every week but I also follow Senator Prendergast's example by calling to people's houses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PhilPrendergast" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Senator Phil Prendergast</from>
          <p eId="para_47">How does the Deputy find the time?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CharlieOConnorFF" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Charlie O’Connor</from>
          <p eId="para_48">That is what we do.  Speakers referred to young carers.  Tallaght Community Council honours young carers through its annual Tallaght person of the year award, which was founded in 1984 to recognise unsung heroes under various categories.  Young children are doing tremendous work for their parents or handicapped siblings.  The award is well-known in Tallaght and I hope other communities around the country follow its example.  Tallaght is always happy to show the way to the rest of the country.  The award gives positive reinforcement to young people who do this work.  I know many younger carers who are delighted to do what they do.</p>
          <p eId="para_49">Approximately 173 days remain to the next budget.  When the Minister for Social Protection visited my constituency a couple of weeks ago, a group of people were assembled to tell him what they believed should be done in regard to social welfare assistance.  The Carers Association must compete with the other groups which will make arguments to us over the coming weeks.  I do not patronise when I say the association has strong support at an all-party level.  I wish it well in its work.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulConnaughton" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Deputy Paul Connaughton</from>
          <p eId="para_50">The delegation is very welcome.  Nobody would deny that the Carers Association does outstanding work but it is in competition with others in the caring area.  I ask Mr. Egan to set out his top two or three priorities.  I appreciate that everything is a priority for the person who is not getting the service to which he or she is entitled but, in the overall context, what should be our main areas of concern irrespective of the pressures created by the budget?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White</from>
          <p eId="para_51">I welcome the delegation, including in particular Mr. Lahiffe.  I ask for further comment on the issue of child carers of parents with alcohol problems.  Further to Deputy Connaughton's question, I ask for a succinct outline of the priorities for child carers and what is happening in this regard.  I imagine that 95% of people in Ireland do not know about the existence of child carers.  Precisely how many child carers does the association think there are?</p>
          <p eId="para_52">I inaugurated an all-Ireland inspirational life award, which is for older people, and it is my pleasure to let everyone know that Mrs. Carmel Devaney, chairperson of the Athlone Carers Association, won the award, which was sponsored by Vodafone, <i>The Irish Times</i> and BT.  She won the award for her efforts to support carers in her community.  It was my pleasure for Mrs. Devaney to be honoured in such a way.  The carers issue does not get the attention it needs.  I thank the delegation for its presentation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiallBlaneyIND" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Deputy Niall Blaney</from>
          <p eId="para_53">Like other members I welcome the deputation from the Carers Association of Ireland.  It does not seem that long ago since we last saw them but it is very good to see them.  The fact remains that it is a very important representative organisation of a group that does much for society and Ireland.  Nothing can take away from that point.</p>
          <p eId="para_54">The group's issues are always well put, precise and not too laboured.  I apologise for not being here for the beginning of the presentation but the group made a number of points.  We will take them on board and speak to the relevant Minister or Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children to get a response.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy David Stanton</from>
          <p eId="para_55">I apologise for being late as I was delayed in the Chamber.  Thank you, Chairman for the opportunity to ask a question.  We have been on the young carers issue for a long time and the report was published earlier this year.  Is there anything that could be done straight away for young carers to assist in their work?  Should we take any action with regard to school and education?  In Australia and other countries there are websites and so on dedicated to support.  Is anything happening to support these people?</p>
          <p eId="para_56">The delegation spoke about the finances involved with regard to €22 per hour for care.  The acute hospital care figure is €5,000 per hour.  Will the delegation comment on direct payments, which have been mentioned, and how much work has been done on that?  Individualised funding means people can purchase their own services.  It is something that has been considered in Canada and the United States, and we have examined the matter of money following the client or patient.  Is it correct to state that the money available, for example, for hospital work and care is not linked to money available for nursing or home care?  There could be a way to link the funding if it was decided that somebody would benefit more from staying at home; for a fraction of the cost of nursing home or hospital care such people could be looked after at home.</p>
          <p eId="para_57">Does the delegation agree that for a person with a disability, an elderly person or somebody needing care, it is much better to be in a home environment anyway rather than in a nursing home or hospital setting?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_58">We have had a comprehensive range of questions but unfortunately we are under some pressure for time because of today's events.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_59">I apologise for not being here to listen to the presentation.  We got held up.  We are busy in the Chamber today with everything that is going on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_60">I ask the delegates to be fairly concise in dealing with questions.  If there are areas we cannot cover perhaps they could correspond with the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Mr. Enda Egan</from>
          <p eId="para_61">There are many questions to be answered so I will try to touch on all of them and come back to others.  I might pass over to some of my colleagues on certain issues.</p>
          <p eId="para_62">Almost everybody mentioned young carers.  There is no doubt that Senator White is right and this is an issue which tends to be overlooked.  Carers in general tends to stay below the radar and young carers, for many, is an issue that does not exist.  People may not have heard of the term and when they hear it they probably would not understand what it means.  It is real.  Kids may be in a family where there is a care issue and because of a range of circumstances they may end up taking on some of the caring duties, which has a significant impact on their physical and psychological development.  There can be a major impact on education and ability to attend and engage in the education system.  We all know the consequences arising from such a lack of engagement.</p>
          <p eId="para_63">The figures are more than 5,000, although it is difficult to put an exact figure on the issue.  One could probably multiply it by two or three from our comparisons with other countries.  The work carried out in Galway proves that the problem exists, although those involved in the work found it very difficult to engage with young carers.  They found it difficult to identify such carers for a range of reasons.  In many cases families do not want people to know the circumstances where a child is providing care, for privacy reasons.  They may be afraid that if the fact is exposed the young child may be taken away by social services.  This feeds into the young carer issue being kept off the radar.</p>
          <p eId="para_64">Deputy Stanton asked what can be done and there are some simple actions that can be taken.  There is no information for young carers so a website that would cost very little would be a good starting place.  It should not just be an information website and should allow young carers to interact with each other and develop support groups across the Internet for young carers.  Information packs can be pulled together fairly quickly specifically for young carers, outlining services and supports.</p>
          <p eId="para_65">A step must be taken before that to develop protocols and consider pilot projects to produce systems of engagement with young carers.  Generally that starts through the education system and getting teachers involved.  All the other organisations and agencies dealing with children right across the country should also be included.  A multidisciplinary approach is required.</p>
          <p eId="para_66">There is nothing specifically for young carers here other than what might be there through existing services.  Many health service people going into homes might not identify young carers or be aware of them.  We are at the greenfield site stage for this issue.  In our recent conference Ireland was measured to indicate that this was an emerging issue.  However, the issue probably has not even begun to emerge here.</p>
          <p eId="para_67">There are many good points around this.  We have not done anything wrong, so we do not need to fix anything.  We must move on the issue fairly quickly and we hope the Minister of State with responsibility for children, Deputy Barry Andrews, can meet us fairly soon to see how we can put the pieces of the jigsaw on the table before fitting them together.  We must consider ways to identify young carers, contact them and engage with them in a way that does not frighten them or their families.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Ms Clare Duffy</from>
          <p eId="para_68">The 2006 census excluded young carers under 15 years from being enumerated and I hope the 2011 census will count the number of carers under 15.  That will give us a start.  The figure of just under 5,500 young carers aged between 15 and 19 is a significant under-estimation because young people are not identifying themselves as carers.</p>
          <p eId="para_69">One of the speakers at the national conference was Professor Saul Becker from the University of Nottingham, who is the international guru of young carers.  He looked at the proportion of young carers in other countries where they are counted and he argued that applying the same formula to Ireland would indicate a number in the region of approximately 28,000 young carers aged under 18, with approximately 54,000 young carers under 25.  At the moment we really do not know how many young carers there are, but I hope from census 2011 onwards we will.</p>
          <p eId="para_70">One of the biggest findings of the study commissioned by the Office of the Minister of State with responsibility for children was that not all young carers are vulnerable.  There is a continuum of care, with the experience of those at one end of the continuum being quite positive, if they are supported.  However, at the other end there are carers who are extremely vulnerable, including young people caring for parents with addiction problems or similar.  To return to the question of priorities for young carers, whatever initiatives or pilot projects we instigate, we must focus on the young carers who are at that end of the continuum.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Mr. Enda Egan</from>
          <p eId="para_71">There were many comments about practical services within the home.  Senator Prendergast asked about the home help service and how it is decided that fewer hours are required.  The answer is that we are not sure, but we are half-certain that it is being driven by reductions in budgets and so on.  That is what appears to be the case.  It is quite unfortunate and hard to believe that although Government policy is to care for people as long as they can in their own homes, in practice we are moving away from this.  One of our concerns — Senator Prendergast mentioned this, and I am aware it is not specifically within the remit of this committee — is that many applications made for carer's allowance are being turned down for health reasons.  Applicants are satisfying the income disregard in the means test, but it appears anecdotally that there is an increase in the number of applications being refused on the basis that the person concerned does not require full-time care and attention.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulConnaughton" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Deputy Paul Connaughton</from>
          <p eId="para_72">Not all the boxes are being ticked.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Mr. Enda Egan</from>
          <p eId="para_73">It is obviously the softer issue for the person making the decision.  It is semi-subjective, I presume.  It is something we have come across.  We have heard of a number of cases in which there is no doubt care is required 24 hours a day, seven days a week, yet the family is not receiving carer's allowance on the basis that the person does not require 24-hour care.  That is a worrying trend that is starting to develop.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PhilPrendergast" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Senator Phil Prendergast</from>
          <p eId="para_74">Is this is an emerging trend?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Mr. Enda Egan</from>
          <p eId="para_75">It is an emerging trend.  There is no doubt about that.</p>
          <p eId="para_76">Deputy Reilly is not with us at the moment, but he asked about long-stay patients being moved into nursing homes.  This does appear to have been happening in recent months.  It is eating into the budget for the fair deal scheme, which is capped, and at some stage that will become a problem.  It certainly appears that long-stay beds are being freed by putting nursing home costs against the budget for the fair deal scheme, the result of which will be that other people who want to gain access to the fair deal scheme will not be able to, and their families will have to cover the cost of their care.  Again, this is evidence of the responsibility being pushed back on to families.</p>
          <p eId="para_77">The issue of a levy on services was raised.  My knowledge of this is that the HSE does not fully fund all services provided by the voluntary sector, and therefore the voluntary sector seeks contributions from families who are availing of services.  This may still be the practice in certain HSE areas for the home help service.  It appears at the moment that the HSE is working on some policy in this area.  The result may well be that organisations such as ours may be deterred from asking for contributions.  It looks as though this might happen suddenly and very shortly.  If it does, the consequence will be a reduction in services.  It appears to be happening where services are not fully funded at local level, so it is being subsidised by families.  It is highly likely at this stage that we will be prevented from continuing with this practice.  I am not sure whether that was what Deputy Reilly was referring to, but I presume it is.</p>
          <p eId="para_78">The HSE is saying that this is similar to the nursing home charges that were in existence a couple of years ago, and it looks as though it may be unconstitutional.  However, the result if this goes ahead is that there will be fewer services.  Common sense should prevail.  In many cases families are delighted to give a small contribution towards the service and would prefer for that to continue.  For the sake of common sense it would be a pity if a reduction in service took place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_79">Are there any other questions Mr. Egan can deal with briefly before we conclude?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Mr. Enda Egan</from>
          <p eId="para_80">A question that came up a couple of times was that of priorities for the budget.  Our statement on this is quite straightforward.  Carers should be protected from all cuts, simply because of the vast sums of money they are saving the State, and because we are being dumped upon, so to speak, in terms of cutbacks, particularly across the health service provision.  It is absolutely vital that the half-rate carer's allowance remains in place.  There is no doubt about that.  If that were to be removed, there would be a reduction of about one third in the incomes of some families.  The respite grant is also of major value to families and we would not like to see that being taken away.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_81">Is there a set amount of funding per annum for carers in the HSE, or is it flexible?  Has the funding for the fair deal scheme had some effect on that, or did I take Mr. Egan up wrongly?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Mr. Enda Egan</from>
          <p eId="para_82">I am sorry; I missed that question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_83">Is there a set amount of capital funding for carers per year, or is it flexible?  Has the money put aside for the fair deal scheme had an effect on this?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Mr. Enda Egan</from>
          <p eId="para_84">There is no particular set funding for carers as such, although there is set funding of about €130 million for home care packages, from which carers benefit across a number of services, including practical help with caring in the home and respite care.  Beyond that, however, there is no specific fund for family carers within the HSE.  Obviously the fair deal scheme is important to families when they feel that nursing home care is the only option left.  Our concern, as mentioned by Deputy Reilly, is that it appears the fair deal budget is being used to move patients from long-stay beds in public hospitals into private nursing homes.  Because of this, the budget for the fair deal scheme will run out more quickly than had been anticipated, which means that people who want to access the scheme will not be able to, and responsibility for their care will fall back on their families.  This will be the knock-on effect.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_85">I thank Mr. Egan for responding to those queries.  If there are other matters we can deal with them by way of correspondence.  I thank the delegates for their presentation.  There are two messages we take from them: they want to see some action on the carers' strategy and they want to protect existing supports in the forthcoming budget.  We are happy to reflect those sentiments on their behalf.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Mr. Enda Egan</from>
          <p eId="para_86">Absolutely.  The support of the committee would be helpful with regard to young carers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_87">We will certainly raise that matter with the Minister.  We will now suspend for about 30 seconds while we invite the next group to join us.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">Sitting suspended at 4.39 p.m. and resumed at 4.40 p.m.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Community Meals Service: Discussion with Domestic Care</heading>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_88">We will now meet a delegation from the Domestic Care group.  I welcome Ms Liz Ensor, Dr. Paul Megarity, Mrs. Leslie Megarity and Mr. John Ferguson.  Their paper has been circulated and we are fascinated by the work they do.  I ask them to make a brief presentation, after which we will have a question and answer session.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Dr. Paul Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_89">I thank the Chairman and members for giving us the opportunity to make a presentation.  I am chairman of Domestic Care.  Mrs. Ensor is group operations director, Mrs. Leslie Megarty is the chief executive and Mr. John Ferguson is a non-executive director.  Mrs. Ensor will make the presentation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Ms Liz Ensor</from>
          <p eId="para_90">Domestic Care was established in 1993 to provide a pilot community meals service in north County Down.  This was in response to the Government's People First initiative.  Domestic Care not only provides a community meals service, it also cares at home for those persons who are older, physically disabled or have dementia, Alzheimer's disease or learning disabilities.  It provides nursing care for both frail and elderly mentally infirm residents in a purpose-built facility.  In short, it is a community care provider in every sense of the word, providing a service for over 5,000 persons daily.</p>
          <p eId="para_91">We are here to demonstrate how the community meals service can fit with the needs of the similar client group in the Republic of Ireland and potentially address such issues as elderly malnutrition, reducing hospital admissions, shortening lengths of stay and expediting discharge, while delivering real cost savings to commissioners of services.  In 2008 the National Council on Ageing and Older People launched its report, The Role and Future Development of the Meals-on-Wheels Service for Older People in Ireland, which was commissioned with the Social Policy and Ageing Research Centre in Trinity College, Dublin.  The report examined in depth the nature of community meals service provision across the State and made recommendations.  Domestic Care's cook-chilled service was the subject of one of the case studies included in the report.  The research confirmed the need for change and the introduction of a provision to meet the needs of a rapidly ageing population.  There are wide variances in service provision across the State, with a significant proportion of services being delivered by ageing volunteers or community service organisations, some in receipt of funding, others not, or through the use of the home help service.</p>
          <p eId="para_92">Our proposal is that a fully professional workforce should be used to deliver and manage the service which could be used to complement a review of home care provision, substituting part of the service currently provided at high cost and enabling more efficient use of the most expensive of all resources, staff.  A system similar to that operating in Northern Ireland could be replicated in the Republic, tailoring meals services to clients' needs and providing from one meal a week to a full seven-day service.  The use of local food production, with menus tailored to meet the Irish palate, would be ideal in achieving acceptance among the client group.  The use of a chilled, locally produced meal is preferred in achieving this.</p>
          <p eId="para_93">How would the service be run?  Clients would make their choice of meal; the meal would be produced to nutritional and dietetic guidelines agreed with the commissioner; and the service would include a full range of specialist diets, for example, diabetic, gluten free and altered-consistency diets.  Local depots would deliver meals within agreed timeframes.  Systems would be agreed with commissioners to ensure reporting protocols and financial and management information were provided.  Our service is supported by custom-built computer software and effective management systems covering all aspects of service delivery.  Our quality system is externally audited annually both in regard to food hygiene and management systems.</p>
          <p eId="para_94">What would all of this cost and what are the efficiencies to be achieved?  We have outlined in our submission the extent of the savings achieved under the original pilot scheme in County Down.  Assuming that home care was commissioned at a rate of €23 per hour and that the time allocated for meal preparation as part of a package of care was between 30 and 45 minutes a day, the cost would equate to between €11.50 and €17.25.</p>
          <p eId="para_95">We have assumed that in the home help model, clients would purchase their own food which would then be prepared by the home help group.  Assuming a continuation of that principle, we regard €3 as a typical client contribution to the cost of a two-course meal.  Taking all of this into account, we believe we could deliver savings in excess of 50% on the current cost.  There are few opportunities within the health and social care system to deliver such a saving, while improving equality, accessibility and reliability of a service.</p>
          <p eId="para_96">On admission to hospital repeated studies have reported that more than 40% of the over 65s are malnourished.  The report of the National Council on Ageing and Older People has expertly detailed the extent and causes of this and the wider issues around malnutrition in the community that lead to ill health.  Malnourishment on admission inevitably leads to slower recovery, a prolonged length of stay and increasing demands on the stretched secondary care sector and contributes to bed blocking.  The reason offered for bed blocking is often the lack of community resources to aid discharge.  Such a meals service could respond within 24 hours to a request for service and might reduce the pressure on the secondary care sector through the adoption of a flexible approach and genuine partnership.</p>
          <p eId="para_97">Domestic Care's service has been proved over a period of 17 years in Northern Ireland, with satisfaction ratings in excess of 90% throughout that time.  It is possible to demonstrate, through the use of pilot schemes, the effective, efficient service we are confident we could deliver.  We would welcome the opportunity to work with the committee to demonstrate the feasibility of introducing such a service in the Republic of Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_98">I thank Mrs. Ensor for her fascinating proposal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulConnaughton" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Deputy Paul Connaughton</from>
          <p eId="para_99">I welcome the delegation.  I am fascinated that Domestic Care believes it could deliver a professional service as cheaply as it has outlined.  Are there other groups or agencies doing similar work to Domestic Care?  How did the initiative start 15 or 20 years ago?  We call it meals on wheels in this country.  Our service is significant, but it is organised by various groups which are not operating under one umbrella group.  I take it from what Domestic Care has stated there is a chain of command in working with local communities.  Does Domestic Care put out to tender the supply of food?  This is of great interest to many groups in the Republic.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PhilPrendergast" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Senator Phil Prendergast</from>
          <p eId="para_100">I thank the delegates who are very welcome.  Many of my queries have been addressed.  What would constitute a pilot study?  Who would comprise the target group?  Would it include people discharged from hospitals or residents of day care centres?  In acknowledging the study stating over 40% of over-65s presenting at hospital are malnourished, I remember that, in the course of my training quite some time ago, this was a recognised syndrome.  It was always a recognised factor and was listed as one of the criteria when somebody presented to hospital.  In the present climate there are many people who may be forgoing proper food because they have not got the money to buy it.  The price listed by the delegates seems quite reasonable.  How does the system work?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_101">That was a most interesting presentation on domestic care.  I wonder how we can roll it out in the South.  As Deputy Connaughton stated, we deliver meals through what is called the meals on wheels service or perhaps through the Society of St. Vincent de Paul.  In the North, is the service just for the elderly or is it for others who find themselves in financial difficulty or poor circumstances?  Is the service state-funded?  Are all the service providers volunteers or are they paid by the state?</p>
          <p eId="para_102">A question was asked about costs.  How is the service co-ordinated on an urban-rural basis?  I am from a rural area.  Is the service rolled out in rural areas or is it just rolled out in cities and towns?  How is the service co-ordinated throughout the Six Counties?  The Republic has 26 counties, many with very rural areas.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiallBlaneyIND" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Deputy Niall Blaney</from>
          <p eId="para_103">I warmly welcome the delegation to Dublin.  Its presentation was very much to the point.  I would like it to develop its ideas a little further, particularly regarding costs and suspected numbers.  The delegates referred to a nationwide service.  I would like a further breakdown of the costs.  Do the delegates expect that State funding will be required to meet costs?  If so, it will have consequences for the rest of the health budget.  Given the current financial constraints, the system would be difficult to introduce.  The overall idea is good and I believe it represents a good way to proceed at some stage.  I foresee difficulties in the current climate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Deputy David Stanton</from>
          <p eId="para_104">Deputy Reilly had to leave so he sends his apologies.  I am a visitor to the committee and am not present at all its meetings.  I was intrigued by what the delegates put forward.</p>
          <p eId="para_105">The delegates' submission refers to a "safe and well" check.  How does this work?  They stated local depots would deliver the meals within agreed timeframes.  Does Domestic Care run and own the depots?  Does it contract the work to hotels or other providers?</p>
          <p eId="para_106">Is Domestic Care a voluntary or not-for-profit group?  How is it structured?  Who are its members?  Its proposals seem quite exciting and interesting and should be considered in more detail.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KathleenLynch" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Deputy Kathleen Lynch</from>
          <p eId="para_107">I apologise sincerely for my absence earlier and hope the delegation will not take offence.  We have had a rather hectic day.  No disrespect was meant; we were genuinely held up.  I apologise for Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, who is still on duty.  We will read all the papers and revert to the delegates.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_108">I join the members in congratulating Domestic Care on its presentation.  It has 19 years of success in the Six Counties and serves 5,000 clients.  It is obviously asking the committee to advocate that the HSE and Department of Health and Children consider a pilot area.  Where would it be and how large?  What population would it have?</p>
          <p eId="para_109">How does Domestic Care propose to deal with the fragmented nature of the service that exists in the Republic?  Volunteers, largely working with church organisations or community groups, go out to deliver meals, and home help is provided by the HSE.  There are other help services also.  How does Domestic Care identify its client cohort and, given the rather complex system we have, how would it move in and provide a service?  How does it relate to the agencies or groups in an area that might already be providing such a service?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Dr. Paul Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_110">On the question of what sparked off Domestic Care, I will ask Mr. John Ferguson to answer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Mr. John Ferguson</from>
          <p eId="para_111">I was the chief executive of North Down and Ards Community Trust.  We were under pressure to effect efficiency savings of 2% to 3% year-on-year.  That meant that every service we were providing in the community, including social services and primary care services, had to be scrutinised.  The service that presented the greatest difficulty was that of meal provision for frail elderly people in their own homes.</p>
          <p eId="para_112">We had a home help staff of approximately 600.  When we considered what they were providing, we found a number of difficulties, one of which was that they did not have proper contracts of employment.  Second, they were doing shopping, lighting fires, and preparing and cooking meals.  This was costing a lot of money.  At the weekends, the staff were on time and a half and on Christmas Day they were on triple time.  The more we considered this, the more we realised it was a service we could not afford and that we had to come up with a different way of providing it.</p>
          <p eId="para_113">What I describe was occurring shortly after trusts were established in Northern Ireland and we were encouraged to be innovative in service delivery.  I shared my views with Dr. Megarity, who was on the planning team in the trust.  After much research and investigation by Dr. Megarity and Domestic Care, we decided there was a better way to proceed, namely, by providing a cooked chilled meal to the homes of the clients on a daily basis.  We approached the Eastern Health and Social Services Board and it agreed to fund the pilot service.  We started off in Newtownards and this allowed us to iron out any difficulties or problems.  The service was an outstanding success right from the beginning.</p>
          <p eId="para_114">There was concern that many home helps would lose their jobs.  They had very casual part-time employment arrangements.  We worked very closely with the union and it was very supportive.  We retrained the great majority of the home helps and gave them contracts for 20 hours per week.  They were trained to become care workers in people's homes and to provide personal care rather than meals.</p>
          <p eId="para_115">What sparked the service off was the drive to lower costs and find a better way of proceeding.  We found that not all our home helps were wonderful cooks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KathleenLynch" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Deputy Kathleen Lynch</from>
          <p eId="para_116">Were cooked chilled meals delivered daily or were clients given a week's supply?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Mr. John Ferguson</from>
          <p eId="para_117">It depended on the client and whether he or she wanted a meal daily or every other day.  It depended on the clients' needs.  In many cases, the meals were provided for seven days or five days per week.  It was a matter of choice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Dr. Paul Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_118">There was always a daily delivery and one did not receive a week's meals together as a pack.  Not everybody received a daily service because some people visited their families at weekends or went to luncheon clubs.  There was a variety of reasons.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KathleenLynch" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Deputy Kathleen Lynch</from>
          <p eId="para_119">Did it save the trust in terms of the percentage?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Mr. John Ferguson</from>
          <p eId="para_120">In terms of savings?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KathleenLynch" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Deputy Kathleen Lynch</from>
          <p eId="para_121">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Mr. John Ferguson</from>
          <p eId="para_122">It was only a small part of north Down.  In today's prices, the saving was approximately €1 million per year.  Over the Six Counties or the Republic, the savings would be very considerable.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Dr. Paul Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_123">There were a number of questions on other groups doing similar work.  I ask Ms Leslie Megarity to answer them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Ms Leslie Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_124">Our business is a tendered business.  There are specifications set by the relevant trusts and the business is competitively put out to tender.  We have won each tender we applied for.  There are some small groups providing services on a very localised basis but the problem that exists and existed in this regard is that there is no standardisation of service.  Issues associated with hygiene and nutrition arose and in this regard the trusts and health authorities in the North believed they needed to standardise further and provide equality of access to services.  The groups doing the kind of work we do are really very small.</p>
          <p eId="para_125">Another aspect of the question concerned a tender to supply food.  We have sub-contracted food production.  At present, we have a large production unit producing all the meals.  That is covered in a number of the questions.  We do not obtain meals from hospitals, hotels or pubs.  There is a specific contract in place to produce the food to a given standard.  That standard is laid down by the dieticians for the health service.  There is an agreement between our group and the health service on the nutritional value of each meal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Dr. Paul Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_126">The food production standard is one that a major supermarket chain would use.  It is a fully audit-controlled service with hazard analysis and a critical control points system.  There is no "back-of-a-van" activity.  It is a professional, fully audited service.  If there is ever a problem, all the batches can be traced.  There is full traceability.  There is what a person who investigated the system called the "farm to fork audit trail".  That is the way it works.</p>
          <p eId="para_127">Senator Prendergast asked about malnutrition among the elderly.  There are various studies on clinical malnutrition.  They usually investigate people on their day of admission to hospital.  A study in the North that I remember very well showed 43% of people over 65 were clinically malnourished on the day of admission to hospital.  This is a reflection of their status in the community prior to admission.</p>
          <p eId="para_128">Clinical malnutrition is not necessarily about people who are very thin.  It often affects people who have sufficient calories in their diet but whose diet is poor in vegetables and minerals.  Calcium is one of the big areas.  People who are clinically malnourished have slower post-operative recoveries and are more prone to fractures.  They are more prone to infection and often have extended stays in hospital as a result.  It is well documented that well-nourished people do better in health stakes than poorly nourished people.  There is no great breakthrough in knowledge in this regard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KathleenLynch" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Deputy Kathleen Lynch</from>
          <p eId="para_129">May I ask one other question?  With regard to home help, the Republic seems to have the same sort of model as in the North, apart from the nutrition aspect.  It often strikes me that home helps are very limited in what they can do, despite their being trained to be almost personal assistants.  Who does the housework for a very elderly, frail person with no family?  Who lights the fire and ensures the kitchen floor and front room are clean and that the sheets are clean?  How is this managed?  In Ireland there are excellent home helps who would do all these jobs but who are barred from doing them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Ms Leslie Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_130">I do not know if that is something the meals service does.  Our experience of delivering community care as part of another part of our business is that the care worker in the main does those tasks.  Generally, there is a domestic aspect to personal care packages in the North to ensure the client's total well-being.  This is one aspect of a package of care.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_131">The question will be explored by our HSE colleagues when they join us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Deputy David Stanton</from>
          <p eId="para_132">Ms Megarity used to the term "business".  Will she outline the structure of her group?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Ms Leslie Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_133">It is privately-owned company and is limited by shares with a board of directors, some of whom are present.  It is a for-profit company.  That said, we take our corporate responsibility very seriously and we sponsor and fund various initiatives through other entities not directly run by ourselves.</p>
          <p eId="para_134">A question was asked on how we would roll out our service in the South.  The current meals on wheels service in the South is very vulnerable.  The report produced by the National Council on Ageing and Older People was very clear that the current service is having difficulty in sustaining its viability.  It is largely run by groups of elderly volunteers who are probably well into their 70s or 80s.  Younger volunteers are not replacing them so the service is falling out of availability.</p>
          <p eId="para_135">The report of the National Council on Ageing and Older People was launched in the spring.  The report demonstrates that the service is working well in some parts of the country but not in others.  There were many small groups.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NiallBlaneyIND" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Deputy Niall Blaney</from>
          <p eId="para_136">To which groups does the report refer?  Are they named?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Ms Leslie Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_137">The groups are not named in the report but there were people at the launch to whom we had an opportunity to speak.  The issues the people were experiencing are referred to in the report.  We were really focusing on the question of people no longer being able to obtain services because there is a limited number on offer, and on the vulnerability of the services.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_138">What population cohort is required to conduct a pilot programme?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Dr. Paul Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_139">It is difficult to say the population.  We would probably need to be delivering approximately 2,000 to 3,000 meals per week, which would probably mean 500 people requiring services.  The average would be approximately five meals per week for 500 or 600 people.  It would be important to examine both a densely urban area and an urban-rural mix because the service is the same.  The logistics behind it are quite different.  That would cover all the bases in Ireland in terms of demographics.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_140">Do members wish to ask supplementary questions?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_141">In terms of urban-rural mix, is the group providing a full service to rural as well as urban areas in the Six Counties?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Ms Leslie Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_142">Yes.  We provide services everywhere from Belfast to the Border areas of County Armagh——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_67">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_143">In remote areas.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Ms Leslie Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_144">——and the Sperrin Mountains.  If the Deputy can name it, we are there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_69">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_145">Is there any division among the age groups?  Is it only elderly people the group cares for or people who have——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Ms Leslie Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_146">It is mostly elderly people but there are people in receipt of the services who are house-bound for some other reason or who have social needs and the service has been put in for that reason.  It can be the young physically disabled or those with a mental health problem.  We provide the services where the person is assessed as requiring nutritional support.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_147">What state funding is involved?  I realise the group is a private company but is there any state funding involved?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Ms Leslie Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_148">There is a contribution from the health and social care trust concerned.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_149">What is the percentage?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Ms Leslie Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_150">It depends.  It would pay about 50% of the cost of each contract.  The client contributes the balance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_75">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_151">The client must pay so much towards the cost.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Ms Leslie Megarity</from>
          <p eId="para_152">They would buy the food anyway.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_153">I hope we are all happy with that.  I thank the representatives for their presentations.  It is a matter that the committee will consider in greater detail.  We will await the next group from the Health Service Executive to join us.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Home Help Service: Discussion with Health Service Executive</heading>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_154">We will now have a discussion with representatives of the Health Service Executive.  I am happy to welcome Ms Monica Sheehan, Mr. Michael Fitzgerald, Ms Geraldine Bermingham-Rigney and Mr. Noel Mulvihill for a discussion on the home care services.</p>
          <p eId="para_155">Before I begin I would like to advise you that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, you are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence you are to give this committee.  If you are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence in relation to a particular matter and you continue to so do, you are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of your evidence.  You are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and you are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, you should not criticise nor make charges against any person(s) or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_156">We are running a little late for which we apologise but momentous events are happening around us in the House today.  I thank the witnesses for joining us.  We have their paper, which has been circulated to members.  We will deal with the executive summary of that following which members will be allowed ask a series of questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_79">
          <from>Mr. Noel Mulvihill</from>
          <p eId="para_157">I thank the Chairman and members of the committee for the opportunity to make an opening statement.  I would like to comment briefly on the home help service and update members on a number of aspects of the service.  Members have been provided with a more detailed paper setting out the aspects of the service which we can discuss later.</p>
          <p eId="para_158">The first issue is the context in which the service is operating and moving towards the integrated care model.  The delivery of health services to older people must change for a number of significant reasons.  They are, predominantly, the following: the fact that people are living longer; the population is increasing and ageing; expectations and demands are increasing; and costs are also increasing.</p>
          <p eId="para_159">Government policy with regard to health services for older persons has the following two core elements: community and home-based care should be developed to maintain older people in their communities for as long as possible and to support the important role of the family and the informal carer; and, where that is not possible, high-quality residential care should be available.</p>
          <p eId="para_160">The integrated care model of service delivery being developed within the HSE provides for appropriate care in appropriate settings, along a continuum from home and community-based services through acute intervention to long-term residential care, with older persons needs and preferences being central to decision-making.</p>
          <p eId="para_161">In that context this report outlines the significant progress made in developing home help services and home care packages since 2006, identifying the impact in terms of people benefiting as well as the significant support to the acute hospital sector.  These developments are part of an overall movement towards an integrated model of care across hospital and community, which will require continued sustained investment if the model is to be successfully implemented.</p>
          <p eId="para_162">The home help service is a core community service supporting older people to remain in their own homes, preventing admission to acute services, delaying or preventing admission to continuing residential care and facilitating early discharge from the acute sector to the community.</p>
          <p eId="para_163">Significant progress has been made in developing home help services since 2006, with significant impact in terms of the numbers of people benefiting as well as providing support to the acute hospital sector.  In terms of numbers, this has increased from 10.8 million hours in 2006 to 11.97 million hours in 2009.  The total number of people<b> </b>in receipt of services increased from 41,400<b> </b>in January 2006 to 53,791 in December 2009.</p>
          <p eId="para_164">The 2010 budget for the home help service is €211 million, which provides 11.9 million home help hours<b> </b>with approximately<b> </b>54,500 persons in receipt of the service at any time.<b>  </b>It is important to outline that this includes all care groups.  It is not just for older people.  It also applies to our mental health services, our disability service and services for children and families.  The 2010 targets are the same targets as applied in 2009.  This level of service, if applied equally to all clients, would equate to four hours home help per client per week.</p>
          <p eId="para_165">While the resources available are substantial, they are finite.  The capacity of the HSE to provide approved levels of home help service continues to be reviewed in the context of overall resources available to the HSE.  Local health managers must ensure that home help services are delivered within the allocated budgets.  This requires a stringent ongoing review of the application of the resources.</p>
          <p eId="para_166">Levels of services provided by the home help service to individual clients are reviewed regularly to ensure they continue to support the clients' assessed care needs.</p>
          <p eId="para_167">In some parts of the country, particularly in Dublin and the greater Dublin area, the home help service is provided by voluntary organisations.  It is recognised that these voluntary organisations provide a valuable service.  They face challenges in the future in terms of standards, and increased professionalisation of the service.  Given the particular relationships that have developed, the HSE will need to provide some support to those providers in facing these challenges.</p>
          <p eId="para_168">Home care packages are enhanced levels of home help services which may be provided through the home care package scheme where the assessed needs of the client indicate that such enhanced service is required.  In 2010, the home care package scheme budget is €130 million, which is expected to benefit over 13,000 people.  By the end of 2010, a total of just over 9,600 people will be in receipt of a home care package at any time<b>.</b>
                    </p>
          <p eId="para_169">Regarding home help service and duties, the development of the home help service has seen the professionalisation of the service in recent years with the implementation of the national home help agreement.  Home helps are now paid at care attendant rate.  This has resulted in greater flexibility in service delivery and improved consistency in service quality, through training, to the benefit of service users.  That has placed a greater onus on the HSE and its role as an employer and with regard to management of risk, which requires increased supervision given the numbers of high-dependent older people now supported in the community.</p>
          <p eId="para_170">Home helps provide a range of services to assist people with activities of daily living based on the assessment of need undertaken by health professionals.  These duties include both personal and domestic care relevant to the individual's assessed needs.  The range of duties is set out in a more detailed paper which has been circulated.</p>
          <p eId="para_171">Home help service training is provided on an incremental basis to facilitate changes in service provision.  For example, where an older or disabled person becomes more dependent, the existing home help may need training to develop his or her skills to provide the necessary personal care.  Initial training for new home helps includes induction, moving and handling, health and safety, and domestic and personal care.</p>
          <p eId="para_172">Moving and handling training is a critical aspect of training, particularly where personal care tasks are involved.  Moving and handling training is arranged locally in each region to address the particular requirements of each local health area.  One example of the extent of training in Cork-Kerry is set out in the detailed paper already circulated.</p>
          <p eId="para_173">FETAC level 5 training is available currently through arrangements with a consortium of all 33 VECs, led by the city of Dublin Vocational Education Committee.  Supervisory staff may avail of the supervisor programme at FETAC level 6. In addition, FETAC programmes levels 3 and 4 are also available where appropriate, for example, if the home help requires literacy support or if English is the second language.  More details on these programmes are set out in the paper circulated to the members.</p>
          <p eId="para_174">The home help service has emerged over the years from what was essentially a friendly neighbour service to one that is becoming more professional and demanding as increased numbers of clients with significant and complex needs are maintained at home.  Although generally the home help service is well regarded by clients there remains room for improvement and in 2010 work is under way to roll out a number of improvements that will ensure all applicants for home help services are treated in a similar way and have their application assessed in a similar way regardless of where in the country they live.  Procedural guidelines for the home help service are in the process of being developed.  Given the large numbers benefitting from the service it is critical that national procedural guidelines for the standardised access to and allocation of home help hours to clients are available to assist staff in managing the scheme in an equitable way across the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_175">Given that the service evolved over a number of years from the old health board structure and because it is a discretionary service — there is no statutory requirement on the HSE to provide the service and no statutory entitlement for clients to receive it — different approaches to accessing the service emerged in different areas.  It is a priority of the HSE to standardise access to this service so that all our clients can expect to be able to access the service using the same criteria regardless of where they live.</p>
          <p eId="para_176">Procedural guidelines will assist staff in applying equitable access criteria to all applicants and in allocating home help services in a consistent way while incorporating flexibility to allow the professional staff allocating the service to take full account of the particular care needs, abilities and dependencies of the client.  In this way for example a client in County Mayo and one in County Wexford can expect to be able to apply for and be assessed for the home help service in a similar way, and, subject to the limit of the resources, have appropriate services allocated to support their differing needs and dependencies.  Guidelines will also help to ensure that important service is provided in an economical way while taking account of individual needs.</p>
          <p eId="para_177">Another aspect of service improvement relates to draft national quality guidelines for home care support services which reflects that the needs of older persons and their carers are based on good practice, will ensure national cohesion and will support the service delivery system to minimise risk in the home care setting.  The guidelines will address key issues across public, voluntary and private providers.  The resource and general capacity implications will need to be considered before a strategic and operational proposal, recommending how the guidelines might be implemented across agencies in the public, private and voluntary sectors, on a phased basis within available resources, can be submitted to the HSE management team.</p>
          <p eId="para_178">The HSE is committed to supporting older people to live in their own homes for as long as possible if that is their wish.  Significant levels of service are available and are being provided across the country.  However, as the population of older people continues to grow, the resources available to support them to remain at home must continue to expand if service provision to individual clients is to be maintained or improved.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_179">Thank you, Mr. Mulvihill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulConnaughton" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Deputy Paul Connaughton</from>
          <p eId="para_180">I welcome the delegation.  We heard a great deal today about caring; both inside and outside the House but that is another story.</p>
          <p eId="para_181">I have a great interest in the home help service and related matters.  In early January, all Oireachtas Members representing County Galway met representatives of HSE west and were told there would be a dramatic cut in home help services for counties Galway, Roscommon and Mayo.  If I understood Mr. Mulvihill, the numbers this year will be slightly higher than last year.  I am not sure whether he meant numbers of people or of hours but either way he mentioned 53,000 or 54,000 as compared to 51,000 or 52,000 the previous year.</p>
          <p eId="para_182">I have met many who now work in an official capacity as home helps for the HSE.  They have enormous industrial relations type problems concerning their employment.  I do not intend to examine this specific issue but there has not been a smooth transition from where these people had been employed to their present place of employment.  Many would argue they got a bad deal with regard to much of the work they did.</p>
          <p eId="para_183">I refer to private providers of home help.  I have been told they pay their home help employees less than the HSE pays and, in some cases, their guidelines are different.  Their employees appear to be allowed to do more in the home than HSE home help personnel.  On occasion, HSE staff have told me they could do more for people if they were so allowed.</p>
          <p eId="para_184">Generally, however, the scheme is excellent by any standards.  I cannot emphasise enough that if it were only a matter of human contact, a person who calls in, it would be worth it and I acknowledge that when it is only a matter of half or three quarters of an hour a day one cannot expect miracles.  Unfortunately, that is the type of division of time that pertains at present.  Given the statistics he has, Mr. Mulvihall might indicate whether he can give a guarantee that for the remainder of this year and for next year, people who now get home help, at whatever level, will continue to receive it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KathleenLynch" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Deputy Kathleen Lynch</from>
          <p eId="para_185">I apologise for the delay.  I hope the delegates understand that all of us are very caught up today.  Mr. Mulvihill spoke of service improvement in home help service, referred to as item 5 on page 5.  He stated:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_186">The home help service has emerged over the years from what was essentially a friendly neighbour service to one that is becoming more professional and demanding . . .Although generally the home help service is well regarded by clients there remains room for improvement and in 2010 work is under way to roll out a number of improvements that will ensure all applicants for home help services are treated in a similar way and have their application assessed in a similar way regardless of where in the country they live.</p>
          <p eId="para_187">Is that code for centralisation?  If so, our experience of the centralisation of medical cards does not augur well for centralising this service.  It is my belief that centralisation is what is meant — in code.  A person who needs a home help must telephone a number in Finglas, but judging by the medical card experience, he or she will not get a reply.  I wish to know what this means.</p>
          <p eId="para_188">I asked the other delegates the same question.  We are upskilling everybody who helps the elderly in the community, which is great.  We all know people who work in this area.  However, some have told me they are upskilled in such a way that they can no longer do what they used to do.  I agree that people should be taught how to lift properly in case they might put their back out and there are certain jobs people should not be expected to do.  Home helps are there to help people in their home and are not domestic servants.  That is not what it is about.  However, on the other hand, one can take the case of a person with no family who does the domestic chores we all need to live a reasonable life.  I examined the figures.  Four hours a week works out at just under 30 minutes a day.  A lady passes my gate every day to do home help chores.  She enters a house and, I assume, takes off her coat, hangs it up and says "Hello" and "How are you?"  That takes ten minutes.  What is she expected to do in 30 minutes?  I realise it is a vital 30 minutes and, as Deputy Connaughton correctly stated, sometimes it is merely the human contact which keeps people alive.  I have no difficulty with that.  I am certain I could not vacuum the front room, wash the ware left in the sink and light the fire in 30 minutes.  However, I am not the greatest around the house.  What can be done in 30 minutes?  During the winter, the fire must be lit every day.  It is not practical to do anything reasonable in 30 minutes.  It is not practical to change the beds, ensure the place is clean, vacuum the bedroom and light the fire.  These are the things certain people cannot do for themselves.  I believe No. 5 on page 5 is code for centralisation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BeverleyCooperFlynn" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Deputy Beverley Flynn</from>
          <p eId="para_189">I welcome Mr. Mulvihill and his delegation and I thank him for his presentation.  I will deal with the last part of the presentation first.  I refer to the amount of money allocated.  The presentation referred to the number of home help hours in 2009 and the number of recipients.  However, it does not refer to what was in the budget.  What was the budget for home help in 2009 and how does it compare with the 2010 figure of €211 million?</p>
          <p eId="para_190">By coincidence, a constituent, an 85 year old woman visited me yesterday with regard to home help and the review currently under way within the service.  She has osteoporosis and severe arthritis.  She is virtually immobile and hardly leaves the house anymore.  She has two children living abroad.  Therefore, the only contact she has with people during the week is from home help.  Until yesterday, she was in receipt of one hour per day for five days per week.  There was some flexibility attached to this and the duties were not specified.  I saw the letter she received when she came to me following the review.  The review has cut her help to three quarters of an hour for three days per week.  The letter also specified exactly the duties of home help.  For this woman, such duties included to shower her and take care of personal hygiene, to change her bed and to tidy her bathroom.  This is the service for a woman who never gets to speak to anyone else during the week.  I refer to the point my colleague made.  We are all aware that part of the service of home help is the essential contact with an older person.  There has been some debate in the national media about how the HSE is allocating time.  The executive may deny it but there is only so much time for a shower, to tidy the bathroom and to change the bed.  Unfortunately, this leaves no time for some conversation.  I am aware from my clinic that it is unclear whether one could get in and out in a half an hour and have a chat because elderly people, by their nature, do not want that chat to end.  They would stay and chat for an hour if they could do so.  Sometimes that is more important than the chores highlighted, which are essential as well.</p>
          <p eId="para_191">I have a problem with the review because when I discussed the matter with my secretary, it turns out that almost everyone who has come to us in receipt of home help hours who was getting one hour per day has been cut to three quarters of an hour.  It seems a blanket cut of 15 minutes has been taken off everyone.  The help for the woman in question was reduced from five days to three days.  If this is the case, it is difficult to justify or verify the figures highlighted by the delegation, which maintains that more people will be in receipt of home help hours this year than last year and that the hours have increased from 11.97 million to 11.98 million, a marginal increase.  How does the delegation square that circle?  Is this the case throughout the country?</p>
          <p eId="para_192">Reference was made to standardising a service.  I appreciate the point that a woman with the same condition in Donegal should receive the same service as a person in Mayo.  There cannot be wild differences in the service and the same argument was made for medical cards.  Why was it some people could get a medical card in one county but others could not do so elsewhere?  The reality for the 85 year old woman who visited me is that I am better off applying for the home care package for her, which will cost the HSE more.  She is better off using that home care package to buy the essential hours she needs.  We will do so.  I will appeal the home help decision for this woman because it seems no consultation took place with her and the decision was part of a blanket cut.  That does not constitute a review.  It is a simply cost cutting exercise and it is unacceptable, especially in this case because she is a deserving case.  Over the years, I have met people in receipt of home help hours who, arguably, could have done without the service.  However, that is not the case in this instance.  I have taken a strong view on the matter having met this woman.  Were she to be left isolated and without essential contact on a daily basis, it will not end up in a happy situation for her.  I call on the HSE to consider this because it is simply not acceptable.</p>
          <p eId="para_193">I refer to training.  The delegation remarked that the HSE is now paying the care attendant rate for people.  I refer to vetting people who carry out the home help service.  Everyone is conscious of the risk of abuse of elderly people and others in society.  There have been cases of abuse of elderly people in the past within families.  I am keen to know the level of vetting.  Are there spot checks of the home help service to ensure people are in receipt of the service as intended?  Can we be sure it is not simply a case that when the home help hours are appointed and the person is allocated, the matter is forgotten about until next year's assessment?  This is a source of concern to many people as well. I refer to the appeal process.  An appeal has been made to the change in home help hours.  Have any appeals been successful to date?  Is the process independent?  How does the process take place?  I trust the appeal in the case of my 85 year old constituent will be heard and the decision overturned when the case is shown to be genuine.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CharlieOConnorFF" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Deputy Charlie O’Connor</from>
          <p eId="para_194">I had to watch the presentation from my office because of other pressures and for this I apologise.  I wish to be associated with the welcome extended to the delegation.  It is important to have this meeting.  I am not always parochial but I heard others refer to their counties and so I am pleased to refer to Dublin.  Mr. Mulvihill will recall that I live in Tallaght.  I am a member of the board of what was the Tallaght Welfare Society which is now Trust Us, an organisation of which he is well aware.  The organisation is responsible for 200 home helps and deals with more than 600 families.  There is no question in my mind of the very substantial contribution it makes to keep people out of hospital and nursing homes.  It is a vital element of community care.  In Tallaght, there is a good deal of pressure on the hospital and on the few nursing homes in the general region.</p>
          <p eId="para_195">It is important to stress, as other colleagues have done, the importance of home help.  The Minister, Deputy Mary Harney, came to Tallaght some weeks ago to open a new facility for Trust Us.  It faces the stadium in Tallaght.  This is important because it contributes to keeping people active and away from hospital.  The home help people look after the elderly and they are taken to a brand new facility, which is tremendous.  I cannot wait to qualify and I do not say so in a facetious way.  I look forward to the day when I need such facilities and when I can get access to them.</p>
          <p eId="para_196">It is important that we stress this point to the HSE.  I realise there are pressures on the executive but we should stress the need for home help.  This committee will hear from delegations every other week during the coming months leading up to the budget.  Everyone will have a strong case to make and we have already shown that we support what the Carers Association is trying to achieve.  It will be difficult for everyone, including the Government and the HSE, to decide on the priorities and funding.  As someone who has seen the system in operation, I have no hesitation in saying that home help works.  Deputy Flynn made a point in this regard but I have never met anyone who did not need the help.  There is a relatively small elderly community in my constituency compared with other parts of the country.  There are more demands on the service at present.  It is important that we stress that.  As I said, I acknowledge there are a lot of pressures on the health service and the HSE budget but I have no doubt people would want us to stress the importance of home help.  I am happy to be able to do that.</p>
          <p eId="para_197">I hope I do not get Mr. Mulvihill into trouble but I want to acknowledge the contribution he has made in my area.  His successors might not want me to say he will be missed but he made a good contribution and I was always happy to work with him.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryOHanlon" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Deputy Rory O’Hanlon</from>
          <p eId="para_198">I thank the delegates for coming before the committee and making their contributions.  We all want to see people live in their own homes for as long as possible and to be supported in doing so.  A lot of progress has been made over the years.  On budgeting, it appears, based on the figures the HSE gave us, that the number of people benefitting has increased by 25% but the budget only increased by 10%.  I have a concern about the distribution of money between hospitals and community care.  If it was my money I would give more of it to community care because one would probably get better value for money.  The cost of the home help service nationally appears to be some 85% of what a large Dublin hospital would get for a year.  It is not an expensive service.</p>
          <p eId="para_199">The HSE must examine how to ensure it is properly resourced because when there are difficulties in finding finance, a certain level of pruning takes place which is not in the interests of some of the elderly people, particularly those living alone.  We all meet people in our constituencies whose number of hours has been reduced.  I am aware of someone who received 10.5 hours which this person needs.  I will not argue with the professionals who made the decision but I hope decisions are made on the basis of need rather than trying to save money.  I fully support the Government in limiting funding to what it can afford and the HSE in living within its budget.</p>
          <p eId="para_200">Having said that, as for the question of home help and the care of the elderly and those in the community with disabilities, one cannot see it in the context of a home help service on its own.  One has to see it in the context of a whole range of needs and facilities which are available, such as the length of hospital stays and how people might be able to leave hospital more quickly in order to save money.  We need to consider the day care facilities and voluntary facilities and supports which are available.  In that context, the delegates said when the home help service started that it was a "good neighbour" support which gradually developed and was eventually taken over by the HSE.  It became a career for people.</p>
          <p eId="para_201">The necessary number of volunteers was not available to do the job.  Now that there are more people available in the community we could consider having a more integrated voluntary State service, from which we could get much better value for money.  That brings me to the review.  While I am in favour of equity in the country and ensuring that everybody has equal access, the nature of the home help service is that there has to be flexibility.  In the review and guidelines one cannot throw up stereotypical guidelines which affect everybody because needs are different and the needs of one individual may change from one day to the next.  We have to take account of that in any review.</p>
          <p eId="para_202">I have a question on the distribution of home care packages within different HSE areas.  I am in the Dublin north-east area.  I do not know what the up-to-date figures are but it seems most of the home care package were in the Dublin area and did not extend to the periphery.  I would like to know what the current situation is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DavidStanton" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Deputy David Stanton</from>
          <p eId="para_203">I will be very brief.  Deputy O'Hanlon mentioned people with disabilities.  The delegation's presentation referred mainly to older people.  Could it give us an idea of the number of younger people with disabilities with which it deals, if any?  It also said that people are living longer, the population is increasing and that resources must be able to support them if the service is to be continued.  Has the HSE any projections regarding demographics on older people?  I am interested in what the trends are and what the demands will be over the next ten years and how many people will be looking for the service.  I am also interested in the onset of dementia and how home help is involved in supporting people with that difficulty.</p>
          <p eId="para_204">The delegation also mentioned the fact that it is a priority of the HSE to standardise access to the service.  Deputy Lynch referred to centralisation.  When does the delegation envisage that happening?  Does it have a timetable or deadline for that to happen?  A related question concerns the second last paragraph which deals with the draft national quality guidelines which, it is stated, will ensure national cohesion and will support the service delivery system to minimise risk.  I ask for examples of what it means by "minimise risk".  It also mentioned that the guidelines will address key issues.  Could it give us examples of those?</p>
          <p eId="para_205">The presentation said that the resource and general capacity implications will need to be considered before a strategic operational proposal recommending how the guidance can be implemented across agencies can be submitted.  What does that mean?  Does it mean that one cannot submit proposals until one comes up with the implications pertaining to resource and general capacity?  How will that work?  I understand the draft national quality guidelines are very important because we have seen all kinds of issues in other sectors and guidelines have been introduced.  It appears that this has been long-fingered.  I may be wrong but I would like more information because these are crucially important national guidelines.</p>
          <p eId="para_206">In its opening statement the delegation referred to moving towards an integrated care model.  We had a presentation earlier from the Carers Association which told us the cost of nursing home care is €800 to €1,000 per week.  The delegation mentioned people moving from community-based to high-quality residential care.  How is it integrated, from a financial point of view, if a certain amount of funding will be made available to have somebody looked after in high-quality residential care?  A fraction of that money could keep the person concerned in his or her home for a lot longer, which is what we all want.  How are the two linked?  Are there any links in the system, whereby an increase in home help services for a person which would cost a fraction of what is needed to keep him or her in a nursing home could be considered?  Maybe I am not making any sense but I am trying to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_87">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_207">It would be remiss of us not to acknowledge the work which has been done for decades by carers, a large number of whom were women.  I do not know of any male carers; there may be some but not very many.  I am very conscious of the number who did the work as good neighbours.  They did this work for £2 per hour for many years before current pay rates were put in place.  They are tremendous people who have demonstrated great humanity and support for people.</p>
          <p eId="para_208">I commend the witnesses for what they are doing to introduce standardised guidelines.  People are coming to me now in dire need and I wonder why they are not getting the service or why it has been reduced.  I then meet people who I am amazed to discover have the service and have had it for some time.  I wonder if they heard about it locally and applied for it because someone they knew had it and because there was discretion they were able to get it.  I hope the medical and human needs of the person will be put at the centre of the review.  If there are people who could do with less time because they are able-bodied and who are using the service as a domestic help, they should be looked at before the people with chronic conditions who obviously need support.</p>
          <p eId="para_209">Professionalisation can mean two things, namely, doing what a person has been doing to a far higher standard or deciding not to do something because it is beneath his or her professional status.  I fear we will enter the latter category if we are not careful because the people we are talking about need to have the fire set and cleaned out or the bathroom cleaned.  A colleague recently told me about someone who came to him about an elderly couple living together.  The husband was approved for home help and when the home help came in, she would only make one side of the double bed because she was only to provide care for one person.  That sort of nonsense should not happen.  Common sense must prevail.  The providers of this care are usually people of great sense and we should not have systems in place that prevent them from operating in a sensible manner.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulConnaughton" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Deputy Paul Connaughton</from>
          <p eId="para_210">I assume she only put down half a fire as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_89">
          <from>Mr. Noel Mulvihill</from>
          <p eId="para_211">I thank Deputy Connaughton for his kind comments.  There were particular issues in the west because in 2009, there was over-delivery in a number of the LHOs so they had to come back on budget.  The budget for 2009 is the same as the budget for 2010, with €211 million in total for home help.  For those to start at the beginning of the year, there had to be a target for where that would have come from.  We are watching this and we monitor the delivery of services for older persons.</p>
          <p eId="para_212">In each of the four regions it is done through a performance contract.  There have been difficulties obtaining data in recent months but that has changed.  We now have clear figures for what is being spent in each LHO area on both home help and home care packages so we can clearly align to the original resource that was given in January.  It is the same amount as in 2009.</p>
          <p eId="para_213">Private provision is a growth area that has evolved in recent years.  We have done a lot of work on it, particularly in terms of standardisation.  We will draw up a tender and contracts.  At the moment it is being worked out because we have a preferred provider list of private providers.  That allows for a level of standardisation and monitoring rather than how it is currently structured.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Mr. Michael Fitzgerald</from>
          <p eId="para_214">We have moved from a situation a few years ago where this work was done by the friendly neighbour to a situation where people have a specific, nationally agreed contract.  Those contracts are specific about duties and hours.  As part of the contract arrangements and the personnel process, all home helps are vetted through the Garda.</p>
          <p eId="para_215">There was a question about home help contracts and the transition from one area to another.  I was not sure what was mentioned.  There was such a huge number of contracts, with various arrangements in place, that we had to work through the process over a nine to 12-month period.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulConnaughton" eId="spk_91">
          <from>Deputy Paul Connaughton</from>
          <p eId="para_216">It took a long time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_92">
          <from>Mr. Michael Fitzgerald</from>
          <p eId="para_217">It did.  Some of that was down to staff numbers in our personnel departments to deal with it, because it was not as if we were recruiting home helps on an ongoing basis.  We had all home helps to deal with and we had to provide contracts to those who did not have them previously.  We are confident now about the contracts that are in place, they are nationally agreed, and arrangements are in place for the provision of contracts to any new home helps who would go into the system.</p>
          <p eId="para_218">Centralisation of the home help service was mentioned.  There is no sense in the document that centralisation of the service will take place.  The service is locally delivered.  Any person seeking a home help has his or her needs assessed by a professional, normally a public health nurse, and the allocation of time required based on that assessment is agreed and provided between that public health nurse and a home help organiser.  It would be impossible for us to centralise that process.</p>
          <p eId="para_219">An issue that has come up, however, is standardisation of procedures.  There is a concern that insufficient care might be provided to a person because a specified length of time would be laid down and it would never change.  The document makes clear what we are trying to do, to introduce standardisation whereby people with similar needs and environments receive similar levels of home help.  That is down to the individual's assessed need.</p>
          <p eId="para_220">Ms Monica Sheehan is the director of public health nursing in Kerry.  She has operated as a provider of home help services for ten years.  There is a procedure for that in the south and she will now outline that to the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_93">
          <from>Ms Monica Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_221">When the "Ageing with Confidence" strategy document for older people was published in 1999, an assessment tool was developed.  It is an objective assessment tool which looks at the needs of clients and it is used predominantly by public health nurses, although occupational therapists, physiotherapists and primary care teams will also contribute to it.  The general practitioners also have an opportunity to give their view.  It is a comprehensive assessment tool.  Much of the literature was reviewed at the time and we have used it very successfully in the south since.  It looks at the environment in which the clients live, their social circumstances, and whether they are disabled or otherwise.  It also looks at the capacity of their carer, if they have one close at hand, family relatives and so on.  It looks at the local environment and what local voluntary groups are available to support this person to remain at home.  It takes a broad approach to the needs of the particular client.  Most old people have a home help service.</p>
          <p eId="para_222">On the issue of how we have allocated home help services, that whole objective, ethos and philosophy was brought forward in 2002 when we started using a tool, which is probably what has gone through all the media which has misinterpreted it, for giving time so that we would continue with the objective of meeting the needs of the particular clients in a professional manner.  A working group comprising the public health nurse, home help organisers and management discussed the tasks performed by our home helps.  The members of the committee have mentioned various tasks such as fire lighting, serving food, making the bed, vacuuming and so on and personal care.  It is broken down into personal care and domestic care.  In the southern area times have been allocated.  To interpret it appropriately, it takes ten minutes for this and ten minutes for that, but it is all the time the home help is in the house.  One does not just go in for the half hour.  It is based on the need of the individual client and on the capacity of the carer and whether they are near a day centre.  We encourage older people to remain socialised, to go to satellite centres and to get involved with whatever voluntary agencies are in the area to keep them independent for as long as possible at home.  This has worked well for us.</p>
          <p eId="para_223">As we progressed we conducted many reviews on how the process was working for us.  We have heard from the clients that no matter what level of service is provided they say it is equitable and accessible and that they get a fair deal compared with other people in, say, Midleton or Ballybunion.  They are dealt with professionally.  Our home helps are valued members of the multidisciplinary team and, hopefully, the training we provide enhances their skills.  We provide on-the-spot training for home helps on special needs such as hoists, moving and handling or putting on special equipment.  The physiotherapist, the occupational therapist, the public health nurse, or oncology nurse may assist.  There is a positive approach to providing a very important service to our older people.  The service is standardised and welcomed by carers and clients alike.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_94">
          <from>Mr. Michael Fitzgerald</from>
          <p eId="para_224">There were a few other questions.  About 85% of all home help service is delivered to older people and the balance of 15% is delivered to those with disabilities, mental health issues and some children and families who may have a requirement.  Home help is provided to people with dementia and people with all types of needs who can be safely maintained in the community as much as possible.  The challenge on a daily basis is to provide a sufficient and adequate level of care.  Down through the years there have always been issues regarding the sufficiency of home help.  Certainly in 2006 and 2007 there was an increase in funding through the home help service and home care packages.  The message from our perspective is that we see it as being an important service.  We are only at the beginning of the provision of that level of service if we are to successfully continue to maintain people at home who can safely remain there.  The level of investment provided in 2000, 2006 and 2007 for home care packages needs to be continued.  Having viewed a Scottish model the investment needs to be continued year-on-year for five years before we can begin to address and reduce the percentage of people over 65 years who have a requirement for continuing care.  It is a daunting task.  There will also be insufficient provision of home help and home care packages.  It is a beneficial and cost-effective service and a very personal service.</p>
          <p eId="para_225">To reiterate, while it is a professional service, home help services, where required, should perform domestic duties.  That issue was raised in the context of professionalisation and people distancing themselves from some of those duties.  Obviously when a resource is scarce one has to maximise its use.  Therefore, if people's needs are to be met, many of which are personal, one has to focus in on that.  That is not to say that the personal duties are not as significant.</p>
          <p eId="para_226">On the provision of guidelines there was an issue concerning the long-fingering of same.  No more than the guidelines that are being adopted for residential care it is a significant development for the home care service and one that should be proceeded with.  Some of the items in the draft guidelines can be implemented in a short period because there are no significant costs associated with them.  They merely provide more oversight on the service.  However, there are issues concerning cost, some of which are in the areas of training and ensuring that everyone would reach certain standards.  We must bear in mind that we have a workforce of people who have come transitionally from being the neighbour providing the service to the present day with specific contracts and training provided.  That is a journey we are on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_95">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_227">I will take two supplementaries from Deputies Flynn and Sherlock.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BeverleyCooperFlynn" eId="spk_96">
          <from>Deputy Beverley Flynn</from>
          <p eId="para_228">I would like the question about the actual review addressed.  An argument was made about the assessment tool with the involvement of GPs and carers.  How can that be true if everybody who is on one hour a day automatically in a review seems to have it cut to three quarters of an hour.  On the face to if, it looks like a straightforward cut.  I fail to be convinced that any assessment tool is being applied.  Is there an independent appeal process?</p>
          <p eId="para_229">In regard to the contract to which Mr. Fitzgerald referred, he said the duties are outlined.  If a woman receives a letter, as in my case, and is told her duties include three things, is there flexibility for the home help to do something else, or does the contract specify that they are the duties she has to fulfil?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_97">
          <from>Deputy Seán Sherlock</from>
          <p eId="para_230">I apologise for coming late to the meeting.  I thank the Chairman for allowing me in and forgive me if some of my points have already been covered.  In regard to the constituency I represent, Cork East, there is a deep sense that there is not a policy in respect of the delivery of home care packages.  I know of nobody who is in receipt of a specific home care package, particularly in the north Cork area.  The sense I have of the situation as it relates to north Cork is such that the policy is <i>ad hoc</i> and that it is a little arbitrary in that there is no consistency for each individual.  One relies on the service but one cannot be guaranteed that it will be delivered to a particular person in his or her home at a given time and it can be cut at a given time also.  We want a national policy or guideline that ensures each person has a minimum right.  I realise Mr. Mulvihill may have addressed that point already and if he has, I apologise but I want to record it anyway.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_98">
          <from>Mr. Noel Mulvihill</from>
          <p eId="para_231">To reply to Deputy Flynn, we take her point that there appears to be a consistent reduction from one hour to three quarters of an hour.  That is something we need to examine, particularly in her area.  We will get back to the Deputy on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BeverleyCooperFlynn" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Deputy Beverley Flynn</from>
          <p eId="para_232">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_100">
          <from>Mr. Noel Mulvihill</from>
          <p eId="para_233">That certainly seems unusual.  What we are saying is that in some areas the position arose where people were providing a service in excess of their budget.  There was a requirement for them to return to their original level of service and I do not know whether that reflects some of what the Deputy is seeing on the ground.  The Deputy's point is about the cut from an hour to three quarters of an hour, and that is something we must examine.</p>
          <p eId="para_234">On the issue of the appeal system, we see two sides to that.  First, there is a needs assessment whereby the professional determines the requirements of the person and, second, there is the provision of hours.  We have in place in all areas a peer review of both sides of that.  The needs assessment is reviewed by a senior manager in a profession.  If it was public health nursing the assistant director of public health or a director of public health nursing would review that aspect.  The provision of hours would be reviewed also by a senior manager in the system.  If the Deputy provides us with the details on the case she mentioned we will pursue that.</p>
          <p eId="para_235">Deputy Sherlock is right about a set of guidelines being required for home care packages.  A Health Service Executive task group is completing a draft document on that issue.  We will discuss it later in the month with the Department with a view to getting it signed off.  We have had some issues with regard to having formal guidelines for home care packages because the question of entitlement keeps cropping up.  There is an issue with regard to the legal status of the provision of home care packages and what one can assess with regard to entitlement.  That has been bothersome in recent years.  A standard approach to the provision of home care packages will be applied and if there are not any further delays in it, it will be rolled out in the last quarter of this year.  There will be a training and roll out application form and an appeals process that will be advertised through the system.  That should——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_101">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_236">Are the means of the applicant being considered as part of that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Mr. Noel Mulvihill</from>
          <p eId="para_237">No.  At this point the means of the applicant cannot be considered.  That was one of the issues that bedevilled the provision of home care packages.  An evaluation of home care packages was undertaken by the Department of Health and Children last year which, on a positive note, concluded that the provision of home care packages was singularly successful in supporting older people with complex needs to live at home, and in supporting acute hospital discharge.  While significant issues arose to be addressed, they are being addressed, mainly in terms of the guidelines.  We will roll that out during the course of the year if we get approval and following conclusion of the discussions with the Department.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_103">
          <from>Mr. Michael Fitzgerald</from>
          <p eId="para_238">I make a point in connection with Deputy Flynn's area and in terms of the review.  I realise it is difficult when there is a reduction in hours.  It is difficult for the client and for everyone involved but we are trying to be careful to ensure that review is carried as efficiently as possible.  The resource is the same as it was for last year but the demand is increasing all the time.  More and more older people now want to stay at home.  We have found also that with the system we have for the movement into residential care, the person is assessed and it is almost the high end, so to speak, that go into residential care.  The demand on home care is much higher but there is a specific budget available.  The division of that budget among that number in that given local health office area often places that demand, which means that we have to review and subsequently reduce hours in some areas where possible to give them to somebody else.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanOFearghaillFF" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_239">I thank the delegates for their presentation and for dealing so comprehensively with the questions.  I ask members to remain while the delegates leave to deal with minutes and some housekeeping items.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">The joint committee went into private session and adjourned at 6.25 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Tuesday, 29 June 2010.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
