<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/committee_on_public_petitions/2017-04-05/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/committee_on_public_petitions/2017-04-05/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-04-05" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/32/committee_on_public_petitions"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/committee_on_public_petitions/2017-04-05/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/committee_on_public_petitions/2017-04-05/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-04-05" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/committee_on_public_petitions/2017-04-05/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/committee_on_public_petitions/2017-04-05/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2019-03-26" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanSherlock" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Sherlock.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Seán Sherlock"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ShaneCassells" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Shane-Cassells.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Shane Cassells"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COISTE UM ACHAINÍOCHA ÓN BPOBAL</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Committee on Public Petitions</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2017-04-05">Dé Céadaoin, 05 Aibreán 2017</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2017-04-05">Wednesday, 05 April 2017</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 01:30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS  PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#ShaneCassells">Deputy Shane Cassells</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#JerryButtimer">Senator Jerry Buttimer.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#DeniseMitchell">Deputy Denise Mitchell</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#EugeneMurphy">Deputy Eugene Murphy</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#SeanSherlock">DEPUTY SEAN SHERLOCK IN THE CHAIR.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
        <summary eId="sum_4">
          <i>The joint committee met in private session until 1.50 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Decisions on Public Petitions Received<recordedTime time="2017-04-05T13:50:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_1">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2017-04-05T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_5">We are now in public session. Petition No. P00024/16 from Mr. Thomas Mackey is on the criteria used to qualify for a primary medical certificate. It is proposed that we invite the Minister of State with responsibility for disability issues, Deputy Finian McGrath, to appear before the committee to discuss the issues raised in the petition. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_6"> The next petition for consideration is No. P00036/16 from Mr. Neil Tolan, which proposes that a regulator be set up for the gambling-gaming industry. It is proposed to correspond with the Department of Justice and Equality and request that it outline a proposed timeline for the introduction of a new executive agency that will act as both the licensing authority and regulator for the gambling sector and to keep the committee updated on any progress in this regard. It is also proposed that we forward the response from the Department to the petitioner and that the petition will remain open to await the outcome of the Gambling Control Bill 2013. Is that agreed? Agreed. </p>
          <p eId="para_7"> The next petition for consideration is Petition No. P00038/16 from Ms Abigail Mulligan to stop the use of Depo-Provera in Ireland. It is proposed, following consideration of this matter, that we forward a copy of the response from the Health Products Regulatory Authority to the petitioner and close the petition. Is that agreed? Agreed. </p>
          <p eId="para_8"> The next petition for consideration is No. P00001/17 from Mr. Oisin Turakhia on the responsible service of alcohol. It is proposed that the committee further examine the issue and write to the petitioner to request that he produce further evidence. Is that agreed? Agreed. </p>
          <p eId="para_9"> The next petition for consideration is No. P00003/17 from Mr. Brian Houlihan on a public consultation on the feasibility of developing a hemp industry. It is proposed that the committee correspond with Teagasc and request an update on recommendations from the 2009 future of the industry study on the development of a hemp industry in Ireland. Is that agreed? Agreed. </p>
          <p eId="para_10"> The next petition for consideration is No. P00004/17 from Mr. Frank Considine on equality for school secretaries. It is proposed that the committee forward a copy of the response from the Department to the petitioner and close the petition. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_11"> The next petition for consideration is No. P00013/17 from Ms. Tara O'Sullivan on making the new English junior certificate examination fairer by adding an extra 30 minutes. It is proposed that we invite officials from the Department of Education and Skills and State Examinations Commission to appear before the committee to discuss how the mock examination papers provided by commercial suppliers to schools will be scrutinised in advance of sale to schools. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShaneCassells" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Deputy Shane Cassells<recordedTime time="2017-04-05T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_12">Ms O'Sullivan deserves praise for corresponding with the committee. I am sure many students leave an examinations hall and have conversations in bike sheds and so forth on aspects of the paper and whether they would have been able to answer question X, Y and Z if they had been given more time. Many of us will have had similar conversations during our junior and leaving certificate days. We should laud Ms O'Sullivan for taking time to correspond with us on the issue. It will be worthwhile to have a further discussion with officials from the Department and show them that someone has taken the time to think about how this issue impacts on students. Examinations should not be shoehorned into a specific time, particularly in English where students should be allowed to demonstrate their skills in creative writing and discussing prose and poetry. It is welcome that someone corresponded with the committee on this matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_3">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2017-04-05T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_13">I concur with the Deputy. Once we have issued the invitation to the Department and State Examinations Commission, it may be a good idea to invite Ms O'Sullivan to appear before the committee, subject to her school schedule. We can consider that issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShaneCassells" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Shane Cassells<recordedTime time="2017-04-05T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_14">Imagine what this would do for school students. A young student has taken time to correspond with the Oireachtas to highlight flaws or an unfairness regarding the time afforded to students to complete examination papers. This would do more than many protests outside the gates of the House. It would also be a great example of the committee's role in dealing with petitioners who advocate for changes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_5">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2017-04-05T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_15">That is agreed. It is proposed to continue our deliberations in private session.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">
          <i> The joint committee went into private session at 1.55p.m. and adjourned at 2.05 p.m. until 1.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 3 May 2017.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
