<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2016-10-13/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2016-10-13/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-10-13" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/32/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2016-10-13/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2016-10-13/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-10-13" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2016-10-13/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_skills/2016-10-13/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2018-09-12" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="CarolNolan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Carol-Nolan.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Carol Nolan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CatherineMartin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Catherine-Martin.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Catherine Martin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FionaOLoughlin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Fiona-O'Loughlin.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Fiona O'Loughlin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JimDaly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jim-Daly.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Jim Daly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MariaByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Maria-Byrne.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Maria Byrne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RobbieGallagher" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Robbie-Gallagher.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Robbie Gallagher"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ThomasByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Thomas-Byrne.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Thomas Byrne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TrevorOClochartaigh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Trevor-Ó-Clochartaigh.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM OIDEACHUS AGUS SCILEANNA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Education and Skills</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2016-10-13">Déardaoin, 13 Deireadh Fómhair 2016</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2016-10-13">Thursday, 13 October 2016</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 09:00 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS  PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#ThomasByrne">Deputy Thomas Byrne</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#MariaByrne">Senator Maria Byrne</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#CiaranCannon">Deputy Ciarán Cannon</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#RobbieGallagher">Senator Robbie Gallagher</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#JimDaly">Deputy Jim Daly</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#TrevorOClochartaigh">Senator Trevor Ó Clochartaigh.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#CatherineMartin">Deputy Catherine Martin</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#CarolNolan">Deputy Carol Nolan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#FionaOLoughlin">Deputy Fiona O'Loughlin</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#FionaOLoughlin">DEPUTY FIONA O'LOUGHLIN IN THE CHAIR.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
        <summary eId="sum_4">
          <i>The joint committee met in private session until 9.30 a.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Scrutiny of EU Legislative Proposals<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_1">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_10">On COM (2016) 381, COM (2016) 382, COM (2016) 383 and COM (2016) 532, is it agreed that the clerk will seek a written response from the Department? Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_11"> As Deputy Catherine Martin is delayed but will be with us soon, I propose that we proceed to the presentation by Wake Up SUSI on the non-payment of maintenance grants to students attending private higher education colleges. I propose that we suspend for a few minutes to allow the witnesses to take their seats.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 9.31 a.m. and resumed at 9.33 a.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Higher Education Grants: Wake Up SUSI<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_2">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_12">I welcome Mr. Pierce Connolly, chairman of Wake Up SUSI and president of Griffith College students' union and Ms Alisha Houlihan and Ms Suzanne Quinn, students, Griffith College; Ms Emma O'Sullivan president, Dublin Business School Students' Union and Mr. James Roberts, student; and Mr. Martin Byrne, student, Irish Colleges of Humanities and Applied Sciences, Limerick, who are here today to discuss the non-payment of maintenance grants to students attending private higher education colleges. I also welcome the students in the Visitors Gallery.</p>
          <p eId="para_13"> Before we begin, I draw the attention of witnesses to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee. However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence. They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable. I also wish to advise the witnesses that their opening statements will be published on the committee's website this afternoon.</p>
          <p eId="para_14"> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_15"> I now invite Ms Alisha Houlihan to make her opening statement. I understand that following her statement, the other students will make a one-minute statement each. Members will have an opportunity after that to ask questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_3">
          <from> Ms Alisha Houlihan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_16">Good morning members, I come from Kiltimagh, County Mayo. I come from a single parent family and I am a full-time second year journalism and visual media scholarship student at Griffith College Dublin. I thank the joint committee for the kind invitation to attending this hearing.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> First, we welcome the statement of the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Bruton, that he proposes to reintroduce grants for part-time post-graduate students but he has forgotten us. We are Wake Up SUSI. We represent about 200 students, eligible for SUSI funding, who applied via the CAO for a full-time QQI validated degree at State recognised institutions that award up to masters level 9 on the NFQ. Our students, from low-income and single parent families, want the same State funding as other third level students attending similar QQI approved institutions. We are not the so-called privileged students that attend private colleges.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> In the past 12 months, we have met SUSI, the HEA, civil servants from the Departments of Education and Skills and Public Expenditure and Reform and over 30 members of the Seanad and Dáil, some of whom kindly tabled parliamentary questions on our behalf. The recently published Cassells report on the funding of higher education recommends that low-income families whose children choose to attend private colleges should receive SUSI funding. Following publication of this report, we met with the Minister, Deputy Bruton. He spent over 35 minutes with us and listened to our case. The Minister noted that Cassells recommended that SUSI grants be extended to our eligible students but he said that he would not make a decision in that regard until this committee had reported to him on the Cassells report.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> Ladies and gentlemen, we are in your hands. We are worried and concerned that in the committee's deliberations on the Cassells report all the attention will be on the issue of student loans and our case will be missed. We are heartened that we have been invited here today. We hope that the committee will support us as the Minister, Deputy Bruton, made it clear he will listen to the committee's recommendations.</p>
          <p eId="para_20"> I am accompanied this morning by other members of the Wake Up SUSI committee. I will shortly ask each of them to make a one-minute statement on how this inequity is affecting them and their families. My first question for the committee is how can SUSI not give those of us from single-parent families and low-income households our entitlement? How can the State on the one hand fund private secondary schools to the tune of over €100 million a year, encourage private health care, private transport and private media and ignore our discrimination?<b>
						</b>We are not here on behalf of the colleges we attend: we want funding for our QQI full-time course. Essentially, we are looking for equality for Irish students regardless of the institution they attend.</p>
          <p eId="para_21"> My second question is why are we being discriminated against for having chosen to undertake a QQI full-time degree course at a reputable private college? We chose Griffith College, the Dublin Business School and the Irish College of Humanities and Applied Sciences because of their reputations and their ability to nurture the student with smaller classes and excellent student supports. Why can we not be treated in the same way as other students attending non-State owned institutions such as the Royal College of Surgeons and National College of Ireland? We have learned that some students attending for-profit colleges such as BIMM, The Sound Training Centre and Setanta College, which are all very reputable and excellent institutions, have been lucky enough to get all their entitlement as their degrees are awarded by institutes of technologies. Our degrees are awarded by QQI. QQI degrees have the same currency as all other degrees awarded in this country. I welcome the opportunity to highlight this point again in our discussion this morning.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> We thank the joint committee for the invitation to attend this meeting and we ask that it make an early recommendation to the Minister, Deputy Bruton, as some of the students we represent are dependent on the Society of St. Vincent de Paul, hand-outs and credit unions to complete their education. Some students have approached the HEA for assistance under its student hardship fund but they were refused as they are not covered by the SUSI scheme.</p>
          <p eId="para_23">Imagine trying to pay €600 a month for a room in Dublin without a SUSI grant or access to the HEA's student assistance fund.</p>
          <p eId="para_24"> I thank the committee for listening to me. I shall introduce each member of our committee who will speak for roughly one minute each. They are as follows: Ms Emma O'Sullivan, who is from Cork and is president of the Dublin Business School students' union; Mr. Pierce Connolly from Roscommon, who is president of the Griffith College students' union in Dublin and is the founder of this campaign; Mr. James Roberts from Cork, who is a Quality and Qualifications Ireland psychology student at Dublin Business School; Ms Suzanne Quin from Raheny, who is a Dublin law student attending Griffith College, Dublin; and Mr. Martin Byrne from Limerick, who is a counselling student at the Irish College of Humanities and Applied Sciences, ICHAS. I call on Ms O'Sullivan to commence her contribution.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_4">
          <from> Ms Emma O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_25">I am a Cork native originally and am the president of the students' union at Dublin Business School where I am studying for my final year of business at law.</p>
          <p eId="para_26"> Each day I encounter genuine students who are eligible for a SUSI maintenance grant. They have come to me to discuss how difficult they have found supporting themselves in Dublin. These students are from low-income families. They chose a private approved third level institution for its reputation and for a full-time QQI degree that was offered as part of the CAO. I would like to share with the committee a blatant injustice. These eligible students have been refused access to the back-to-education allowance and the student assistance fund that has given over €43 million in the past six years to over 77,000 students. Why is this the case? Why have we not been included as part of the scheme? In other private institutions students have been assisted. As I am here to represent DBS students, I put that question to members of the committee. I will hand over to Mr. Pierce Connolly, who is the chair of the Wake Up SUSI campaign and president of Griffith College students' union. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_5">
          <from> Mr. Pierce Connolly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_27">I thank Ms O'Sullivan and the chairperson. My name is Pierce Connolly and I am president of students' union in Griffith College, Dublin. I have gone into my fourth year of a full-time QQI approved degree in journalism.</p>
          <p eId="para_28"> I am eligible for a SUSI grant as only one of my parents works. The reason I established the Wake Up SUSI campaign was because of the unfairness and inequity in the current system. As president of a students’ union, like Ms O’Sullivan, I have seen a lot of students who are struggling. I want to make the committee aware that the State pays €5 million each year for students to go to the UK and over €2 million to students in private colleges that have partnerships with institutes of technology but yet the State will not fund us. I have also discovered that more than 400 students receive SUSI funding even though they attend private for-profit colleges that have partnerships with institutes of technology. I shall discuss further details of this matter with the committee but shall now hand over to Mr. Byrne.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_6">
          <from> Mr. Martin Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_29">I thank the committee for inviting us and listening to us. I am a third year student in ICHAS in Limerick. I hope to be a counsellor and then to go on to be a psychotherapist. I am eligible for the grant. I attended the University of Limerick for a year to study health and safety but left after one year due to mental health reasons. I suffered from depression and the course did not suit me but I was drawn to studying counselling. My college is one of the very few colleges that provide training in counselling. The closest such college to Limerick is Cork but there are two further away in Dublin and Maynooth. These three colleges were the only QQI-accredited courses in counselling that I could find. Unfortunately, we do not get a grant.</p>
          <p eId="para_30"> For members who do not know, ICHAS is a very small college. I can see the University of Limerick, UL, from my college and all I have to do is look out of the door and I can see it. The only difference is that I am across the road. When I crossed the road I immediately lost my grant. This year I have to undertake work experience for my course. For every five hours of work experience I must have an hour of supervision that costs me €50 per hour and I need 25 hours of supervision. I have no subsidies to pay for this. My work experience has eaten into the time that I can work, as it depends on when a person is available to see me. If there is time later in the meeting I wish to go into more detail about my story but for now I will hand over to Mr. James Roberts. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_7">
          <from> Mr. James Roberts<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_31">I am an Irish citizen who has lived in this country for over 15 years. My Dad works hard for his family. He is a taxi driver who works in the city of Cork. There are five children in my family, including myself. I am the second born and my younger siblings are aged 15, 17 and seven. I have always wanted to study for a degree in psychology. My family was very happy with my choice and encouraged me when I was accepted, on my CAO, by Dublin Business School. It is a college that has a great reputation in the area of business. I honestly did not know that DBS was a private college when I applied because the fact was not noted on the CAO form. It was not until I was offered my college place that I was informed I would not receive a SUSI grant.</p>
          <p eId="para_32"> My Dad works mad hours. He works a lot of hours just to keep me in the Dublin Business School. Recently I got a job just to help him and myself as my tuition fees are €5,900 a year and my travel and maintenance costs are at least €700 a month. There are very few colleges that offer a course in psychology. If I attended the Dublin Institute of Technology, DIT, that is located up the road from the Dublin Business School, I would be entitled to a SUSI grant of €2,800 and a registration fee of €3,000, which amounts to nearly €6,000 a year from the State. Is it fair that my family should carry the stress and burden of loans? I now hand over to Ms Quin. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_8">
          <from> Ms Suzanne Quin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_33">I thank the committee for having us. I am from Raheny, Dublin and I am entitled to a SUSI grant, including a registration fee. I am also eligible for a disability access route to education, DARE, place. I come from a low-income family. My Dad was made redundant last year and my Mum is disabled and so receives a disability allowance.</p>
          <p eId="para_34"> I am a second year LLB student at Griffith College in Dublin. I chose the college to improve myself and gain confidence. The college also has an excellent reputation as a law school. I hope to later share the story of two of my colleagues. Ms Amy Liggett is from County Down. She is a law student and is here today. At the last minute she was refused funding to attend Griffith College and is now in a limbo situation. There is also another student who has requested not to be named. She has worked alongside the CLAY Youth Project in Crumlin and with its help, she was able to receive a scholarship to Griffith College but has since been refused a SUSI maintenance grant. As a result she has found it very difficult to keep afloat financially while attending college.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_9">
          <from> Ms Alisha Houlihan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">I thank my colleagues for their contributions. The committee has heard examples of genuine stories and members must see that we are not the so-called privileged kids. There are many more examples that we could give. We have learned from our research that there are no more than 200 students who are eligible for SUSI grants but attend the three colleges, namely Dublin Business School, Griffith College in Dublin, Cork and Limerick and the Irish College of Humanities and Applied Sciences in Limerick. As far as we know this is the total number of institutions that are impacted by this inequity. I thank the Chairman again for the invitation to attend.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_10">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_36">I thank Ms Houlihan, Mr. Connolly, Ms Quin, Ms O'Sullivan, Mr. Roberts and Mr. Byrne for their passionate and strong opening statements. They have raised pertinent points. I commend them on the work they do on behalf of the other 190 students who have been impacted by this matter. I congratulate Mr. Connolly for starting the campaign. Sometimes it just takes one person to stand up and draw attention to an inequity. The committee appreciates the work the witnesses have done to bring this campaign to this point.</p>
          <p eId="para_37"> I ask members to indicate to me now their wish to speak and ask questions. Mr. Byrne has addressed this point to a slight extent but I am interested in how the witnesses chose their colleges. Was it possible for them to apply or attend other colleges that operate the SUSI scheme? </p>
          <p eId="para_38"> The committee is getting into its work programme and will deal with the Cassells report. I would like to hear the views of the witnesses on student loans. Do they think they are a good idea for students in the future?</p>
          <p eId="para_39">We will discuss with a number of different groups all the different options. The witnesses are students on the ground, so I am interested in their views.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_40">I will not delay the witnesses because I have met the group and much of what they say is self-explanatory. However, to be absolutely clear, am I right in saying the campaign is only seeking the maintenance grants?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_12">
          <from> Ms Alisha Houlihan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_41">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">Is it not seeking the fee grants?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_14">
          <from> Ms Emma O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_43">If it is okay, I will take the question-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_15">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_44">No. To be fair, we will group the questions and then return to the witnesses because if we do not, we will take-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">I ask the witnesses to elaborate on that point. That is all. I will not delay them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_17">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">If that is Deputy Byrne's only question, okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">I will be very brief. First, I welcome the witnesses here this morning. I am inspired by them all. They are a credit to themselves and their families, and I compliment them on their campaign and the way they have organised themselves. It is fair to say there is something badly wrong with a system that holds such people back. I for one, and I am sure other members, will give serious consideration to their request. The number to which they referred, 200 students, seems minimal, and the cost of funding 200 people, if they are all on a par with the witnesses, would be a great investment for the State to make because we would get it back tenfold.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MariaByrne" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Senator Maria Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_48">First, I welcome the Wake Up SUSI campaign here this morning. I met members of the Limerick branch of the campaign in Limerick recently and was inspired by the many stories I heard. It is strange that all these courses appear on the CAO yet students are not informed so they go into the application process blindfolded and do not realise that they will not be eligible to receive any of the grants. These are all very legitimate courses. Taking Mr. Byrne's story, he did not have much choice; the course he chose was the only one on offer in his area. I am sure many more such stories are replicated across the 200 students, so I take the campaign very seriously. We need to consider it seriously because why should the 200 students across the country be disenfranchised while we pay for people to go abroad on courses and so on?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_49">I also welcome the group and commend it, as other speakers have done, on its campaign. The witnesses' presentations were very impressive and have given us plenty of food for thought. I have two brief questions. One concerns what Senator Byrne touched on. I am struck by Griffith College, for example, and other colleges that do not inform students of their status as private colleges. Some of the witnesses referred to the fact that they had applied to Griffith College and only realised afterwards that the grants would not be provided. Do the colleges make an effort to inform students in this regard? Second, I am curious to know what SUSI's response to the students has been to date. What kind of reasoning or rationale has been offered to them? In other words, what is the other side of the story that SUSI is putting forward? I am curious to know that. I apologise as I must leave but I will pick up the responses afterwards from the official record.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CarolNolan" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Deputy Carol Nolan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_50">I welcome each and every one of the witnesses. I am amazed that only 200 students are involved in this matter. The situation of the students affected is extremely unfair. If the information being sent out by colleges is not clear, as in a couple of cases in which people genuinely did not realise they were applying to private colleges, that needs to be addressed. I commend all the witnesses. Are the other 196 students all fully behind this campaign? Have they been lobbying as strongly as the witnesses on the issue?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_22">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_51">Does Senator Ó Clochartaigh want to come in?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TrevorOClochartaigh" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Senator Trevor Ó Clochartaigh<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">No. I concur with what has been said already. The witnesses find themselves in a desperate and very unfair situation. What we need to do as a committee is put our heads together and see what solutions can be found to try to make sure that nobody is discriminated against financially because of what would appear to be a lack of information being provided through the CAO system. I thank the witnesses for coming before the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_24">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_53">My apologies, I had skipped over Deputy Martin without meaning to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">That is not a problem. I welcome the witnesses, a few of whom I have met already. It is appalling that they are being left in limbo. I think it was John F. Kennedy who said that education should be the greatest equaliser of all. There is no level playing field in this situation at all, and I am a firm believer in equal access. I was particularly struck by Mr. Byrne's contribution when he said that he lost his grant when he crossed the road.</p>
          <p eId="para_55"> Following on from Deputy Byrne's question, will the witnesses clarify they are only seeking the maintenance grants? I submitted a parliamentary question on this matter and got quite a convoluted answer, at the end of which the Minister stated, "It is open to private higher education institutions that operate on a 'for profit' basis to use their own resources to provide financial supports to students that they consider to be in financial difficulty." I am curious to know whether that happens. Is there any sort of support being offered in any of these colleges?</p>
          <p eId="para_56"> Finally, I agree with the other members about the lack of clarity. I think it was Ms Houlihan who, when I met her, said she was excited to get the course she wanted only to find out she would not get the necessary support. We need to tackle that obstacle as a committee for the witnesses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_26">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_57">I thank members for their questions and comments and give back the floor to the witnesses. Shall I start with Mr. Connolly as chair of the group?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_27">
          <from> Mr. Pierce Connolly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">Yes, that is no problem. The first question concerned student loans. We have not made an informed decision as to whether student loans would be good or bad for us so we will not answer that question.</p>
          <p eId="para_59"> The second question concerned colleges letting us know whether they are private institutions, which is the case. However, our problem is that when we apply through the CAO, we are not told that because we are applying for a particular college we will not get a SUSI grant. One will not see that anywhere on the application form and that is our problem. It is not that the college has not said that it is a private institution; it is that the CAO does not tell us that because we are applying to a particular private institution, we will not get a SUSI grant. My situation is that I applied to Griffith College and then, once I accepted the offer, I was sent back a letter from SUSI stating I would not get any sort of funding from SUSI. That left my family in a very difficult situation as we had to take out credit union loans, borrow from my grandparents and so on. I know of further cases in which people had to borrow from the Society of St. Vincent de Paul as well.</p>
          <p eId="para_60"> Every student who is eligible for a SUSI grant but is not getting it is behind us. It is just that we cannot bring 200 students in here. They are fully behind us. I have talked to so many students. Yesterday I was talking to one who shook my hand and said, "Thank you so much for doing this for us. This will help me. This will benefit me so much." The person about whom I am talking and whom I will not name works ridiculous hours. He does his college work and then goes straight to work four or five days a week after college. In that regard, every student who is eligible for a SUSI grant is 100% behind us and backing us.</p>
          <p eId="para_61"> Other questions-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_28">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">If Mr. Connolly wants to ask any of the other witnesses to answer or respond to any of the questions, he should feel free to do so. We are not putting him in the hot seat all the time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_29">
          <from> Mr. Pierce Connolly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">That is fine.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">Could you answer my question about maintenance and-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_31">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">Through the Chairman.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_32">
          <from> Mr. Pierce Connolly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">What we want is what every other SUSI-eligible student gets, that is, maintenance grants and registration fees.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_33">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">Is the group therefore seeking both?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_34">
          <from> Mr. Pierce Connolly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">Yes. We are asking for equality. We are asking what the difference is between a person who goes to Griffith College and a person who goes to DIT. They both get the exact same Quality and Qualifications Ireland-approved degree at the end of the day, and I do not see why there should be a difference.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">I seek clarity on this point. Regarding the so-called free fees sector, fees were abolished but then a registration fee was brought in. I do not know what it started off at, probably €100, and it is now up to €3,000. That is the registration fee. There is also allegedly a fee that is not charged. In Griffith College is there a registration fee and a further fee, or when Mr. Connolly says "registration fee", does he mean the entire fee that must be paid?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_36">
          <from> Mr. Pierce Connolly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">In the case of Griffith College there is a registration fee and then an extra fee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">How does that break down?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_38">
          <from> Mr. Pierce Connolly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">I would have to ask the president of Griffith College. I would not know fully. I am not involved in the finances of Griffith College.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_39">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">No, but Mr. Connolly knows what he is paying as a registration fee and an extra fee, or are the two combined?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_40">
          <from> Ms Emma O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">It is a combination. It is €5,650 and this comprises the fees for the year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_41">
          <from> Ms Suzanne Quin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">In Griffith College it is broken down. The registration fee is a small part of the total fee. People register and then get access to Moodle, which is where they get their class notes and information from the college. There is a €250 fee at the start of the year, which is taken from the total fee, which for my course is €6,579 a year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_42">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">I thank the witnesses for the clarification.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">The campaign is seeking this entire fee to be funded by SUSI.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_44">
          <from> Ms Emma O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">The common goal is that we have an equal stance. We are not looking for the Government to pay more because the college is asking for more. We want it to be relative to what someone in a public institution receives, such as a €3,000 registration fee, and the student would be liable to pay the top-up. We are not suggesting for one moment that just because a college decides to charge more we should subsequently receive more.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">That answers my question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_46">
          <from> Mr. Martin Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">I want to reiterate that what we seek is to get exactly what any other student gets and we would make up whatever difference exists. This would be a huge help to us. I would say €200 would have got me out of a hole over the past two years I have been in college. Luckily, the support in my college has been very good. We were asked whether we have financial support. My college is very good in the sense I have missed payments, perhaps more than I should, but there has never been any call to the office or a lock-out. If I needed to pay it over the summer that was no problem. If I wanted to leave it for two or three months and come back there was no issue. If it can do anything to help me it will. I mentioned I must do supervision for €50 an hour. My class went from 58 in first year to the high 20s or low 30s. One can argue that a few of them might have left because the course was not for them, and that is perfect, but I know that in many cases the reason was cash. They could not fund it. They could not get the money together, and no matter how much the college accommodated them they could not get it across.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">Are the fees charged by private colleges on a par with non-private colleges? Is it more expensive to go to a private college than to any other?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CarolNolan" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Deputy Carol Nolan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">The situation is unfair and unacceptable, and it discriminates against low income people. I am glad to hear that in Mr. Byrne's case there was some leeway with the college and it provided support and was flexible. Were the other colleges as flexible and supportive?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_49">
          <from> Ms Suzanne Quin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">I have not paid my fees yet and I have not received anything threatening or bad from the college. It has not said anything, just that I need to pay. I have paid my registration fee but there has been no issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_50">
          <from> Ms Alisha Houlihan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">Griffith College has a scholarship scheme, and we have a story from a girl from the Clay project in Crumlin which Ms Quin will relate. I was awarded a scholarship in leaving certificate, due to work I had done with Foróige. This scheme exists for people who cannot afford to go to a private college but perhaps a course there suits them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_51">
          <from> Ms Suzanne Quin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">The girl in question, who would prefer not to be named, is from a very poor background. She got involved with the CLAY youth project in Crumlin and with its aid she was granted a scholarship for Griffith College. She was refused a SUSI maintenance grant and works three days a week while doing a law degree. I also study law and I know the hours that are required for research. She is doing this along with working shifts three days a week to keep herself going. It is difficult. She is in the same situation as we are.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">Are the fees charged by the private colleges the witnesses attend any more expensive than a similar course in a non-private college?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_53">
          <from> Mr. Pierce Connolly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">As far as I am aware they are roughly the same, but if people attending DIT or Trinity College are eligible for SUSI they receive a grant, but those going to Griffith College, Dublin Business School, DBS, or the Irish College of Humanities and Applied Sciences, ICHAS, do not receive any SUSI funding.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">I understand this, but the fees are quite similar.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">Ms Houlihan mentioned in her presentation that she met the Minister, Deputy Bruton, and she seems to be aware of the Cassells report. Did the Minister indicate any opinion on this or will he leave it to the committee?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_56">
          <from> Ms Alisha Houlihan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">He did not give too much away really.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Mr. Pierce Connolly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">To be very fair, he honestly said he would send it to the committee and make a decision based on its decision. We have a letter from the Minister which Ms Quin will explain.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_58">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">That would be useful because the Minister certainly did not write to the committee asking it. It would be helpful if it were read into the record.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_59">
          <from> Ms Suzanne Quin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">I have two letters. The first is dated 3 October 2016. It thanks me for dropping down to the Minister's advice clinic to discuss the case for extending student support schemes to private colleges. The Minister states he will check out exactly what support is extended to colleges such as the National College of Ireland, NCI, and the Royal College of Surgeons of Ireland, RCSI. He states the Department has met the Wake Up SUSI campaign to better understand the case and see whether any facility can be extended, but that, as he mentioned, extending student support schemes which make up a substantial part of €1.5 million spent on higher education to private colleges would be a very big decision with large financial implications needing budgetary provision and Government approval. The second letter comprises education legislation. Shall I read it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_60">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">Is it just the legislation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_61">
          <from> Ms Suzanne Quin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">It is dated 5 October and the Minister states under the Department student grant scheme eligible candidates may receive funding provided they attend an approved course at an approved institution as defined in the scheme. He states the definition of an approved institution is set out in section 7 of the Student Support Act 2011 and regulation 3 of the Student Support Regulations 2016. He states that section 7 defines the matters the Minister for Education and Skills can consider when prescribing an educational institution as being an approved institution. The letter then lists the legislation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_62">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">There is no need to read that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_63">
          <from> Ms Suzanne Quin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">After the legislation he wrote-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_64">
          <from> Mr. Pierce Connolly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">This is in the Minister's own personal handwriting on the actual letter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_65">
          <from> Ms Suzanne Quin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_99">This states the RCSI and NCI have been deemed eligible and both are private colleges. It also states that so far new for profit institutions have not been accepted. The issue this raises is with regard to new institutions. Griffith College and DBS have been around for a long time so why is it not being extended to our colleges?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_66">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">I thank Ms Quin and all of the witnesses, and those who have come to support them. They have raised pertinent and highly relevant points about the blockages that exist. We have another witness coming before the committee so I will allow people to speak briefly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_67">
          <from> Mr. Pierce Connolly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">I have a point on the new for profit institutions. I have done research, and students in three private for profit colleges in Dublin receive a SUSI grant.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_68">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">That is interesting information to have. Will Mr. Connolly name them?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_69">
          <from> Mr. Pierce Connolly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">I have the list here, but unfortunately I do not have a prospectus for any of them. They will be sent to the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_104">There are three main ones which we have discovered. One is that IADT has a partnership with the Sound Training College in Temple Bar, which is a bit of a distance away. That is a partnership in creative music production which costs the State over €150,000. The DIT is in partnership with BIMM music college, which is the British and Irish Modern Music Institute. That course is called "commercial music" and it costs the State €1.2 million. Finally, we have Setanta Sport, which runs a course in conjunction with LIT on sports strength and conditioning, which costs the State €630,000. Over the last year alone, €847,000 was paid to approximately only 400 students attending these courses and getting SUSI grants. I know one of them personally. It was €847,000 in just maintenance grants alone. It is very unfair and upsetting. These are private, for-profit colleges like Griffith, DBS and ICHAS but because they have a partnership with an institute of technology, their students receive a SUSI grant. I think the members can agree that it is very unfair.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_70">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">The point is well made. The whole presentation has been very informative. There is a great deal of empathy from the members in regard to the particular situation in which the witnesses find themselves. We are all very supportive of equal access to education for all. As I indicated, the Minister has not written to us to say he wanted us to make a recommendation to him. He has written to us about a number of other situations, of course. We discussed that earlier this morning. However, we will be happy to make a recommendation, in particular when we are considering funding for higher level in the context of the Cassells report. We will take on board the presentation that was made this morning.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Higher Education Authority: Chairperson Designate<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:10:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_71">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">I welcome on behalf of the joint committee Mr. Michael Horgan, the chairperson designate of the Higher Education Authority. Mr. Horgan is with us today to discuss the approach he intends to take if and when appointed to the role and his views on the challenges currently facing the HEA, of which there are many. The joint committee welcomes the opportunity to meet the chairperson designate in public session to hear his views.</p>
          <p eId="para_107"> I draw the attention of the witness to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee. However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence. They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable. Any submission or opening statement provided to the committee will be published on the committee's website after the meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_108"> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_109"> I ask Mr. Horgan to make his opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_72">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">Sé mo phribhléid bheith i bhur measc inniu mar cathaoirleach ainmnithe an tÚdarás um Ard Oideachas. It is a privilege and an honour for me to come before the joint committee as chairperson designate of the Higher Education Authority. I record my thanks and appreciation to the joint committee for rearranging the original date of this meeting and facilitating me. In opening, I will take a few minutes to give the committee some background on myself. I woke up in the middle of the night last night thinking about this and I realised that I had not mentioned my family in the text of my opening statement. My wife Carmel and children, Emma and Dave, are the rock of anything I have done and anything I will do in future, notwithstanding which I realised at about 4 a.m. I had not mentioned them.</p>
          <p eId="para_111"> I was born in Cork and went to the North Monastery Christian Brothers school. When I left school, I went straight to work at Cork Corporation as a clerical officer. After being a clerical officer, I was what was called at the time a "work study assistant" which was a role dealing with time and motion and method studies. It was an unusual thing to do at the time. From there, I joined AnCo, the industrial training authority and precursor to FÁS, as a training advisor and, subsequently, I moved to the Institute of Public Administration as training specialist. I was there for approximately two and a half years before moving from the IPA to the Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland, RCSI, where I was an administrative assistant. I remained in the RCSI until I stepped down as chief executive in December 2009.</p>
          <p eId="para_112"> During my time in the RCSI, I was involved in all aspects of college management, including student affairs, curriculum development, faculty administration, examinations, human resources, and project management. Finally, I worked there as chief executive.</p>
          <p eId="para_113">I was deputy chief executive for nine years before I became chief executive. In the 1990s, I was also deputy director of a contract we had to manage in a hospital in north-western Saudi Arabia. Later in the 1990s, from 1993-94, I was involved in the establishment of the first overseas campus of RCSI in Penang, Malaysia - the Penang Medical College. In early 2000, I initiated and led the project of developing the first online surgical training programme, at the time the first in the world. It is named BeST, which stands for Basic electronic Surgical Training. This training programme comprised over 400 hours of online instruction in all aspects of the basic sciences of surgery. It is still in use and continues to be an exemplar of what is possible in terms of e-learning. In 2002, I led the negotiations and the team establishing our campus in Bahrain. This campus has a purpose-built medical school building next to a general hospital. The building was officially opened by President Mary McAleese in 2006.</p>
          <p eId="para_114"> Not long after joining RCSI, I applied to and entered Trinity College as a mature student on its evening course leading to a BSc in computer science. Having completed that degree, I took a break of two to three years and then enrolled in University College Dublin to complete a masters degree in industrial engineering, which was also an evening programme. Because of that background, it is fair to say that I have a different or non-traditional view of education and, obviously, would be an advocate for flexible learning, lifelong learning or any kind of programme that makes it easier for citizens or residents of Ireland to access education in any form.</p>
          <p eId="para_115"> I am a chartered director, having completed the Institute of Directors programme and I currently hold directorships in a number of organisations. I chair the Health and Safety Authority, where my term ends in December of this year, having served two terms. I was honoured to be nominated for the first term by the former Minister of State, Deputy Dara Calleary, and for the second term by the Minister, Deputy Richard Bruton. I should declare that I am not a member of any political party and never have been, although I am not sure whether that is a good or bad thing. I also chair the board of TransferMate, which is a global payments FinTech company based in Kilkenny and part of the Taxback Group. I am on the board of Intuition Limited, a knowledge management learning company based in the IFSC, where I first came across e-learning in the true sense. I am a board member of Respect, the fund-raising arm of the Daughters of Charity services for people with intellectual disabilities and I have been chairing its research board for the past five years. Through the stellar work of Professor Brian Harvey, our director of research, we were awarded a Marie Curie co-fund research grant with a total value of over €7 million that will fund a total of 25 research fellows.</p>
          <p eId="para_116"> I applied for the position of chairperson of the Higher Education Authority, HEA, through the Public Appointments Service in January of this year and was recommended to the Minister following a competition run by that agency. My background in education and a strong sense of duty to make a positive difference was probably my main motivation to apply.</p>
          <p eId="para_117"> The HEA was established under the Higher Education Authority Act 1971, with amendments in the Universities Act 1997 and the Institutes of Technology Act 2006. It is the statutory funding authority for the universities, institutes of technology and a number of other designated institutions, and is the advisory body to the Minister for Education and Skills in regard to the higher education sector. The HEA also has responsibility for the effective governance and regulation of higher education institutions and the higher education system. As such, the HEA is the lead organisation for the development of a higher education and research system that meets the needs of Irish society and the Irish economy and is accountable to the Minister for Education and Skills for that leadership. A key aim of the HEA is to create a higher education system that maximises opportunities and ensures a high quality experience for students.</p>
          <p eId="para_118"> The Irish Research Council operates as a sub-board of the HEA and is responsible primarily for funding early-stage career researchers across all disciplines, including frontier research - it uses the tag "From arts to zoology". The vision of the council is for a healthy research ecosystem in Ireland which provides a diversity of supports and opportunities, and which enables the country to reap the full value and benefits of research.</p>
          <p eId="para_119"> Last year, the HEA was responsible for the allocation of €1.1 billion in Exchequer funding to the higher education institutions and is responsible for evaluating the impact of that funding through reporting on system performance. The national strategy for higher education to 2030 is a key challenge as it assigns certain operational responsibilities to the HEA. These include reform of the relationship between Government funding and institutions through performance agreements, significant structural reform on a thematic basis and the process of technological university development. The Minister has also set priorities in regard to the following: widening participation in higher education by the most disadvantaged socioeconomic groups by 7%; a 5% increase in participation by under-represented groups in initial teacher education; a 5% increase in participation by lone parents; and a 25% increase in the number of entrants studying on a flexible basis. Other priorities include doubling the number of apprenticeships by 2020, increasing work placement or work-based projects as part of the course and significantly improving retention rates. These are all exciting objectives and, with the collaboration and support of the leadership of universities and institutes, they should be more than achievable. I have no doubt that, if this is implemented, our society will benefit greatly.</p>
          <p eId="para_120"> Research is a vital part of the work of third level institutions. It is often said that the research of today becomes the practice of tomorrow, and that is true whether it is in medicine, technology, engineering or any aspect of academic study. Research poses many challenges, especially funding. Not everyone sees the advantages of research or recognises the outcomes of research in everyday life. It is a long-term play and requires long-term commitment. This is something not always obvious to the public but one of the truly strategic decisions any group of legislators can make is to provide sustained funding for third level research.</p>
          <p eId="para_121"> Most commentators agree that the current funding arrangement for higher education is unsustainable and that reform is needed to redress the cut in resources over the past eight years. The projected increase in student demand in the order of 25% over the next ten years due to demographic trends will also put additional strains on the system. The Cassells report has identified both the funding quantum and possible funding sources, of which the committee will be aware. Once political decisions are made on these major issues, it will be the responsibility of the HEA to implement them. I am very grateful to committee members for their time and attention and I would be delighted to answer any questions they may have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_73">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">I thank Mr. Horgan for his opening statement. He certainly has a wealth of experience both nationally and internationally in the education sector. It would be interesting to hear a little more about the best education scheme, in particular in regard to online training, which is becoming increasingly popular.</p>
          <p eId="para_123"> Mr. Horgan stated that his main motivation in applying for the job was a strong sense of duty in regard to making a positive difference.</p>
          <p eId="para_124">It is striking to note that Mr. Horgan is an advocate for flexible and lifelong learning, especially in terms of access to education. Mr. Horgan referred to the low level of take-up by disadvantaged groups. I would be interested to hear if he has any plans or proposed strategies to improve the situation.</p>
          <p eId="para_125"> He also mentioned the Cassells report. We are setting up a strong work programme for the next few months and we are interested to hear any views or observations on the report that he could share with us today to assist us in our work.</p>
          <p eId="para_126"> I am pleased to note the positive references in terms of doubling apprenticeships because it is hugely important to all of us in the skills area. Any insights or observations he has on how that would be achieved would be very welcome also. I will now hand over to my colleagues. Members should indicate if they wish to speak.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">I welcome Mr. Horgan. I am conscious that he is the chairperson designate; he is not the chairperson or CEO. He will not be the CEO so I will not test him on his knowledge. What is of interest is his CV and his overall philosophy of education, in particular on higher education.</p>
          <p eId="para_128"> The question of funding is at the root of everything at the moment. We have had a major political debate in recent weeks and I hope we succeeded in making a start and introducing change. What is Mr. Horgan’s view of excellence in education, in third level education in particular? In recent years the major universities in this country have gone down the rankings and that is rightly partially blamed on the funding model and the lack of funding. What can we do to improve that and is it a target of Mr. Horgan that we would have universities at the top level and then that there would be other universities and institutes of technology, which are all doing a particular job?</p>
          <p eId="para_129"> The Oireachtas has not finalised its position on the Technological Universities Bill. It seems to me that there are arguments for and against it. Some of the arguments against it relate to the fact that it was initially conceived from a cost-cutting point of view on foot of the famous McCarthy report and an bord snip nua back in 2009. I know the situation has moved on since then but that is where it started. One argument I have heard is that if that is the only reason, then why do it? Some of the colleges that are part of the proposal on technological universities are very much rooted in local communities and people see it as being very important to keep a certain college in a locality because it serves an area where it is needed. Where does Mr. Horgan see the Higher Education Authority, HEA, in that space at the moment where there are arguments for and against and the Bill has not gone through the Oireachtas? In the past year, considerable funding was provided to pursue the model despite the lack of legislation.</p>
          <p eId="para_130"> That is all I have to say at the moment. If there is time I might come back in at the end given that there are not too many members present.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_75">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">I will take a question from Deputy Nolan before I go back to Mr. Horgan for a response.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CarolNolan" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Deputy Carol Nolan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">I welcome Mr. Horgan here today. Access has been a huge problem and it was identified in the Cassells report that lower socioeconomic groups are not taking up education. Adult learning is also an issue. Mr. Horgan went into education as an adult in later life. Could he indicate what approaches are needed? The Government has a strategy in place and it has acknowledged that there is a problem and that is good but we need action. What action does Mr. Horgan consider necessary?</p>
          <p eId="para_133"> Educational funding is essential. Politicians are aware that it is needed and that we cannot continue without it. Have there been cuts to educational research over the years and has that had a detrimental effect? What kind of funding would be needed to bring it up to the required level?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_77">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">I will hand over to Mr. Horgan to respond to the first set of questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_78">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">If you do not mind, Chairman, I will respond to Deputy Byrne's questions first. In response to the question about excellence in education, the problem with excellence is that one cannot measure it. It is not a final point. It is like quality. It is a journey one is going on. To me, excellence is something one never achieves because one keeps working to improve things. If one looks at a quality improvement system, one never gets to a stage where one says one is absolutely happy now that it has been reached. Excellence is a word that is thrown around all the time but one cannot measure it and say this is it. It is a perpetual road that one is on and one never arrives. One needs other ways to measure it. When one looks at the Irish education system, it provides all sorts of different services and outcomes in different ways, between the universities and colleges of further education, and in particular the institutes of technology. They are all involved in education and they all consider that they are doing excellent programmes but it is what is appropriate to the country that we should be looking at. We need an education system that suits the way the economy is going, the way the workforce is going, and the way trends are going in the sectors within the economy before we start to look at international rankings.</p>
          <p eId="para_136"> My view is that if international rankings improve because of what we are doing internally, that is great, but the idea of having international rankings as a strategic objective now is unsustainable. The word "unsustainable" keeps being used. There is a report by the World Bank on achieving world status in university rankings and the No. 1 factor in that regard is funding. It is said that funding alone will not get one there but without funding all the other things that one needs will not be in place to get one there. Therefore, one needs funding. Last year €1.1 billion was spent on third level education. That is probably equivalent to the total budget of a relatively small college in the United States. Without the kind of funding that is required, in order to go up the rankings one would need significant investment at this stage. If we discovered oil off Kerry and suddenly we had loads of money coming in, of course one would do that but where we are at the moment, we need to get what we have working optimally and then look again at the situation. If the rankings improve because of what we are doing well internally, that is great.</p>
          <p eId="para_137"> Technological universities originally came from the Colm McCarthy report. That is probably where the idea came from but there is also the idea of having clusters. From the HEA's point of view, it is a political policy so it is something that, is handed over to us to progress. In terms of whether it is a good thing or a bad thing, my personal opinion is that it is a good thing. I do not see why there should be a difference in the qualification of those who graduate from institutes that are grouped together and are providing programmes that are approved by Quality and Qualifications Ireland, QQI, and are accredited. I do not believe the qualification would be of a different standing or ranking. Personally, I do not have a problem with the policy.</p>
          <p eId="para_138"> I will now respond to the question on access.</p>
          <p eId="para_139">It is about the culture of the institutions. If leadership does not filter down to all staff in the universities and institutes and access is not seen as a daily event in the work of an institution, it will not work. I have seen great examples of universities and colleges having superb access programmes to reach out and identify students in pre-third level education and work them through the system. It is most definitely a cultural issue within an organisation and it must be nurtured and grown. The way the HEA can improve access to increase the numbers is through the performance measures we agree with each of the universities and institutes. We are looking for access to be front and centre in terms of performance. It means everything. It is not just for disadvantaged students; it is also for those who did not go to college full time and want to go back to get a degree. That is very close to my thinking. I know that it is already included in the objectives for the year, but it is something we must target to ensure we will be able to measure improvements in access to the colleges. Once it becomes a habit and part of every day life, it will work forever.</p>
          <p eId="para_140"> When Deputy Carol Nolan asked about research funding, did she mean funding for educational research separate from funding for any other purpose?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CarolNolan" eId="spk_79">
          <from>Deputy Carol Nolan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_80">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">Given my experience of online learning under the surgical training programme, we were probably about six to eight years too early in terms of broadband speed to really make a bang. In 2001 and 2002, when online courses became available, one did not have the same broadband speeds; there were ISDN lines and dial-up systems. Downloading graphics took a long time; however, at the time we conducted research into how individuals learned. The aim was to include it in the structure of the programme. There have been enough developments both on the IT side and on the broader networking side that the issue of research into educational development probably needs to be looked at again. Technology has become part of everyday life. No matter where one goes, somebody has a mobile phone and he or she will know how to use a tablet and if he or she knows how to use a tablet, he or she will know how to use a PC. Technology is now way beyond what used to be the barriers to online learning. I suspect that funding for educational research will have to increase to meet the next wave of technology to apply education to real life.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">I welcome Mr. Horgan and thank him for his presentation.</p>
          <p eId="para_144"> The previous chief executive, Mr. Tom Boland, retired in July. I believe his replacement announced that she would only be staying on for a few months. It is a key position. Is Mr. Horgan aware of plans to fill it?</p>
          <p eId="para_145"> The Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Richard Bruton, appeared before the committee a few weeks ago to brief us on the mid-year expenditure review. The reference to the early payment of grants to universities and institutes of technology is worrying. Were grants paid earlier because they were under water? Were they paid early because the institutions were running out of money and reaching insolvency? Does Mr. Horgan have a handle on the overall scale of problem with their cash flows?</p>
          <p eId="para_146"> I believe the last real benchmark report on third level institutions was produced in 2013 and indicated a significant decline. I know that we have had some quantitative and qualitative data since. When will the HEA produce the next benchmark report to measure accurately the impacts on third level education in the past few years?</p>
          <p eId="para_147"> I raise the question of gender. When I was preparing for this meeting, I learned on the HEA's website that in Ireland 81% of professional positions were held by men. While women comprised 62% of non-academic staff, men comprised 72% of the highest paid. While there are four female presidents of institutes of technology, there has never been a female president of a university in the Republic. Recent media reports indicate that some institutes are struggling in meeting the challenge of gender equality. I welcome the strides made in some colleges. DCU recently renamed a significant number of buildings after accomplished women. Because of initiatives such as Athena and Swan, 50% of candidates who are short-listed must be female. What has the HEA learned to date in this regard and is there more that could be done?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_82">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_148">Let me tell the committee about the position of chief executive officer. The interim CEO, Dr. Anne Looney, is present. She has very kindly taken up the post on a short-term contract and will be starting as head of the new institute of education in DCU in January or February. A competition was held in February or March this year, but nobody was appointed. The day before yesterday we started the competition to find a new chief executive officer which is a key position. There are two major things that I will push to have done. I will push for the recruitment of a new chief executive officer and a new strategic plan for the Higher Education Authority. These are two major issues. We hope to advertise for a new CEO sometime in the next few weeks and that we will have a name by about December. It will then be a matter for the person to be appointed to give notice as to when he or she can start. We might also have to negotiate with Dr. Looney and perhaps DCU at that stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">Has Mr. Horgan a contingency plan in place in case there is a holding period?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_84">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">We might have to come up with something at that stage. We cannot presume anything, but we hope to be in a position to persuade.</p>
          <p eId="para_151">On the question of the cash flow of colleges and institutes, I cannot answer that because I do not have the knowledge as I have had only one board meeting. However - and I ask Dr. Looney to correct me if I say something heretical - we have colleges and institutes that we class as borderline and that we need to mind carefully and so on in terms of funding. That is for various reasons. It could be that they are not meeting budgets. I suspect that is why that funding has been moved forward a little. I am guessing that is the case but I have not caught up on the matter yet.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">I might pursue that with Mr. Horgan at a later stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_86">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">Sure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_87">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">Institutions flagged as borderline and their future are of concern to me, particularly if they are underwater.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_88">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">In respect of the reports we get back from the colleges and universities, we must have safeguards in place all the time to make sure of where their budgets were and what their plans were to ensure they will not get deeper into a worse situation. That is what we are doing at the moment. It is fair to say we are doing much hand-holding with various colleges.</p>
          <p eId="para_156"> Regarding the Deputy's question about benchmarking, I think she probably means the performance-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_89">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">Institutional and sectoral progress.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_90">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">We are just about on to that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_91">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">Good.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_92">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">We want to move quite soon on it.</p>
          <p eId="para_161"> Regarding gender equality and the way we can influence it, gender is part of our performance metrics as well with the universities, so we ask-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_93">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">On a point of order, is Dr. Looney entitled to sit beside the chairman designate if she or he so wishes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_94">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">Apparently not.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_95">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">Okay. Excuse me for raising the point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_96">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">It is a very lonely spot over here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_97">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">The Garda Commissioner had an entourage of 14 yesterday, so I thought Mr. Horgan might be entitled to one.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_98">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">I had imagined that Dr. Looney would be here and that she would be able to write me notes.</p>
          <p eId="para_168"> The committee knows all about the gender equality issue. Members know of the issues in Galway. It is not just Galway; it is elsewhere too. It goes back to culture again. I am pretty certain that it concerns the culture within organisations. However, it is one of the elements within our performance metrics now, so we look to see how it is changing. I suspect it will take a little time but it is bound to come to where it should be and probably beyond quite quickly if one considers the demographics of graduates leaving various university areas at the moment. We are working on it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_99">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">I understand there was a report published with recommendations regarding-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_100">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_170">I think it only came out last year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_101">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">Yes. I assume from what Mr. Horgan is saying that those recommendations will be implemented.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_102">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">Within our performance metrics.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_103">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">Senator Gallagher has indicated. I suggest that this be the last round. Does anybody else want to come in? No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">I will be brief because I know the Chairman is under pressure. I too welcome Mr. Horgan. I enjoyed his opening presentation. His journey and the road he has travelled to lead him here this morning is quite impressive, and I compliment him on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_105">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">I thank the Senator.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">I have a couple of questions. What is the term of his contract and what does he feel he can achieve within that time constraint?</p>
          <p eId="para_177"> The post-Brexit situation is an issue that affects us all. How does Mr. Horgan see that affecting his particular area, and what risks and indeed opportunities might there be for Ireland regarding Brexit?</p>
          <p eId="para_178"> He mentioned apprenticeships, an area which is vitally important to our future. How does he see that developing? A key issue for me is the speed of delivery of apprenticeships.</p>
          <p eId="para_179"> Earlier he talked about and seemed to be a champion of lifelong learning and online learning. How do we compare internationally in these areas? These are doors that can open up education to people whom it would have passed by heretofore. We should concentrate on these areas.</p>
          <p eId="para_180"> Finally, I hope I am correct in saying that institutes of technology are not allowed to borrow money at present to enhance their facilities and so on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_107">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">That is right.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_108">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">How does Mr. Horgan feel about that? Is that an area we should consider?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_109">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">Nobody else is indicating, so I will hand the floor back to Mr. Horgan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_110">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">My term is five years. Regarding my achievements, in a first draft of my statement I put in what I thought I might do but I took them out. Education is a very big ship, and to turn it will take a long time in all sorts of ways. From my initial experience with the HEA, I would like to see the governance of the institutions change because, from what I have seen, I do not think they have governance that is fit for purpose in place. Many issues come back to the HEA, almost like a child to a parent, when the organisations should be dealing with them internally themselves. I would also like to see a greater emphasis on the area to which Senator Gallagher referred in one of his last questions, that is, lifelong learning and access to it. I would like to see that opened up much more, and I suspect that competition is what will change that. Since I got word in July of my appointment, I have been doing much reading, and I found in one of the subjects that I followed up on with the Brookings Institution in Washington that one of its researchers is showing that the cost of education in the US is starting to drop. That is because of competition, and well-known, reputable universities are now coming into the electronic age in the provision of education. If that trend continues, it will have profound effects, both good and bad, on Irish education, but has very positive effects in terms of what it could make available to the population of the country. It may be that one will not study with an Irish institution but with some other institution, which is interesting because competition will make the Irish education sector sit up and take notice.</p>
          <p eId="para_185"> My gut feeling is that Brexit is an opportunity for education in Ireland, in both the research and international student areas. It is a matter of whether that will balance out the downside elsewhere of what it is being predicted in the food and agriculture areas. However, there is, I suspect, significant potential for us within the education sector, so we need to be ready for that and ready to take advantage of it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_111">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">On that point, through the Chairman, if I may, in order for us to tap into that potential, what should we be doing that we are not doing currently?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_112">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">We have probably started already. We have already had a round-table discussion with the heads of all the institutions and they have been making contact with, for instance, UK universities because there is potential for partnerships there, whereby we would be the EU partner and they would be the non-EU partner. Then there is the identification of the markets that are big for UK international students. We should be considering those also to see what the opportunities are there for us.</p>
          <p eId="para_188">A question was asked about borrowings, and it is correct that the institutes of technology cannot borrow. This is in the Act which established them. The universities can do so without the approval of the HEA or the Minister. It is just one of those quirks of the statutes. It is probably why some of the institutes of technology are not on as sound a financial footing as others, but this is the fact of the legislation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_113">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">On behalf of the committee, I thank Mr. Horgan very much for coming before us and for engaging in such an interesting, worthwhile and certainly very productive morning. We could stay here for hours discussing the many different facets of education that will come under his remit. On behalf of the committee, I wish him well in his very important role in higher education at what is a very challenging time. We look forward to perhaps having further discussion with Mr. Horgan when we are dealing with the Cassells report. I propose that the Clerk sends a letter to the Minister for Education and Skills stating the committee approves Mr. Horgan's appointment. It that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_114">
          <from> Mr. Michael Horgan<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">I thank the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 11 a.m. and resumed at 11.04 a.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="motion" eId="dbsect_5">
        <heading>State Examinations: Motions<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_115">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">We will now deal with the motions from Deputies Thomas Byrne and Catherine Martin regarding the 10% loss of marks in the junior certificate English exams for students in ASTI-staffed schools.</p>
          <p eId="para_192"> Before we commence, I advise members that if the motions or amended motions are agreed by the committee, the agreed motion will be reported to both Houses. In addition, the report containing the agreed motion will be sent to the Minister for Education and Skills for a response. Given that we have two motions on the same issue, I propose to ask Deputies Byrne and Martin to move and speak on their respective motions. I will then ask Deputy Daly to move and speak on his amendments to Deputy Byrne's motion. Deputy Byrne submitted his motion first, hence I will take his first and members may ask questions. Following the conclusion of the debate I will put the questions in accordance with standing orders.</p>
          <p eId="para_193"> Deputy Thomas Byrne has submitted a motion that the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Education and Skills, being concerned that students in ASTI-staffed schools will automatically and unfairly lose 10% in their English exams this academic year, recognises that talks between the Department of Education and Skills and the ASTI are continuing in an effort to resolve this dispute but, despite these talks, the ongoing dispute between the ASTI and the Department over changes to the junior certificate cycle is a significant cause of frustration and concern to students and their families; that the position of the Department of Education and Skills that the students affected by the dispute, but not other students, will automatically lose 10% of their marks through no fault of the students, is deeply unfair to those students and cannot be allowed to happen and is placing an undue burden of stress on the students; and calls on the Minister for Education and Skills to instruct the State Examinations Commission, together with the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment, co-ordinated by the Department of Education and Skills, to devise and implement this year a new method of assessment for students who will be unable to undertake the classroom-based assessment of their English junior certificate cycle due to the non-co-operation with the junior cycle changes by ASTI members; and to immediately withdraw the threat of the punishment of students by the deduction of 10% from their English exams.</p>
          <p eId="para_194"> Deputy Catherine Martin has submitted a motion that the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Education and Skills asks the Minister for Education and Skills to move quickly to put in place a plan B to protect those students who might lose out on 10% of their grade in English due to the ongoing dispute between the ASTI and the Government.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_116">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">I move:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_196">That the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Education and Skills, being concerned that students in ASTI-staffed schools will automatically and unfairly lose 10% in their English exams this academic year, recognises that talks between the Department of Education and Skills and the ASTI are continuing in an effort to resolve this dispute but, despite these talks, the ongoing dispute between the ASTI and the Department over changes to the junior certificate cycle is a significant cause of frustration and concern to students and their families; that the position of the Department of Education and Skills that the students affected by the dispute, but not other students, will automatically lose 10% of their marks through no fault of the students, is deeply unfair to those students and cannot be allowed to happen and is placing an undue burden of stress on the students; and calls on the Minister for Education and Skills to instruct the State Examinations Commission, together with the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment, co-ordinated by the Department of Education and Skills, to devise and implement this year a new method of assessment for students who will be unable to undertake the classroom-based assessment of their English junior certificate cycle due to the non-co-operation with the junior cycle changes by ASTI members; and to immediately withdraw the threat of the punishment of students by the deduction of 10% from their English exams.</p>
          <p eId="para_197">Over the past two weeks, since I tabled the motion, I have continued my engagement on behalf of my party with the ASTI, the TUI and the Department of Education and Skills. As the motion acknowledges, talks are taking place between the Department and the ASTI on the issue of junior certificate reform. I understand talks will take place again next Wednesday.</p>
          <p eId="para_198"> There seems to have been a huge gap between last November and the formation of the Government in May when much time was lost and wasted by the Department and the Government. This is deeply unfortunate and this time cannot be got back. We will have a ballot result from the ASTI, which is protesting outside the Dáil today. Many things are happening. Fianna Fáil remains deeply concerned about the 10% of marks, as do parents and children. At this point, we are at a few seconds to midnight in this process. If the ASTI is to do what the Department is asking it to do, or if there is to be any other move, it will have to ballot its members which will take some time.</p>
          <p eId="para_199"> The interests of children must be at the centre of all of this. Talks are continuing, and I do not want to do anything to upset those talks, and the sentiment is in the motion. While the talks continue and there is still hope that officials and the Government can sort this out with the ASTI, and the ASTI might be in a position to move on this and I cannot say whether it is or not, it might be wise for me not to put this motion today but rather to withdraw it, with leave of the committee, to resubmit it at some point in the near future, to allow these talks to continue and not create an atmosphere around them. It might be more helpful if we did not pass a motion today.</p>
          <p eId="para_200"> The fact we are having this discussion here today, with two motions and an amendment to the motions on the table, should alert the Department and the ASTI to the deep concern the committee has about the issue, and the various parties on the committee who have engaged on the issue in the weeks since I have tabled the motion. We want to see this sorted out in the best interests of the children.</p>
          <p eId="para_201">I will withdraw my motion, but what Deputy Martin does is a matter for herself. We will not be for or against. We will abstain on amendments or motions to be consistent with our position today, but I may have to raise the issue again.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7"> Motion, by leave, withdrawn.</summary>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_117">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">I thank Deputy Byrne. It is a matter of grave concern for all of us, students and their parents. As to the possibility of tabling this motion in future, I suggest that the Deputy do so as he sees fit.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_118">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">Sure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_119">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">It will be up to him and not the committee. I call Deputy Martin, who has a motion on the same issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_120">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">I move:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_206">That the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Education and Skills asks the Minister for Education and Skills to move quickly to put in place a plan B to protect those students who might lose out on 10% of their grade in English due to the ongoing dispute between the ASTI and the Government.</p>
          <p eId="para_207">Recently, the Minister for Education and Skills appeared before the committee and said that he could not guarantee that junior cycle students sitting the English course would not lose out on 10% of their grades next year. This is causing them and their parents considerable worry and uncertainty. Talks are continuing, but a plan B is needed. Since we do not know what the end result of the talks will be, the Minister must put a plan B in place for the students. It should not be the case that thousands of junior cycle English students will enter exam halls next June knowing that they are down 10% before they even put pen to paper. That would be unacceptable. The Minister has a duty to put a contingency plan in place. The results of the ballot will be revealed tomorrow and, as Deputy Byrne mentioned, the ASTI is protesting outside Leinster House today, but we need to put our children front and centre. I appeal to the Minister to address this issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_208"> The aim of my motion is to put a plan B in place in order that no students are worried as they face their first State examinations. They are already worried. I am a former English teacher. I know how stressed out students get. There is so much talk about the stresses upon students these days. Given that the first State exam places them under extreme stress, can we not soothe their worries and their parents' worries by showing that, if the dispute continues into June, the Department and the Minister will take action and put a plan in place?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_121">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">I thank the Deputy. Deputy Jim Daly has submitted an amendment to Deputy Martin's motion which reads that, despite these talks, the ongoing dispute between the ASTI and the Department over changes to the junior cycle is a significant cause of frustration and concern to students and their families. His amendment would replace that to the effect that the position that students affected by the dispute and not others will automatically lose 10% of their marks through no fault of the students is deeply unfair to these students and cannot be allowed to happen and is placing an undue burden of stress on the students; that the ASTI's current directive is now directly negatively impacting on examination students; that such selective targeting of students is an unprecedented and wholly unjustifiable industrial relations strategy; that, as a result of the directive, current ASTI English teachers are now in their third year of delivering a new curriculum for which they have been prevented from receiving full professional development; that the Minister for Education and Skills requested the ASTI to provide an immediate derogation from its directive for current teachers of English while talks between the Department and the union on the junior cycle proceed; that the Department remains in discussions with the ASTI on this issue; and that the Minister for Education and Skills remains willing and available to engage with the ASTI on this issue; urges the ASTI to engage positively on this issue with a view to finding a solution; and calls on the ASTI to respond immediately and positively to the Minister's request for an immediate derogation from its directive for current teachers of English while talks between the Department and the union on the junior cycle proceed, and to engage urgently with the Department to resolve outstanding concerns. I invite the Deputy to speak in support of his amendment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_122">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">I move that Deputy Martin's motion be amended to read:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_211">That the position that students affected by the dispute and not others will automatically lose 10% of their marks through no fault of the students is deeply unfair to these students and cannot be allowed to happen and is placing an undue burden of stress on the students; that the ASTI's current directive is now directly negatively impacting on examination students; that such selective targeting of students is an unprecedented and wholly unjustifiable industrial relations strategy; that, as a result of the directive, current ASTI English teachers are now in their third year of delivering a new curriculum for which they have been prevented from receiving full professional development; that the Minister for Education and Skills requested the ASTI to provide an immediate derogation from its directive for current teachers of English while talks between the Department and the union on the junior cycle proceed; that the Department remains in discussions with the ASTI on this issue; and that the Minister for Education and Skills remains willing and available to engage with the ASTI on this issue; urges the ASTI to engage positively on this issue with a view to finding a solution; and calls on the ASTI to respond immediately and positively to the Minister's request for an immediate derogation from its directive for current teachers of English while talks between the Department and the union on the junior cycle proceed, and to engage urgently with the Department to resolve outstanding concerns. </p>
          <p eId="para_212">I thank the Chairman for facilitating this conversation. No one has a monopoly on concern. We all share a concern for the students and their education. That we are discussing this matter is welcome. As Deputy Byrne stated, this has had an impact, given that there appears to be some movement. That is welcome and positive. As a committee, we can play a part, but we must be careful when going down the road of tabling motions to the Dáil. By doing so, we are involving ourselves in a level of detail that might not be fully known to us. I have reservations about the committee tabling motions related to an industrial relations situation and sending them to the Dáil. This is not for a second meant to take anything from our ability to discuss the matter, but getting the motion right will be difficult and challenging for us as a committee. We could make matters worse rather than better.</p>
          <p eId="para_213"> At the heart of this situation are the students. Other Deputies alluded to this. There is discrimination between students who are being taught by ASTI members and those who are being taught by TUI members. By tabling a motion to advance a plan B for a set of students over another set of students, we as a committee are furthering the existing apartheid. That would be wrong. All students should be treated equally. As a committee, we need to tread carefully in how we proceed in this instance.</p>
          <p eId="para_214"> By insisting on putting a plan B in place, we are also asking the Minister to facilitate a directive by the union, which I am not comfortable doing. I do not believe that it was the intention, but the directive segregates one group of students from the other. I would have a difficulty with that.</p>
          <p eId="para_215"> By involving ourselves in industrial relations disputes in schools, we could be setting a precedent and be drawn into any other issue, grievance or division that arises if we proceed with a motion directing that a plan B be put in place.</p>
          <p eId="para_216"> What is of significance is that we would be undermining the integrity of the State exams by creating a plan B for one set of students over another. By directing the Minister to create a plan B and, therefore, a divide, we would be fundamentally challenging the integrity of our examination system. I appeal to the committee to be very careful before doing something like that.</p>
          <p eId="para_217"> As my amendment points out, that the union's directive targets the students' exams - I do not believe that it was intended in that way - is unprecedented. The students are pawns in this situation. That is regrettable. I urge talks and hope that there will be greater immediacy as a result of this debate, but I would prefer not to agree the motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_123">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">I thank the Deputy. I will allow other members to contribute.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MariaByrne" eId="spk_124">
          <from>Senator Maria Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">I agree with my colleague, Deputy Daly. He has articulated it well. This is setting a precedent and we could be supporting one group above the other. We must be cautious as well as fair to all involved. I support the Deputy's amendment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_125">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">I have already spoken on my motion. I assure Deputy Daly that I understand all the ramifications of the motion. Nothing that has emerged since submitting it has come as any surprise to me in terms of the reactions of various parties. I have engaged with all those involved. At this point, it would be helpful for the ongoing talks that I withdraw my motion. However, that does not get away from the fact that the children's marks are on the negotiating table. Whoever's fault that is does not matter. They are there. That must be the committee's main concern. The committee is entitled to take a view on this, but we should not do so today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">We are discussing Deputy Catherine Martin's motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_127">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">I am discussing Deputy Martin's motion as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_128">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_223">I am trying to be helpful. I thought I heard Deputy Byrne say it had been withdrawn.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_129">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">I am discussing Deputy Martin's motion while also responding to points raised on my motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_130">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">The points made were not directly related to Deputy Byrne's motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_131">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">I will speak to Deputy Martin's motion which is not hugely different from mine.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_132">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">I just wanted to clarify that we are discussing Deputy Martin's motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_133">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">My motion and Deputy Martin's are similar. The have the same intent in that they both seek to have this issue sorted out from the point of view of the children. In regard to Deputy Martin's motion, we are in the last seconds of this process. I had intended to propose that an independent mediator be appointed but, of course, that has already happened. It could happen again, I do not know. It seems to me that a huge amount of time was lost in the interregnum from last November to May this year. That time cannot be bought back. If Deputy Martin pursues her motion, to be consistent and to allow the talks next week a chance Fianna Fáil will abstain. Perhaps at that point the joint committee would invite in officials from the Department of Education and Skills and the State Examinations Commission to get their views on the matter and to encourage them to engage with the unions, including the TUI. This matter must be resolved. I hope and pray that the talks next week will be successful. I believe with a bit of give and take, and putting the interests of the students at the centre, a resolution will be found. The pay issue is separate. The committee is not dealing with that issue at all. As I said, in this matter the children's interests must be first.</p>
          <p eId="para_229"> Perhaps in terms of my motion and Deputy Martin's motion we should stay out of this for the moment in that in terms of this very discussion a signal has been sent out that we want this matter sorted and the children, in particular, looked after. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_134">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">The common thread running through these three motions is the children and the stress this situation is causing them at a time, as outlined by Deputy Martin in her presentation, when they are faced with taking their first State examination, which in itself is a stressful enough experience. This discussion has been worthwhile. Ultimately all we are seeking is an outcome. It is unfortunate that the children appear to be the meat in the sandwich but hopefully, Deputy Thomas Byrne said, a resolution is close. For that reason, I will follow the same line as my colleague, Deputy Byrne.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_135">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">By way of clarification, we are discussing two motions and an amendment to one of the motions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_136">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">I have moved my motion. I will not be supporting the amendment because it seeks to remove the action which I believe is needed to protect the children and to signal to the Minister that he needs to ensure they do not lose the 10%. I am aware that the talks are ongoing but I believe the Minister needs to put a contingency plan in place.</p>
          <p eId="para_233"> On the point regarding undermining the integrity of the examination, I do not believe that is the case. There are already alternative models in operation which could help resolve this problem and provide a guarantee to students that they will not be adversely affected. For example, students who do not participate in the oral component of examinations at junior cycle have their written examinations marked out of 100%. This means that students who do not take the oral component of a language examination do not automatically lose marks. This model, or an alternative, may not be ideal but we have to accept the urgent need to have a contingency plan in place. It must be acknowledged that putting in place such planning requires a great deal of preparation and as such the process needs to start now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_137">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">I have heard the ASTI make the point that there is precedence in this regard. We are all concerned for students. On Deputy Martin's point regarding precedence, this situation is completely different. Taking a student-centred view as opposed to a union-centred view of this particular issue the student has the choice on whether to take the oral and he or she is wholly in control. The student is then marked according to his or her choice. In this case, students have no choice. The decision is being made for them or against by the union. We cannot compare an apple and an orange or this situation with the oral examinations process. If a student decides to take the oral examination he or she will be awarded 40% of the marks for doing so but a student can also decide not to take the oral examination. In that case the student gets to choose but in the situation about which we are speaking now the student has no choice. That is why this is discriminatory. My fear is that this would undermine the State Examinations Commission.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_138">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_235">All of the points are well made. We are all concerned and want to see this matter resolved. Is the amendment to the motion agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_139">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">I do not propose to seek a vote on the amended motion. As I said earlier, I would prefer that this committee would not put any motion forward because I do not believe that is helpful at this stage. As such, I am not proposing that the motion, as amended, be forwarded to the Dáil.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_140">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">The Deputy must then withdraw it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_141">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">What do I need to withdraw?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_142">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">We still have to vote on the motion. Am I correct that Deputy Daly does not want to withdraw the amendment to the motion, but he does not want the amended motion put forward?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_143">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">I would welcome if Deputy Martin would agree that the committee not send forward any motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_144">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">Deputy Martin has already said she is putting her motion forward. It is clear then that she is not agreeing to Deputy Daly's suggestion that no motion be sent forth.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_145">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_242">Am I correct that Deputy Martin's motion has been amended?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_146">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_243">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_147">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">What we are discussing now is the amended motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_148">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_149">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">The motion now before us calls on the ASTI to do what the Department is asking, which I think amounts to the committee taking the Department's side of the argument. It is up to Deputy Martin but we are trying to be balanced.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_150">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">In terms of procedure, when does one withdraw an amendment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_151">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">It is too late now to withdraw it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_152">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">I am not withdrawing my amendment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_153">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">I know but the Deputy wants to withdraw the amended motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_154">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">I do not want the motion, as amended, to be sent forth to the Dáil.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_155">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">I do not think the Deputy can do that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_156">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">When the Chairman puts the question on whether the motion, as amended, is agreed, I can disagree.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_157">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">I can only put the question if members seek a vote.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_158">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">The motion that will be sent forth by the committee will be the amended motion, which is a Fine Gael motion, and not Deputy Martin's motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_159">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">It will be my motion in Deputy Martin's name.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_160">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">It will still be a motion from the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_161">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">I believe the committee would be better off not proceeding further on this issue. We should not send forth a motion on the matter to the Dáil.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_162">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">We are speaking now to the motion, as amended. The committee now has to vote on whether the motion, as amended, is agreed to. Do members wish to call a vote on the question?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_163">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">We are talking about sending my motion to the Dáil in the name of the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_164">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">Yes. Does Deputy Martin want to call a vote on this?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_165">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_262">I do not want the motion, as amended, being sent to the Dáil.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_166">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_263">Neither do I.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_167">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">There is no option on that one, Deputy Martin.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_168">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">Deputy Martin would need to withdraw her motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_169">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">What is before us now is a completely different animal to the motion I put forward.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_170">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_267">Yes but that is what is in front us now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_171">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_268">That is why I suggested it be withdrawn.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_172">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_269">Either we have a vote or it is withdrawn as it is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_173">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_270">Who decides whether it is withdrawn?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_174">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_271">I propose we withdraw the motion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MariaByrne" eId="spk_175">
          <from>Senator Maria Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_272">I second that proposal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_176">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_273">We have a proposal and a seconder that the amended motion that was originally put forward by Deputy Martin be withdrawn. We can call for a vote on that matter or have a vote on the amendment. Either way, it will be the same result in terms of numbers. We can have a vote or the motion, as amended, could be withdrawn.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_177">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_274">Is that down to me?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_178">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_275">It is for the Deputy to withdraw it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineMartin" eId="spk_179">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Martin<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">I wish to put on the record that I will withdraw it but the reason being the amendment has completely turned the motion on its head and would put the dispute front and centre, which is not needed. My motion was about putting the child, that is, the children suffering as a result of the dispute, front and centre. For the record, I am withdrawing the motion because the nature of it has completely changed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8"> Motion, as amended, withdrawn.</summary>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_180">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_277">That is fair enough and understood, and I thank the Deputy.</p>
          <p eId="para_278"> I accept that sometimes motions can be contentious even though we all have the same end goal in terms of trying to resolve the issue. We might examine the possibility of the committee proposing resolutions that contain everyone's input and are agreed by us all. We will not be able to do it at this point in terms of this issue. However, we should consider that process for issues on which we all agree but there is a question on how to deal with them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_181">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">I completely agree. I know the engagement was brief this morning but I discussed my position with every party. I thought it was useful to do so. The matter, however, has been dealt with now. The point is that this issue has reached the committee and we have collectively decided not to put a motion on the record to the Dáil in order to help the talks. Deputy Catherine Martin has now decided that. The point is that it is done in the context of talks between the ASTI and the Government taking place next week. We do not want to stand in the way of those talks and we are encouraging both sides to conclude them successfully. By having the discussion and not putting forward a motion, we have decided that we will not interfere in that process for the moment although we obviously have huge concerns about what is happening.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JimDaly" eId="spk_182">
          <from>Deputy Jim Daly<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">The reason I do not wish for the committee to proceed with this motion to the next level is that I think we should be avoiding division and votes in so far as practicable on an issue such as this one where we all share the same common goal and concern. My main driving force is to avoid division and votes where possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_183">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2016-10-13T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_281">It was helpful and useful to have the debate today and I thank the members for their support and agreement on the way forward. We need to examine the resolution process, however. Further, other members asked to table motions after the deadline had passed and I had a discretion on whether to allow them. I decided not to allow them as we would be here forever if we did not stick to the deadline and would have ongoing problems and issues. We are now clear on where we stand on this matter and I know we all hope there will be a positive resolution following the talks. As there is no other business at this point, and I am conscious the Dáil and the Seanad will sit at 11.30 a.m., the committee will adjourn.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_9"> The joint committee adjourned at 11.35 a.m. until 9.00 a.m. on Thursday, 27 October 2016.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
