<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2006-05-04/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2006-05-04/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2006-05-04" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/house/seanad/22"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2006-05-04/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2006-05-04/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2006-05-04" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2006-05-04/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2006-05-04/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference eId="#vol_183" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183" showAs="Vol. 183"/>
          <oir:numberReference eId="#no_12" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/no/12" showAs="No. 12"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_913" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/913" showAs="Col. 913" refersTo="#None"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_914" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/914" showAs="Col. 914" refersTo="#spk_2"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_915" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/915" showAs="Col. 915" refersTo="#spk_3"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_916" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/916" showAs="Col. 916" refersTo="#spk_4"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_917" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/917" showAs="Col. 917" refersTo="#spk_7"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_918" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/918" showAs="Col. 918" refersTo="#spk_9"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_919" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/919" showAs="Col. 919" refersTo="#spk_11"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_920" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/920" showAs="Col. 920" refersTo="#spk_13"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_921" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/921" showAs="Col. 921" refersTo="#spk_16"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_922" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/922" showAs="Col. 922" refersTo="#dbsect_2"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_923" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/923" showAs="Col. 923" refersTo="#spk_28"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_924" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/924" showAs="Col. 924" refersTo="#spk_38"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_925" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/925" showAs="Col. 925" refersTo="#spk_41"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_926" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/926" showAs="Col. 926" refersTo="#dbsect_2"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_927" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/927" showAs="Col. 927" refersTo="#para_91"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_928" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/928" showAs="Col. 928" refersTo="#spk_53"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_929" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/929" showAs="Col. 929" refersTo="#spk_53"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_930" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/930" showAs="Col. 930" refersTo="#spk_53"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_931" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/931" showAs="Col. 931" refersTo="#spk_53"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_932" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/932" showAs="Col. 932" refersTo="#dbsect_5"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_933" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/933" showAs="Col. 933" refersTo="#spk_54"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_934" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/934" showAs="Col. 934" refersTo="#spk_54"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_935" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/935" showAs="Col. 935" refersTo="#spk_54"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_936" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/936" showAs="Col. 936" refersTo="#spk_55"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_937" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/937" showAs="Col. 937" refersTo="#spk_55"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_938" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/938" showAs="Col. 938" refersTo="#spk_55"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_939" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/939" showAs="Col. 939" refersTo="#spk_55"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_940" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/940" showAs="Col. 940" refersTo="#spk_63"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_941" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/941" showAs="Col. 941" refersTo="#spk_65"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_942" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/942" showAs="Col. 942" refersTo="#spk_65"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_943" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/943" showAs="Col. 943" refersTo="#spk_65"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_944" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/944" showAs="Col. 944" refersTo="#spk_66"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_945" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/945" showAs="Col. 945" refersTo="#spk_65"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_946" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/946" showAs="Col. 946" refersTo="#spk_68"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_947" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/947" showAs="Col. 947" refersTo="#dbsect_5"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_947" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/947" showAs="Col. 947" refersTo="#spk_67"/>
          <oir:column eId="col_948" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/183/col/948" showAs="Col. 948" refersTo="#spk_69"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCEvent eId="bill.2002.26.seanad.2" href="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2002/26/seanad/2" showAs="National Economic and Social Development Office Bill 2002: Seanad Second Stage"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AnnOrmonde" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ann-Ormonde.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Ann Ormonde"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BrendanDaly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Brendan-Daly.D.1973-03-14" showAs="Brendan Daly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BrianHayes" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Brian-Hayes.S.1995-12-20" showAs="Brian Hayes"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CamillusGlynn" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Camillus-Glynn.S.1997-09-17" showAs="Camillus Glynn"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DiarmuidWilson" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Diarmuid-Wilson.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Diarmuid Wilson"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="GeraldineFeeney" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Geraldine-Feeney.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Geraldine Feeney"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeMcHugh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-McHugh.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Joe McHugh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeOToole" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-O'Toole.S.1987-04-25" showAs="Joe O'Toole"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnMinihan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Minihan.S.2002-09-12" showAs="John Minihan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="KateWalsh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Kate-Walsh.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Kate Walsh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="KathleenOMeara" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Kathleen-O'Meara.S.1997-09-17" showAs="Kathleen O'Meara"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LabhrasOMurchu" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Labhrás-Ó-Murchú.S.1997-09-17" showAs="Labhrás Ó Murchú"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaryHenry" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mary-EF-Henry.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Mary E.F. Henry"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaryMWhite" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mary-M-White.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Mary M. White"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelKitt" href="" showAs=""/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelMcCarthy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-McCarthy.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Michael McCarthy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaddyBurke" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paddy-Burke.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Paddy Burke"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulCoghlan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Coghlan.S.1997-09-17" showAs="Paul Coghlan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RoryKiely" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Rory-Kiely.S.1977-10-27" showAs="Rory Kiely"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SheilaTerry" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Sheila-Terry.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Sheila Terry"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="UlickBurke" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ulick-Burke.S.1981-10-08" showAs="Ulick Burke"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Cathaoirleach" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/office/cathaoirleach" showAs="Cathaoirleach"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Leas-Chathaoirleach" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/office/leas-chathaoirleach" showAs="Leas-Chathaoirleach"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_the_Taoiseach" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/taoiseach" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>SEANAD ÉIREANN</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2006-05-04">Déardaoin, 4 Bealtaine 2006</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2006-05-04">Thursday, 4 May 2006</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="volume">
        <docNumber refersTo="#vol_183">Vol. 183</docNumber>
      </block>
      <block name="number">
        <docNumber refersTo="#no_12">No. 12</docNumber>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary eId="sum_1">Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar10.30 a.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">Paidir.
  Prayer.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Order of Business.</heading>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_1">The Order of Business is Nos. 1, 2 and 3. No. 1, a motion which sets out the arrangements to allow the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture and Food to meet in the Dáil for a debate on European agricultural policy on Wednesday, 10 May 2006, to be taken without debate; No. 2, a referral motion whereby the subject matter of No. 16 on today's Order Paper, concerning the extension of the Freedom of Information Act 1997 (Prescribed Bodies) Regulation 2006 to additional bodies which now brings to more than 500 the number of bodies covered by the Act, will be referred to the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Finance and the Public Service for consideration, to be taken without debate; and No. 3, the National Economic and Social Development Office Bill 2002 — Second Stage, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business and to conclude not later than 2 p.m., with the contributions of spokespersons not to exceed 15 minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed ten minutes each, the Minister to be called on to reply not later than five minutes before the conclusion of Second Stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianHayes" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Mr. B. Hayes</from>
          <p eId="para_2">The decision of the Christian Brothers to give a one-year reprieve to St. Michael's national school in Inchicore is obviously belatedly welcome. However, we have a longer-term problem in that area and in many other parts of the city, which relates to the provision of new schools and education facilities for growing communities. I ask the Acting Leader to arrange a debate at the earliest possible time with the Minister for Education and Science so she can set out her policy in this area.</p>
          <p eId="para_3">We have a particular problem in south-west and west Dublin in the provision of new schools. Thousands of new houses are being built with no new schools to meet the housing demand. We should consider amending the terms of Part V of the Planning and Development Act to allow developers and builders to make specific contributions towards funding new primary schools in areas with extensive new housing developments.</p>
          <p eId="para_4">It is ridiculous that people should need to wait for 8,000 or 9,000 new homes to be built before getting a new national school. The problem with St. Michael's in Inchicore is being reflected in many other parts of the city. We need a debate on this issue. We need to ensure the Minister for Education and Science has a new policy to meet this demand. There is no lateral planning and thinking between the Department of Education and Science and any of the local authorities in Dublin on this urgent matter.</p>
          <p eId="para_5">The Acting Leader may be aware of the particular new craze within the Dublin criminal fraternity of cars being stolen to order. As we know, without the key it is virtually impossible to steal a car fitted with an immobiliser. However, cars now being stolen to order involve two crimes, namely, breaking and entering as a means of getting the keys of the car, and robbing the car. These cars are then transferred on to the Continent where very lucrative trafficking of stolen cars takes place.</p>
          <p eId="para_6">I ask the Acting Leader to use his good offices to raise with the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform a particular solution in use in Northern Ireland. PSNI patrol cars are fitted with a satellite vehicle recognition system, which allows stolen cars to be detected automatically by those patrol cars. Garda cars in this jurisdiction do not have the same technology. In consultation with the Garda Commissioner, the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform needs to take up this issue. Very substantial sums of money are being lost as a result of cars being stolen in Ireland and ending up in the lucrative continental car market. We must address the issue and one way to do so is to advance technology in Garda cars.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOToole" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Mr. O’Toole</from>
          <p eId="para_7">We recently had a very moving debate on the report into the activities of Dr. Neary in Our Lady of Lourdes Hospital in Drogheda. Members on all sides share the same kinds of views. We were appalled at the hardship, trauma and suffering imposed on those women who went to have their children in that hospital. We looked at the recommendations of the learned judge who produced the report — I do not recall anybody objecting to any one of them — and we asked for them to be implemented. It now transpires that the judge has made a return trip to the hospital to discover what kind of action has been taken on foot of the recommendations. We find, appallingly, that whereas the hospital has made a serious effort to implement what was required of it at hospital authority level and staff level within the hospital, the HSE has done nothing whatever to implement the recommendations of the report.</p>
          <p eId="para_8">Considering that the report galvanised this country and shocked all of us, it is absolutely incredible that nothing would be done. The Tánaiste and Minister for Health and Children, Deputy Harney, would be within her rights to demand an explanation from the HSE as to why nothing has been done. I would welcome an opportunity to discuss with the Tánaiste how the recommendations of the report will be implemented and what action she proposes to take, or can take, to ensure they will be implemented. I look forward to an early debate on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcCarthy" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Mr. McCarthy</from>
          <p eId="para_9">I congratulate Judge Maureen Harding Clark on her follow-up report on the Neary case. That sorry saga is very important, and we express our appreciation to Judge Harding Clark for her work.</p>
          <p eId="para_10">The Irish Nurses Organisation meets in conference this week, and there has been much debate in media circles on whether the Tánaiste had received an invitation, replied to it and was available to address the conference. We understand that it is the first time in the history of the INO conference that the serving Minister for Health and Children will not address it. It is only fair and right that we put on the record that the INO made every effort to facilitate the Minister. A spokesperson from the Minister's office said that she would be in the United States but, over three days, it is not unrealistic to expect the Minister to make some serious effort to address the INO as it meets to discuss serious issues in the health service, not least in accident and emergency services. It is an affront to the INO that the Tánaiste would snub it in this manner.</p>
          <p eId="para_11">I also wish to raise the issue of the motor tax on-line payment provision on the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government website. This issue was first raised when the system was introduced two years ago. There is now a situation whereby people can tax their cars without actually having them insured. The old manual system meant that when one sent details to the local licensing authority, one had to include a certificate of insurance. That is not the case any longer; one can now enter bogus insurance details and still get one's tax disc in the post three or four days later. In an era of carnage on our roads that seems to be never-ending, it is a disgrace that uninsured cars are being taxed in this country, and that no serious attempt has been made to curb that loophole. It is vital that we bring this loophole to the attention of the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy Roche, as soon as possible. There is a major issue about road carnage and about cars that are not of a certain standard, and sadly the matter of non-nationals losing their lives for a variety of reasons, including speeding and the use of left-hand-drive cars. The State is promoting the fact that uninsured cars are taking to the roads; that loophole is being enabled by the State. I appeal to the Acting Leader to communicate that message urgently to the Minister so the loophole can be closed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LabhrasOMurchu" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Labhrás Ó Murchú</from>
          <p eId="para_12">In recent years there have been far-reaching changes in the tourism industry, most of which were to reinforce our position in the marketplace and prepare us for the changes in the competitive nature of the business. Those changes also take account of the all-Ireland nature of tourism. Indeed, a number of successes have arisen from these changes, but one area requires attention. I refer to the role of bed and breakfasts. As we know, more than 40 years ago this concept of tourism was brought into Ireland with the idea that people could come and have the experience of the authentic Ireland, living with a family. The bed and breakfasts were very competitive and there was a great social interaction involved but recent figures would suggest that the number of people getting out of this business is alarmingly high at the moment, with several hundred if not more leaving it.</p>
          <p eId="para_13">There are reasons for this. The visitor has different needs and there is increased competition from three-star hotels and so on. But it is important that we find some way in which to help the bed and breakfasts because they have a role to play. There are areas such as tax incentives, which have already been given to hotels in the past, and the licensing laws could perhaps be more flexible to help the bed and breakfasts. I am surprised that the alarm bells have not been ringing somewhat louder because anybody on the ground is clearly aware of the radical changes that are taking place for bed and breakfasts. I do not want to be a prophet of doom, but I would go as far as saying that, if we do not do something, in another four or five years the whole bed and breakfast aspect of tourism will be completely gone. It might be worthwhile to have the Minister in here to discuss this urgent matter that seems to have been played down up to this point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Mr. Coghlan</from>
          <p eId="para_14">The groceries order was, as we know, abolished to much fanfare, and commitments and promises were given that it would save consumers something like €1,000 a year. Despite all the commitments and promises, the cost of a basket of staple goods in Tesco, Dunnes and Superquinn has increased in all cases. It has not led to an era of lower prices. As we know, prices are gradually going up — I refer to the survey in last Sunday's edition of <i>The Sunday Times</i>. This included everyday items for every household, such as butter, eggs and tea. Was the abolition of the order a con job? It would be worthwhile if the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy Martin, could attend for a debate on the matter because the commitments given have certainly not been lived up to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnnOrmonde" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Ms Ormonde</from>
          <p eId="para_15">I support the point raised by Senator Brian Hayes on development plans and how they move forward, particularly on having an action plan and making sites available for schools or neighbourhood centres. There is a lot of vagueness here due to a lack of co-operation between the Department of Education and Science and the Department responsible for local authorities, particularly with regard to the development plan. Perhaps the Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Hanafin, could come in and express her views on future plans for sites for schools. It is hard to predict these things in the long term but the situation could be clarified. The Minister is very clear in her own thinking on it, so perhaps she could enlighten us accordingly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryHenry" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Dr. Henry</from>
          <p eId="para_16">Could the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, Deputy McDowell, come to the House to debate the forensic medical services in Ireland? For those of us who are colleagues of the former State pathologist, it is very depressing to hear the criticism of his work that has been voiced, especially as there was no criticism when he was in office. We need that debate as soon as possible, because the gardaí are complaining about the difficulties they are having in getting doctors to come and take blood samples from people suspected of drink driving. We know that is a serious issue in road safety regulations.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">I am also very disappointed that in the legislative programme for this session the new coroners Bill does not seem to be featuring until the very end of the year. That legislation has been sought for quite some time, and in the newspapers recently we read about the distress of a lady because the inquest into the death of her four year old child was put off year after year. She had no knowledge whether her child died instantly at the scene of the accident or died later in hospital because those details have to be kept private until the inquest takes place. I would be grateful if a debate on forensic medical services could take place as soon as possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CamillusGlynn" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Mr. Glynn</from>
          <p eId="para_18">I support the remarks made by Senators Brian Hayes and Ormonde on education, a matter I raised only last week. Developers have a role to play in the provision of additional school places. A debate on education with the Minister for Education and Science would be useful. I am sure many useful suggestions would be made by Senators on all sides of the House.</p>
          <p eId="para_19">On the issue of motor insurance, I do not want to be accused of being racist but I believe in calling a spade a spade. The reality is that the statistics show a trend in the number of non-national motorists without motor insurance involved in accidents, some of which are serious. This matter was raised previously by Senator Finucane, on which occasion I supported him. Efforts must be intensified to address this serious matter. A number of people have lost their lives. I am not saying that some nationals are not also at fault, but a worrying trend is evident in terms of the overall population and something must be done to address it. The established garages ensure that cars are insured before they leave their premises but other sales outlets do not and that is where the problem arises.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SheilaTerry" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Ms Terry</from>
          <p eId="para_20">I support the call by the Leader of the Opposition, Senator Brian Hayes, for a debate on the serious problem of car theft, which is escalating on a weekly basis. It is a cause of great distress to many people. A person can break into their home, steal the keys of the car and subsequently sell it to a person in the UK or elsewhere in Europe. Something radical needs to be done to address the issue. Senator Brian Hayes proposed a means of dealing with it which is currently in force in Northern Ireland and the UK. I would welcome a debate on this issue at an early time.</p>
          <p eId="para_21">I call once again for a debate on the sexual health of young people. The Joint Committee on Health and Children recently had a debate on this issue during which a consultant from St. James's Hospital gave startling figures on this growing problem, which is not being addressed. The necessary services are not in place around the country for young people to access. A broad education programme on sexual health is needed.</p>
          <p eId="para_22">On a related but broader issue, I call for a separate debate with the Minister for Foreign Affairs, and perhaps involving the Tánaiste and Minister for Health and Children, on tackling the spread of AIDS throughout the world, particularly in Africa and South America. I am thinking particularly of condoms being made available to people in those countries, accepting that the use of condoms is the best way to help stop the spread of AIDS. I cautiously welcome a potential new development which we are not sure will come about. The Roman Catholic Church is considering changing its stance on the use of condoms as a means of fighting the spread of AIDS. The Department of Foreign Affairs and the Minister of State at that Department, Deputy Conor Lenihan, are doing wonderful work in this area, but much more is required to press home what we believe needs to be done. I would welcome a debate on the matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Ms White</from>
          <p eId="para_23">I call on the Acting Leader to request the Minister concerned to debate the issue of age and ageism, which I have raised previously. The people who created this Celtic tiger during bleak economic times have a right to have their issues raised. One of the key issues concerning older people is that of carers. I compliment the Minister concerned on increasing the carer's leave entitlement from 15 months to two years. A person in employment can now take two years' leave of absence to look after a person who does not want to go into residential home care or a person who sadly may have a short-term terminal illness. The employer does not have to pay the employee but the latter is entitled to reap the reward of having paid his or her PRSI. Such a carer is entitled to receive €180 per week. An important development is that the carer does not have to be related to the person who requires caring. In other words, the carer does not have to be a family member but simply a person who is defined by a doctor as being able to care for a person who needs medical care in his or her own home.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#UlickBurke" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Mr. U. Burke</from>
          <p eId="para_24">Yesterday a report of the court proceedings of the Meath school bus tragedy heard that further summonses were to be issued to CIE in regard to a bus that was known to be a danger to the public and that had a known defect that could easily have been detected had it been checked. There was a repeat of a similar tragedy in Clara and a further accident occurred in south Roscommon only two weeks ago. I call on the Minister for Education and Science to demand a full audit of the CIE school busfleet.</p>
          <p eId="para_25">It cannot be said that the same dangers apply to the private operators contracted to provide a transport service for students. In circumstances where such comments emerged yesterday, surely parents with children travelling to school must be concerned about their safety. The Minister said there is a low incidence of accidents occurring. Luckily that is the case but it is only luck that is resulting in the current safety record. If vehicles with known defects are being used, that is a scandal and it must be quickly dealt with.</p>
          <p eId="para_26">Agricultural research and development is slowly disappearing, which is a tragedy for agriculture and those involved in agricultural training. Teagasc sold much of the property and lands throughout the country used for research and development in the past and few remain. We read that a national educational institution such as UCD is proposing to continue to sell further lands at Lyons Estate, which it purchased in the late 1950s or early 1960s and at which its department of agriculture developed a strong research and development centre. Some 500 acres were sold for the development of playgrounds, a golf course and a leisure centre.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">It is understood that the UCD authorities are about to sell the remaining part of the Lyons Estate for a similar development. I ask the Acting Leader to request the Minister for Education and Science to immediately consult the authorities in UCD to ensure this will not happen. The people in UCD who are pushing this sale want to stay in Dublin city and develop agricultural policies from there rather than travelling from there to observe the reality at the coalface. I ask the Acting Leader to contact the Minister for Education and Science as a matter of urgency to prevent the disposal of these properties.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrendanDaly" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Mr. Daly</from>
          <p eId="para_28">One of the most important recent appointments was that of Professor Drumm as the head of the Health Service Executive. A major reorganisation of administration of the health service and matters related to health is under way and there is widespread concern about the effects of these changes on various communities.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">We have heard contributions in this House on a number of occasions from EU Commissioners, Members of the European Parliament and others.</p>
          <p eId="para_30">I would like to ask the Acting Leader to tell the House whether he might raise with the Committee on Procedure and Privileges the possibility of getting Professor Drumm to come to the House for a full and frank discussion with Members about his philosophy, his objectives and other matters relating to the health service in general. Perhaps we should consider whether it will be possible to arrange such a debate in the context of the reorganisation that is taking place and the appointment of Professor Drumm, who has a major responsibility for the whole health service.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KathleenOMeara" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Ms O’Meara</from>
          <p eId="para_31">Before Easter, I asked the Leader of the House to tell Senators when the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform was likely to introduce legislation on press freedom. I referred in particular to the establishment of a press council. I was told that the Minister anticipated that the legislation in question would be prepared just before Easter.</p>
          <p eId="para_32">Around the same time, I asked the Leader to tell the House when the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Lenihan, intended to publish the review of crèche regulations, particularly in light of media reports highlighting concerns about the management of the care of small children. I was told that the review of the regulations would be published around Easter. Neither the press freedom legislation nor the review of the crèche regulations have been published, even though Easter has come and gone.</p>
          <p eId="para_33">I would like the Acting Leader to tell the House as soon as possible when the media legislation will be introduced and the review of the crèche regulations will be published. I would like a debate in this House on the review of the crèche regulations, in particular. I am sure such a debate will probably not be necessary, but I would like it to take place nevertheless.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldineFeeney" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Ms Feeney</from>
          <p eId="para_34">I support Senator Daly's request to the Acting Leader to clarify whether it would be possible for Professor Brendan Drumm to address the House. As a member of the Joint Committee on Health and Children, I was present during a most worthwhile meeting of the committee, at which Professor Drumm was in attendance, approximately a month ago. The House would benefit greatly from a question and answer session with Professor Drumm.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Mr. McHugh</from>
          <p eId="para_35">As we are aware, the unique personal relationship between public representatives and the electorate is the bedrock of Irish democracy. It is a feature of politics at Oireachtas and local authority levels. I was saddened to learn last Friday that the Taoiseach said during a visit to County Donegal that he was unaware of the extent of the crisis in the health service in that county. While it may have been an off-the-cuff remark, it has some relevance.</p>
          <p eId="para_36">It would be too easy to ask why the filtering system, or conduit, between Fianna Fáil's representatives in County Donegal and the Cabinet is not working, as such a question would cast the five Fianna Fáil Deputies in the county as scapegoats. We need to ask a bigger question as part of the real debate that needs to take place on this issue. I congratulate Senator Daly for contributing to the debate this morning by asking the Acting Leader to inquire into the possibility of Professor Brendan Drumm coming to the House. The big question that needs to be asked is whether a small party should hold ultimate responsibility for a serious portfolio like health. Should we allow such an arrangement to continue?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryKiely" as="#Cathaoirleach" eId="spk_17">
          <from>An Cathaoirleach</from>
          <p eId="para_37">I do not think the Seanad has any power in that regard. It is a matter for the Taoiseach.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_38">Senator McHugh should apply for Professor Drumm's job.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Mr. Coghlan</from>
          <p eId="para_39">The Acting Leader will have an interesting reply on this subject.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Mr. McHugh</from>
          <p eId="para_40">We are all aware of the anomalies in the health system. Senator Daly has reflected the frustration of many people in this regard. Some members of his parliamentary party expressed their frustration last night. The people of Donegal have been ventilating their frustration for nine years, but they are not being heard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianHayes" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Mr. B. Hayes</from>
          <p eId="para_41">Hear, hear.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Mr. McHugh</from>
          <p eId="para_42">The Taoiseach said in Donegal that he is unaware of the crisis. What is happening? We should start the debate on this issue by considering whether, as a democracy, we should authorise the transfer of ultimate responsibility for the health service to a smaller party that does not have a mandate from the whole country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryKiely" as="#Cathaoirleach" eId="spk_23">
          <from>An Cathaoirleach</from>
          <p eId="para_43">I do not think that is fair. I do not think the Seanad has any power in that regard. I do not think it is an appropriate matter for debate in the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianHayes" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Mr. B. Hayes</from>
          <p eId="para_44">The Progressive Democrats will have to find a candidate in County Donegal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#UlickBurke" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Mr. U. Burke</from>
          <p eId="para_45">The Acting Leader will have to think of a reply.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_46">I would like to start by responding to the final speaker, but I will wait.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Mr. Coghlan</from>
          <p eId="para_47">The Progressive Democrats are supposed to be the meat in the sandwich.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_48">Senator Brian Hayes welcomed the announcement that was made by the Christian Brothers today in respect of St. Michael's national school in Inchicore. He spoke in general terms about the planning, development and construction of schools. He asked whether legislation is needed to ensure that schools are provided in newly-developed areas. He was joined by Senators Ormonde and Glynn in calling for the Minister for Education and Science to come to the House for a debate on the matter. I agree that such a debate would be welcome, as it would give the Minister for Education and Science, who was in the House recently, an opportunity to outline her policies in this regard. I will endeavour to arrange such a debate.</p>
          <p eId="para_49">Senator Brian Hayes discussed a new phase of criminal activity, involving car trafficking, in the Dublin area. Senator Terry also spoke about that issue. Senator Hayes asked me to convey to the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform his proposal that vehicle recognition systems, like those in Northern Ireland, be installed in Garda patrol cars. I will be happy to communicate that worthy proposal to the Minister, Deputy McDowell.</p>
          <p eId="para_50">Senator O'Toole spoke about the Neary report in the context of Judge Maureen Harding Clark's report on her return visit to Our Lady of Lourdes Hospital in Drogheda. While we join Senator O'Toole in congratulating Judge Harding Clark on the report she compiled, which was debated in full in this House, it would be remiss of us not to refer to a similar report in which Mr. Tom Flynn, who is the assistant national director of the Health Service Executive, responded to some of the points made in the Neary report.</p>
          <p eId="para_51">I do not want to detract in any way from what Judge Harding Clark has said, or undermine in any way the report she has produced, but it is fair to recognise and acknowledge what Mr. Flynn said this morning. He pointed out that action has been taken by the HSE. The development of a new national epidemiology centre in Cork was announced within three days of the publication of the Neary report. The appointment of an executive management board was approved within two weeks of the publication of the report. Doctors have been informed of the timeframe within which the board will be put in place. They have been put in touch with their counterparts in other hospitals in which similar boards are in place. A national review of maternity services is under way and is due to be completed in June. The HSE's action may not have been taken as quickly as people would have liked, but it is right that it is working to a timeframe in conjunction with the medical practitioners. We have to consider the issue in its entirety.</p>
          <p eId="para_52">Senator McCarthy raised the same issue. I think I have dealt with that. He also spoke about the Tánaiste's non-attendance at this week's conference of the Irish Nurses Organisation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcCarthy" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Mr. McCarthy</from>
          <p eId="para_53">She refused to attend the conference.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_54">It is incorrect to suggest she refused to attend the conference. On 25 October 2005, the Tánaiste received an invitation to attend an international conference in Pennsylvania. She agreed to attend the conference. On 18 January last, she received a request from the INO to attend its conference. She replied to the INO on 24 February, stating that she was unable to attend its conference because she had an existing diary commitment in Pennsylvania. She nominated the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Lenihan, to attend the conference on her behalf. I have outlined the facts of the paper trail. The Tánaiste did not refuse to attend the INO conference. She has never refused to attend anything at any stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcCarthy" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Mr. McCarthy</from>
          <p eId="para_55">She refused to attend the INO conference. It is the first time in 50 years that a Minister has failed to attend an INO conference.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_56">The Tánaiste did not receive any communication from the INO after she sent it the letter of 24 February until it sought its soundbites this week.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcCarthy" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Mr. McCarthy</from>
          <p eId="para_57">That is unfair.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_58">I am led to believe that——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#UlickBurke" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Mr. U. Burke</from>
          <p eId="para_59">Now we are talking.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_60">I have given the facts. She would have been quite happy to facilitate the INO at any stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcCarthy" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Mr. McCarthy</from>
          <p eId="para_61">By going to Pennsylvania.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_62">She had made a prior commitment to attend a very important international conference. I think that deals with that issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_63">Senator McCarthy also spoke about on-line motor taxation. He was joined by Senator Glynn in raising the question of non-insured drivers, an issue which he had raised on a previous Order of Business about the sale of cars and the need for insistence on motor insurance. The Senator has also highlighted a loophole as regards on-line taxation and that is something on which we will seek clarification from the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government.</p>
          <p eId="para_64">Senator Ó Murchú raised the issue of tourism and the role of bed and breakfast facilities in particular. We all value their contribution to the tourism industry. A general debate on tourism would be welcome in the House. I am not sure whether we have had one, but it is something we should seek, where——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Mr. Coghlan</from>
          <p eId="para_65">It would be timely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_66">——these issues can be highlighted. I will endeavour to arrange for such a debate in the near future.</p>
          <p eId="para_67">Senator Coghlan raised the question of the abolition of the groceries order and the recent survey reported in <i> The Sunday Times</i>. In fairness, we have had the debate on the groceries order, and in terms of the abolition’s impact the report may be premature. The abolition came into effect only a couple of months ago and we must see how matters unfold. However, it is an issue that must be kept under review and in the fullness of time the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy Martin, should come to this House to address the success of the initiative.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Mr. Coghlan</from>
          <p eId="para_68">Or the failure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_69">Senator Henry raised the important issue of forensic medical services. In light of recent media reports, it is somewhat disturbing that there is a conflict between medical professionals. In everyone's interest it is vitally important that as a society we have confidence in our forensic services, particularly given the linkage with court cases and the judicial process. A debate on that area should be facilitated in the House. She also raised the legislative programme and the new coroners Bill. I will have to come back to the Senator on that, as I do not have the answer to hand.</p>
          <p eId="para_70">Senator Terry raised the issue of sexual health, particularly as regards young people, and the broad educational programme in this area. Again, this is something that must be kept to the fore continually, given the statistics that appear regularly in the newspapers about the increased incidence of sexually transmitted diseases, STDs, particularly among the young. She also raised the issue of AIDS and Ireland's contribution to a worldwide policy for dealing with that issue. As she said, the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs, Deputy Conor Lenihan, plays an active role in our overseas development. He comes regularly to the Seanad to talk about overseas aid and we will endeavour to raise this matter on his next visit to the House.</p>
          <p eId="para_71">Senator White raised the issue of age and ageism and sought a debate on the subject of carers and the elderly. Those of us who heard one of the enumerators of the census recently on radio describing how he had detected the fear and loneliness among the elderly people he visited were affected. It is a subject of which we are all conscious and we should have regular debates on age and ageism in this House. I will raise that with the Leader.</p>
          <p eId="para_72">Senator Ulick Burke raised the recent bus crash and reports that further summonses were to be issued. I will not comment on that aspect in particular, but the whole question of an audit of bus fleets should be examined. A review of the roadworthiness of all public transport is something that must be ongoing. We have the NCT and various other tests and it is not acceptable that any vehicle which is not fully operational or safe should be on the road. Again, I will bring those comments to the attention of the Minister for Education and Science. The Senator also raised the issue of the agripolicy <i>vis-à-vis</i> the Lyons Estate, UCD, and I will relay his comments in this regard to the Minister.</p>
          <p eId="para_73">Senator Daly, joined by Senator Feeney, raised the issue of Professor Drumm addressing the House, which is rightfully a matter for the Committee on Procedure and Privileges. Senator Feeney confirmed that Professor Drumm addressed the Joint Committee on Health and Children recently. He spoke at the Progressive Democrats annual conference and other party conferences and he is well worth listening to. However, the question as to whether people should be brought into the House is a matter for the CPP. There is a forum in the committee system, which we are all entitled to attend and we should concentrate on that area. If we were to open the doors to invite everyone to address the full Seanad, I am not sure whether that would be the right way to go. That is a personal opinion.</p>
          <p eId="para_74">Senator O'Meara raised the issue of legislation in two regards, the matter of a press council and the child care regulations. She is correct that the House was told around Easter that the legislation would be coming this term. I cannot tell the Senator it will be next week because I do not know. My understanding, however, is that both pieces of legislation are imminent.</p>
          <p eId="para_75">That brings me to Senator McHugh who gave the House a lecture on democracy. Then he undermined democracy by saying members of a junior party in Government should not hold a ministerial role. That is a matter for Government and for the Taoiseach who allocates the ministerial offices.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Mr. McHugh</from>
          <p eId="para_76">It will be a matter for the people the next time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_77">If he is suggesting a whole new democratic system in which Cabinet positions will be graded on the basis of the number seats a party holds, that is a whole new invention——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianHayes" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Mr. B. Hayes</from>
          <p eId="para_78">The Government has done this before.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_79">Following his initial comments on democracy the Senator then went on to speak against it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Mr. McHugh</from>
          <p eId="para_80">I just asked the question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_81">The less said about that——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrendanDaly" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Mr. Daly</from>
          <p eId="para_82">The Donegal democrat.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_83">I suppose the excuse one can offer is that there is an election in the air.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_3">Order of Business agreed to.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Joint Committee on Agriculture and Food: Motion.</heading>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_84">I move:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_85">That, notwithstanding anything in Standing Orders, it be an instruction to the Joint Committee on Agriculture and Food that at its meeting for the purpose of a debate on European agriculture policy, to be convened in the Dáil Chamber on Wednesday, 10 May 2006, at 12.10 p.m. until 1.40 p.m., that the following arrangements shall apply:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_86">(i) that EU Commissioner for Agriculture and Rural Development, Ms Mariann Fischer Boel, be invited to attend and take part in the discussion on European agriculture policy at that meeting; and</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_87">(ii) that the proceedings on the debate on European agriculture policy shall, if not previously concluded, be brought to a conclusion at 1.40 p.m.; the statements shall be confined to Commissioner Fischer Boel and the Minister for Agriculture and Food and shall not exceed 15 minutes in each case and shall be followed immediately thereafter by a question and answers session which shall be not less than 60 minutes, at which the Commissioner may participate; Provided that subject to the discretion of the Chair, a Member may intervene during the course of the contributions of the Commissioner and the Minister to query or comment on points made; Provided further that, in the unlikely event Commissioner Fischer Boel is unable to attend the joint committee meeting, the Chairperson of the joint committee may adjourn the meeting; Provided further that the Ceann Comhairle may act as Chairperson for the purposes of that meeting."</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_4" refersTo="#agreed" title="decision">Question put and agreed to.<entity name="reference" refersTo="#para_84"/>
                </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Freedom of Information Act 1997 (Prescribed Bodies) Regulations 2006: Referral to Joint Committee.</heading>
        <speech by="#JohnMinihan" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Mr. Minihan</from>
          <p eId="para_88">I move:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_89">That the proposal Seanad Éireann approve draft regulations entitled:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_90">Freedom of Information Act 1997 (Prescribed Bodies) Regulations 2006,</p>
          <p eId="para_91">copies of which were laid before Seanad Éireann on 28 April 2006 be referred to the Joint Committee on Finance and the Public Services, in accordance with paragraph (1) (Seanad) of the Orders of Reference of that committee, which, not later than 24 May 2006, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 67, and Standing Order 69(2) shall accordingly apply.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5" refersTo="#agreed" title="decision">Question put and agreed to.<entity name="reference" refersTo="#para_88"/>
                </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_5" refersTo="#bill.2002.26.seanad.2">
        <heading>National Economic and Social Development Office Bill 2002: Second Stage.</heading>
        <summary eId="sum_6">Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</summary>
        <speech by="#MichaelKitt" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_the_Taoiseach" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. T. Kitt)</from>
          <p eId="para_92">I thank the Members of the Seanad for the opportunity to commend the National Economic and Social Development Office Bill to this House. The purpose of this Bill is to establish the National Economic and Social Development Office, comprising three bodies, the National Economic and Social Council, NESC, the National Economic and Social Forum, NESF, and the National Centre for Partnership and Performance, NCPP. Both the NESC and the NESF have been in existence on their own for some time but the more recently established NCPP — successor to the National Centre for Partnership — arises from the commitment in the Programme for Prosperity and Fairness that it be located with the NESC and the NESF, within the National Economic and Social Development Office, where it would work with IBEC and ICTU in supporting the deepening of partnership. All three bodies have been operating on a non-statutory basis since their establishment. This Bill, when enacted, will place them for the first time on a statutory basis.</p>
          <p eId="para_93">The National Economic and Social Development Office, or NESDO as it is known, which is being established under this Bill is, as I have already said, made up of three separate bodies and I would like at the outset to say a few words about the important work of each. The National Economic and Social Council was established in 1973 as an advisory body to the Government on the development of the national economy and the achievement of social justice. The council also provides a forum in which views can be exchanged between people who have a common interest in the development of the economy and the pursuit of social justice. The council is representative of the major economic and social interests in our society and this fact is reflected in its membership.</p>
          <p eId="para_94">The council has undertaken innovative and pioneering work in a number of areas. Many of its strategy reports have provided the framework for negotiations of the national agreements between Government and the social partners since 1987. Last December, the NESC published its three-yearly strategic overview of Irish economic and social policy entitled, NESC Strategy 2006, People, Productivity and Purpose, which paved the way to the current negotiations on a successor to Sustaining Progress. As Senators are aware, discussions with the social partners are currently under way in the context of securing a new social partnership agreement.</p>
          <p eId="para_95">The first strand within the negotiations on a new pay agreement has been focusing on concerns about maintaining and protecting employment standards and it is recognised that there is a need to find the right balance between ensuring decent employment standards and maintaining our competitiveness, flexibility and attractiveness to investment. The agreement of the ICTU executive council on 26 April that sufficient progress has been made in this regard is welcome and this means that the talks have now moved on to address pay and other workplace related issues.</p>
          <p eId="para_96">Several other plenary and bilateral meetings have been held which have discussed, among other things, the NESC report entitled Developmental Welfare State, the implications of the proposed longer-term framework for social partnership, the macro-economic context for the negotiations, the economic, environmental, infrastructural and social policy priorities within a new agreement, and the wider, non-pay issues and priorities, where the social partners have agreed that a longer-term perspective is appropriate for full implementation. We look forward to further progress in the new round of talks and hope that the overall negotiations will be successfully concluded at the earliest possible date.</p>
          <p eId="para_97">The National Economic and Social Forum, NESF, was originally set up by the Government in 1993 for the purpose of widening the social partnership process and of achieving consensus on as wide a basis as possible on major economic and social policy issues. Since 1998, the forum's work has focused on evaluating the implementation of policies dealing with equality and social inclusion. The main tasks of the forum are as follows: to monitor and analyse the implementation of specific measures and programmes identified, especially those concerned with the achievement of equality and social inclusion; to do so through consideration of reports prepared by teams comprising the social partners, with appropriate expertise and representatives of relevant Departments and agencies and its own secretariat; to prepare reports to be published by the forum with such comments as may be considered appropriate; and to ensure that the teams compiling such reports take account of the experience of implementing bodies, customers and clients — including regional variations, in such experience. The forum may consider such policy issues on its own initiative or at the request of the Government.</p>
          <p eId="para_98">The National Centre for Partnership and Performance was established by the Government and launched in October 2002. Its purpose is to support and drive change in the Irish workplace. It enables organisations in the private and public sectors to respond to change, to build capability and to improve performance through partnership. The NCPP's mission is to support and facilitate organisational change, based on partnership, to bring about improved performance and mutual gains. This contributes to national competitiveness, better public services, higher living standards, a better quality of work life and the development of the workplace of the future.</p>
          <p eId="para_99">The centre will carry out this role by carrying out research, identifying past practice and developing new national strategies and new models for partnership in the workplace. These are the distinct bodies which will come together to operate as the National Economic and Social Development Office, NESDO. Their own roles are separate yet complementary, and this legislation will establish the new office as a means of supporting the three constituent bodies, promoting complementarity between them and providing administrative and logistical support on a cost effective basis. It will also act as the employer of staff, and so provide a better career structure for the secretariat of the three bodies.</p>
          <p eId="para_100">I now propose to deal with the Bill and its provisions. The Bill deals with the practical arrangements for the establishment of the office and for the benefit of this House I would like to touch on some of its main features. Section 6 sets out the establishment of the office and refers to its constituent parts as including the NESC, the NESF and the NCPP. It also states that the office and each body established under this section and section 7 shall have all such powers as are necessary for, or incidental to, the performance of its functions under the Act.</p>
          <p eId="para_101">Section 7 gives the Taoiseach the power, following consultations with the Minister for Finance and any other Minister he or she considers relevant, to establish by order such other bodies as he or she consider appropriate, to prepare advice and reports on any aspect of any matter relating to the functions of the office.</p>
          <p eId="para_102">Section 8 states that the function of the office shall be to advise the Taoiseach on all strategic matters relevant to economic and social development in the State. This fits in naturally with the individual roles of the NESC, the NESF and the NCPP as set out in their own terms of reference.</p>
          <p eId="para_103">Sections 9, 10 and 11 set out the functions of the council, the forum and the centre, respectively. The functions of the council shall be to analyse and report to the Taoiseach on strategic issues relating to the efficient development of the economy, the achievement of social justice, the development of a strategic framework for the conduct of relations and the negotiation of agreements between the Government and the social partners.</p>
          <p eId="para_104">The functions of the forum shall be to advise the Taoiseach on policies to achieve greater equality and social inclusion, and such other matters as may be specified by the Taoiseach in the context of social partnership arrangements, by analysing, monitoring and evaluating relevant programmes and policies.</p>
          <p eId="para_105">The functions of the centre shall be to support and facilitate organisational change and innovation based on partnership in order to bring about improved performance and mutual gains, and to contribute to national competitiveness, better public services, higher living standards, a better quality of life and the development of the workplace of the future.</p>
          <p eId="para_106">Section 13 sets out the composition of the office as being the chairperson and deputy chairperson of the council, the forum and the centre. Sections 14, 15 and 16 explain the nominating procedures for the ordinary membership of each of the bodies. In all cases the members shall be appointed by the Taoiseach. Section 17 gives the Taoiseach the power to alter by order the composition of the council, forum or centre.</p>
          <p eId="para_107">Section 18 sets out the term of office of both the chairperson and of an ordinary member of a body, and the conditions under which they both will hold office. This section also calls for an equitable balance to be achieved between men and women in the composition of a body. Section 20 outlines the conditions which apply to a member of the council, the forum, the centre or a member of staff of the bodies when they are nominated or elected to the membership of either House of the Oireachtas or European Parliament, and thereupon cease to be a member of the particular body.</p>
          <p eId="para_108">Sections 21, 22 and 23 relate to the establishment of committees and how they will function, the disclosure by members of the office, the three bodies and staff of interests, and the prohibition on the disclosure of confidential information. Section 24 deals with the role of the chief officer of the office and indicates the duties assigned to him or her, the method of his or her appointment and removal by the Taoiseach, and other conditions which apply to the post. Section 25 deals with the directors of the bodies and outlines their functions, as well as the conditions and term of office.</p>
          <p eId="para_109">Section 26 is concerned with the staff of the office and how such staff are to be recruited. This will require consultation between the office and the director of the body concerned and must have the consent of the Taoiseach and the Minister for Finance. It also deals with the removal of any officer or employee who fails to perform his or her functions satisfactorily.</p>
          <p eId="para_110">Sections 29, 31 and 32 cover the financial arrangements in regard to the office and, in particular, the advancing to the office of moneys provided by the Oireachtas, the keeping of accounts and the conditions which apply to their submission to the Comptroller and Auditor General. Section 31 relates to the giving of evidence by the chief officer to the Dáil committee established to examine and report to Dáil Éireann on the appropriate accounts and reports of the Comptroller and Auditor General.</p>
          <p eId="para_111">The office shall be required under section 33 to prepare a strategic plan for approval by the Taoiseach not later than six months after the establishment day of the office and every three years from the submission of the first statement. Once approved, a copy of the plan will be laid before each House of the Oireachtas. Section 34 requires the office to make a report to the Taoiseach at the end of the financial year and the Taoiseach shall cause copies of the report to be laid before each House of the Oireachtas.</p>
          <p eId="para_112">Section 35 allows the Taoiseach the right to dissolve the council, the forum, the centre and any body established under section 7, following consultation with the office and any Minister who has representation on the body. The office will be included in the First Schedule to the Freedom of Information Act 1997 and will thereby be covered by its provisions. This is set out in section 36.</p>
          <p eId="para_113">The remaining sections are concerned with the dissolution of the non-statutory bodies on the establishment day of the new office, the transfer of rights and liabilities of the dissolved bodies, the drawing up of the accounts of the dissolved bodies and, of particular importance to the staff of the bodies, the conditions which apply to their transfer to the new statutory bodies.</p>
          <p eId="para_114">The Bill will put in place the structures referred to in the Programme for Prosperity and Fairness by combining the NCPP alongside the NESC and the NESF to ensure that their complementary roles are acknowledged and developed to support the economic and social fabric of our society. I am confident that the new office will achieve this and I wish it well in this important work.</p>
          <p eId="para_115">I appreciate that much of my contribution is mundane and unexciting. However, as someone who is a former Minister of State with responsibility for labour affairs and who serves with a Taoiseach who held the labour portfolio, I commend everyone involved in this work. I used the word "partnership" frequently because Ireland is recognised as a country that promotes partnership and there is no better person than the Taoiseach in this regard. Everybody is aware of the time and energy he puts into the process and he is doing so again during the current round of talks on a new agreement.</p>
          <p eId="para_116">Ireland is the envy of many countries, particularly in Europe. They constantly refer to the success and advancement of the economy, which has come about primarily because of this process, and it is important to recognise that. The Taoiseach and all the social partners have demonstrated tremendous leadership within their organisations and representation has been widened. They have done significant work since the process commenced in 1987 to develop the economy for the benefit of the people. I commend the Bill to the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianHayes" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Mr. B. Hayes</from>
          <p eId="para_117">I warmly welcome the Minister of State to the House. I congratulate him on being the first official substitute in the Department of the Taoiseach.</p>
          <p eId="para_118">My initial reaction to the latter part of his contribution is that we need to be careful not to overegg the partnership process. It has been a success but, as Brendan Behan said, we are all very popular, popular among ourselves. The notion that the driving force behind our success over the past 20 years has its genesis in the partnership process is wide of the mark. The Bill was published in 2002 and it was introduced in the Lower House in 2003 but it has taken three years to get to this House. It does not augur well for the Government's strategic drive that a Bill published four years ago is only coming before the House now. If we are serious about reforming the way both Houses do their business, the expeditious passage of legislation should be ensured once it is promised and published. This legislation was promised under a partnership agreement a number of years ago.</p>
          <p eId="para_119">The Minister of State alluded to a problem in this process. The centralised control of the process is exercised by the Taoiseach's office and not the Houses of the Oireachtas. Sections 14, 15 and 16 provide that all the council's members shall be appointed by the Taoiseach. Under section 24, the Taoiseach is given the absolute right to remove the members, while section 26 provides that all new bodies established under section 7 require the consent of the Taoiseach. Section 33 refers to the preparation of a plan that must be forwarded to the Taoiseach's office, while section 34 provides for a report to the Taoiseach of the end of year financial results. Section 35 gives the Taoiseach the right to dissolve the council in its entirety. We are putting into law a highly centralised process under the absolute control of the Taoiseach.</p>
          <p eId="para_120">Significant questions are raised privately by both Government and Opposition Members when I converse with them about the way in which this process is completely devoid of oversight by the Houses of the Oireachtas and resides within the Department of the Taoiseach, to the exclusion of virtually all politicians. They say what we have witnessed in recent years is a dumbing down of Parliament and the control of Parliament by the partnership process. The Bill will not change that because it puts the office that contains the three divisions overseeing the partnership process on a statutory footing.</p>
          <p eId="para_121">The entire process is top heavy and it is largely irrelevant to the vast majority of workers. Approximately 70% of workers are not represented at the negotiating table because they are not in unionised labour, while the vast majority of small and medium-sized business are also not represented. Partnership involves a deal between the public sector unions and the Government. I fully understand why the Government and Governments, of which my party was a member, want that to happen but it should not be overegged. The process should not be described as something it is not and we should not overdramatise its effect on the economy since the mid-1980s.</p>
          <p eId="para_122">My party has made many comments on the benchmarking process in recent years. When the issue was first raised, we sought accountability regarding the determination of the awards and we also wanted greater flexibility in the establishment of the awards. The new benchmarking formula is better than the original and the proof of the pudding will emerge in the next few weeks. Many people in the private sector are agog at the way in which increases can be given to the staff of an entire Department, irrespective of their performance.</p>
          <p eId="para_123">If we are serious about benchmarking going forward, a more flexible process must be established, based on delivering results in the public service, in which significant funding and staff resources have been invested in recent years. The increase is justifiable for many, but not for all, and it must be based on a new system. I hope the new process will deliver a better result for public service consumers but it should be recognised it is too often based on vested interests, including public sector unions, and the people at the trough to the exclusion of the 70% of workers who are not unionised and who are not represented at the negotiating table. They have experienced a significant reduction in their take home pay compared with public sector staff and that issue needs to be addressed.</p>
          <p eId="para_124">I was astonished by the Taoiseach's comments last September when he was doorstepped entering Dublin Castle for the first phase of talks on the new partnership deal. He said his ambition in the new round was to concentrate on health and education issues. He was right but why should these issues be raised during these talks? They are matters for the Houses of the Oireachtas. If the Government's view is that health and education funding is not sufficient, Ministers should say that in Parliament, not in Dublin Castle. Much of the baloney and verbiage that is part and parcel of the process must be unravelled. The idea that the Taoiseach needs the approval of the social partners to increase funding in health and education is anathema to the notion of a representative parliament and representative democracy.</p>
          <p eId="para_125">Part of the success of this country is due to former Deputy Ray MacSharry when, as Minister for Finance in the late 1980s, he decided to curtail much of the expenditure we could not afford. He was supported in that decision by former Deputy Alan Dukes, then leader of my party, in the Tallaght strategy.</p>
          <p eId="para_126">Between 1987 and 1989, we managed collectively to turn the economy around by dealing with the gross overexpenditure on the current side. That was a radical thing to do and a new departure in politics, where a national consensus was reached among the two biggest parties in the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_127">However, references are rarely made to this and we often hear verbiage that the partnership process was the catalyst for the economy. That is not the case and anyone who believes it needs to look at the facts. A partnership process is essential in difficult times, when we have high levels of unemployment and when the public finances are not as healthy as they are now. However, there may be a case for bilateral agreements between workers and their employers to ensure those workers get a better deal. The notion that a blanket increase across industry leads to a better situation for all workers may have to be questioned.</p>
          <p eId="para_128">There is a mania for establishing quangos that started in the early 1990s and for which I do not necessarily blame Fianna Fáil. It started with partnerships, bodies and unelected, unaccountable people in well-paid positions who produce endless reports that nobody reads. This mania affects all Governments, including my own Government. In 1992-93, an obsession developed whereby new boards were established all over the country. However, we are cementing this in legislation today.</p>
          <p eId="para_129">There are three bodies in existence at the moment and I wonder if they would be better off as one body. That would curtail much of the expenditure on administration, salaries and costs. It is difficult to understand the differences between them. Much of the work could be done by the ESRI, which is in existence for more than 40 years. Is it necessary to have the NESC, the NESF and the NCPP in operation, given the current level of expertise in the public sector? I accept that if there is a partnership process, then there needs to be a backup for that process. However, I do not understand why the process should be segmented in three different areas when the State is already developing it in many Departments. In the Department of the Taoiseach, there are very substantial resources and excellent public servants who can do this work. Do we need to make jobs for others? These bodies have grown exponentially in recent years like plants in the ground and nobody is prepared to stop them.</p>
          <p eId="para_130">The Minister of State spoke about the National Centre for Partnership and Performance, yet one could argue much of its work is done by the strategic management process in the public service, which aims for greater efficiency, consumer focus and organisational change. I served on that committee for a number of years and I understood that these developments were already under way in the public service. However, this Bill seems to reinvent it once more.</p>
          <p eId="para_131">Section 7 gives the Taoiseach absolute power to set up any subgroup or body within this framework, following consultation with the Minister for Finance and any other Minister. We are putting into law a centralised process that has its beginning, middle and end in the Department of the Taoiseach. That is bad for our Parliament. If politicians want to take ownership of this process, we need a hands-on approach and we need to be involved in the process. Whatever comes from the partnership process may be debated here, but it does not require a positive resolution of either House of the Oireachtas. It only requires the assent of the Government. Is there any other plan with such significance over a three or five-year period which would not require a resolution of both Dáil and Seanad Éireann? This is bizarre. We are now giving power to the Taoiseach to establish any other body as he sees fit, without recourse to legislation. We will have to tease this out on Committee Stage.</p>
          <p eId="para_132">The Minister of State referred to the fact that the office now comes under the Freedom of Information Act. Will the constituent bodies under the office also come under the Act? The public has a right to know what is going on in feeding the partnership process itself. The problem with benchmarking the first time was the lack of public accountability about the information being supplied to the decision-making body. Does the FOI provision apply to all three bodies under the office to be established? On Committee Stage of the Bill in the Dáil, Deputy Bruton attempted to have a much more rigorous procedure put in the Bill which would involve the Oireachtas. I will return to that issue on Committee Stage in this House.</p>
          <p eId="para_133">Politicians say one thing in private and another thing in public. In fairness to Senator O'Toole, he is consistent on this issue. However, colleagues in the Minister of State's party and in my party say very different things about this process. We must make it work, we must make it more accountable and we must ensure that our Parliament is not sidelined as it has been so often by different Governments in the past ten years.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LabhrasOMurchu" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Labhrás Ó Murchú</from>
          <p eId="para_134">Is mian liom fáilte a chur roimh an Aire Stáit agus buíochas a ghabháil leis toisc an léirithe a thug sé dúinn ar an mBille seo. Ní gá dom a rá go n-aontaím go hiomlán le gach rud a dúirt sé. Tá sé ciallmhar, bunúsach agus níl aon amhras faoi ná go mbaineann sé leis an stádas atá ag an tír seo i láthair na huaire ó thaobh cúrsaí eacnamaíochta agus sóisialta de.</p>
          <p eId="para_135">There are many in this House who are old enough to remember the bad old days. When we travelled abroad, the perception of us was that our begging bowl was seldom far from the table. We should not forget that people threw around labels such as "banana republic" and "deprivation."</p>
          <p eId="para_136">Last year, I visited Shanghai where together with our consul general I met with a top local official who had high praise for Ireland. Shanghai has a population of 20 million people, yet the chairman of its foreign affairs office, a position which is almost the equivalent of prime minister, told us that the city had much to learn from Ireland. On St. Patrick's Day, I visited Latvia, where the Irish ambassador and I held an open session with the mayor. Shortly after our welcome, we were told that, as a new EU member state, Latvia has much to learn from Ireland's accomplishments. On Easter Sunday, I met with 300 members of the Irish community in New York. I remember going to America in the late 1960s, when dollars were being collected to send to Ireland. The debate on my most recent visit, however, was about Ireland's economic success and what the change in the country's image means for the Irish in America.</p>
          <p eId="para_137">That success does not pertain only to economic or social affairs. Our international status has become what it is today because we have proved ourselves. That has impacted on many aspects of Irish life, none more so than the Northern Ireland situation, which was our Achilles heel on many occasions. If we had not taken centre stage in world and, especially, European affairs, the President of the United States would not have had a hands-on role in trying to bring about a solution to the Northern problem. Those problems also had economic aspects because, as anyone who dealt with foreign tourism bodies could explain, an incident in the North of Ireland could undo an advertising campaign just as progress was about to be made.</p>
          <p eId="para_138">Today's Bill is another milestone on a phenomenal road of success and progress. I accept Senator Brian Hayes's argument that its passage has been slow but that has not detracted from the work of the three constituent bodies in any way. It is important to remember this Bill fulfils a commitment given under the Programme for Prosperity and Fairness. I was interested to hear the points made by Senator Hayes, some of which were also raised by Senator McHugh on the Order of Business. They implied that the job of Government is not to govern but governance is fundamental to democracy and is the reason Governments and taoisigh exist. It would be wrong to suggest that interaction does not take place because hardly a week goes by in which Senator Ross does not expound on many of the ideas raised by Senator Brian Hayes. In turn, Senator O'Toole, who represents the trade union movement, puts the other side of the argument. These issues are discussed in virtually every Bill pertaining to the economy that comes before the House.</p>
          <p eId="para_139">It is not right to use the word "quango" in the way it was used by Senator Brian Hayes. When the National Economic and Social Council was established in 1973, the Government took an important step in terms of engaging on a broader basis with people who were focused on the national economy. The advisory body employed people who were in touch with reality and were the best in their fields. That did not detract from the role of parliamentarians in any way and actually extended the role of the Oireachtas. Had the partnership model not been developed, the country would have experienced constant industrial strife. What investor would be attracted to a country riddled by strikes?</p>
          <p eId="para_140">I come from the small town of Cashel, which has a population of 3,000. Every time the opportunity arose of attracting a new industry to the town, we put together a business formula. After a while, I discovered that prospective investors knew more about us than we realised and subsequently learned that they studied local newspapers to investigate whether Cashel's environment was fertile for their industries. Wherever there was an overemphasis on industrial action, they fought shy because they realised that problems would arise down the road. Investors no longer have to buy local newspapers because modern technology allows them to receive reports on a minute-by-minute basis. However, it is still the case that prospective investors will not risk their money if the environment is not conducive to growth.</p>
          <p eId="para_141">We have succeeded in that strikes are virtually an issue of the past. When threats of strike action previously arose, everybody went to the wall but these threats are now dealt with through the structures we have developed. While we all knew that a solution had to be found, we only did so after the damage had been done. Invariably, workers suffered because strike pay did not compensate them for loss of money. Generally, they returned to somewhat improved employment conditions but the damage done by the strike meant the workplace was less able to cope. Through our structures, the confidence we built and, above all, the trust that currently exists, the bad old days are in the distant past. I give credit for this to the visionaries who established the first body.</p>
          <p eId="para_142">The establishment of the National Economic and Social Forum in the 1990s sent out the statement that great progress had been made but that more people had to be brought into the process. Contrary to the arguments of Senator Brian Hayes, the net has in fact been spread to allow more people to interact with each other within the forum. This step favoured the worker by supporting the changes needed within the workplace. Progress was made, people were given opportunities to interact and the process reached ground level. Changes have taken place in all Irish workplaces at all levels. For example, aberrations in health and safety, which are fundamental, make the headlines because they are so few and far between. Issues such as sexual harassment and equal opportunity have been addressed. The new body, the NCCP, will address the few issues remaining on the priority list. Not only have these three elements contributed to our current affluence but they also ensure that the social element will at all times be to the fore.</p>
          <p eId="para_143">I do not know how many people go back on bóithrín na smaointe and compare like with like. We are pushing out the parameters from a base of unprecedented success but when we look back at ten or 20 years ago we do not compare like with like. With the new body bringing the three constituent bodies together into one office I can understand why that commitment was sought at the time and why it was readily provided.</p>
          <p eId="para_144">According to economic forecasts we look forward to another three or four good years, but nothing remains static. There will be new competition from eastern Europe and others. If we remain static and just pat ourselves on the back we will not see the dangers and opportunities that might arise in a year or two. We have not lost many industries as a result of the opening up of the EU but we have lost some and may lose more, largely due to our success, the level of wages and work conditions available.</p>
          <p eId="para_145">It is important we take account of our situation. While I do not suggest the three constituent bodies have not interacted, there is a need for co-ordination, pooling of resources and a totality in the work they do. I cannot see how anybody would suggest we do not need the bodies. It would be like a layman saying he would take the stones from the foundation of a house and expect it to stand. It will not. If any of the bodies, quango or otherwise, is removed, we would endanger the process.</p>
          <p eId="para_146">The Bill allows the Taoiseach to be Taoiseach. He is the Leader of the Government and the country. Members of the Houses and the media hold taoisigh to account for everything they do, and rightly so. To suggest, as it would mean, that he should abdicate his responsibilities and powers, which he has by mandate from the people through the elected representatives and the creation of the Government, would be a negation of democracy. That is why I refer to what Senator McHugh said this morning about the Progressive Democrats having the Ministry for health and children because it is a small party. That is not how government works. It is not about numbers but the responsibility placed on them by being in government. The only way the Taoiseach can govern is by ensuring he has full accountability and responsibility.</p>
          <p eId="para_147">Let us examine the Oireachtas committees. This is important. The powers, responsibilities and opportunities of the Oireachtas committees are possibly the most expansive in the world. Many a country, those with existing as well as developing legislatures, will study our model in the future. Every day of the week the committees sit and deal with Government business handed down to them by the Houses of the Oireachtas and they have the power to invite witnesses to appear before them. Any of the bodies listed here can be asked to come before the Houses of the Oireachtas.</p>
          <p eId="para_148">It has been suggested that trade unionists and businesses are under-represented. The democratic structure has always been that one joins an association, elects a leadership, agrees a constitution and tells the organisation what are one's views. The leadership of the organisation takes a consensus and promotes that. This is what IBEC and the Irish Congress of Trade Unions do. There is no other way except to go back to the fair day when one raises one's hand to say one agrees. We have gone beyond that and it is particularly important not to underestimate how the structures operate.</p>
          <p eId="para_149">The Houses of the Oireachtas have a direct input if there are issues in the Bill with which we do not agree. Senator Brian Hayes has proposed some good points. I would not take them from him and I am not trying to score political points. This is not the sort of Bill on which to score political points as fundamentally, we all agree. We have to say something to use up our 15 or 20 minutes and get on the record of the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianHayes" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Mr. B. Hayes</from>
          <p eId="para_150">We do not have to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LabhrasOMurchu" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Labhrás Ó Murchú</from>
          <p eId="para_151">It would be difficult to disagree——</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" as="#Leas-Chathaoirleach" eId="spk_58">
          <from>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</from>
          <p eId="para_152">The Senator has almost used up his time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LabhrasOMurchu" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Labhrás Ó Murchú</from>
          <p eId="para_153">This Bill will go through smoothly because fundamentally, we are proud of our success and are anxious to ensure it is protected. Above all, each of us who has any visionary element in our spirit looks to the future to maintain, expand and develop what we have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KateWalsh" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Ms K. Walsh</from>
          <p eId="para_154">I am pleased to have these few minutes to speak on this Bill and I welcome the Minister of State to the House. I have just run here so I am exhausted.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" as="#Leas-Chathaoirleach" eId="spk_61">
          <from>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</from>
          <p eId="para_155">Senator Feeney may speak first.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KateWalsh" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Ms K. Walsh</from>
          <p eId="para_156">Yes, let her speak first. I apologise.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldineFeeney" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Ms Feeney</from>
          <p eId="para_157">I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach. I am happy to allow my colleague Senator Kate Walsh to get some oxygen while I use my few minutes. I welcome the Minister of State and the Bill. The National Economic and Social Development Office will be established under the terms of the National Economic and Social Development Bill. The new office will incorporate three bodies, the National Economic and Social Council, the National Economic and Social Forum and the National Council for Partnership and Performance. When enacted, the Bill will place the three constituent bodies on a statutory basis as part of the National Economic and Social Development Office. It will also be responsible for other such bodies that may be established in the future by the Taoiseach or his office.</p>
          <p eId="para_158">I would like to speak on the body of which I am a member, the National and Economic Social Forum. This body is chaired by Dr. Maureen Gaffney.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" as="#Leas-Chathaoirleach" eId="spk_64">
          <from>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</from>
          <p eId="para_159">I understand Senator Feeney is sharing time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldineFeeney" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Ms Feeney</from>
          <p eId="para_160">No. As the Minister of State has pointed out, the NESF was the first established, in 1993. Its purpose was to contribute to the formation of a wider national consensus on social and economic policy initiatives, particularly on unemployment, equality and social exclusion. I am pleased to have been asked by The Taoiseach to join the NESF. I share my membership with other Members of this House, namely, Senators O'Rourke, Mooney, Daly, Coghlan, Quinn and Kate Walsh.</p>
          <p eId="para_161">In 1998, the Government asked the NESF to undertake a new role in the national policy process, mainly to focus on monitoring and analysing the implementation of particular measures and programmes identified in the social partnership arrangements, especially those concerned with achieving equality and social inclusion. The NESF has produced a wide range of influential policy reports and every member of this House is familiar with them as we have debated some of them here over the years. These provide a solid basis for facing future policy challenges.</p>
          <p eId="para_162">The NESF had its term of office renewed in 2003 and in doing so the Government asked it to convene public consultations, particularly on policy issues, so that the Government may refer to it from time to time for examination. This strengthens the role given to the NESF. It provides the forum and individuals, as well as the members of the wider voluntary community and other sectors who make contributions to it that affect policy, which I know first-hand from having sat on the body.</p>
          <p eId="para_163">Some of the reports produced by the NESF in recent years included Creating a More Inclusive Labour Market which was published in January of this year, and Care for Older People which was published in November 2005. I sat on the sub-committee which produced the latter report with Senator Kate Walsh, which gave me the first-hand knowledge to which I referred. I could see the valuable work done by voluntary members and groups, together with civil servants from the different Departments involved. The report, which was debated in this Chamber, made excellent recommendations. Another report was Early Childhood Care and Education, published in July 2005. The NESF is the one of three bodies about which I know most because I am a member of that body.</p>
          <p eId="para_164">The second body is the National Economic and Social Council, established in 1973. The function of the council is to analyse and report to the Taoiseach on strategic issues relating to the effect of development of the economy, the achievement of social justice and the development of a strategic framework. The council is chaired by the Secretary General of the Department of the Taoiseach and contains representatives of trade unions, employers, farming organisations, NGOs, key Departments and independent experts.</p>
          <p eId="para_165">The third body is the National Centre for Partnership and Performance. The NCPP was established by the Government to support and drive change in the Irish workplace. The centre's remit is to enable organisations in the private and public sectors, through partnership, to respond to change, build capability and improve performance. The NCPP is currently finalising its new strategic plan, which will be published shortly.</p>
          <p eId="para_166">The work of these organisations has contributed greatly to policy formation and implementing change. Through my work on the NESF, I have gained valuable insight into a wide variety of issues through interaction with representatives from the outside bodies and the various organisations represented on it. As the Minister of State outlined, this approach is all about partnership and is one with which I agree and would like continued. It is through such organisations that we, as legislators, will obtain these comprehensive reports, which are the blueprint for legislation.</p>
          <p eId="para_167">Having listened to the contribution of Senator Ó Murchú, I believe the NESF can take a proud bow because it has played its part in the economic and social success that we experience today, a success of which we are openly proud. I commend the role of the chairperson of the NESF, Dr. Maureen Gaffney, and pay tribute to the members who sit alongside myself and Senator Kate Walsh for their fine contribution to the work of the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_168">As the Minister of State noted, this is not a Bill that one can really get one's teeth into. We have often had great debates and arguments in the House but this Bill is rather technical in nature. I shy away from technical things. Perhaps a woman would not really know what technical issues are about, no more than she would know how to hammer a nail into a wall. If it can hurt me, I do not go near it. I stay on a straight road. However, while the Bill is technical, I have some experience in that I sit on one of the bodies involved. My contribution is focused on discussing the important role of that body.</p>
          <p eId="para_169">This debate is not about scoring points but I did not agree with the point made by Senator Brian Hayes regarding the Taoiseach's that this was all about examining the issues of education and health. The Government is not trying to take away from the role of Government or dilute the powers of Government in any way. It is showing leadership by including bodies such as these. The Government involves not just legislators and elected politicians but also the electorate in general, community groups and people who would heretofore have felt themselves to be outside of politics. It is in this way that the Taoiseach is showing leadership. If we are to say anything about the Taoiseach, he is certainly a man of the people. He is trying to be inclusive and bring everybody on board.</p>
          <p eId="para_170">This is an important Bill. It is all about partnership, which has proven it can work well. I look forward to the contribution of Senator O'Toole, who knows more about partnership than any other Member of this House or the Lower House. I wish the Bill a speedy passage through the House. I commend the staff of the various bodies involved and look forward to the next Stage of the Bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOToole" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Mr. O’Toole</from>
          <p eId="para_171">I am delighted to have the opportunity to contribute and welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Kitt, to the House. Two of these three organisations are reasonably well known, the NESF and NESC, and while the public are still getting to know the National Centre for Partnership and Performance, the work done by Peter Cassells and Lucy Fallon-Byrne has been extraordinary.</p>
          <p eId="para_172">We all know social partnership but as far as most are concerned, it is something that happens in Kildare Street, where the trade union movement, the business community and Government and various other groups meet at the top level. One of the problems is that one can agree to something across a table in Dublin but to get that agreement understood in a small workplace in another part of the country is difficult. As politicians we have seen this in other ways. The NCPP is trying to deepen the concept of partnership.</p>
          <p eId="para_173">We need to give a clear guideline as to what goes on in the partnership talks and what these three bodies are doing. In every partnership discussion going back to 1987 — I was involved in every one — we would begin with the most recent report from the NESF and NESC and on that would build the partnership process. That is how important these organisations are. They are not prescriptive but they outline the situation. Issues are agreed in principle, then they are fleshed out in negotiation.</p>
          <p eId="para_174">How does this process work? One important point is that the process requires people to develop a coincidence of objectives. They must have an understanding and agreement as to where they are going. The first issue is one that some in the trade union movement would argue is not their business, and one that some in the business community would argue is not the business of the trade unions. It is only when one can force people to sit around a table and listen to each other that progress can be made on this first issue, which is that of wealth creation. There is no point in my arguing from the trade union side about redistributing wealth if there is no wealth to redistribute, and the same applies to the management side. We must all agree to create the conditions necessary to create wealth. That is the basis of the Celtic tiger, and involves issues such as employment, labour law and, in particular, competitiveness.</p>
          <p eId="para_175">We must be competitive. When one hears a discussion on competitiveness, it almost always boils down to how much workers are being paid, which is only one small part of the issue. The job of the trade union side has been to say it is not only that and that it is about profits, etc.</p>
          <p eId="para_176">Over the past 20 years, the level of wealth creation — in other words, the growth in the economy each year — has been quite extraordinary. This year growth will be 5% to 5.5%. With the exception of the blip around 2001-02, the development of wealth in this country has been quite extraordinary. We have moved from a time where the <i>per capita</i> wealth of the country was way below the European average. It is now above that. I am only using that as a measurement or a benchmark. It does not mean anything for many people who do not share in that wealth and that is why we need further social partnership.</p>
          <p eId="para_177">When we create the wealth, we must decide what to do with it, which is the crucial part. We have grown the wealth of the country by 5% this year, so what should we do with it and who should get it? How difficult is that? The longer one spends thinking about it, the more difficult it gets but one can begin with the top-line issues. Some of that money will have to be reinvested in industry or in whatever is creating wealth and in research and development to ensure our industries develop and more wealth is created. If we do not do that, we will have no future. That is crucial for the following reason. We will no longer make widgets or have huge manufacturing industries. Any add-on value we create will come from intelligence — intellectual add-on and investment. That is why we need research and development in new products, new markets, new industry and new services. If that is not done, we will have no future.</p>
          <p eId="para_178">I refer to that dirty word "profit". It was years before the people I represent became comfortable with discussing the idea. We must accept that profit is a motivator and is part of the deal. Some of us might not like to see too much of it around but it must exist. It is the job of those of us on the left or the labour side to ensure we hold down the profit level so there is more left for the share-out. However, the shareholders, risk-takers and entrepreneurs in a company deserve to get their cut.</p>
          <p eId="para_179">When industrialists here talk about how much they are being overtaxed, they have no argument. This country has the lowest tax regime in Europe in terms of capital gains tax and corporation tax. I have argued with Government for 20 years that it does not need to be quite so low. The reality is industrialists are getting a very good deal and whether it is right or wrong, nobody can argue with the fact it has worked and has created wealth. Industrialists are operating in a very relaxed regime.</p>
          <p eId="para_180">Tax money is spent on services such as those provided by the school in Dunquin, the hospital in Drogheda and the jail somewhere else. There must be money for health, education, justice and social welfare. What do the disadvantaged in our society, voluntary bodies, pensions, etc., get? Suddenly it all becomes very clear. It is easy to do a flow chart of the above.</p>
          <p eId="para_181">Everyone must agree on the conditions needed for the creation of wealth. Those conditions include interest, competitiveness, inflation, etc. The next question is what we do with the money generated. Some of it must be reinvested in research and development, some will be taken as profit, some will be used to pay workers and some will be used to pay tax. The Government uses tax revenue to run the country and look after people, including some of those who have taken a profit because they still send their children to school, avail of the health service, drive on the roads, use the airports, etc. These are real issues and as soon as we bring them together, we recognise that is what social partnership is about.</p>
          <p eId="para_182">Social partnership is important because if we did not have it, we would have a comfortable situation where people would not go outside their own tents. The trade unions would never have to eyeball or do face time with those on the other side of the argument. If the social partners did not have to deal with each other, they would never have to hear the arguments of those on the other side. If those on the business side did not have to argue their point or listen to the other side, life would become very easy.</p>
          <p eId="para_183">The guy who makes the most extreme demand or comment gets the loudest applause at meetings with his own crowd and everybody leaves the meeting with a feel-good feeling. However, if he is brought into Government Buildings the following day, lined up with the Government, the farmers, the voluntary bodies, etc., on the other side and told to listen to responses to his argument, he will hear things he never heard. That is the value of social partnership and that engagement is crucial. People might dislike it and might not like what they hear but they must listen.</p>
          <p eId="para_184">There is always compromise and every national agreement is a sell-out by all parties. There has never been an agreement where all parties have got all they looked for. What we can have with a partnership agreement and which we have had many times is what I refer to as a "Chinese bargain" where every party gets something positive out of it. No party gets all it looked for but each gets some of what it looked for.</p>
          <p eId="para_185">In all of that, we try to raise the boats of all groups. However, we have failed to look after people who need more help because this has become a competitive and survivalist society. Recently I listened to a French person living here whose view was that this is a great country in which to live if one is healthy, doing well and working in a good job but that it is a difficult one in which to live if one needs support or help. That is why we must welcome this legislation.</p>
          <p eId="para_186">This legislation copper-fastens much of the basis for the above, which is why I commend it. It is the way forward. Even if there is no partnership agreement, there will always be partnership. If there is no partnership, we would spend our time pulling each other apart. For many years, we have had the best industrial relations record in Europe. No country has had fewer strikes. In fact, public service strikes are almost unheard of in Ireland these days compared with what we have seen in France, Belgium, Italy and Germany in the past year where there have been strikes over pensions, public services, investment and labour law, issues which are dealt with in partnership negotiations here and, as consequence, it is a boost for the economy. This legislation is important as it gives a statutory basis to the various bodies.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#KateWalsh" eId="spk_67">
          <from>Ms K. Walsh</from>
          <p eId="para_187">I have a particular interest in the points relating to the function of this new office. The Minister of State referred to section 8 and the individual roles of the NESF, the NESC and the NCPP. These valuable groups have their own terms of reference and this legislation fits naturally with them. As a member of the committee, I am proud of the role played by the NESF. It currently provides advice to the Government on policies to achieve greater equality and social inclusion which is a valuable contribution. By analysing, monitoring and evaluating relevant policies identified in the context of social partnership, the NESF contributes greatly to the ongoing efforts by the Progressive Democrats and this Government to ensure the fruits of our prosperity are used to help the most vulnerable in our society.</p>
          <p eId="para_188">It is correct that we put in place the necessary structures under social partnership and I welcome the recognition and complementary roles of the NESF, the NESC and NCPP. The purpose of this legislation is to ensure we have proper arrangements to develop and support the social and economic fabric of our changing society. In this context, I hope the House joins with me in welcoming this Bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Mr. Wilson</from>
          <p eId="para_189">I welcome the Minister of State. As other speakers have said, the purpose of the Bill is to establish the National Economic and Social Development Office comprising three bodies, namely, the National Economic and Social Council, the National Economic and Social Forum and the National Centre for Partnership and Performance. Section 9 states the functions of the council shall be to analyse and report to the Taoiseach on strategic issues relating to the efficient development of the economy and the achievement of social justice, and the development of a strategic framework for the conduct of relations and the negotiation of agreements between the Government and the social partners.</p>
          <p eId="para_190">Section 10 deals with the functions of the forum, which are to advise the Taoiseach on policies to achieve greater equality and social inclusion and such other matters as may be specified by the Taoiseach in the context of social partnership arrangements by analysing, monitoring and evaluating relevant programmes and policies, and to facilitate public consultation on policy matters referred to it from time to time by the Government.</p>
          <p eId="para_191">Section 11 states the functions of the centre are to support and facilitate organisational change and innovation based on partnership in order to bring about improved performance and mutual gains, and to contribute to national competitiveness, better public services, higher living standards, a better quality of life and the development of the workplace of the future. I concur with what my colleagues have said about the progress made since the partnership process first came about and the great developments that have taken place.</p>
          <p eId="para_192">Section 14 deals with the composition of the council and section 16 deals with the composition of the centre. Section 15 deals with the composition of the forum. The ordinary members of the forum shall include: 15 Members of either the Dáil or Seanad; not fewer than three representatives of business and employer interest groups; not fewer than three members of the Irish Congress of Trade Unions; not fewer than three representatives of farming and agricultural interests; and not fewer than ten and not more than 15 members representing the "community and voluntary sector". I would like this to state "community, voluntary and youth sector" because I would like youth to be mentioned specifically in the legislation.</p>
          <p eId="para_193">I welcome the fact that section 15 also states that not fewer than three and not more than five members shall be persons nominated by organisations which the Taoiseach considers representative of the local government system. I would like clarification that this means councillors rather than members of the administrative sections of councils.</p>
          <p eId="para_194">Section 20 states:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_195">20.—(1) Where a member of the Council, the Forum (subject to subsection (2)), the Centre or a body established under section 7—</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_196">(<i>a</i>) is nominated as a member of Seanad Éireann,</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_197">(<i>b</i>) is elected as a member of either House of the Oireachtas or to be a representative in the European Parliament,</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_198">(<i>c</i>) is regarded pursuant to Part XIII of the Second Schedule to the European Parliament Elections Act 1997, as having been elected to that Parliament to fill a vacancy, or</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_199">(<i>d</i>) becomes a member of a local authority (within the meaning of the Local Government Act 2001),</p>
          <p eId="para_200">he or she shall thereupon cease to be a member of the Council . . .</p>
          <p eId="para_201">If somebody is doing a good job as a member of either body and is elected to the Oireachtas, a council or the European Parliament, he or she should not be barred from being a member of any of the groups.</p>
          <p eId="para_202">I have much more to say but am aware that the Minister of State is pressed for time. I welcome the Bill and look forward to contributing on Committee and Report Stages.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelKitt" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_the_Taoiseach" eId="spk_69">
          <from>Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. T. Kitt)</from>
          <p eId="para_203">I welcome this debate. I will not be able to address all the issues raised but will make a commitment to deal with them as best I can on Committee Stage. Some very important, detailed points were made.</p>
          <p eId="para_204">I am a great supporter of social partnership and respect Senator Brian Hayes's opinion that Members, across party lines, have different views thereon. Senator O'Toole, a strong proponent of this system who has been an active player, made the key point that there are always other issues to address. We all know the issues that need to be addressed in respect of health, marginalisation and poverty and we must do more work on these.</p>
          <p eId="para_205">Senator Brian Hayes mentioned the democratic deficit, which has been discussed previously, and Senator Ó Murchú covered it in his contribution. There is a role for the Oireachtas in this regard. The Taoiseach has taken well in excess of 300 oral questions on social partnership since 1997. Each of our six social partnership agreements to date has been negotiated on the basis of the primacy of the programme for Government within the framework of the NESC three-year strategic, economic and social overview. I assume the negotiations leading to Partnership 2000, overseen by the then rainbow coalition Government, were conducted on a similar basis.</p>
          <p eId="para_206">The monitoring and review of the implementation of the social partnership agreement operates on a number of levels in the Oireachtas. The detailed quarterly progress report on implementation, keynote speeches and other relevant documents are laid before the Oireachtas for close scrutiny and probing. In excess of 40 key documents have been laid before both Houses in respect of the current agreement. Ministerial colleagues have also engaged in extensive debate on social partnership-related issues. The Oireachtas strand of the National Economic and Social Forum, a key social partnership institution, comprises Members of the Dáil and Seanad. I welcome the debates in the Seanad on this issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_207">On the NESC strategy for 2006, the report provides a guiding vision for economic and social development in the future. The strategy report represents a particularly valuable input into the necessary process of dialogue. The social partnership process is more than a pay agreement — it represents a set of relationships between Government and social partners which helps to produce a problem-solving response, as stated by Senator Ó Murchú. I have personal experience of this and I remember the famous dispute involving baggage handlers in Ryanair. A mechanism exists to solve problems as they arise and it has been marvellous in terms of the partnership approach and in managing change in the direction of strategic progress. This point was made by Senator O'Toole.</p>
          <p eId="para_208">On the accountability of NESDO, Senator Brian Hayes said we are putting in place a process centralised in the Department of the Taoiseach. However, section 32(1) gives the Committee of Public Accounts a role in examining the expenditure of the respective bodies. Section 32(2) requires the directors and chief officers to give an account of their operations to a committee of both Houses. Freedom of information guidelines will apply to each of the three bodies of the office. I have covered briefly the role of the Oireachtas in the partnership process.</p>
          <p eId="para_209">I regret that, in my capacity as Government Chief Whip, I must now leave for some pressing business concerning a necessary part of the democratic process, namely, voting. I welcome this debate and assure Senators that I will address some of the outstanding issues on Committee Stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7" refersTo="#agreed" title="decision">Question put and agreed to.<entity name="reference" refersTo="#sum_6"/>
                </summary>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" as="#Leas-Chathaoirleach" eId="spk_70">
          <from>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</from>
          <p eId="para_210">When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LabhrasOMurchu" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Labhrás Ó Murchú</from>
          <p eId="para_211">Next Tuesday.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8">Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 9 May 2006.</summary>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" as="#Leas-Chathaoirleach" eId="spk_72">
          <from>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</from>
          <p eId="para_212">When is it proposed to sit again?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LabhrasOMurchu" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Labhrás Ó Murchú</from>
          <p eId="para_213">Next Tuesday at 2.30 p.m.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_9">The Seanad adjourned at 12.40 p.m. until2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 9 May 2006.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
