<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2022-11-15/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2022-11-15/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2022-11-15" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/house/seanad/26"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2022-11-15/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2022-11-15/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2022-11-15" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2022-11-15/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2022-11-15/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2022-11-17" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <parliamentary>
          <voting eId="vote_1" href="#sum_18" outcome="#lost" refersTo="#sum_17">
            <count eId="vote_1-count_1" href="#qty_1" refersTo="#ta" value="4"/>
            <count eId="vote_1-count_2" href="#qty_2" refersTo="#nil" value="19"/>
          </voting>
          <voting eId="vote_2" href="#sum_29" outcome="#carried" refersTo="#sum_28">
            <count eId="vote_2-count_1" href="#qty_3" refersTo="#ta" value="20"/>
            <count eId="vote_2-count_2" href="#qty_4" refersTo="#nil" value="4"/>
          </voting>
        </parliamentary>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCConcept eId="#lost" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#DeclaredLost" showAs="Declared Lost"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="#carried" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#DeclaredCarried" showAs="Declared Carried"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="#staon" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#StaonVote" showAs="Staon Vote"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="#nil" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#NílVote" showAs="Níl Vote"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="#ta" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#TáVote" showAs="Tá Vote"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AidanDavitt" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aidan-Davitt.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Aidan Davitt"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AislingDolan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aisling-Dolan.S.2020-06-29" showAs="Aisling Dolan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AnneRabbitte" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Anne-Rabbitte.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Anne Rabbitte"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BarryWard" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Barry-Ward.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Barry Ward"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CatherineArdagh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Catherine-Ardagh.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Catherine Ardagh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CharlieMcConalogue" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Charlie-McConalogue.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Charlie McConalogue"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DamienEnglishFG" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Damien-English.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Damien English"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DiarmuidWilson" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Diarmuid-Wilson.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Diarmuid Wilson"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ErinMcGreehan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Erin-McGreehan.S.2020-06-29" showAs="Erin McGreehan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FintanWarfield" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Fintan-Warfield.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Fintan Warfield"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FionaOLoughlin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Fiona-O'Loughlin.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Fiona O'Loughlin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="GarretAhearn" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Garret-Ahearn.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Garret Ahearn"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="GerardPCraughwell" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Gerard-P-Craughwell.S.2014-10-10" showAs="Gerard P. Craughwell"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="GerryHorkan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Gerry-Horkan.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Gerry Horkan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="HelenMcEntee" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Helen-McEntee.D.2013-03-27" showAs="Helen McEntee"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JerryButtimer" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jerry-Buttimer.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Jerry Buttimer"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeOReilly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-O'Reilly.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Joe O'Reilly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnCummins" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Cummins.S.2020-03-30" showAs="John Cummins"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnMcGahon" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-McGahon.S.2020-03-30" showAs="John McGahon"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LisaChambers" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Lisa-Chambers.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Lisa Chambers"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LorraineCliffordLee" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Lorraine-Clifford-Lee.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Lorraine Clifford-Lee"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LynnBoylan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Lynn-Boylan.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Lynn Boylan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LynnRuane" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Lynn-Ruane.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Lynn Ruane"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MalcolmByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Malcolm-Byrne.D.2019-11-29" showAs="Malcolm Byrne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MartinConway" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Martin-Conway.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Martin Conway"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MarySeeryKearney" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mary-Seery-Kearney.S.2020-06-29" showAs="Mary Seery Kearney"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelMcDowellPD" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-McDowell.D.1987-03-10" showAs="Michael McDowell"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichealCarrigy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Micheál-Carrigy.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Micheál Carrigy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NedOSullivan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ned-O'Sullivan.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Ned O'Sullivan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="OllieCrowe" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ollie-Crowe.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Ollie Crowe"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulDaly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Daly.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Paul Daly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulGavan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Gavan.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Paul Gavan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulineOreilly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pauline-O'Reilly.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Pauline O'Reilly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PippaHackett" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pippa-Hackett.S.2019-11-01" showAs="Pippa Hackett"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RebeccaMoynihan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Rebecca-Moynihan.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Rebecca Moynihan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ReginaDoherty" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Regina-Doherty.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Regina Doherty"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RobbieGallagher" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Robbie-Gallagher.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Robbie Gallagher"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RonanMullen" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Rónán-Mullen.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Rónán Mullen"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanKyne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Kyne.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Seán Kyne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ShaneCassells" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Shane-Cassells.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Shane Cassells"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SharonKeogan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Sharon-Keogan.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Sharon Keogan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TimDooley" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Timmy-Dooley.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Timmy Dooley"/>
        <TLCEvent eId="bill.2022.42.seanad.3" href="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2022/42/seanad/3" showAs="Judicial Appointments Commission Bill 2022: Committee Stage (Resumed) (Seanad)"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Acting_Chairperson" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/office/acting_chairperson" showAs="Acting Chairperson"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_for_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister/agriculture__food__marine" showAs="Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_for_Justice" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister/justice" showAs="Minister for Justice"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/agriculture__food__marine" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Enterprise,_Trade_and_Employment" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/enterprise__trade__employment" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Health" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/health" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Health"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>SEANAD ÉIREANN</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>SEANAD ÉIREANN</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2022-11-15">Dé Máirt, 15 Samhain 2022</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2022-11-15">Tuesday, 15 November 2022</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="volume">
        <docNumber refersTo="#vol_289">Vol. 289</docNumber>
      </block>
      <block name="number">
        <docNumber refersTo="#no_13">No. 13</docNumber>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus>Unrevised</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus>Neamhcheartaithe</docStatus>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 02:30 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">Machnamh agus Paidir.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Reflection and Prayer.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:30:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_1">I have received notice from the following Senators that they propose to raise the following matters:</p>
          <p eId="para_2">Senator Micheál Carrigy - The need for the Minister for Transport to make a statement on funding for the N4 Mullingar to Rooskey road project to bring it to full planning permission stage.</p>
          <p eId="para_3">Senator Ollie Crowe - The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the delays in the opening of two new orthopaedic operating theatres at Merlin Park Hospital, Galway.</p>
          <p eId="para_4">Senator Martin Conway - The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to make a statement on the changes to the Burren programme for farmers which may result in a potential loss of income and decrease in incentives for conservation measures. </p>
          <p eId="para_5">Senator Paul Gavan - The need for the Tánaiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment to make a statement on the recommendations of the Labour Court regarding redundancy terms for employees of Rehab Enterprises.</p>
          <p eId="para_6">Senator Malcolm Byrne - The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs to make a statement on Ireland's policy on engagement with China.</p>
          <p eId="para_7">Senator Erin McGreehan - The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Marine to provide an update on the actions taken by his Department since the publication of the wool feasibility study and an update on the establishment of the Irish Wool Council.</p>
          <p eId="para_8">Senator Garret Ahearn - The need for the Minister for Education to make a statement on the provision of funding for Cólaiste Dún Iascaigh, Cahir, County Tipperary, for the construction of extra accommodation.</p>
          <p eId="para_9">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin - The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to make a statement on the use of the Brexit adjustment reserve fund to support the horse breeding sector.</p>
          <p eId="para_10">Senator Robbie Gallagher - The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to initiate a review of the current terms and conditions of the retained fire service to ensure staffing levels are maintained.</p>
          <p eId="para_11">Senator Lynn Boylan - The need for the Minister for Rural and Community Development to make a statement on the capacity issues at local authority dog pounds and the contingencies in place to deal with a lack of shelter space.</p>
          <p eId="para_12">Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators Micheál Carrigy, Ollie Crowe, Martin Conway and Paul Gavan and they will be taken now. I regret that I had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Boylan on the grounds that it is a repeat of a matter raised on 26 October 2022. The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:35:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
          <heading>Road Projects<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:35:00+00:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_2">
            <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:35:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_13">It is my great pleasure to welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, to the House. I invite Senator Carrigy to elucidate the matter he has raised.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_3">
            <from>Senator Micheál Carrigy<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:35:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_14">I welcome the Minister of State and thank her for taking this Commencement matter. Unfortunately, the Minister for Transport was unavailable, which is disappointing. I wish to highlight the matter of the extension of the N4 from Mullingar through Longford and on to Rooskey and County Leitrim. The Government launched the renewed National Development Plan 2021-2030 in October last year. This was the largest national development ever plan delivered in the history of the State, valued at €165 billion, with a particular focus on priority solutions to strengthen housing, climate ambitions, transport, healthcare, jobs growth in every region and economic renewal for the decades ahead. The Tánaiste stated that we needed to anticipate what the Ireland of 2040 will look like, what our jobs will be like and how we will travel and live.</p>
            <p eId="para_15"> With a rapidly rising population, Ireland needs to invest in big infrastructure. If we were to look at a map of Ireland and at the road infrastructure, in the context of the national development plan referring to balanced regional development, we would be struck by the fact that the only region not being serviced by a proper motorway or dual carriageway is the north west. I am referring to counties Westmeath, Longford, Leitrim, Roscommon, Mayo, Donegal and Sligo. This entire region is not being serviced. While a significant amount, in the hundreds of millions of euro, is being spent on the works on the N5 from Castlebar running towards County Longford and on the N4 from Sligo eastwards, there is a missing link. The project went to preferred route stage in 2008. It was later removed from the national development plan. It was included once more when Project 2040 was announced by the previous Government. In December 2021, Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, announced it had no money available to continue with the project. We understand that a significant number of families, including farmers and landowners, have been greatly affected by these delays and not knowing what will happen to their family land, homes, etc.</p>
            <p eId="para_16"> We received a reprieve earlier this year when a great deal of pressure came from public representatives. Money was found by TII to continue the project and identify an emerging preferred route. Based on the work that has been done, I expect this will be announced in quarter 1 of 2023. My understanding, though, is that this is where it ends. An increasing number of lives are being lost and serious injuries suffered on the current routes. Since 2008, we have had more than 20 fatalities, 34 serious injuries and 218 minor incidents.</p>
            <p eId="para_17"> The N4 transportation solution would support the Government's goal of balanced regional development by improving accessibility to the midlands and north west. A strategic corridor would be provided for reliable and safer road-based public transport in rural Ireland. It would also strengthen the tourism sector by linking Ireland's Ancient East with the Hidden Heartlands and the Wild Atlantic Way. It will not be possible to provide opportunities for active travel in towns and villages through the provision of dedicated walkways if we have continued congestion in a certain number of towns. On the way down west we can see this in Ballinalack, Rathowen and Newtownforbes. These may be small towns but they account for major bottlenecks.</p>
            <p eId="para_18">However, the reality is that we have a large number of landowners and householders who are in a state of suspension since 2006. That is 16 years and counting. They are unable to make decisions on what they can do with their property.</p>
            <p eId="para_19"> This particular project is a crucial one for the island of Ireland in the context of the Government's ambition for the national development plan. It is likely to take between ten and 15 years to develop if sufficient multi-annual funding is made available, and if coupled with the usual judicial reviews which seem to be commonplace in this country. This needs to be prioritised.</p>
            <p eId="para_20"> I mentioned earlier that if one looks at a map of Ireland, there is an entire region that is not serviced with that. I understand money has to be part of projects from 2026 onwards. However, my understanding is that if this project does not continue to planning permission stage, we will have to go back to the start again, which we already have. We will have wasted multi-millions of euro. Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, needs to make sure that funding is in place for this project and that the national roads office based in Mullingar will continue the process over the next couple of years and bring it down. The route and all the issues would be ironed out and compulsory purchase orders and planning permission put in place. If it has to be delayed due to funding for a year or two, so be it. However, we have a route and our planning permission. The landowners know where they stand and we do not have to go back to the start again. However, balanced regional development in the north west, and all those counties I have named, are entitled to the same opportunities as the rest of the country.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Health" eId="spk_4">
            <from>Minister of State at the Department of Health (Deputy Anne Rabbitte)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:40:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_21">I thank the Senator for raising this matter, which I am taking on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Ryan. The Minister for Transport has responsibility for overall policy and Exchequer funding for the national roads programme. Once funding arrangements have been put in place with Transport Infrastructure Ireland under the Roads Acts 1993-2015, and in line with the national development plan, NDP, the planning, design, improvement and upgrading of individual national roads is a matter for TII, in conjunction with the local authorities concerned. TII ultimately delivers the national roads programme in line with Project Ireland 2040, the national planning framework and the NDP.</p>
            <p eId="para_22"> In the new NDP, launched in October 2021, approximately €5.1 billion is earmarked for new national road projects until 2030. The funding will enable improved regional accessibility across the country, as well as compact growth, which are key national strategic outcomes. The funding will provide for the development of numerous national road projects, including the completion of projects which are already at construction stage and those close to it, as well as the development of a number of others. Exchequer funding under the new NDP will also facilitate continued projection and renewal of our national roads infrastructure, including motorways, in line with Government policy. </p>
            <p eId="para_23"> The N4 Dublin to Sligo road is a national primary route which connects to the N5 to Westport and the N6 to Galway and Athlone. It is a critical strategic corridor from Dublin to the north-west region and Border counties. The project is 54 km in length and connects Mullingar in Westmeath to Roosky in Longford. The existing route is a single carriageway road that passes through, or close to, several settlements, including Ballinalack, Rathowen, Edgeworthstown, Longford and Newtownforbes. Through the provision of reliable transport infrastructure, the project would improve connectivity between Dublin, Sligo and the north west. The proposed project would enhance regional accessibility and improve road safety along the route. This project is intended to support the economic performance of the local and wider region through the provision of improved transport infrastructure, while minimising the environmental impact.</p>
            <p eId="para_24"> The project has reached the route options selection phase. Initially, TII was unable to provide an allocation for this project in 2022, given the level of funding available for major road projects. However, funds became available early in the year and it was possible to provide a reallocation in order to progress the options selection phase. As a result of this, the options selection process was reactivated. Studies were subsequently undertaken in relation to various environmental disciplines and additional appraisal was carried out to take account of the national investment framework for transport in Ireland, NIFTI, which was published in December 2021. It is expected that an emerging preferred route corridor will be published in quarter 1, 2023, and that this route options selection process will be completed in quarter 2, 2023.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_5">
            <from>Senator Micheál Carrigy<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:45:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_25">I thank the Minister of State. She said that it is a critical strategic corridor for the north west and critical to our national development plan. However, the reply states that funding is in place to complete the route option selection process by quarter 2. Therefore, it will be stalled. I ask the Minister of State to tell the Minister that this needs to be prioritised. TII needs to make the funding available for that office, based in Mullingar, to continue its work on the N4 and bring it to a further stage, to a planning permission stage, and to compulsory purchase orders. It is not a significant amount of money. The vast majority of the funding is in the construction stage. We need to bring it to that stage. I am not hearing good soundings and I do not think that is acceptable. It is a vital piece of infrastructure for the entire midlands and north west and it needs to be prioritised. It needs to be brought to a planning permission stage, so if it is stalled for whatever reason, including a lack of funding, at least we will not have to go back to the start and start spending tens of millions of euro again, which we have already done. It needs to be done and needs to be prioritised. TII, in its funding for 2023, needs to set aside money to the National Roads Office in Mullingar to continue that process over the next 18 to 24 months.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_6" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Health">
            <from>Deputy Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:45:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_26">I thank the Senator. I will bring back to the Minister, Deputy Ryan, exactly what the Senator said. To be fair to the Minister, Deputy Ryan, he really acknowledges what the Senator said, that it is critical. It has so many other nodes feeding into it. It is single lane carriageway. There is also a health and safety risk there. We are half way through a process and it needs to be completed and left to a particular standard. I will bring that back to the Minister, Deputy Ryan.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_5">
          <heading>Hospital Facilities<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:45:00+00:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#NedOSullivan" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_7">
            <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Ned O'Sullivan)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:45:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_27">Ba mhaith liom fáilte is fiche a chuir roimh rang a cúig don Gaelscoil Mainistir Fhear Maí. You are very welcome here. Tá súil agam go mbainfidh sibh taitneamh as an turas go dtí Teach Laighean. I hope you enjoy your time here with us. Maybe you might learn something and maybe you might be able to teach us something as well.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#OllieCrowe" eId="spk_8">
            <from>Senator Ollie Crowe<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:45:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_28">I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, to the House. She is a fellow Galwegian who is often in the House and does great work for us. The issue I want to raise is the two new orthopaedic operating theatres in Merlin Park Hospital in Galway, which the Minister of State will be aware cost €10.5 million. They opened last June and were due to be fully operational shortly thereafter. It is now five years since surgical appointments had to be cancelled when a leaky roof at Merlin Park led to the closure of the old facilities there. In that time span, naturally, a considerable back log has built up. Unfortunately, there are now long waiting lists. It was expected that the new operating theatres in Galway would have a significant impact on reducing waiting times for orthopaedic surgery in the west. Unfortunately, five months after these theatres opened, they remain non-operational.</p>
            <p eId="para_29"> As the Minister of State will be aware, I have been contacted by constituents and by patients who have been waiting years for operations. Despite these theatres having opened, they do not seem to be any closer than they were prior to this multi-million euro investment in facilities. There are very harrowing stories. One woman needed a hip replacement over five years ago. She had an MRI scan carried out over three years ago and met with a specialist 18 months ago. She met with the surgeon due to do the operation in the first quarter of this year. The situation is so bad that she has to sleep in a recliner downstairs in her house and she has gone from having an active life with various activities to being someone who rarely gets out of the house.</p>
            <p eId="para_30">I spoke to her again last week. She is struggling to go to mass and that is unacceptable. The reality is that she has no timeframe and as the Minister of State will be aware, the uncertainty is difficult. That is just one example among thousands of people in Galway West, Galway East and across the west of Ireland. The reality is that the longer this situation drags on, the more people are being added to the waiting list and the bigger the backlog is becoming. We must address this with urgency. These theatres must become fully operational. This is something that will make an enormous difference to the quality of life of people in Galway city and beyond, as the Minister of State is aware. Whatever measures are required to be implemented to resolve this need to be taken immediately.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_9" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Health">
            <from>Deputy Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:50:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_31">I am taking this matter on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, and I will adhere to the script that has been provided to me. Before I do so, it is important for me to say as a fellow Galwegian that it is five years since the roof started to leak in Merlin Park University Hospital. It is five years since they went out of operation, since they were not fit for purpose and since we had all these meetings. A lot of good work has been done since then. It is fantastic to see that two theatres have been completed, and to see the energy and drive that went into the projects in recent times to bring them to the stage they are at. I will read the Minister's script but I will then finish with my own abiding words.</p>
            <p eId="para_32"> I thank Senator Crowe for raising the matter of the two new orthopaedic theatres in Merlin Park University Hospital Galway. I welcome the opportunity to update the House on this important service. As part of the Saolta University Health Care Group, Merlin Park University Hospital is a level 2 hospital delivering non-complex elective medical surgical services including orthopaedic and minor surgeries and renal services. It has two designated rehabilitation units along with a number of specialist outpatient clinics. As the Senator will be aware, work on the two orthopaedic surgical wards to serve Merlin Park hospital was completed in 2022. The purpose of these theatres is to increase elective surgical capacity at the site. Construction was completed earlier this year and commissioning was finalised on 10 June 2022. Currently one of the theatres is fully operational. Staff were originally put in place to allow for the provision of 16 theatre sessions per week, but currently ten theatre sessions are provided per week. These sessions are provided in one theatre running five days a week.</p>
            <p eId="para_33"> From 7 November 2022, theatre sessions were planned to increase to 12 per week. However, staff vacancies mean that ten theatre sessions are provided per week at present. Management at the hospital, in conjunction with the Saolta University Health Care Group, has approval for additional positions and is currently recruiting staff for these posts. For reasons of patient safety, which we can all agree is of paramount importance, it is not possible to open a second theatre until adequate staffing levels are in place. Currently the hospital requires an additional anaesthetist to allow the number of sessions to increase<b>. </b>International recruitment for nursing is also being progressed in order to increase staff resources and facilitate the operation of the second theatre. Management in Merlin Park hospital currently plans for the number of sessions to return to 16 a week from 9 January 2023. I do not know how they can do that. They will not have the staff.</p>
            <p eId="para_34"> Recruitment of key staff for health posts remains challenging. However, as a result of the commitment to sufficiently staff the health service in the long term, 2020-21 saw record numbers of recruitment into the workforce. In 2020 we saw the largest increase in the health sector workforce since the foundation of the HSE and in 2021 we saw the second largest increase.</p>
            <p eId="para_35"> There is no doubt that the Covid-19 pandemic had an impact on waiting lists and to be honest it is great to see the theatres now commissioned. We need to ask the HSE and the Saolta University Health Care Group to prioritise the recruitment of the anaesthetist and the staff to ensure elective surgeries can take place. The Senator outlined the need clearly when he spoke about the woman who is waiting for five years. </p>
            <p eId="para_36">I have a book full of women who are waiting five years for services. It is incumbent on the HSE to prioritise. One way of driving down waiting lists is to recruit into the elective space. That is why we talk about needing an elective hospital. Surely how we clearly demonstrate we can deliver an elective hospital is to recruit enough staff to work in two theatres.</p>
            <p eId="para_37"> I thank the Senator.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#OllieCrowe" eId="spk_10">
            <from>Senator Ollie Crowe<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:55:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_38">I sincerely thank the Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, for her response. What I like about her is that she gave her own response. Outside the written script, she calls it as she sees it. That is what the House heard.</p>
            <p eId="para_39"> It is incomprehensible that on 9 January 2023 we will increase services by 60%. That will not happen. It is frustrating - I hear that in the Minister of State's voice as well - that we receive bland answers in this House. If I could explain in my own language to the people in Galway city, who elected me as a councillor for 11 years and gave me the opportunity and help to serve in this House, what the process is, what is causing the delay and how I cannot help this woman who is almost 80 years of age, it would make it much easier for me and perhaps the woman would understand it. However, being told that we will increase theatre sessions by 60% when we know it will not happen is fundamentally flawed. I hear the Minister of State's frustration. She is familiar with the situation in east Galway and concurs with my concerns.</p>
            <p eId="para_40"> I thank the Minister of State for her frankness and openness. It is a priority for this Government. It must happen. I am confident the Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, will raise the matter at the appropriate level of Government.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_11" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Health">
            <from>Deputy Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:55:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_41">I thank Senator Crowe for giving me the opportunity to articulate to the people of Galway that this is a priority for the Government. The Government brought the theatres to the point of being commissioned. They have been approved by HIQA and so on at this stage. This is not news. We knew that two theatres would come on board. I wonder why our recruitment process did not start sooner and why we did not have the staff in place. We all knew we would need an anaesthetist. Having said that, the Minister, Deputy Donnelly, has provided the required funding to staff the two theatres. It is incumbent now on the HSE and the Saolta group to prioritise the recruitment of the staff. Whether in Ireland or abroad, they must prioritise it because we can no longer continue to explain to the people of Galway and the surrounding areas that we have two theatres but they cannot be looked after in the west.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#MartinConway" eId="spk_12">
            <from>Senator Martin Conway<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:55:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_42">Well said.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_6">
          <heading>Environmental Schemes<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:55:00+00:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#NedOSullivan" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_13">
            <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Ned O'Sullivan)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:55:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_43">I welcome the Minister, Deputy McConalogue, to the House.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#MartinConway" eId="spk_14">
            <from>Senator Martin Conway<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T14:55:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_44">I thank the Minister for coming to the House. I know he is under pressure due to commitments in Dáil Éireann. It shows his commitment to try to come up with a solution to this issue which is a big issue in north Clare. Everyone in farming circles, certainly in County Clare, and in environmental circles understands the huge benefits that the Burren life programme has had in the past ten years and more. We have seen a situation where there has been a contribution in environmental benefits in the region of €40 million and that is in addition to the money that has been put into the pockets of the almost 1,000 farmers who have participated in the programme. We have a situation where the farmers promoted the environment. They promoted green policies, the protection of the flora, fauna and landscape and became ambassadors for the area.</p>
            <p eId="para_45">For the tourists and bus tours with people from all over the world, the ambassadors or tour guides and the people who tell the story are the farmers who have worked and lived there and derived an income and at the same time maintained what is beautiful and unique about the Burren.</p>
            <p eId="para_46"> Everybody wants to see a situation where what has been done in the Burren in terms of the environmental commitments is expanded because clearly this is where we want to go. We want to be in a situation where farmers can earn a living from their farms and at the same time protect the environment; they are not mutually exclusive. They do go hand in hand.</p>
            <p eId="para_47"> In many ways, what Brendan Dunford and his team have proven in the Burren through their work over the years is that they go hand in glove, if it is done properly. Their concern with ACRES in the first instance is that the key decisions were made before meaningful negotiations took place. There are a number of issues. The first is the incentivisation, where the more people did on their farms to protect and promote the environment and to farm in an environmentally-friendly way, the more they earned from it. That is a key principle. That is the incentive.</p>
            <p eId="para_48"> Second, there was a situation where organic farmers are being particularly penalised. They can derive benefits and incentives after level 8, whereas for ordinary farmers it is after level 4. That is a concern. In addition, with the CAP and caps in place, where is the incentive for farmers to environmentally develop and promote agri-incentives across all of their farms; they will just do it where they are getting paid. Human nature being what it is, why would they?</p>
            <p eId="para_49"> Another key point is the local involvement of experts who will do a bespoke review of a farm and advise a farmer in a very direct way to get results. It is like boots on the ground. There is no real provision for that in the scheme. That knowledge benefits and is gleaned and gained by the people on the ground engaging with the farmers, coming up with bespoke approaches. That has in the past been fed into the system and has proven to be of great benefit.</p>
            <p eId="para_50"> This project was nominated by previous Governments for European awards and won. It has been seen as a positive, natural way of marrying environmental concerns and profitable farming where people can live and work on and derive an income from their farm and protect it for future generations and - as I said already - be the ambassadors and the people who promote the landscape millions of people come to our country to see.</p>
            <p eId="para_51"> I hope that the Minister will get his officials to re-engage and look at the key pillars that the Burren project is concerned about and sit around a table and come up with a solution. These are very reasonable people who want to engage in a positive way because they understand that the Minister is trying to do his best to expand the environmental targets through farming. What has been achieved in the Burren could easily regress if this is not dealt with.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#CharlieMcConalogue" as="#Minister_for_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine" eId="spk_15">
            <from>Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine (Deputy Charlie McConalogue)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:00:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_52">I am sure Senator O'Sullivan will join with me in welcoming the Fermoy students here today and their teacher. I hope the students enjoy their day in the Seanad and the Dáil.</p>
            <p eId="para_53"> I thank Senator Conway for raising this important issue. I have been engaging with Senator Dooley, Oireachtas colleagues and Deputies Crowe and Carey, along with Senator Conway, who have been raising this important issue. We have been discussing, addressing and considering the issues over the last few weeks. I had committed to coming back about a potential meeting with some of the farmers in the Burren project this week. I will be engaging my colleagues this week regarding meeting some of the farmers concerned to discuss the issues which they have raised today.</p>
            <p eId="para_54">The Burren programme, which will conclude at the end of this year, has been a successful agri-environment climate measure that encompasses results-based habitat management and complementary non-productive capital investment works. The new national agri-environment scheme under the CAP strategic plan 2023–2027, the agri-climate rural environment scheme, ACRES, builds on the learnings and experience of the Burren programme and the Department's successful European innovation partnerships, EIPs. ACRES is a €1.5 billion scheme with two approaches. The first is the co-operation project, CP, which applies in eight mapped zones that are areas of high nature value; hold significant carbon stores; and are home to some of the most pristine waters in the country. The second, ACRES general, is for all other farmers who do not fall within co-operation project zones. </p>
            <p eId="para_55"> One of the eight CP zones is the Burren, which is expected to see some 1,300 farmers approved to join the scheme, more than four times the number participating in the Burren programme.</p>
            <p eId="para_56"> It was always the intention to scale up the positive aspects and actions from the EIPs or locally-led schemes, such as the Burren programme, and to mainstream them into large-scale national agri-environment schemes. This will provide a much larger environmental benefit and enable a greater number of farmers to contribute to environmental public good such as biodiversity and water quality. I am pleased to see the outgoing Burren programme team successfully tender and win the right to be the new co-operation project lead under the ACRES scheme, ensuring the transition I mentioned.</p>
            <p eId="para_57"> Further building on the work of the Burren programme, the ACRES co-operation programme has been designed to deliver significant long-term environmental improvement through the participation of a substantial number of farmers on the most appropriate land. As colleagues will be aware, there are currently some 300 farmers participating in the Burren programme. It is proposed that an additional 1,000 farmers in the Burren zone would participate in ACRES CP, an increase of more than 300%. This increase will benefit a huge number of farm families and the environment in the area, as well as being an economic catalyst and support for the area. With more farm families benefiting, there will be greater opportunities all round. Increasing farmer participation numbers beyond the limited numbers at present in the Burren programme requires a balance to be struck to ensure that as attractive a payment rate as possible is offered while ensuring that as many farmers as possible can join, with the resulting increase in the amount of land providing environmental benefit. As colleagues can see, this will represent a very significant upscaling of participation in the Burren region and will provide a larger cohort of farmers with access to the specialist skills of the CP team. Not only will there be a major increase in the number of farmers participating, there will be a substantial increase in environmental monitoring and assessment in that region.</p>
            <p eId="para_58"> Under the current Burren programme, a total area of just over 11,000 ha of species-rich grazed habitat is scored under the result-based assessment. By comparison, under ACRES CP, it is estimated that almost 40,000 ha will be scored in the Burren zone. I recognise there are concerns in the Burren area, with several current participants farming extensive areas of high-quality lands. We are working closely with the Burren CP team to develop a bonus structure to incentivise those farmers.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#MartinConway" eId="spk_16">
            <from>Senator Martin Conway<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:05:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_59">I thank the Minister for his response. There is no doubt that the ACRES scheme has huge benefits; nobody is disputing that. We are talking about a few hundred farmers who will be negatively impacted. In the overall scale of the financial commitment under ACRES, it is very small. There is a sense of morale, support, recognition and appreciation but ultimately, in these very difficult times, it is down to pounds, shillings and pence. I welcome the Minister's commitment to engaging with the farmers and their representatives this week. I am delighted he has confirmed that he will do that. I believe this can be successfully resolved through negotiation. I welcome the commitment from the Minister that he is going to directly engage with the farmers and the Burren Life programme this week to achieve a resolution. I thank him for coming in and addressing this directly.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#CharlieMcConalogue" eId="spk_17" as="#Minister_for_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine">
            <from>Deputy Charlie McConalogue<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:10:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_60">I thank Senator Conway. It is about striking the balance between increasing the number of participants and ensuring good payments for those who participate. The EIP schemes of which there were a number of over the past few years and of which there will be more in years ahead was very much about piloting new initiatives so that we could learn from them and then incorporate them on a much wider scale. That is what is happening now as regards the Burren EIP and it is also what is happening in case of the hen harrier EIP, for example. They are being brought to a much wider audience, the environmental benefit is being increased and they are being learned from. I know the transition brings challenges and my officials have been engaging with the Burren programme around that transition. I have had many discussions with Senator Dooley, Deputy Crowe, Deputy Carey and Senator Conway on this matter and I had committed that I would come back this week as regards a meeting. I will engage with them to facilitate a meeting for some time next week.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_7">
          <heading>Redundancy Payments<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:10:00+00:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#NedOSullivan" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_18">
            <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Ned O'Sullivan)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:10:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_61">I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy English.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_19">
            <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:10:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_62">I thank the Minister of State. In February last year workers at Rehab Enterprises in Limerick were informed by senior management that the company would make 36 workers redundant following a 30-day consultation period. Most of these workers were earning the minimum wage of €10.20 at the time, of which 75% was subsidised under the long-standing disability wage subsidy scheme. The workers concerned who subsequently lost their jobs as of 2 April 2021 are among the most vulnerable people in society. They include people with visual impairments, learning difficulties and Down's syndrome. They lost their jobs in the middle of a pandemic and some of these workers had given decades of service.</p>
            <p eId="para_63"> Regrettably, the Rehab Group management made a unilateral decision to depart from a well-established redundancy agreement with SIPTU. This decision was totally unacceptable and an affront to the principles of equality and fairness. Instead of offering four weeks' per year of service plus statutory uncapped as per the long-standing agreement with SIPTU, Rehab offered just two weeks' plus statutory capped at one year's salary.</p>
            <p eId="para_64"> To put that into simple terms, as one worker who had been with the company for 30 years said, he should be entitled to €60,000 redundancy but he was offered just over €21,000. The 49-year-old added:</p>
            <p class="indent_1" eId="para_65">It is an insult. We feel cheated like we are dirt. It is a slap in the face. We are astounded at what Rehab had the cheek to offer us. My heart has been torn out of me. It is so hard to take.</p>
            <p eId="para_66">His family said they fear that he and his colleagues would struggle to find other suitable work and that their lives would be negatively impacted by the lack of routine.</p>
            <p eId="para_67"> SIPTU has since been engaged in a long-running battle with Rehab, via the Labour Court, to secure the redundancy package the workers are entitled to under that long-standing agreement with the company. In April last year, the Labour Court recommended that a financial review be carried out to assess the ability of Rehab Enterprises, and the parent company Rehab Group, to honour the existing redundancy agreement. That review established that the Rehab Group, which owns 100% of Rehab Enterprises, has as custom and practice contributed to previous redundancy packages and has the ability and means to pay the full redundancy terms in the collective agreement with SIPTU.</p>
            <p eId="para_68"> In an updated commentary this year, the same analyst referenced a significant improvement in the finances of the Rehab Group with a net current asset year-on-year improvement of <i>circa</i> €3 million, and cash or cash equivalents of €20.8 million, which is an improvement from €11.8 million the previous year. The same analyst also noted a significant sum was paid to a senior executive in 2020. While the sum was not fully disclosed by the company, the analyst also noted that packages of €813,000 were paid to senior management in 2018 and 2019. So it would appear that there is one rule for senior management when it comes to redundancy packages and quite a different rule for front-line workers.</p>
            <p eId="para_69">Last week SIPTU won a significant victory at the Labour Court after the third and final round of hearings. Quoting the financial analyst's clear determination that the Rehab Group has options to explore to meet this claim the court determined that it could find no clear and undisputed basis not to uphold the existing collective agreement and consequently recommended that it be respected.</p>
            <p eId="para_70"> The Rehab Group receives significant funding each year from the State. It has been demonstrated that it can afford to honour the redundancy agreement for these workers who are among the most vulnerable in the state. It has literally tens of millions of euro in available funds and has no problem splashing the cash for senior management. Will the Minister of State give a clear call on the management of Rehab to honour the existing redundancy agreement, as endorsed by the Labour Court?</p>
            <p eId="para_71"> It is interesting reading SIPTU’s submission to the Labour Court as it details the procrastination and delay that has been a constant feature of the Rehab Group’s response to this issue. It has dragged it out and these workers have been waiting for more than 18 months for the redundancy they should have received, so a clear message from the Minister of State would be very welcome and I look forward to his response.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#DamienEnglishFG" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Enterprise,_Trade_and_Employment" eId="spk_20">
            <from>Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment (Deputy Damien English)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:15:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_72">I thank Senator Gavan for raising this matter. We discussed this issue in 2021 as well. I again extend my sympathies to the workers in Rehab Enterprises who have been made redundant. I fully appreciate how difficult the situation is for those involved and for their families.</p>
            <p eId="para_73"> By law it is an employer's responsibility to pay statutory redundancy to eligible workers. In situations where an employer is genuinely unable to pay statutory redundancy entitlements due to financial difficulties or insolvency, the State provides a safety net and may make the statutory redundancy payments on the employer's behalf from the Social Insurance Fund. However, negotiations on enhanced redundancy packages over and above the statutory entitlement, which is the case we are discussing here, are entirely a voluntary matter between employers and workers. The State has no role in this matter.</p>
            <p eId="para_74"> For its part, in the event of a dispute, the State provides the industrial relations dispute settlement mechanisms, that is, the Workplace Relations Commission, WRC, and the Labour Court, to support parties in their efforts to resolve their differences. I must emphasise that Ireland's system of industrial relations is essentially voluntary in nature and that responsibility for the resolution of industrial disputes between employers and workers rests in the first instance with the employer, the workers and their representatives. Recommendations arising from the WRC and the Labour Court are not legally binding. While I strongly encourage parties to engage in the industrial relations process in a constructive manner, the State cannot compel a party to comply with a Labour Court recommendation.</p>
            <p eId="para_75"> It is my understanding that negotiations are still in play and I would hope that the parties could reach a solution. I know there were offers and counter-offers and I hope a solution can be found. I am not in a position to tell the company. We have the industrial relations infrastructure and it has to do its job. I afraid that beyond the statutory redundancy, we do not have a role when it come to a commercial case.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_21">
            <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:15:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_76">I thank the Minister of State for his reply, which I am a little disappointed with. I understand the State cannot compel an employer to make a payment above statutory but, as a Minister of State, I would have thought he would have a responsibility to support the industrial relations machinery of the State. The Labour Court is the highest court in that regard. It has made a clear call on Rehab to pay these very vulnerable workers the moneys they are due under the collective agreement. We both know there has been a whole host of issues over collective agreements in recent years. I would think it is quite within the Minister of State's powers to ask Rehab Group to respect the recommendation of the Labour Court. This is the Labour Court, which is the industrial relations court of the State. When one reads the history of this dispute, and in particular the incredibly cynical attitude of the Rehab Group in relation to dragging out this process - as I said, these workers have been waiting 18 months and longer for the redundancy entitlements agreed collectively - it should not be allowed to walk away from that collective agreement. The Labour Court has said it should not walk away from this agreement. I ask the Minister of State to endorse the Labour Court's recommendation in this instance and give badly needed support to those vulnerable workers and their families.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#DamienEnglishFG" eId="spk_22" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Enterprise,_Trade_and_Employment">
            <from>Deputy Damien English<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:15:00+00:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_77">The Government agrees the workers involved are a vulnerable cohort of the workforce. That is why every effort was made to work with them as far as possible from our end of it, in terms of the industrial relations agencies.</p>
            <p eId="para_78">Apart from that, as the Deputy is aware, the Department of Social Protection and the Intreo office had intensive engagement at local level with all the workers to assist them on their journey and ensure they got all their statutory entitlements. They also gave the workers advice and direction regarding other potential jobs and worked with local employers to achieve that.</p>
            <p eId="para_79"> I understand that at the time of the announced job losses, on a local level, dedicated staff in the Department of Social Protection were assigned to work directly with the employees affected by redundancy because we recognised the position they were in and to ensure they received their proper entitlements and other services available to them. Officials also held group information sessions and one-to-one phone meetings with the workers involved. They advised the workers on supports for jobseekers with disabilities, including the EmployAbility service, which is an employment and recruitment service, to help people with a disability secure and maintain employment. Many of these people had built up skills working in this business for a long number of years. This action ensured employees were able to access their entitlements swiftly and in a manner that hopefully did not cause further distress.</p>
            <p eId="para_80"> I understand that the workers and their families are disappointed with the terms of the proposed redundancy package but, as Minister of State, I am precluded from intervening in this matter. This is because the Workplace Relations Commission, WRC, and the Labour Court are independent offices of our Department. As I mentioned, recommendations arising from the WRC and Labour Court are not legally binding. I agree with the Deputy that everybody should try to respect the arms of the State and the industrial relations machinery put in place, which works extremely well and effectively in most cases.</p>
            <p eId="para_81"> The Government cannot compel a party to comply with a recommendation. The ultimate responsibility for compliance with any Labour Court recommendation rests with the employer, the workers and their representatives. I understand there is still room for negotiations and some offers were made as well. I hope common sense will prevail and a solution will be found involving all three groups in this decision.</p>
          </speech>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <i> Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionraí ag 3.22 p.m. agus cuireadh tús leis arís ag 3.30 p.m.</i>
          </summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <i> Sitting suspended at 3.22 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m. </i>
          </summary>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="orderofBusiness" eId="dbsect_8">
        <heading>An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:30:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#ReginaDoherty" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Senator Regina Doherty<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">I wish to put on the record of the House my feelings at the passing of Vicky Phelan. Over the past number of years we have seen a woman of courage and determination. Her strength and dignity through her illness and her fight for the rest of the women of this country has been something to behold. Through her tireless efforts she has ensured that the women of Ireland who were involved in the 221 scandal but indeed every woman going forward will be protected. I wish to extend our deepest sympathies to her husband, her children and her family.</p>
          <p eId="para_83"> The Order of Business is Nos. 1, 2 and 3 on the Order Paper. No. 1, motion regarding the Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund Regulation 2022 referral to committee, to be taken on conclusion of the Order of Business without debate; No. 2, statements on forestry, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and to conclude at 6.15 p.m., if not previously concluded, with the time allocated to the opening remarks of the Minister not to exceed ten minutes, group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes, all other Senators not to exceed five minutes and their time can be shared, and the Minister to be given no less than eight minutes to reply to the debate; and No. 3, Judicial Appointments Commission Bill 2022 - Committee Stage, resumed, to be taken at 6.30 p.m. and to adjourn at 8.30 p.m. if not previously been concluded.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">On behalf of the Fianna Fáil group I also wish to be associated with the acknowledgement of the great life of Vicky Phelan. I am cognisant of the fact that it was Vicky's wish that on her death she would not receive tributes from politicians but that we would instead take actions. I hope that we can continue to take the necessary actions to right the wrongs that caused Vicky to come to notoriety initially. Other than her own campaign for and with the cervical cancer issue she was an inspiration to people in general, irrespective of what their personal problems may have been at any time. We saw somebody who was terminally ill dealing with a cause in such a manner always with a smile on her face and always so respectful. She could have had so much grievance with the system yet tried to reach solutions amicably. Her rejection of the confidentiality clause in her court case was a statement that she could come out and advocate for what she felt so strongly about. I wish to take this opportunity on behalf of the Fianna Fáil group to extend our sincerest and deepest sympathies to her husband, Jim, and her children Amelia and Darragh.</p>
          <p eId="para_85"> I would also like to include sympathies to the family of Dr. Éamon Phoenix, the historian who has passed away.</p>
          <p eId="para_86">He was a very valued member of the Government's expert advisory group on the centenary commemorations and played a major role in that. We are also sorry to hear today of his passing. I again extend our sympathies to his wife, Alice, and daughter, Mary-Alice.</p>
          <p eId="para_87"> I am a member of the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine, which recently produced what I call, and I know self-praise is no praise, a very good report on the issues impacting on dog welfare in Ireland. This report has been previously mentioned in the House by Senator Boylan, who is also a member of that committee. Indeed, I am the first to admit that Senator Boylan championed much of the work we did for that report. I plead with the Leader to try, if she can, to get that report onto the agenda for discussion in this House as soon as possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_25">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:35:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">I congratulate Senators Daly and Boylan on the committee's report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinConway" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Senator Martin Conway<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:35:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">I, too, echo the words of our Leader and Senator Daly on the passing of Vicky Phelan. As Fine Gael spokesperson on health, and having the privilege to be a member of the Joint Committee on Health, I am even more cognisant of the impact that Vicky's campaigning, and the terrible tragedy that happened to her, had in terms of positive change. That positive change certainly has a long way to go. The best way we can pay tribute to Vicky Phelan's legacy is to get the disclosures legislation over the line. I welcome the fact that the Taoiseach has announced that this will happen before the Christmas recess. That is very welcome, even though it is late. It should have happened before now but the fact it will now happen is the best way we can pay tribute to Vicky Phelan.</p>
          <p eId="para_90"> We could also pay tribute to her through the setting up of an Oireachtas committee on dying with dignity, an issue that she campaigned for and had a great interest in. We have looked at setting up citizens' assemblies on matters such as biodiversity. While these matters are important, health and dying with dignity are far more important. I cannot for the life of me understand why we would delay setting up a committee to engage in this issue, hear all sides and come back with recommendations on what should happen. These are the tangible ways that the Oireachtas, the Seanad and society can pay tribute to Vicky's legacy and the tremendous work she did. I take great solace from the fact that she spent much of her quiet time in County Clare, on Doughmore beach in Doonbeg, and that she got great peace from Doughmore and west Clare. West Clare will always have a connection with Vicky Phelan because she spent so much quality time there.</p>
          <p eId="para_91"> I propose that we observe a minute's silence for Vicky Phelan, perhaps tomorrow, and that we notify all Members of it in order that as many people as possible who would like to be here for it would be in a position to attend. Perhaps a good time to do it would be at the conclusion of the Order of Business tomorrow.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RonanMullen" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Senator Rónán Mullen<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:35:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">Déanaim comhbhrón le muintir Vicky Phelan freisin agus le muintir an Dr. Éamon Phoenix – go ndéana Dia trócaire orthu. Rinne an Dr. Phoenix sár-obair mar a luaite.</p>
          <p eId="para_93"> In response to what my friend, Senator Conway, had to say, I will point out that everybody dies with dignity. The question always is whether people's dignity is respected. Nothing disrespects people's dignity like making them feel as if they are a burden in life. That is one of the single biggest fears people have about euthanasia, assisted suicide, assisted dying or whatever people care to call it. We should move very carefully in that area and not just rush to have another citizens' assembly discussion that seems, whenever these happen, to be designed to bring about a preordained or pre-desired change.</p>
          <p eId="para_94"> The matter I want to raise today is a similar human dignity issue. It was reported last Saturday that the Government plans to make telemedicine abortion, so-called, or telephone-based appointments for abortion, a permanent feature of Ireland's abortion policy. I think this is misguided and that it will have negative consequences. The HSE confirmed in October last year that no report or analysis into the operation of so-called telemedicine or remote consultations had been carried out in Ireland since the policy was introduced in early 2020 in the context of Covid. We were told by the Secretary General of the Department of Health in March 2021 that telemedicine would lapse when the pandemic was over. In 2018, the then Minister for Health, Deputy Simon Harris, said in the context of the abortion legislation that there would absolutely not be abortions by telemedicine in this country. Yet here we are, despite the fact we know from England that over 10,000 women there had to receive hospital treatment following the use of at-home medical abortion pills between April 2020 and September 2021. England has also seen a dramatic spike in the number of ambulance call-outs dealing with the adverse effects of the self-administration of abortion pills.</p>
          <p eId="para_95"> We also have the safeguarding issues associated with the removal of the need for in-person consultations. When we substitute that for a telephone call, we remove the privacy afforded by a GP’s surgery. There is no way for a doctor to verify that a woman requesting an abortion is actually alone and that she is not being pressured by a partner or third party. We had an alarming report in October describing how an underage girl in this country was locked in a room and forced to ingest abortion pills. This is highly disturbing. It would be terrible to think that the Minister and the Department of Health would be enablers of such abuse by their overly lax attitude to telephone appointments for abortion.</p>
          <p eId="para_96"> There needs to be a serious discussion about this. I call on the Minister for Health not to recklessly make telemedicine abortion permanent but to immediately instigate a comprehensive investigation into the operation and impact of such abortion appointments in Ireland to date. The very least we could do in this House is to have a serious discussion about something so potentially far-reaching.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PippaHackett" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Senator Pippa Hackett<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">I too extend the sympathies of my Green Party colleagues to the friends and family of Vicky Phelan. She was a once-in-a-generation advocate for change. May she rest in peace.</p>
          <p eId="para_98"> Here in Ireland, the vast majority of homes and buildings are made from concrete and steel. We have yet to embrace timber construction in the way many of our near neighbours and European partners have. This is a huge opportunity for us. Last week at COP27, Climate TRACE, a global not-for-profit organisation, released a huge bank of data listing the top known sources of greenhouse gas emitters across the globe. The data for Ireland made for some eye-watering headlines and reinforce the urgent need for us to rethink every aspect of our lives in order to reduce emissions. On the top-ten list of known emitters in Ireland, there was one road network, one oil refinery, one gas field, three airports and - something a lot of people may not be aware of - four cement plants. Many of us do not normally think of cement when we think of greenhouse gas emissions. We tend to think more of cars and planes, energy production and agriculture, but there is an entire industry in the built environment that we do not tend to think about in the same way as other industries in the climate change battle.</p>
          <p eId="para_99"> If we are serious about climate action, we need to look at our built environment and remove whatever barriers exist to using timber in construction where and when we can. Timber may never be a total replacement for cement but, in many cases, it can be the sustainable alternative. Some simple statistics speak for themselves. Producing 1 tonne of cement releases 0.6 of a tonne of CO2 and producing 1 tonne of steel releases 1.85 tonnes of CO2, whereas producing 1 tonne of wood actually absorbs about 0.75 tonnes of CO2.</p>
          <p eId="para_100"> Using timber in construction is not unproven territory. There are many countries leading the change across Europe, not only in building homes and commercial buildings with timber, but in using it to construct ground-breaking tall buildings, once thought impossible to build with anything but steel and cement. In Scotland, for example, home building is now dominated by timber construction, with about 80% of homes being timber frame.</p>
          <p eId="para_101">In Ireland, the figure is closer to 20%. As the House knows, we are big producers of timber and at present export over 70% of it. We have seen some innovative use of timber in Ireland, most notably in Avondale in County Wicklow, where Coillte has used Irish timber almost exclusively in the construction of its pavilion and treetop walk. </p>
          <p eId="para_102"> We now need to move beyond innovation and into the mainstream. It can and must be done, and we must now all work together to rapidly increase the use of timber across the construction sector. Through the education of our architects, engineers and planners, the skills of our construction workers, planning laws and our own attitude in government, we must encourage and assist those who want to build with timber to do so by offering assistance across all levels of the building process. We have to do more work with the general public. We must convince them that timber homes are as warm, if not more so, and as solid and safe as those constructed with cement. We have to do all we can in the coming months and years to reduce the emissions profile of our built environment. Timber can help us do just that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:45:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">Like others, I want to begin by expressing sympathy on behalf of our party on the passing of Vicky. Even though we knew she was very ill, it was still shocking to hear that she had passed away. Vicky Phelan was a graduate of UL and had particularly close links to Limerick. She was a past staff member of the university and of course was awarded an honorary doctorate in 2018 in recognition of her courage and incredible leadership on all the issues she faced. I agree with Senator Paul Daly. Rather than words, the best tribute we can pay is the actions she wanted to see regarding all of the issues she raised. May she rest in peace.</p>
          <p eId="para_104"> I met a group of security workers at a SIPTU meeting at the weekend. We have 16,000 security workers throughout the State. I could not begin to describe the level of anger expressed by workers who continue to wait for a pay rise. An employment regulation order, ERO, due to come into being at the end of August was challenged by just three employers. An injunction was raised. These workers are now on €11.65 per hour. They are front-line workers who kept many of our factories and hospitals open during the darkest days of Covid, yet they are only earning €11.65 an hour. A new ERO would have lifted their pay to €12.50 initially and then up to €12.90 in February. Quite frankly, that is not enough, but it would have been of some significance. </p>
          <p eId="para_105"> The difficulties I have, which the workers asked me to express here today, is that while we understand an injunction was raised we also know the Minister has it within his remit to challenge the injunction. It is a matter of more than regret that three months later no such challenge has taken place. It looks as if the Minister is content to let the challenge meander. It is Groundhog Day for the workers because they have been in this situation before. It may well go on for the best part of another year. </p>
          <p eId="para_106"> Frankly, it is simply not good enough for the Minister to allow the workers to twist in the wind. They are low-paid workers and work in an industry that has seen significant cutbacks over the past number of years, often with consequences for themselves. The ERO would also ensure the right to sick pay, payment while injured on the job and some improvements to the basic rate pay, yet once again the workers have been left behind. They were very clear to me that they will go on strike if some action is not undertaken. The consequences of that for our hospitals, key factories and other sectors across the State will be massive. </p>
          <p eId="para_107"> I cannot understand the lack of action by the Minister of State, Deputy English, in regard to this issue. He can and should challenge the injunction. He should work collectively to defend the ERO system. We have seen a new, and very welcome, ERO for childcare workers. Where is the Government when it comes to defending this ERO and standing up for our security workers? I am at a loss as to why this has not happened. I ask for an urgent debate and the support of the Leader on this matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RebeccaMoynihan" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Senator Rebecca Moynihan<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:45:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">I thank the Leader for outlining the Order of Business, which we will support today. As others in the House have done, I want to start by paying tribute to Vicky Phelan.</p>
          <p eId="para_109">My former party leader, Deputy Alan Kelly, worked very closely with Vicky on the CervicalCheck tribunal. Because of her refusal to sign a non-disclosure agreement, she took a stand and shone a light on behalf of other women. It was not enough for her to be vindicated herself; she wanted other women to have that vindication and to be informed where their slides had been misread or they had been misdiagnosed. The women of Ireland and, in particular, screening programmes in Ireland will owe her a debt of gratitude for decades to come because of her simple refusal to stay silent or to sign that non-disclosure agreement.</p>
          <p eId="para_110"> This morning I attended the launch of the Raise the Roof campaign, which is calling for a national rally on housing on 26 November in Dublin. Among the issues highlighted at the press conference today were access to social housing and people in the insecure private rented sector. I have raised this many times on the floor of the House. There are two key things the Government could be doing that it has not done. Since 2011 we have not reviewed the income thresholds for social housing, with the exception of five counties that secured special dispensations in September. Since 2017 we have not reviewed HAP, even though we have allowed the discretionary limits for the scheme to change. That means that low-paid private renters in private high-rent housing such as Tathony House, in my constituency, where we are looking at 35 people being evicted from those apartments, are not able to access basic social housing or, more crucially, HAP for assistance in the private rented sector. I am calling today for a debate on the income limits for social housing. There is a report that has been sitting on the Minister's desk for over a year at this stage. We keep being told that something is being brought forward, but then we saw that tinkering around the edges with the five counties in September. We need a full and frank debate because people's wages have grown, yet the rate at which they can go on the social housing list and then access other supports has not grown or changed since 2011, during which time rents in the private rented sector have at least doubled.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JerryButtimer" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Senator Jerry Buttimer<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">I also wish to be associated with the expressions of sympathy to the late Vicky Phelan and I thank her for her advocacy and campaigning zeal. I think we all agree that we should not lament her passing without ensuring that the action she fought for is fully implemented. May she rest in peace, and to her family we express our deepest sympathies. Senator Conway's suggestion of a motion of sympathy tomorrow is a good one and I hope the Leader will acquiesce to it.</p>
          <p eId="para_112"> I ask that the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Fleming, come to the House to discuss the issue of insurance and, in particular, insurance costs. While I welcome the fact that motor insurance premiums fell by 17% between 2017 and 2021, there are still issues for consumers that need to be addressed, notwithstanding the reforms initiated by the former Minister of State, Michael D'Arcy, which are now being continued, thankfully, by the Minister of State, Deputy Fleming. It is clear that reform in the insurance industry is working and it is very important we continue that work. That is to the benefit of the insurance customer, the consumer. I would like that debate to be expanded to include home insurance premiums, in respect of which there are all sorts of clauses whereby customers of longevity get penalised. All those issues should be addressed in the debate on the issue of insurance, both motor insurance and home insurance. It is important we have a real debate, to include also business and the cost of insurance for businesses in a very challenging environment for our small and medium-sized enterprises. Again, I welcome the reform happening in the insurance industry. I ask that we have a debate in the House on it. It is a matter of huge concern to consumers, and I hope that debate can be held prior to Christmas, if possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MalcolmByrne" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Senator Malcolm Byrne<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">I, too, join in the expressions of sympathy to the late Vicky Phelan.</p>
          <p eId="para_114"> I raise today the issue of fire services and retained fire services.</p>
          <p eId="para_115">As the Leader is aware, outside the main cities we rely very much on fire services operated by local authorities. As a result of the model that is currently in place, fire services across the country are experiencing many difficulties in recruitment and retention. The fire staff are paid a retainer, but, for that, they are expected to remain close to the fire station and could be called on at any time. That presents a difficulty if they are trying to keep down other employment at the same time as operating on a retainer. It is becoming increasingly difficult for the fire services. The model worked well when it was originally designed in the 1930s and 1940s but in modern society, where we travel significant distances, it is not a model that works. As the Leader is aware, there is a major Government programme of capital investment in fire stations across the country but it is not good enough that we have state-of-the-art fire stations without necessarily having the crews to staff them. Although negotiations have been going on between the unions, the Local Government Management Agency and the Department, a more comprehensive overview of how fire services operate in the modern age is needed. It is critical that we have well staffed and trained fire officers. Those who currently provide that service across the country do a wonderful service in all our communities but they are they are finding it difficult to get new staff to come on board, and then to retain them. This is happening not just in my home county of Wexford but across the country. They love what they do and are very committed to it. Part of it relates to pay and conditions but another part relates to flexibility and having enough numbers in all fire stations to be able to do the work. I ask for statements on the future of the fire service and an update from the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FintanWarfield" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Senator Fintan Warfield<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:55:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">A selfless and inspiring campaigner, Vicky Phelan truly was the very best of us. Her tireless work in speaking truth to power has improved lives and saved lives. We will be forever grateful for her contribution to Irish society. As we honour Vicky Phelan today, I am reminded of her words two years ago after the death of her fellow cervical cancer sufferer, Ruth Morrissey. She said:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_117">I don't want your accolades or your broken promises. I want action. I want change. I want accountability.</p>
          <p eId="para_118"> This morning I attended the launch of the findings of a survey by BeLonG To. The survey is the largest ever of lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender young people in this State. It is stark and somewhat upsetting. It highlights the significant difficulties that face LGBTQ young people in schools. It also highlights the incredible support that many teachers are to those young people. However, we know life in school can be difficult, even without the external factors of homophobia, biphobia and transphobia. A shocking 76% of LGBT youth feel unsafe in school. A majority of LGBT youth have heard homophobic remarks, both from students and from school staff, which is troubling in its own right. I ask that when the Minister of Education is invited to the Seanad for statements on education, she be informed the Seanad will be raising this issue with her.</p>
          <p eId="para_119"> In the short time I have left, I call on the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment to get moving on the programme for Government commitment in respect of the roadmap for digital creative industries. Obviously, that concerns games, augmented reality and graphic design domestic companies. SMEs and micro SMEs are just as important, particularly with the whole tech situation in the news. When will we see action on that roadmap?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCummins" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Senator John Cummins<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T15:55:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">I join with colleagues in conveying my deepest sympathy to the family of the late Vicky Phelan.</p>
          <p eId="para_121"> I refer to the expansion of the Croí Cónaithe towns scheme which has been announced by the Government in recent hours.</p>
          <p eId="para_122">It is very welcome news that this excellent scheme, which focuses on rural one-off properties and properties in our city centres, is to be expanded. The scheme provides a grant of €30,000 to renovate a property which has been vacant for two years. A top-up grant of €20,000 is available where structural work to the property is required. Importantly, it can also be combined with the Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland, SEAI, better energy support scheme which provides grant aid of nearly €30,000. All in all, grant support of nearly €80,000 is in place to do up a vacant and derelict property anywhere in Ireland. That will be very much welcomed by young people, in particular, who are looking to get their foot on the ladder. We have all seen what can be achieved in TV programmes such as the "The Great House Revival" and "Cheap Irish Homes". That is often where the best value is to be achieved on the current market. Thus, the expansion of this scheme is very much welcomed. It is one of many schemes, including the repair and release, buy and renew, living city and Croí Cónaithe schemes, which seek to bring vacant and derelict properties back into productive use for housing. There is no longer an excuse for any property to lie idle in this country. The Government has put all of the schemes in place to encourage the owners of these properties to take them on or to offload them and give others the opportunity. Where that does not occur, local authorities need to be far more proactive in using their compulsory purchase order, CPO, powers to take them on under the buy and renew scheme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RobbieGallagher" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Senator Robbie Gallagher<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">Firefighters from Monaghan, the Leas-Chathaoirleach's county of Cavan and elsewhere throughout the country will make their way to Leinster House today to call for reform of the fire service model and to try to rescue this essential service. Firefighters will tell you that the current model, which dates back to the early 1950s, is not fit for purpose in the modern world in which we find ourselves. They will also tell you that people are applying to join the fire service but, unfortunately, when they get in there for a while and realise the restraints under which it operates, they leave. We first have a recruitment issue and second have a retention issue. Something needs to be done to address that and to modernise the model in such a way as to attract new people to join and, more importantly, to be in a financial position and an employment situation to be able to stay there once they do. We need a wide-scale debate on fire service personnel, including on how we attract people into the profession. That may include incentivising employers or increasing the retention payment, but something needs to be done. Firefighters are coming to the capital city today to look for help. These are the very people to whom we turn when we are in an emergency. It is time we listened. I would welcome a debate with the Minister, arranged by the Leader, in order to come up with a model and suggestions which might alleviate the current situation in which we find ourselves because communities depend on our firefighters.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LynnBoylan" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Senator Lynn Boylan<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">I too offer my condolences to Vicky Phelan's family. The State is mourning her loss but mná na hÉireann are really feeling her loss today.</p>
          <p eId="para_125"> I thank Senator Paul Daly for calling for a debate on the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine report on dog welfare issues. I echo the call. A debate on those issues is very urgent. I will raise the annual crisis we face with regard to dog shelters at Christmas. We tell people not to give dogs as Christmas presents and to adopt rather than to shop but it seems that Christmas is very much coming early this year, because we are only in November and the dog shelters are already in crisis. </p>
          <p eId="para_126">In the past two weeks, 11 dog pounds have shut down or announced that they are full. On Monday, five shelters shut down in a single day. I am afraid to say that in classic fashion, the Government did not heed the warning signs. Three weeks ago, I raised this issue with the Minister for Rural and Community Development, who is responsible for pounds. She was not available and instead of sending a junior Minister from her Department, she sent the Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Deputy Browne. I mean no disrespect to him but he does not know the subject so he duly read out the statement of which he had a tenuous grasp. The opening line of that statement said that the Department of Rural and Community Affairs has policy responsibility for dog control while the local authorities are responsible for all operational activities. The Department passed the buck to the local authorities but when I requested this week that the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage come in to address the question of whether the local authorities have the resources for the dog pounds, I was told that it is not a matter for that Department but rather that it is a matter for the Department of Rural and Community Affairs. They are passing the buck between them and in the mean time, dogs are dying, pounds are crumbling and the shelters are saying they cannot take the dogs from the pounds so we are seeing dogs being abandoned and thrown into rivers. In one case a dog was left in a cage at a canal in Dublin. We need a debate on the capacity of pounds to deal with the number of dogs being surrendered or abandoned and puppy farming. This is why the debate on the report is so essential.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AislingDolan" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Senator Aisling Dolan<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:05:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">I pass on my sympathies and deep condolences on the very sad news of the loss of Vicky Phelan.</p>
          <p eId="para_128"> Last week, we saw the mid-term elections in the US and a groundswell of support for candidates who stood up for the democratic and electoral process. They stood up for women's choice. One of those candidates has ancestral links with my home town of Ballinasloe - Béal Átha na Sluaighe. I congratulate Governor Maura Healey from the Democratic Party. She is the first woman to hold the position of governor in Massachusetts and one of the first openly gay candidates to run for and be elected to office. Governor Healey is changing the <i>status quo</i>. She is a woman who drives change. She has been the state's attorney general since 2014. She brought forward so many lawsuits against the previous administration challenging the Muslim travel ban, protecting immigrant rights and challenging the rolling back of environmental regulations.</p>
          <p eId="para_129"> Maura Tracy Healey grew in New Hampshire. She is a former professional basketball player turned civil rights lawyer. Her grandmother, Katherine Tracey, who was born in 1897, which is 125 years ago, to Michael Tracey and Mary Hogarty, was a native of Ballinasloe. Governor Healey's paternal grandparents hail from County Kerry and Macroom in County Cork. This election was unique in that it showed the highest number of young people in two or three decades vote and vote for rights for women as well. The new governor said afterwards, "to every little girl out there, we want you to know - there's no ceiling you can't break." From a Senator from Ballinasloe to a governor of the state of Massachusetts whose grandmother came from Ballinasloe, I ask the Leader of the House to invite Governor Healey to visit Ireland and address Seanad Éireann.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_38">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:05:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">There must be something in the air in Ballinasloe.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AidanDavitt" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Senator Aidan Davitt<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:05:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">Like everyone in the House today, I extend my condolences to the family and friends of Vicky Phelan. It is a very tough time, particularly for her young family.</p>
          <p eId="para_132"> Senator Buttimer spoke about the report of the Minister of State, Deputy Fleming, on insurance. I worked on that committee for a while. Much time and work went into that report and it would be a good idea to invite the Minister of State to come to the House to discuss it. It would be very worthwhile. As has been stated in the media, insurance premiums have come down.</p>
          <p eId="para_133">Motor insurance premiums came down by 17%, on average, between 2017 and early 2022, so over the past four or five years. There have also been reductions in other areas. Some of the key findings are well worth discussing in this House and there are some other issues we could thrash out. The costs are down mainly due to a mix of legislation, the strengthening of the Personal Injuries Assessment Board, PIAB, and the promotion of its board, which made it a strong option to engage with. Insurance companies, their practices and how they dealt with different claims have also fed into the decrease. I support Senator Buttimer's comments. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnMcGahon" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Senator John McGahon<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">I call for a debate on cross-Border tourism. The reason I do so is the work done by the Social Democratic and Labour Party, SDLP, in the Newry, Mourne and Down regions. In particular, my good friend Mr. Killian Feehan, who I met last week, outlined the work the SDLP is doing in advocating and promoting the inclusion of counties Armagh and Down in Ireland's Ancient East. A unanimous motion was passed by all political parties, including the Democratic Unionist Party, DUP, two weeks ago at Newry, Mourne and Down District Council. All parties and politicians at local and council level are in agreement and would love to see Armagh and Down added to Ireland's Ancient East.</p>
          <p eId="para_135"> This issue is very important for a number of reasons. First, it would considerably enhance the tourism opportunities on both sides of the Border. What often happens with tourism in certain instances is that you get to the edge of Dundalk or the County Louth border and tourism drops off a cliff. There is an excellent tourism initiative and seafood trail called "Sea Louth" and we should be trying to expand that across Carlingford Lough into County Down. In the same way, we should include counties Armagh and Down in Ireland's Ancient East.</p>
          <p eId="para_136"> It is a important to always include both sides of the Border. The world does not end at the Border when it comes to tourism. We see major increases in tourism through greenways and blueways. Having two counties from the North included in Ireland's Ancient East would be a really productive and positive step. That is why I would like to have a debate on this.</p>
          <p eId="para_137"> I am aware there are discussions with Tourism Ireland and Tourism Northern Ireland on the issue. That there is local buy-in from all political parties is really positive. There is certainly political buy-in from political parties on this side of the Border. I would appreciate a debate on the wider aspects of cross-Border tourism and how we can continue to foster economic prosperity on both sides of the Border. This is about bringing economic prosperity to both sides of the region, in particular to the Dundalk, north Louth, south Armagh and County Down region. I would appreciate a debate about that at some stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShaneCassells" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Senator Shane Cassells<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">It is "winner alright, winner alright" today, with the publication or approval of the publication of the gambling regulation Bill by the Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Deputy Browne. It is among the most significant Bills to be brought before these Houses in respect of this industry. The impact of gambling on so many people, families and individuals, has inflicted pain over the decades, the last decade in particular given the nature of social media, which allows people to be targeted individually and exploits their weaknesses. In that respect, the provisions in the Bill in this digital age to address the particular proliferation of gambling advertisements on social media and prohibit such advertising by default are a very welcome addition. It will also prohibit the use of credit cards as a form of payment and the offering of inducements and promotions. All the various aspects of this Bill are hugely advanced.</p>
          <p eId="para_139"> The chief executive of Extern Problem Gambling, formerly Problem Gambling Ireland, Mr. Barry Grant, described the Bill as hugely significant. The Cathaoirleach, Senator Wall and I have met Mr. Grant several times. He said this was the first time in over a decade that we have eventually got something over the line in this sphere.</p>
          <p eId="para_140">The holding company of Paddy Power, Flutter Entertainment, which operates in the UK and Ireland, welcomed the Bill. It said the industry has not always got it right. I am sure a public relations company was formulating the words of that statement this morning, but it is right. I hope that when the Bill makes it to the Houses, we do not see amendments from parliamentarians that were written elsewhere, rather than in these Houses, to try to water down the Bill. Well done to the Minister of State, Deputy Browne, on making sure this Bill has got to where it needed to be.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_42">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:15:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">I thank Senator Cassells for acknowledging my involvement with him on that question. The Leader knows I have raised it often from the floor. I concur with all the Senator's remarks. It would not be in order for me to more while in the Chair.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GarretAhearn" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Senator Garret Ahearn<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:15:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">I welcome the announcement by the Minister, Deputy Charlie McConalogue, of the €15.5 million that is being given in advance payments for the sheep welfare scheme. In Tipperary, 374 farmers will receive a total of just under €500,000. It is a substantial amount and I know they are grateful for it. Would it be possible to have a debate with the Minister on lamb prices? They are much lower than they are in France and other European countries. It is a real challenge. People who are not too familiar with farming would think it is going quite well. Some sectors are, including dairy, tillage and one or two others. It is important that we keep our sheep farmers. They play a vital role in important areas of rural Ireland. I ask for a debate with the Minister about his views on the viability of that sector.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Senator Erin McGreehan<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:15:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">I express my deepest condolences to the family, friends and loved ones of Vicky Phelan. She fought hard to live and she fought for others to live. I hope she is at rest. My thoughts are with her family and loved ones. I thank her for her work on behalf of all the women of Ireland.</p>
          <p eId="para_144"> It seems almost futile to go onto my next point after speaking about Vicky Phelan but I want to express concern about health and safety on the Dublin-Belfast train line. At off-peak times recently, there have not been enough rail carriages on the line, which is the busiest in the country. They are completely unsafe. People are squashed on to these trains. They are crushed. There are warnings at Dundalk that there is standing room only. It is really face-to-face room only. In the era of Covid, never mind any other health and safety issues, if people have a disability or any sort of illness, it is completely unsafe. We are coming up to a busy period of off-peak travel as people travel for shopping, to see family and for many other reasons. Iarnród Éireann and Northern Ireland Railways are aware of the problem. They are just not doing anything about it. We need an urgent resolution to this matter.</p>
          <p eId="para_145"> I support my colleague, Senator Ahearn, on having a debate on sheep. I have spoken often about sheep in this House. I was born and reared on a sheep farm. Sheep farming is part of the fabric of our rural community. Sheep farmers are getting older and sheep farming is an incredibly laborious job. We need to make sure we not only protect all sectors but that we place an emphasis on sheep farming because it has been the poor cousin for a long time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimDooley" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Senator Timmy Dooley<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:15:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">Leaders from around the world met last week and again this week in Sharm el-Sheikh to try to move the world towards having greater respect for the environment by targeting the reduction in carbon emissions. While much of the talk is about policies, targets, limits and restrictions, it is up to us in these Houses to put more time into the actions that need to take place.</p>
          <p eId="para_147">It is fine to have the policies, targets and ambition. It requires concrete action. If anything has come out of the various intergovernmental reports it is recognising laws that are passed. However, the emissions continue.</p>
          <p eId="para_148"> Perhaps we should have a debate in this House on the practical measures that we as a society could implement and begin that dialogue and debate about practical measures rather than just looking at the targets. I am taken to some extent by matters I have read about what has been done in France for some time. They put solar panels over every carpark. It seems an easy win, a no-brainer. Here we are talking about planning permission for rolling out solar farms and that is good. Many communities do not want wind farms anymore. I get that. We need to expedite the offshore potential but that is seven or eight years away. Every public carpark can with a stroke of a pen without any necessity for further planning have solar panels installed. It seems an easy win if there is a directive that solar panels are put over them and that it is a requirement before any future carparks are allowed to be built to put solar panels over them. They can act to some extent as protection from the rain which we have seen plenty of in recent weeks. I make that suggestion as an aside. I would like some time here for a discussion because many Senators meet many people and hear a great many ideas. Perhaps we could have a debate about practical measures that could be brought forward to assist in the decarbonisation of our economy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_46">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">I thank Senator Dooley. For this country that is a novel proposal and one that should be taken seriously. The Leader will now respond.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReginaDoherty" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Senator Regina Doherty<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">I thank Senator Dooley. We proposed on a number of occasions that we have a rolling debate on climate change here last year and probably even more recently. It is an incredibly important topic for us to talk about but every conversation and topic we have every week is urgent and important and it seems to consistently be put back until we have an emergency. However the Senator is right, it is time for us to have a practical debate on measures that we all know could advance our reducing emissions. The Taoiseach’s speech at COP27 this week was poignant. We are all aware that our emissions are still going up, not down. They are not going in the right direction. Sometimes I think we need to get out of our own way and do the things we know would make a difference.</p>
          <p eId="para_151"> Senator McGreehan spoke about the health and safety or lack thereof on the Dublin to Belfast train. She is seeking answers from Iarnród Éireann. Senator Ahearn called for a debate on the sheep welfare scheme and particularly lamb prices. The sheep welfare scheme was announced this morning by the Minister, Deputy McConalogue. It provides €15.5 million to pay towards the welfare of sheep throughout the country which is welcome.</p>
          <p eId="para_152"> Senator Cassells mentioned that finally the Gambling Regulation Bill has been published. A number of Members of this House, including Senator O'Reilly, who has literally raised it with me week in and week out since I became Leader a couple of years ago, have engaged with this Bill. I commend Deputy James Browne. It would be remiss of me not to commend Deputy Stanton who for years in that Department laid the groundwork for what is a tremendous Bill. I look forward to us all debating it in the next couple of weeks and getting it passed so that we will see the restrictions on the industry that we have all called for over the years so as to try to lessen some of its damaging aspects. </p>
          <p eId="para_153"> Senator McGahon called for a debate on cross-Border tourism, particularly since the all-party motion at Mourne Newry Council in recent weeks. We will try to arrange that debate. Senator Davitt, along with Senator Buttimer, has sought a debate on the insurance report that was published recently by the Minister of State, Deputy Fleming. That would be a worthwhile debate. We will organise that as soon as we can.</p>
          <p eId="para_154"> Senator Dolan spoke about governor-elect, Maura Healey. I googled her earlier and funnily enough she is exactly the same age as I am. There is only one week between us but by Jove she has some legacy and career to date for a woman so young. It would be a lovely thing to recognise her connections with Ireland and her granny and grandad who were from Kerry and Ballinasloe. I can certainly write to her and ask her to consider visiting us here and with the permission of the Leas-Chathaoirleach and the Cathaoirleach to address the Seanad if she was to come. The connection between Massachusetts, particularly Boston, and Ireland are renowned. That would be lovely.</p>
          <p eId="para_155">Senators Boylan and Daly asked for a debate on the dog welfare report. I have already asked for it; I am just waiting for a date. We spoke about the greyhound industry, about which a debate is coming, but it is not the same thing. The dog welfare report is such a good one - Senator Boyhan gave me a copy when it was published a couple of weeks ago - it needs to be debated on its own. I will get that date as soon as I can and will try to do so in the next couple of weeks.</p>
          <p eId="para_156"> Senators Gallagher and Malcolm Byrne both spoke about our retained fire services. Any of us who live outside Dublin are totally reliant on retained firemen and firewomen. It is incredibly difficult to be a retained firefighter and have any sort of normal job or normal life. We owe them an enormous debt. The fact that they had to come to the city today to talk about looking for reform, not just of their conditions and pay but in the way they structure their lives so they can look after the safety of our lives, is an incredible shame. We owe it to them to make sure we do them justice and have a debate as quickly as we can. I will try to arrange that as soon as I can.</p>
          <p eId="para_157"> Senator Cummins spoke about the expansion of Croí Cónaithe this morning, which is great. The fact that €80,000 per dwelling is now available to people, not just in our towns and villages but for the one-off rural houses we know are dotted all over the counties of Ireland, is very welcome.</p>
          <p eId="para_158"> Senator Warfield spoke about the transgender survey that has been published. Some of its findings are pretty stark when we consider that in 2022 such a huge percentage of our young people still feel maligned by views that have no place in Irish society. The Senator asked that the Minister come to the House to have a conversation about what we will do to alleviate that system. I will organise that as soon as I can but it will probably take place after the Christmas recess at this stage. What is very sad about the report is that we all know of schools and teachers who are tremendous advocates, and look after and are mindful of our younger people, especially when they are finding their sexuality and going through different stages of their lives. That such a high percentage of people still suffer at the hands of people's hurtful words and malignant views is very hard to take. I will organise that debate as quickly as I can.</p>
          <p eId="para_159"> Senator Buttimer looked for a debate on the finance and insurance Bill, which we will organise. Senator Moynihan spoke about the Raise the Roof campaign and looked for a debate on the review of income limits, not just on social housing applications but for the HAP. We can certainly organise that.</p>
          <p eId="para_160"> Senator Gavan spoke about security workers and the very understandable anger at the lack of action. I tried to get the information he referenced earlier but do not have it. I will get the answer today and get back to him. Whatever the excuses are, they are not good enough when we have people who are providing security to businesses, clubs and venues throughout the country but are being paid €11.65 an hour, mostly for unsociable hours. It is just not good enough. I will come back to him as soon as I can.</p>
          <p eId="para_161"> Senator Hackett spoke about embracing timber construction and the value of the absorption of CO2 by timber houses. Senator Mullen looked for a debate on telephone appointments for abortion. It is odd that we had commitments and now we have had changes without proper consultation. I will try to organise a response for the Senator as quickly as I can.</p>
          <p eId="para_162"> Senator Conway spoke about Vicky Phelan, with whom I know he had contact over the years. For all the other colleagues who expressed their deepest sympathies, we will hold a minute's silence tomorrow at the end of the Order of Business to give everybody enough time to make sure we show the dignity and respect that such a tremendous lady requires. Senator Daly spoke about a lady who always sought solutions. That is something we can all definitely concur with. She was not looking to finger-point; she just wanted to make the world a better place. Ireland, for all of us knowing her, certainly has become better. We will pay our tribute to her tomorrow following the Order of Business.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_48">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:25:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">The Leader will have the support of every one of us for that tribute.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6"> Order of Business agreed to.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_9">
        <heading>Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund Regulations 2022: Referral to Joint Committee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:25:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#ReginaDoherty" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Senator Regina Doherty<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:25:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">I move:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_165">That the proposal that Seanad Éireann approves the following Regulations in draft:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_166">Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund Regulations 2022,</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_167">copies of which were laid in draft form before Seanad Éireann on the 13th October, 2022, be referred to the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine in accordance with Standing Order 71(2)(<i>b</i>), which, not later than 23rd November, 2022, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 75, and Standing Order 77(2) shall accordingly apply.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7"> Question put and agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_8">
          <i> Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionraí ar 4.30 p.m. agus cuireadh tús leis arís ar 4.47 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
        <summary eId="sum_9">
          <i> Sitting suspended at 4.30 p.m. and resumed at 4.47 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="statement" eId="dbsect_10">
        <heading>Forestry: Statements<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:45:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#PippaHackett" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine (Senator Pippa Hackett)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:45:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">I am delighted to have the opportunity to address fellow Senators on the important topic of forestry. I thank them for the invitation. It is timely that I bring forestry matters to the House, especially in light of the current focus on climate change, with COP27 now into its second week, and the urgent need for climate action.</p>
          <p eId="para_169"> It is well recognised that planting trees is one of the most efficient methods at our disposal to reduce carbon emissions and that forests have a vital role to play in helping us to address the climate crisis and global warming. The sustainable management of forests can also increase carbon sequestration and produces renewable wood products that act as carbon stores. Forests offer multifunctional benefits. They improve the environment not only in terms of climate change mitigation but also by enhancing biodiversity and water quality. They also contribute to the rural economy and provide health-enhancing recreational spaces for the enjoyment of all.</p>
          <p eId="para_170"> In order to increase tree planting and the sustainable management of forests, however, we must incentivise farmers and other landowners to so do. After all, the planting of trees is a permanent land use change. That is why I am so pleased to have recently secured funding of more than €1.3 billion for forestry. This will fund the new forestry programme from 2023-27, as well as continued premium payments to current forest owners. This €1.3 billion package is a vote of confidence in farmers, landowners, forest owners, nurseries, sawmills, public bodies and communities and, indeed, all other stakeholders in forestry. This comprehensive package increases premiums by between 46% and 66%, depending on the forest type. I sought these levels of increase because I believe them necessary to attract the level of interest we need to see in our afforestation schemes. It is my belief that the package will help to reverse the recent trend away from tree planting. The new programme will align with our ambition to reach 8,000 ha of new planting per year.</p>
          <p eId="para_171"> We know from extensive consultation across society that people wish to see more trees, would like greater diversity in our forests and very much value access to them.</p>
          <p eId="para_172">These insights have certainly informed the development of our shared national vision and, in turn, our draft forest strategy and forestry programme. It is worth repeating our shared vision which captures our ambitions for forestry into the future. We want the right tree in the right place, for the right reasons and with the right management, to support a sustainable and thriving economy and society, and a healthy environment.</p>
          <p eId="para_173"> It is clear from the extensive public consultation we have carried out over the past year that the public wishes to see more diverse forests. The table of proposed grant rates and premiums that we have published shows a substantial increase in all broadleaf and diverse forest types. This a clear commitment by Government to encourage landowners to plant more diverse forests. In line with this thinking, Members will have seen that we proposed in the draft forestry programme to increase the minimum percentage of new broadleaf trees we wish to see planted to at least 35%. It is important to stress that this figure is simply an early indicative estimate of uptake based on past planting practices.</p>
          <p eId="para_174"> Members will note from the breakdown of the proposed grant and premium rates for the various forest types that Government has very clearly sought to incentivise the planting of native broadleafs and more diverse forest types. If farmers and landowners seek to take up these measures in greater numbers than have been estimated in the draft programme, my Department will continue to issue approvals for those forest types, provided all other conditions required for a licence to be granted are met. We have also put forward a new forests-for-water measure and we aim to encourage closer-to-nature forestry with an expanded continuous-cover forestry initiative. Furthermore, we wish to incentivise forest owners to deliver enhanced ecosystem services and to encourage reforestation that encompasses species diversity.</p>
          <p eId="para_175"> Positive farmer engagement will be critical to the success of the next forestry programme. I am very excited therefore by the potential for the new 1 ha native tree area scheme to be a viable option for large numbers of farmers to diversify their income, as well as an entry point for engaging with forestry. As Senators will recall from the time the relevant legislation passed through the House, farmers will not need to apply for a licence in order to avail of the scheme but, of course, they will have to meet the environmental safeguards that will form part of the scheme. I am confident the new scheme will bring new applicants into forestry and encourage those who already have trees to add more.</p>
          <p eId="para_176"> Also of particular interest to farmers will be the move from the standard 15-year premium to a 20-year premium. The change was sought by farming organisations and I am glad to deliver on it, as we will only achieve our ambitious forestry targets with our farmers on board. We will of course continue to support and incentivise productive forestry which is the bedrock of the forestry industry and supports rural jobs and the rural economy.</p>
          <p eId="para_177"> Earlier today, I spoke in this Chamber about the need to move to far greater levels of timber-based construction, and productive soft woods will be key to this. Clearly, there have been issues in the past with monoculture plantations which is why we are proposing to move to a position where Sitka spruce plantations will have a minimum broadleaf content of 20% on top of 15% space for nature.</p>
          <p eId="para_178"> All of these proposals are laid out in the draft forestry programme which is part of the implementation plan for the new forest strategy. Both the programme and the strategy are currently open to public consultation until 29 November. I strongly encourage all interested parties to engage with the consultation in advance of the finalisation of the strategy and programme. The new programme will very much depend on a well-functioning licensing and approvals system and we have been working hard on delivering such a system.</p>
          <p eId="para_179"> As is well known and, indeed, I have spoken to Members on this matter before, when I first took office we were faced with serious issues following a succession of EU and Irish court decisions in the complexity of the licensing environment and the requirement to meet exacting environmental standards. My Department and I have addressed these issues robustly and have taken a number of steps to resolve them. There has been considerable investment in resources with additional ecologists and forestry inspectors and additional administrative staff assigned to licensing. Furthermore, we have introduced efficiencies to the process and system which have helped streamline delivery. We remain firmly committed to continual improvement to achieve all possible gains in efficiency.</p>
          <p eId="para_180"> Important work undertaken this year was the expert independent legal and regulatory review of forestry licensing carried out by Philip Lee solicitors.</p>
          <p eId="para_181">Following extensive stakeholder engagement, its report was published in June and it reaffirmed the requirement under Irish and EU environmental law for a robust licensing system as well as making a number of recommendations in areas where further efficiencies and streamlining could be achieved within the existing system. The project board for Project Woodland has responded to these recommendations and my Department will now finalise a plan for the implementation of the report.</p>
          <p eId="para_182"> The positive impacts of the steps we have taken to tackle previous backlogs in licensing can be seen in the increase in the number of licences issued. We have issued over 4,000 licences to date this year. The pace of processing has picked up significantly. We are issuing nearly 30% more licences than applications received and this means that the backlog continues to drop with faster turnaround times for new applicants. To give Members an idea of the progress we have made, the backlog has reduced from 6,000 in August 2021, to 3,700 in January of this year and now stands at 1,606. This means that while we still have work to do, we are moving in the right direction and a great deal has been achieved.</p>
          <p eId="para_183"> I am pleased to say that this year will be a record year for roads and timber volumes licensed. A total of 266 km of forest roads have been approved, which is already the highest on record for any given year. The volume of felling licences issued year-to-date is impressive at 8.4 million cu. m. This is in the context of the COFORD forecast for harvesting this year of just over 4.5 million cu. m. In terms of afforestation, we have issued 621 licences this year and we are prioritising the further clearance of afforestation files in the coming weeks. We intend to maintain the momentum in terms of issuing forestry licences but what we really need now are more applications. How do we persuade farmers of the benefits of forestry and get them to apply? I believe this new programme offers the opportunity to promote the benefits of forestry and I would ask all those interested in forestry to advocate for more planting.</p>
          <p eId="para_184"> We have reached a major milestone in securing funding for an ambitious programme but we are not fully there yet. We are engaging with the European Commission now to secure the state aid approval for the programme. This will be an intensive process and I will be keeping stakeholders updated as it proceeds. I believe we are on the cusp of a new and exciting era for forestry in Ireland and my mission now is to bring people on this journey with us. I thank Members for listening. I look forward to hearing their views and feedback and I am happy to answer any questions they may have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T16:55:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">I also welcome the recent announcement by the Minister of State, the Minister and the Taoiseach of the €1.318 billion investment in the forestry programme and many of the concepts therein. I am a member of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine, which has deliberated on the forestry sector too many times to mention. I know our focus was mainly on the backlog in licensing. I welcome the numbers given by the Minister of State and the fact that there has been some alleviation of the problem but we are still not out of the woods, if she will pardon the pun.</p>
          <p eId="para_186"> The forestry sector has an enormous role to play in our environmental, climate and biodiversity challenges. We have not come anywhere close to harnessing the potential therein because of the aforementioned issues and problems. Hopefully, this new forestry programme will go a long way towards getting things back on track albeit that the programme is still out for public consultation and by virtue of the fact the moneys mentioned are from the Exchequer, we must still get approval from the Commission under state aid rules. </p>
          <p eId="para_187"> Hopefully, when all those bridges have been crossed, we will then be up and running in what will hopefully turn the entire sector around. I also welcome the initiative announced by the Minister of State for agri-forestry where a farmer can sow up to 1 ha without having to apply for a licence. </p>
          <p eId="para_188"> I still have some queries about the entire licensing system and process. I do not want to be negative because I welcome the proposal and I know it is a move in the right direction, particularly the increase in premium by anything from 46% to 66% and the extension of premium payment from 15 to 20 years.</p>
          <p eId="para_189">All of this is to be welcomed. If people buy into the programme, as we want them to, then the first problem we must address, and this was mentioned by the Minister of State herself, is regaining confidence in the sector. I refer specifically to the farming community. The debacle of the last several years has meant that people who have had issues with licences being caught up in the system have moved on and done something else. From observing their problems, other people have now decided it is not worth the hassle, that they will not go near forestry and that it is impossible to do so. These are facts and I am not fabricating them. They are facts we must address and turn around.</p>
          <p eId="para_190"> How we do this is going to be a major issue. The question is how this sector can be resold in its new clothes to people who may and, hopefully, will invest in it. This is going to be a major issue for the Minister of State's Department, all the associated bodies and people with vested interests. The current lack of confidence in the sector will need to be reversed. We must work on this aspect from the word "Go". As the Minister of State is aware, the joint committee published a report in which we addressed many of the issues regarding licensing problems and made several recommendations. I still advocate for these suggestions. Specifically, we recommended an initial application for an afforestation licence would also include single consent for future road building, thinning and felling. What is really adding to the backlog in processing licence applications is the need to apply for three separate licences at each juncture in the progression of a forest: to develop a road; to thin the trees; and then to fell them. I still advocate the adoption of this recommendation from our report.</p>
          <p eId="para_191"> Based on the dashboard information, as received today, I have some questions for the Minister of State. As she rightly stated, the numbers have improved and the backlog of applications has decreased. If we look, however, at the number of afforestation licences issued in the year to date, these amount to 621. In the same time, 2,894 felling licences were issued. Four times more licences have been issued for felling than for afforestation. I do not need to explain the consequences of this. If we are cutting down more trees than we are planting, then we are facing a problem. We are a long way short of meeting our 8,000 ha target. Given the average afforestation licence is for 7 ha, how many afforestation licences does the Minister of State envisage we would need to approve annually to meet this 8,000 ha target?</p>
          <p eId="para_192"> Equally, what communication has there been with the nursery sector? This is an area that again, because of what happened in the past, has not been able to predict what availability of saplings will be needed and, therefore, what number of seedlings it will need to sow every year. These nurseries have no idea what number of licences are going to be granted, so it has been nigh on impossible for them to predict what volume of saplings they will need to supply the forestry industry. Hopefully, and we all do hope this, applications for afforestation licences will take off again based on the new announcement. Are the nurseries ready and prepared to meet demand when it increases?</p>
          <p eId="para_193"> Based on other conversations we had in the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine today, I request that the Minister of State and her Department keep a close eye on, and thoroughly monitor, the proposed new EU nature restoration law. If we are to believe what we have been told, there is potential in this regard for a requirement that up to 70% of our blackbog-type, previously drained soil be restored to its original standard of 70 years ago. We are led to believe that this includes such land that is planted. If it was not planted 70 years ago, this would have an enormous effect on our overall acres of forestry. It is, therefore, extremely important that the Minister of State's Department monitor this aspect. I wish to hear her comments at the end regarding this proposal and what effect it would have on our overall forestry figures if it were to come to fruition. </p>
          <p eId="para_194"> I would also like the Minister of State to give some more detail on the newly-proposed road grants in the programme, if she has any more information on this aspect. As I said, I am aware the Minister of State's plan is still at the stage of public consultation. The t's are not crossed nor the i's dotted and I accept this. </p>
          <p eId="para_195"> Turning to a few other queries, the forestry type, FT, 11 and 12 grant rates are probably not going to be accurate in future now, based on the change to the species requirement, with the requirement for a plantation to have 20% broadleaf trees. This will mean that people involved in forestry will incur additional costs. There is no allowance for an increase in these grants contained in the programme, as far as I am aware. </p>
          <p eId="para_196"> While I welcome everything in this plan and it is all well intentioned, will large-scale institutional bodies be able to avail of the same grants? If so, it is vitally important that we monitor the progress of this programme to ensure that, albeit unintentionally, it does not enhance large-scale institutional developments further. As the Minister of State said in her statement, this plan is intended to bring more farmers into this scheme and this is what we all want.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Senator Micheál Carrigy<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">I welcome the Minister of State. I am standing in for Senator Lombard. Today's statements are based on a request submitted by the Senator several weeks ago in respect of the justifiable concerns we had concerning forestry. I refer to the absence of the figures for the new forestry programme. We were hearing talk of that information not being available until January.</p>
          <p eId="para_198"> The Government has set a target to plant 8,000 ha in 2023, and yet we only reached 2,000 ha this year. In this regard, Glennon Brothers sawmill group is a significant employer in my area. There are many concerns in this regard for the forestry sector in future. It is important, though, to note and welcome the announcement made last week. I record my thanks to the Minister of State, Senator Hackett, the Minister of State, Deputy Heydon, and the Minister, Deputy McConalogue, for getting this programme across the line, the significant funding that has been put in place and for letting the farming community know exactly where it stands in this context.</p>
          <p eId="para_199"> There are significant increases of up to 70% in the premiums and, as the Minister of State and Senator Paul Daly said, an extension from 15 to 20 years. This will now give the farming community the opportunity to decide on whether a profitable use of land is to plant forestry or to use it for tillage or alternative farming. I noticed the figures in the plan referring to a 10-acre plantation moving from €70,000 to €150,000 in premiums over the 20-year period, with a cut out after 30 years at €500,000. It works out, therefore, at roughly €21,500 annually for that 10-acre plot over the 30-year period. A significant amount of money, therefore, has been put in place.</p>
          <p eId="para_200"> As Senator Paul Daly said, however, there has been a lack of trust in this area. To be quite honest, this needs to be rebuilt. If we go back to the downturn in the economy, when people planted forestry back in 2004, 2005 and 2006, we have had a reduction in premiums since then and also seen the whole issue of ash dieback strike and the significant number of forests that were planted impacted by this disease. Many people in this situation do not feel they have been adequately looked after or compensated. Are there any plans to help farmers in this situation? </p>
          <p eId="para_201"> In the context of a Commencement matter discussion with the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, I put forward a proposal regarding Lough Ree power station. This was back when there was talk of electricity shortages. We have a power station that has been shut, as is the case in County Offaly in Shannonbridge. We accept the issue with bogland, but we have a large acreage of forestry affected by ash dieback. What do we do with it? Is it worth considering cutting this timber, bringing it to the site, chipping it and then burning it in the power plants? This would be one way of addressing the issue of ash dieback in our forests while also providing power.</p>
          <p eId="para_202"> Turning to the issue of licences, this topic is cropping up regularly. It has been discussed in this House since I was elected more than two and a half years ago and we still do not seem to have made any inroads into it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PippaHackett" eId="spk_53" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine">
          <from>Senator Pippa Hackett<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">We have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Senator Micheál Carrigy<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">They have not been sufficient. When a planning application for a house is made, a reply must be received within a set period of three months at most.</p>
          <p eId="para_205"> We still have not cleared up the issue of having three different licences in forestry. We need to create a system which allows that when a person applies for a forestry licence, thinning, roads and everything else is built into a single system. That would give people a bit more confidence and reduce the chances of people objecting to the planting of forests.</p>
          <p eId="para_206"> We are seeking to increase the percentage of housing built from timber to 80%. It is difficult to see us reaching that target, although I happen to have returned from Finland last weekend where most of the houses are built of timber and I must say they are extremely warm. It is the way to go but we have a lot of work to do to change that narrative. If we could, we could build an entire industry to build timber frame houses. However, perhaps we need to put a little more pressure on our local authorities. The State is building and funding X number of thousands of social houses per year. Should we require a minimum of those houses to be timber frame houses? We have not done that yet we are funding them.</p>
          <p eId="para_207"> We have a lot of work to do. We are aiming to move from 11% to 18% of forestry cover, whereas the EU average is 38%. The Department of Housing, Local Government and Housing, which is funding social housing, should provide that a minimum number of these be timber frame houses. That would help the industry as well.</p>
          <p eId="para_208"> I welcome the forestry plan. It gives certainty where there was none a number of weeks ago but more work needs to be done to build trust. There are many strong ambitions in it but it is up to the Government to put policies in place to meet those ambitions. We have an ambition to increase the number of timber frame houses in the country to 80% of those built, yet the Government has not done anything with regard to the houses that we fund and build.</p>
          <p eId="para_209"> I commend the Minister of State on securing such a significant amount of funding for the forestry industry.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LynnBoylan" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Senator Lynn Boylan<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">I dtús báire, ba mhaith liom fáilte a chur roimh an Aire go dtí an Teach. Tá áthas orm go bhfuil an deis agam labhairt sa díospóireacht seo.</p>
          <p eId="para_211"> There was quite a bit of media fanfare about the new forestry strategy and while I welcome its publication, it amounted to only a single page dealing with payment rates. The previous strategy amounted to almost 150 pages and it will likely be the new year before that is available.</p>
          <p eId="para_212"> The draft plan is open for consultation until the end of the month. We are all on the same page on some elements of the forestry strategy. It is important that we get it right. There is a lot riding on it. Ireland's forestry cover is very low compared with our international peers. Only 2% is native woodland and that is among the lowest in the world. We are all in agreement that many jobs in rural communities rely on forestry. It is an understatement to say that forestry is an important sector in our economy. It is vital not only for our economy and society but also in environmental terms. Many of our carbon neutrality targets are riding on us getting the forestry strategy right. It am not overstating the case when I say how important it is that we get this right and point out the role forestry must play.</p>
          <p eId="para_213"> The main show in town is first and foremost reducing the amount of greenhouse gases we release into the air. Our focus must be on reducing emissions. We must not allow ourselves to be sidetracked into thinking we can continue a business as usual approach and somehow compensation by forestry and other removals will get us out the gap. That is simply not correct.</p>
          <p eId="para_214"> We also cannot forget that the impact of forestry on emissions takes decades to be felt. For example, any changes in forestry today will have very little impact on reducing emissions by 2030. That said, emissions will continue to be released from hard to abate sectors of the economy and we will need forestry to compensate for those. It is important to note that the land use, land-use change and forestry or LULUCF sector, which is much easier to say, is currently a net source of emissions and we face a major challenge to reduce those. The Joint Committee on Environment and Climate Action heard today about some of the potential for land use in reducing emissions. </p>
          <p eId="para_215"> Biodiversity is another environmental aspect to forestry. People often conflate the biodiversity crisis and the climate crisis. They are not the same thing. They are two separate crises. Biodiversity is impacted by climate change but it can equally be impacted by climate action and it is important that we protect both and address both of those crises. For too long, forestry plantations have been a major driver of biodiversity loss, especially the mono-crop plantations of Sitka spruce. For this reason, it is particularly welcome to see the increased focus on native forestry in the document that was launched. There are higher payment rates for native forestry and a new rewilding payment. I would like to hear the Minister of State's rationale for setting it at a lower rate than the other schemes. I would also like to know why the space dedicated to rewilding is being limited to 50 ha per annum compared with the 4,645 ha of Sitka spruce monocultures.</p>
          <p eId="para_216"> The Government's publication has got it off the hook for the time being but we all accept that delays are threatening the sector's viability. There is a long history of administrative issues in the forestry sector. It is all well and good offering higher payment rates and establishment grants are welcome but there were underspends of €7 million and €8.9 million in forestry in 2021 and 2022, respectively, and more than 6,000 ha of licensed afforestation remains unplanted. Those figures indicate that the challenge in the forestry sector is one of confidence. The Government must address that issue as well.</p>
          <p eId="para_217"> There are still significant issues with applications for licences. I know the Minister of State employed additional ecologists when she came into office and that is welcome but we must do better at screening out the bad applications upstream so they do not cause delays downstream. I have figures for the soft licensing target, which show that 100 per week have been missed in 65% of weeks to date this year. The Government missed the target for 28 weeks and only met it for 15 weeks. Some 1,683 licences remain on hand for more than 120 days. Only 2,000 ha have been planted this year to date, while 2,016 ha were planted in 2021 and 2,435 ha were planted in 2020. The last time the State's afforestation rate reached 2,000 ha per year was in the middle of the Second World War.</p>
          <p eId="para_218"> Members will all remember the heated debates of 2020 as the forestry legislation made its way through these Houses. I warned then that the draconian reforms would not be adequate to address the problems in the system. As is the case in the planning system, it is not good enough to simply fast-track bad plans. We end up with a mess and do not achieve what we all say we want to achieve, namely, greater afforestation rates. We have the same issue with housing. When we try to block people's access to justice and fast-track bad plans we do not get to the root of the problem and it does not speed up the process. That is why it is so important to protect the right of the public to participate in the judicial process. Sinn Féin has a track record of seeking to amend legislation to strengthen public participation and bring greater clarity, especially with respect to those who feel existing afforestation has been detrimental to their communities. Until their concerns are addressed and the bad applications are weeded out far earlier in the process, we will continue to fall short of our targets.</p>
          <p eId="para_219"> Sinn Féin looks forward to working with the Minister of State because, as I stated, we are all in agreement that we need greater afforestation. We need it for our communities, employment and timber built houses but also to address climate change and the biodiversity crisis.</p>
          <p eId="para_220"> I apologise for leaving shortly. I have to attend another meeting but I will listen back to the Minister of State's responses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LynnRuane" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Senator Lynn Ruane<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">I welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber. It is useful to briefly reflect on the fact these statements are taking place while COP27 is ongoing in Egypt. Sustainable and nature-focused forestry is essential to both climate action and biodiversity. In that global context, I welcome that President-elect Lula of Brazil is committed to the protection of the Amazon rainforest and I also welcome the fact that the world's three biggest rainforest nations, Brazil, Indonesia and the Democratic Republic of Congo, have formally launched a climate partnership to work together on conservation.</p>
          <p eId="para_222">Countries in the global north, including Ireland, must do everything we can to support the protection of our rainforests and ensure there is an end to multinational companies actively destroying nature and biodiversity. I am not sure if the Minister of State heard the speech made by the President of Colombia at the UN. It was one of the most powerful speeches I have ever heard on the Amazon and climate. If she has not heard it, I recommend that she listen to it as it was impressive.</p>
          <p eId="para_223"> To return to Ireland, in its annual review for 2022, the Climate Change Advisory Council, CCAC, stated that Ireland is not achieving its national ambition for afforestation. We need to be clear that forestry is currently a net emitter of greenhouse gases in Ireland, not a carbon sink. This is according to the FRL 2021-2015 report from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine titled, Ireland: National Forestry Accounting Plan. The report concludes with the extremely worrying information that Ireland's forest estate transitioned from a carbon sink capturing CO2 to a source of CO2 during the 2012 to 2017 period and that there are indications of likely increases in greenhouse gas emissions from 420 gigatonnes in 2018 to 2,161 gigatonnes CO2-equivalent by 2025. </p>
          <p eId="para_224"> On the accounting and budgetary framework we use for forestry, there is a concern that carbon sequestration potential for forestry is not being accurately portrayed. We need to be honest about the fact that trees when planted take between 20 and 30 years to sequester significant amounts of carbon. If a whole area is then subsequently clear-felled, this releases a huge amount of carbon from the soil. This needs to be reflected in our accounting frameworks and from a scientific point of view, we need to ensure that forward-counting or double-counting is not part of our forestry accounting frameworks.</p>
          <p eId="para_225"> With regard to our wider forestry policy, we do not have a model in Ireland which supports biodiversity or climate action. For example, we still have one of the highest rates of plantation forestry in the EU and the highest share of forest area comprised of invasive species, particularly Sitka spruce which makes up over half of our forest estate. In investigations conducted in 2020, Noteworthy documented many of the issues with our forestry system. For example, between 2010 and 2020, only three environmental impact assessments were carried out in respect of 17,000 afforestation licence applications received by the forest service and that licences for plantations continued to be approved on, or near, peat soils and other high nature value areas.</p>
          <p eId="para_226"> On the issues of planting on peatlands, we need to wake up to the scientific evidence. Experts, including from An Taisce, have repeatedly warned that planting on peatlands has a huge impact on drainage and the water quality of our rivers. There are examples of cases where afforestation licences have been granted for planting peatlands which have direct hydrological connections to special areas of conservation, SACs, such as the River Moy SAC. Currently, the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine allows planting on peatland of a depth of less than 50 cm. Peatlands are the largest natural land-based carbon store. The area covered by near natural peatland worldwide, which is greater than 3 million square kilometres, sequesters 0.37 gigatonnes of CO2 a year and stores more carbon than all other vegetation types in the world combined. Peatlands are essential to our survival as a species and for the planet as we know it. It is dangerous when they are damaged. Emissions from drained peatlands are estimated at 1.9 gigatonnes of CO2 annually, the equivalent of 5% of global anthropogenic greenhouse gas emissions. This is a disproportionate amount considering damaged peatlands cover just 0.3% of land-mass.</p>
          <p eId="para_227"> I will ask a series of questions at this point. How does the Government plan to reverse the trend by which Ireland is becoming a net emitter on forestry? On accounting, will the Minister of State commit to no forward- or double-counting and a scientific-based approach? Will the Department pursue a policy of the right tree in the right place, as described in the CCAC's technical note on the carbon budgets, including ensuring appropriate prioritisation is given to native tree species and appropriate species diversity? Will the Department institute a policy of refusing licences on any form of peatlands, including bogs that have been degraded, given the potential for rewetting?</p>
          <p eId="para_228"> I will conclude by addressing our national history. Ireland was once covered in forests and native tree species such as birch, oak and elm. We then had periods of fast deforestation over centuries. Today, we need a forestry model that is sustainable and protects our planet. We need to move away from the current model. I urge the Minister of State to seriously reflect on the questions I have asked.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FintanWarfield" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Fintan Warfield)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_229">I welcome members of the fire service to the Chamber. They are very welcome to the Houses of the Oireachtas. We are discussing forestry and our next speaker is Senator Timmy Dooley.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimDooley" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Senator Timmy Dooley<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">I welcome the opportunity to contribute to this debate. Since my good friend Senator Malcolm Byrne has arrived with a number of fire crew members, I assure them I am not about to say anything explosive that will require their skill sets. I live in a part of County Clare that has a considerable amount of afforestation. We regularly have forest fires at certain times of the year. I pay tribute to the fire services and crews in that context because the work they do can be long, laborious and very dangerous, in addition to everything else they do. I am delighted to see members of the fire service here and I welcome them.</p>
          <p eId="para_231"> It is great to have the Minister of State, as one of our own, in the House. It is great that she sits at the Cabinet table and gets an opportunity to reflect more directly the views of this House. It was often said that Ministers paid less regard to this House than the other House and other aspects but the Minister of State, as a Senator, has a capacity to listen and share our thoughts. I welcome the work she has done to date and the significant amount of funding she and the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy McConalogue, have secured in this year's round of funding, as identified by my colleague Senator Paul Daly. As previous speakers said, there is significant work to do to regain the confidence of potential forestry owners. There have been repeated announcements over the years about the volume of land that needs to be planted to meet our timber let alone climate change needs and we have fallen short on a continuous basis. There are many reasons for it but we have to learn from that and move on.</p>
          <p eId="para_232"> As the Minister of State is aware as we have discussed it in the House, there are significant issues about licensing too. I met a number of forestry owners and people who want to get into forestry recently. They cannot get their heads around the notion that if planting commercial timber involves going through so many different aspects of licensing. As night follows day, if you put a cake in to bake, at some point you will take it out of the oven and it will be eaten. If you plant a forest on a commercial basis, it follows that it will have to be harvested and processed. I cannot understand why there cannot be a one-time approach where all the work gets done at the beginning or part of the way through. I have numerous files in my office relating to people who have been waiting for felling licences for a considerable period. When they are told it will be two or three years, they just cannot get their heads around it. That is a disincentive. Perhaps the situation is improving and I have no doubt it will improve given the ecologists the Minister of State has appointed. We have work to do now to convince others who have been turned off as a result of this.</p>
          <p eId="para_233"> I have also met foresters and I received an email from the Social, Economic, Environmental Forestry Association, SEEFA, with which the Minister of State will be familiar, in which it raised a number of questions. I will put these to the Minister of State and perhaps she will get an opportunity to address them. As average sites are 7 ha and only 50% of licences progress to planting, how many licences are required each week to achieve the 8,000 ha afforestation target? Over the past six weeks, how many ecologists were involved in processing an average of 14 licences in that period? What is the cost of ecology input alone to issue an afforestation licence? How long on average did it take the Department to process each application and are these likely to proceed?</p>
          <p eId="para_234">There are real concerns here. I know the Minister of State will not get a chance to answer all of those questions but I will pass them on to her.</p>
          <p eId="para_235"> Senator Carrigy has spoken about the concerns with regard to ash dieback. I regularly hear from farmers who do not feel that they have been appropriately compensated or that there is enough support for them. In that context, I ask the Minister of State to come back to us at another stage on the reconstitution and underplanting scheme, RUS. She might identify what the current uptake is under the existing scheme. How many hectares, out of the total number of acres applied for, were actually affected? Are health and safety risks associated with dead and rotten ash trees breaking in strong winds? I spoke to a farmer yesterday who has a row of ash trees along a boundary fence adjoining a main road. There is a concern that these trees will fall. Are they the responsibility of the farmer, given that they were not planted as part of a forestry? Should the local authorities, in recognition of ash dieback, have a programme or a scheme to remove these trees where they are along the boundaries of main roads? It would be appreciated if it could be done in conjunction with the local authorities. I thank the Minister of State.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AislingDolan" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Senator Aisling Dolan<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House for this debate. I got to hear some of her speech. I understand there are no copies of her opening statement available, which is funny given that we are talking about trees, timber and paper. If we are not going to be provided with paper copies of speeches, perhaps they could be emailed to us when the opening statement is made.</p>
          <p eId="para_237"> I have questions for the Minister of State around the industry in my local area of Roscommon and east Galway. Senator Doherty and I were fortunate to be part of a group that visited Murray Timber Group in Ballygar. It was so impressive to see the measures the company is putting in place to adapt and be ready for the industry of the future, for example in terms of automation and upskilling the existing workforce there. Ballygar is a small town on the boundary between Galway and Roscommon and this company offers employment to people in that area.</p>
          <p eId="para_238"> I would like to see a balance between the demands we have here that ensures industry is supported in rural areas. The challenge we have is that so many workers are being drawn to city centres and so much of our workforce is on the high end. People can get degrees in areas like medical technology, pharmaceuticals and manufacturing, but we also need to ensure we are supporting a workforce that is available locally. Arbor Forest Management, another group that has a company based in Ballinasloe but has its headquarters in Cork, deals with farmers around licences. I know that this was a major issue a number of years ago, and that changes have been made, but there is still an impact around ensuring we have the ecologists. Could the Minister of State comment in her closing statement on the number of ecologists who have been brought into the Department and the number of licences that have been issued in the last while around afforestation and access?</p>
          <p eId="para_239"> Ash dieback was mentioned by colleagues earlier. There is real concern around ash dieback in many garden centres I have been in recently. People in that sector are very interested in the environment, forestry and trees in general and are very knowledgeable on those topics. The ash dieback issue is across the Shannon and really has an impact on the west. I would welcome whatever comments the Minister of State has on that.</p>
          <p eId="para_240"> We have had presentations from an industry that is fearful of change in this area. I understand the elements the Minister of State is bringing forward in terms of the promotion of the broadleaf tree - she wants to ensure we have more native trees and they are broadleaf trees - and the impact that brings. We know from the oak tree that 200 types of insects are supported. However, there needs to be a balance with local industry. I am conscious of rural industry, in particular.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FionaOLoughlin" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Senator Fiona O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">I thank the Minister of State for being here to listen to our comments. I welcome the plan. It is very significant to have a proposed investment of €1.3 billion in the Irish forestry sector. As we know, it is the largest ever investment by any Irish Government in tree planting. I wish to acknowledge that it is part of the national forestry programme. It is absolutely essential in helping us to reach the objectives of the strategy, which is designed to provide an overarching framework that identifies the actions needed to implement the changes required for Ireland's forests and reflects the ambition contained in the shared national vision for trees, woods and forests in Ireland until 2050. The programme is built around the principle of the right trees in the right places for the right reasons with the right management. That is absolutely crucial to deliver a more diverse forest and to meet multiple societal, economic, social and environmental objectives.</p>
          <p eId="para_242"> In County Kildare, we have wonderful forests that people walk in for leisure. Forests such as Donadea, Killinthomas, Moore Abbey and Mullaghreelan are very sociable and environmental places where people can go and, as they say, bathe in trees. They say now that it is more therapeutic than being beside water. Obviously, that part of it is really important. In terms of planting trees for commercial and climate purposes, I had a look at the Kildare County Council development plan. In the last survey that was done, 10,396 ha of the county was in forest, which accounts for just 6.1% of the overall land of the county. Given that the average around the country is 10.5%, we are falling well behind. Of that area, 50% is in public ownership and the remainder is in private ownership. My own family has land in forestry. It is good that a majority of native species - approximately 62% - are planted in the forest. There is huge scope to support and encourage landowners to use their land in this way. It goes without saying that forestry activities should be appropriate in terms of nature and scale so they are not visually intrusive on the landscape and do not cause damage to important habitats or the ecology of the area.</p>
          <p eId="para_243"> Senator Dooley touched on the importance of building supports and trust with the landowners. It is of concern that the average number of licences issued over the past six weeks was just 14. Average sites are 7 ha and only 50% of licences progressed to planting. We need a sizeable number of licences to achieve the targets we have. I would like the Minister of State to address this. It is critical that the forestry programme matches our climate ambitions with significantly increased financial supports to encourage farmers and landowners to consider forestry as a viable land use on their land. We have a lot of work to do to ensure everybody buys into this and gets what they expect. The Minister, Deputy McConalogue, has said that unprecedented incentives will provide a valuable addition to farm income and help to meet national climate and biodiversity objectives. It is important that this funding guarantees continued payments to forest owners who have planted under the current scheme and are still in receipt of premiums, while offering new and improved financial supports to those who undertake planting and sustainable forest management under the new programme.</p>
          <p eId="para_244"> I wish the Minister of State, Senator Hackett; the Minister, Deputy McConalogue; and the Department well in terms of the roll-out and meeting the challenges that are there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PippaHackett" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine (Senator Pippa Hackett)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">I thank the Acting Chairperson and the Senators for the invitation to speak and their passionate input into their questions and statements. This issue has been discussed at length since I took office and continues to be discussed. After a little over two years, we are getting to a stage where the sector is in a much healthier position and state. We are about to embark on a new strategy for trees, woodlands and forestry in Ireland over the next decade. The vision that extends to 2050 is about what we hear all the time - the right tree in the right place for the right purpose and under the right management. That management piece is important, given many of the concerning legacy issues regarding forestry. Another word that came up was "balance". That is where I see my place in striking the right balance so that we are delivering not only for rural economies, the climate, water quality or biodiversity into the future but also for people. That amenity value shone through in Senator O'Loughlin's remarks.</p>
          <p eId="para_246"> A number of Senators, including Senators Paul Daly, Carrigy, Dooley and Dolan, touched on the lack of confidence in the sector. We have seen that over the last few years in the low levels of interest in planting trees. It is now getting to a crisis stage regarding the targets we need to hit. We have announced the new programme and we have sizeable incentives in place for forest owners. We are relying almost wholly on private landowners to plant the trees of the future. We need engagement and confidence injected back into the sector. The Government has worked hard to deliver a lucrative incentive and reward for farmers. Farmers will now be paid for up to 20 years, as opposed to 15 years. Non-farmers will stay at the 15-year payment rate. We are trying to incentivise private farmers and landowners to plant trees. The variety of options now available to farmers should also make them have a look at the new programme and scheme rates. As I alluded to, the premium rates have increased quite substantially. There is a shift towards wanting to plant more native and broadleaf trees, but that is the direction of travel. That is where the direction from the EU is going and what our citizens want. Again, it is about striking the balance with the commercial sector and the need to continue to supply softwoods into the softwood sector. I spoke earlier about the need to increase significantly the amount of timber we use in construction, whether it is in domestic homes or larger builds such as schools and multi-storey buildings. The scope is massive. We need to work hard to deliver on that over the next few years and even the next decade. I would like to see that significantly improved upon.</p>
          <p eId="para_247"> I will focus on some of the specific matters raised. Senator Daly spoke about the comparison between the afforestation licences and the areas planted versus the felling licences. A felling licence comes with an obligation to replant. It is not like the lands are no longer used for trees; they are replanted. Afforestation is the figure we look at in terms of increased land. There may be individual examples of that not happening, particularly in areas that should perhaps not have been planted in the first place. Many of those are under State ownership. In the cases of many peatlands in the west, which are more than likely under public ownership by Coillte, forests have failed because they should not have been planted in those places. There are some good developments between Coillte and the National Parks and Wildlife Service, NPWS. They will be transferring lands to manage them for biodiversity. Examples across the western seaboard include Coillte Nature delivering the wild western peatlands project and the collaborative effort by Coillte and Bord na Móna on the midlands native woodland project. There are movements away from poorly planted areas to areas that will now be managed with biodiversity.</p>
          <p eId="para_248"> The nursery sector is well aware of the situation. It is represented in my forestry policy group and in Project Woodland. I have visited nurseries. The Minister, Deputy McConalogue, recently visited a nursery. Plantation rates have increased in FT 11 and FT 12. In the case of FT 11, the annual rate has increased from €590 to €863 per hectare. In the case of FT 12, the annual rate has increased from €510 to €746 per hectare. This is quite a significant increase in funding under those schemes.</p>
          <p eId="para_249"> A number of Senators brought up the issue of the single consent. Philip Lee does not agree with the single consent. The EU does not agree with the single consent process. At the end of the day, applications for felling licences are going to be decades apart. It is going to be a decade or more before one looks for a thinning licence and another decade or so before one looks for the final felling licence. It is not as if they all have to go through three years in a row or anything like that. The single consent is not going to work because things change - management changes and environmental law changes. We ran aground on that in 2018 and 2019. We will be back there fairly swiftly if we look at a full single consent. There is scope within the Phillip Lee report to look at mechanisms to make the process more efficient. We cannot avoid the requirements under environmental law but we can make them more efficient. That is what we have been working towards.</p>
          <p eId="para_250"> A number of Senators spoke about ash dieback. I was expecting it to come up because it always does. I want to look at it. So far we have had over 500 applications under the RUS, which was established in June or July 2020. I accept that not everyone is happy with it, but it is something I want to look at, perhaps in the new year. A Senator spoke about roadside trees, which are the responsibility of the landowner. The wider issue of ash dieback in our countryside is going to have huge impacts aside from the issue of plantation ash. We need to look at that.</p>
          <p eId="para_251"> Senators Ruane and Boylan brought up the challenges due to our forestry now becoming a net emitter, as it will continue to be, as well as the LULUCF challenges for our forestry and land use regarding peatlands. That is something we are cognisant of across government. It needs to be addressed. We need to get trees in the ground in the right place as quickly as possible to try to offset any of these issues into the future. I hope this programme will instil enthusiasm for planting trees among our landowners. It is worth saying that we currently have about 4,000 ha of afforestation licences issued this year. Between programmes, people will back off and wait for the next year. Potentially, farmers who are listening now have a licence already granted this year but will wait until January or February to plant. There are trees going into the ground as I speak. People are utilising the licences they currently have. People still want to plant under the current programme for various reasons. It has not entirely ground to a halt, but we need an injection of confidence back in the sector. A lot of that will come from the sector itself. There has been a lot of negativity around forestry in recent years. It falls on all of us, and not just the Government, to try to boost that. I have met many forestry owners over the last few years. I have even met happy owners, but we do not tend to hear from them.</p>
          <p eId="para_252">Perhaps there could be more positive stories about forestry and how beneficial it is. I have met a lot of farmers who are interested in planting legacy forests for the future for their grandchildren. It might only be small areas. Perhaps something like the 1 ha scheme might attract them but there is a variety of interests around forestry. We are trying to strike that balance so we get that right.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LynnRuane" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Senator Lynn Ruane<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">Did the Minister reference the accounting relating to sequestration?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PippaHackett" eId="spk_63" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine">
          <from>Senator Pippa Hackett<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">All of that will be part of the LULUCF calculations, which are separate from agricultural emissions. This will come into play in the next year or year and a half when we complete the land use review. That involves how we use our land. Forestry will be included in that but we certainly need to get moving in terms of planting trees.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Senator Micheál Carrigy<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">Ash dieback has to be burned but burning it in our power plants-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PippaHackett" eId="spk_65" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine">
          <from>Senator Pippa Hackett<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">Perhaps that is something we can look at further down the line. We are not overly keen on burning anything but energy. There might be something for heat.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineOreilly" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Pauline O'Reilly)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">We must be careful. It is not a Commencement matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PippaHackett" eId="spk_67" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine">
          <from>Senator Pippa Hackett<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">I know there are some other issues relating to-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">I asked about the proposal for nature restoration.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PippaHackett" eId="spk_69" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Agriculture,_Food_and_the_Marine">
          <from>Senator Pippa Hackett<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">We are cognisant of that and need to look into it. We have made mistakes in the past in terms of what we have done with our peatlands and forestry. There are also some good examples. It is not good to be negative all the time about it. Our engagement with the public and stakeholders this year has been like nothing before. I welcome the general warm welcome for the programme. I know the public consultation on the strategy and the programme is still ongoing and I ask people to engage with that. If there are any specific questions, I can probably get back to Members directly. A number of parliamentary questions on the number of ecologists involved with licensing have been answered so those details should be available.</p>
          <p eId="para_261"> Senator Boylan mentioned the amendment to the appeals legislation in 2020. That was successful in removing the backlog because we increased the number of forestry appeals committees from one to four, which quadrupled the turnaround of the appeals. We still get appeals in, which is the right way. We need to allow that access to justice but we have a system that is much more efficient at dealing with appeals. </p>
          <p eId="para_262"> I think the overall sense was that it is important to get this right. The short-term part of this is the forestry programme, which will be for the next five years. It will be subject to a mid-term review. We can see what is working, what is working really well and whether parts of it are not working. There is potential to amend that at that stage. I look forward to farmers engaging with this. As I said in my opening statement, it will be subject to state aid approval from the Commission, which will not be a straightforward process. We must find that balance. The Commission will be looking to us in terms of environmental outputs from our forestry programme while we are spending €1.6 billion. What is the return across the board? It is important to say that this balance needs to shine through. </p>
          <p eId="para_263"> If there is anything I have not dealt with, I am happy to deal with it. Senators can contact my office. It is clear that we share a common desire for the next forestry programme to be a success. That is important. We know afforestation is a key tool in our attempts to mitigate climate change and all the co-benefits that can come from trees in the future. It is fair to say that we do not come from a culture of tree planting in Ireland. We have plantation forests and have one of the youngest forest stocks in Europe. We do not have those 100- or 150-year-old massive swathes of forest that are potentially managed in a continuous cover way. We are not there yet. We are a way from that but we have to do what we can to embark on that process and keep the sector and those rural economies going. However, that must be balanced with environmental outcomes and that is what we aim to do. I thank Senators for their comments.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_10">
          <i> Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionraí ar 5.55 p.m. agus cuireadh tús leis arís ar 6.30 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
        <summary eId="sum_11">
          <i> Sitting suspended at 5.55 p.m. and resumed at 6.30 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" refersTo="#bill.2022.42.seanad.3" eId="dbsect_11">
        <heading>Judicial Appointments Commission Bill 2022: Committee Stage (Resumed)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T18:30:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <summary eId="sum_12">NEW SECTION</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_13">Debate resumed on amendment No. 33: </summary>
        <summary eId="sum_14">In page 25, between lines 32 and 33, to insert the following:</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_15"><b>“39. </b>Nothing in this Part shall be construed as limiting the advice that the Government may give to the President under Article 35 of the Constitution with respect to the appointment of a person to be a judge.”.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_16">-(Senator Michael McDowell)</summary>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_70">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T18:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">The Minister is welcome, as always. I remind the House that amendment No. 33 is being discussed with amendment No. 36.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T18:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">Regarding amendment No. 33, I have been considering what the Minister said on the last occasion we discussed this Bill. She made the case that what was proposed in this Bill was in line with international practice. I was a bit taken aback by that because clearly it is clearly not in line with the practice in America. I am not holding that out as the great model but I am just saying that is the case. I then checked on Canada, Australia and New Zealand and I found that nothing like what we are proposing here was proposed in any of those jurisdictions. They are significant common law countries. The only country that has similar provisions, in some respects, is the United Kingdom and it has different provisions for the various different courts.</p>
          <p eId="para_266"> I genuinely believe there is a constitutional issue here. I wrote about it in <i>The Irish Times</i> since we last met to discuss this Bill. Nobody is infallible when it comes to the Constitution, as we have just learned in the last week. Things can happen that people did not see happening. Regarding the CETA treaty, it should be said that the matter was to be put before Dáil Éireann and the Government decided to guillotine it, with 55 minutes for the total debate. The Green Party kicked up a fuss and as a result it was sent to a committee. The 14 members of the joint committee divided equally on the issue, with seven saying there were constitutional issues and it went back to the courts under Deputy Costello's challenge.</p>
          <p eId="para_267"> The constitutional implications of this Bill are fairly substantial. We have made provision for the Chief Justice and nine ordinary members of our Supreme Court. If a vacancy occurs in the post of Chief Justice, three names are to be put on a shortlist to be sent to the Government and it is to be attempted to make it illegal to appoint anybody other than somebody on the shortlist to that position. Allowing that some Court of Appeal or High Court judges may be on the shortlist, rather than just ordinary members of the Supreme Court, six or seven members of the Supreme Court will be excluded from eligibility to be appointed Chief Justice at the hands of the Government if such a vacancy arises. That is remarkable. These seven people - or six or five, depending on who else is on the shortlist - are up there in the Supreme Court and the Government will have had an opportunity to see them administering justice there for many years. The Government is then to be told it cannot appoint a majority of the Supreme Court but can only appoint whoever this commission decides should have their name put before it. There is a constitutional issue there.</p>
          <p eId="para_268"> This Bill refers to merit. Merit is almost like picking up mercury with a fork. It is very hard to define what it is. Is a conservative more meritorious than a liberal? Is a Europhile judge more meritorious than a constitutionalist? Those are the issues that arise when appointing somebody to the Supreme Court. No matter who is in office, those issues will arise. What kind of person will they be? Are you appointing somebody who is radical in temperament or somebody who is extremely conservative in temperament? They can both be claimed to be meritorious. If they are both interviewed by this commission or a subcommittee of the commission, can they be asked questions about those kinds of issues? Can they be asked if they are conservative, liberal or radical, pro-European or Eurosceptic or whatever? None of those questions seem appropriate to ask people, particularly practising members of the Judiciary, to answer. Maybe the Minister will help us with regard to this issue. The Bill states that when the shortlist is sent to the Government, the commission is obliged to inform the Government that it has interviewed the candidate who is about to be appointed.</p>
          <p eId="para_269">I want to know whether that interview is supposed to happen before or after he or she is short-listed. Is it to be the case that it is sufficient to interview the candidate after he or she has been short-listed or is it to be the case that it is to be done before being short-listed?</p>
          <p eId="para_270"> Moving on to amendment No. 36, this is where the Minister, I have to warn her, is about to walk onto a landmine with the Bill as currently constructed. Amendment No. 36 is designed to create a situation in which, if somebody who is a member of the superior court is appointed to a position either in the next court above, to the presidency of a court or whatever, and a vacancy arises on that account in the court in which he or she was serving prior to his or her appointment, it is quite possible, for example, if an ordinary judge of the Supreme Court is appointed Chief Justice, that the question could arise as to who should succeed that person as an ordinary judge of the Supreme Court. As I read this Bill, one has to start the process all over again. One cannot, as is the case now, at Cabinet state that Ms Justice so-and-so is being appointed to the Supreme Court, that creates a vacancy in the Court of Appeal and that the Cabinet will appoint A or B to fill that position, that she happens to be a High Court judge and that the Cabinet will fill that as well and there is a shuffle upwards of positions. Under the Bill, if it is passed, the consequential vacancies will have to be filled one-after-another because one cannot anticipate that it will be an ordinary judge of the Supreme Court is being made Chief Justice or a member of the Court of Appeal. One cannot advertise the vacancy in either court on the assumption that that will happen. It could be an ordinary judge of the High Court who is made Chief Justice or whatever. The process has the requirement for interviews, advertisements and invitations for applications.</p>
          <p eId="para_271"> It is interesting that the Bill prohibits one from putting in a standing application. One cannot, as a member of the High Court, state, if any vacancies occur in the Court of Appeal, consider him or her as applying. That is prohibited by this Bill. The process has to be run repeatedly. With the best will in the world, is an appointment duly made in accordance with this process to take place in respect of any vacancy within three months of its arising? If an ordinary member of the Supreme Court is made Chief Justice, a judge of the Court of Appeal is eventually found to be short-listed and approved by the Government to fill that vacancy and a High Court judge is eventually found suitable to fill the Court of Appeal vacancy, that will take at least nine months. Why should we do this to ourselves? Why should we create such a tortoise-pace system of appointments? Why should it not be open to the Government to state that it knows who the candidate is for Chief Justice, that creates this vacancy, the Government would consider A, B and C should fill the vacancies that arise from that, and the Government does not consider it necessary to start advertising all of those positions or to leave them vacant for up to nine months, if this Bill is enacted in its present form.</p>
          <p eId="para_272"> I raised this issue in relation to the previous Bill, which was the project of the former Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Mr. Ross, and I got no satisfactory answer. I got many answers from the then Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Flanagan, but he had no way of answering what would happen to this cascading line-up of delay in filling vacancies. That is where this amendment comes from. We tabled it on the previous occasion. We got no explanation as to whether it is satisfactory that it takes nine months to fill three vacancies which arise in the manner that I have described.</p>
          <p eId="para_273"> It should not be attempted. It is wrong in principle to attempt to do this. It is wrong in principle to say that if one appoints somebody to be Chief Justice and that takes three months with interviews, etc., and that if that person is already a member of the Supreme Court, it takes another three months to fill that position.</p>
          <p eId="para_274"> This is a dog's dinner of an approach in terms of legislation. When I was Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform and when others were Minister for Justice, and others were Attorney General, one sat down and asked what we would be doing to the Judiciary if we appointed A to a position and who would be the right person to achieve gender balance or whatever else in his or her wake. The Cabinet came to a rational decision among the people who were there on the proposal of the Minister for Justice, with consultation of the Attorney General and the party leaders in a coalition Government and stated that this is effectively the series of changes it would make that afternoon. That is entirely impossible now.</p>
          <p eId="para_275"> I take it the Minister accepts what I am saying that if there are three appointments in a chain like that, it would take nine months at the earliest to fill them. If that is the case, the Minister should accept amendment No. 36 and bring some level of sanity to the problems which this legislation is bound to create.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" as="#Minister_for_Justice" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Minister for Justice (Deputy Helen McEntee)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T18:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">To respond briefly to the previous conversation, I reiterate nobody is being excluded and nobody is being disqualified. Everyone must go through the same process, irrespective of what level along the Judiciary he or she is. They merely have to go through a process. Nobody should be excluded from that, irrespective of who he or she is, particularly where we are talking about a promotion.</p>
          <p eId="para_277"> In terms of the international standards, I suppose what I was saying or meant was to some extent having regard to international standards, not saying we must go with one or the other. The Senator has referenced some. It is to take into account international standards as well as European rulings and European standards.</p>
          <p eId="para_278"> It is my advice - I appreciate the advice I receive at Government level - that three is the appropriate number for the recommendations. It limits in a way the current position, where I could potentially have 40 names which some could argue is not the right way either, but it still allows discretion for Government to be able to appoint off those three names. That would be my view on that and that is the advice I have received. </p>
          <p eId="para_279"> In terms of amendment No. 36, I suppose the purpose of the reform of this Bill is that we are filling individual positions as they arise. I am aware now, even as positions arise in the various different courts, there may be requirements at different stages for different types of expertise, knowledge and cases and a specific surge in particular types of areas of law that is required by the President of any new judge being appointed. This ensures that the appointments, the interview process, the questions and the requirements are specific to the role that is being filled as it changes. I suppose that is one of the main reforms proposed in this Bill that every person going for appointment goes through that process and it is specific to the role that has arisen, not potentially somebody who has sat on a panel or has been put forward already for a different role where circumstances may have changed. It is for that reason that I am not in favour of the amendment. It goes against what many of the core changes in this legislation are trying to achieve.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">I have to say the following: we live in a real world rather than a theoretical world. If I apply as a judge to be appointed to a vacancy on the Supreme Court for which I am interviewed but unsuccessful - I could be in the top three - it would be bonkers for me to have to go through the interview all over again when a second vacancy arises in that court for whatever reason a week later. Why can I not say I applied two months ago, was interviewed three weeks ago and my application stands? Why would one wish to interview me again? Will different people interview me? Will they put different questions to me? It is the same vacancy at the same level and for the same purpose. If I was on the shortlist the last time, why in the name of heaven should I sit down to be re-interviewed for the same job?</p>
          <p eId="para_281"> We are dealing with "Alice in Wonderland" nonsense here. No company would interview the same person again and again for promotion to chief clerk or another position. The company would remember it had interviewed the person three weeks ago when the person was second on the list and decide to appoint him or her. However, here we have the cruel system of forcing people to go through the whole process again and we are putting down a statutory requirement whereby a person who was interviewed a month ago has to be re-interviewed for the same position because it arises in different circumstances.</p>
          <p eId="para_282"> If a child was listening to this debate would he or she think it was a reasonable thing to do? If a person applies to be a High Court judge on the death of Mr. So and So, is in the top three and recommended to the Government and somebody else is chosen, does it make any sense not merely to ask the person to apply again and restart the effort of getting referee but to interview the person again by the same or a different group of people? A child would realise that is a stupid thing to provide. No other organisation in Christendom or anywhere else for that matter would operate on that basis and, yet, a rigid approach has been taken whereby it is said not a word of this Bill can be changed now that it is in the Seanad because we might have to bring it back to the Dáil. We are now on a kind of autopilot. This plane is on autopilot to crash into the mountain but we cannot change course. It is too late now because we have made our decision. It just does not make sense. </p>
          <p eId="para_283"> I am sceptical enough about what would happen to a Court of Appeal judge at interview for promotion to the Supreme Court. What questions will the person be asked? Will the person be asked whether he or she plays golf, has a family or likes walking or swimming? Will it be something to do with the person's temperament as a judge when he or she deals with counsel? If one has been in the Court of Appeal everybody knows whether the judge is good, bad or indifferent on that front. Will the person be asked about his or her general attitudes? Will the interviewers be asked to be completely agnostic as to whether the person before them is a deeply conservative person or a social liberal? Is the interview to have nothing to do with that issue which is fundamental to why the Government might choose one rather than another to be appointed to the Supreme Court?</p>
          <p eId="para_284"> It is based on a fiction, when the Minister says all appointments will be made on merit, that she can say social conservatism is less meritorious than social liberalism. To say appointments should not be made on that basis to a Supreme Court of a constitutional State is deeply misguided. It is simply wrong to say the Government of the day should not be concerned with whether Mr. Justice Bloggs or Ms Justice So and So is a deep conservative or a raving social liberal on moral matters and other things. It is wrong to think a Government should not say it does not wish to fill up the Supreme Court with that kind of a person.</p>
          <p eId="para_285"> An appointment is effectively made at the behest of sitting members of the Judiciary because the four lay people will be at a considerable disadvantage in some respects compared with the four judicial people. To say the appointment is made on merit is to suggest that there is some kind of merit test which decides between being left wing and right wing or liberal and social conservative. That does not make any sense whatsoever. It is a choice for Government. The Minister then says that nobody is being disqualified. Yes, people are being disqualified. If one says to a Supreme Court which has a Chief Justice and should have nine ordinary members, that only three of them can be considered by Government, by definition, six or eight of them cannot be considered depending on who the other candidates are.</p>
          <p eId="para_286"> I do not see any basis on which it is constitutional to say to the Government of the day that somebody who has already been on the Supreme Court for a number of years cannot be appointed Chief Justice, because four judges in particular come up with a list of three which does not include that judge. That is a person being excluded. There is no way around it. It is precisely what is being planned here. That is not what happens in Canada, New Zealand or Australia which are great and very commendable common law jurisdictions. Canada has a written constitution. None of those states has done this to vandalise the method of appointment of people and to restrict the capacity of the Government of the day to make proper decisions in the manner that has happened heretofore with regard to appointing Chief Justices or members of the Supreme Court.</p>
          <p eId="para_287"> I do not want to be accused of filibustering but I protest very strongly against this Bill and the failure of the Minister to face up to what is in amendment No. 33 and, in particular, amendment No. 36 which is nonsense. It is nonsense to say that it can take nine months to fill three ladder consequential appointments. We have never had to do this until this day. I remember many times the Cabinet said that if So and So was going to the Supreme Court, So and So would go to the High Court, or if So and So had been made Chief Justice, somebody else from the High Court would go to the Supreme Court. It is all done in an afternoon and, sometimes, even Circuit Court people are appointed in the same train of succession to the High Court. It is all done at a Cabinet meeting because the people who are in a position to judge these things put their minds to it and come up with good solutions.</p>
          <p eId="para_288"> It is ridiculous to say that the Minister will appoint someone on foot of a three-month selection process and another three-month process will be started to fill any vacancies it creates. It is simply ridiculous and indefensible.</p>
          <p eId="para_289">I will not put it any further than that. </p>
          <p eId="para_290"> This is a dog's dinner of a Bill. It is not best practice internationally. The Minister mentioned European this and European that. I want to say one thing about Europe. In Europe judges become judges, except in systems like the Conseil d'État in France, through a system of promotion much like departmental officials. People join the judiciary at a lower level and keep moving up. It is a completely different job. People are not independent arbiters, chosen in their 50s to hold the scales evenly between the State and citizen. That is not the common law system. The civil law system in France is radically different from ours. Its concept of judge is radically different from ours. </p>
          <p eId="para_291"> There is no point in us pretending that because we are members of the European Union our system of common law and adversarial justice, rather than documentary justice done through processes such as we see in the Court of Justice of the European Union, are one and the same. They are quite different. The kind of people we need are quite different. In order to make our system work, we need to appoint people who are wholly independent of the State, people who have not worked their way up through promotion from assistant judge to judge of this, that or the next thing. That is not the system we have. </p>
          <p eId="para_292"> Our courts system is one of our biggest national assets. In the context of the CETA decision, let us remember that American and Canadian investors in Ireland understand our system of law and have confidence in its ability, transparency and integrity. We do not need to make these deeply damaging changes to the way in which we appoint judges. This is a solution in search of a problem. There is no problem. I ask the Minister, in the strongest terms, to take on board amendments Nos. 33 and 36 to save the Bill from a constitutional challenge under Article 36 or elsewhere. </p>
          <p eId="para_293"> It is all very well for the Minister to say she has been advised X and Y. So were the people who attempted to pass CETA. I am not claiming to be infallible and nobody else is either. That is all I am saying.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_74">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_294">Before I ask the Minister for a brief response and put the question, it is my pleasure to welcome our Dáil colleague, Deputy Cormac Devlin, to the Gallery, along with his friends from the Rotary Club of Dún Laoghaire. They are welcome and it is great to have them here. They are here for an interesting Bill. I hope they enjoy the debate and their entire visit to the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_75" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_295">I fundamentally disagree with the argument that just because one is a sitting member of the Judiciary one should not have to go through an interview process. I have not engaged with just the Attorney General, but also the Chief Justice and many others. There does not seem to be a view that this is something that should be excluded or removed from the Bill. What does anybody ask anyone in an interview process? Structures need to be set out, and that will be done.</p>
          <p eId="para_296"> What the Senator is suggesting is that a panel on the commission will intentionally exclude certain people because they do not like them and have their own reasons for that. That can happen anywhere, with members of Government or a Minister. I am trying to make sure that we have as clear and transparent a process as possible. The Senator asked a question about the interview process concerning when the names are presented to the Minister. They will have gone through the interview process and it will be helpful for the Minister in making a recommendation to Government colleagues, be it in a coalition or any other Government. </p>
          <p eId="para_297"> I fundamentally disagree that because someone is a sitting judge he or she should not have to go through the process any other person at any other stage goes through. We might differentiate between our Judiciary and another type of profession, but if one is seeking a promotion an interview process is the normal process to go through. I do not see why this should be any different. </p>
          <p eId="para_298"> I value the advice of the Attorney General. It is important that we listen to the advice he gives to Government. What we have here makes the process even more transparent. </p>
          <p eId="para_299"> I fully agree with the Senator that our Judiciary is one of our strongest and best assets. We are renowned worldwide in terms of the qualifications and exemplary way in which our Judiciary works. This Bill will only benefit those who are sitting judges and are seeking to become judges. I disagree with the Senator's argument. What is proposed is not just for the sake of it or to slow down or speed up the process. I have not filibustered or tried to prevent the debate from happening. We are giving as much time as possible to this discussion. I take on board everything Senators have said here and what Deputies said in the Dáil. </p>
          <p eId="para_300"> The interview process is a fundamental part of the Bill. Three names will be put forward and each individual position will be based on that position, the requirements of the day, the requirements of the President, the types of cases and situation we are in at that point in time. That is why the Bill has been set out in the manner in which it has been.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_76">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_301">Is the amendment being pressed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_302">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection name="division" eId="dbsect_12">
          <summary eId="sum_17">Amendment put: </summary>
          <summary title="division" eId="sum_18">The Committee divided: Tá, <quantity refersTo="#ta" normalized="4" eId="qty_1">4</quantity>; Níl, <quantity refersTo="#nil" normalized="19" eId="qty_2">19</quantity>.</summary>
          <debateSection name="ta" eId="dbsect_13">
            <p eId="para_303">Tá</p>
            <p eId="para_304">
              <person refersTo="#GerardPCraughwell">Craughwell, Gerard P.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_305">
              <person refersTo="#PaulGavan">Gavan, Paul.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_306">
              <person refersTo="#MichaelMcDowellPD">McDowell, Michael.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_307">
              <person refersTo="#RonanMullen">Mullen, Rónán.</person>
            </p>
          </debateSection>
          <debateSection name="nil" eId="dbsect_14">
            <p eId="para_308">Níl</p>
            <p eId="para_309">
              <person refersTo="#CatherineArdagh">Ardagh, Catherine.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_310">
              <person refersTo="#JerryButtimer">Buttimer, Jerry.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_311">
              <person refersTo="#MichealCarrigy">Carrigy, Micheál.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_312">
              <person refersTo="#LisaChambers">Chambers, Lisa.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_313">
              <person refersTo="#LorraineCliffordLee">Clifford-Lee, Lorraine.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_314">
              <person refersTo="#MartinConway">Conway, Martin.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_315">
              <person refersTo="#OllieCrowe">Crowe, Ollie.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_316">
              <person refersTo="#PaulDaly">Daly, Paul.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_317">
              <person refersTo="#AidanDavitt">Davitt, Aidan.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_318">
              <person refersTo="#AislingDolan">Dolan, Aisling.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_319">
              <person refersTo="#PippaHackett">Hackett, Pippa.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_320">
              <person refersTo="#GerryHorkan">Horkan, Gerry.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_321">
              <person refersTo="#SeanKyne">Kyne, Seán.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_322">
              <person refersTo="#JohnMcGahon">McGahon, John.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_323">
              <person refersTo="#PaulineOreilly">O'Reilly, Pauline.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_324">
              <person refersTo="#NedOSullivan">O'Sullivan, Ned.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_325">
              <person refersTo="#MarySeeryKearney">Seery Kearney, Mary.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_326">
              <person refersTo="#BarryWard">Ward, Barry.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_327">
              <person refersTo="#DiarmuidWilson">Wilson, Diarmuid.</person>
            </p>
          </debateSection>
          <summary title="tellers" eId="sum_19">Tellers: Tá, Senators Michael McDowell and Gerard P. Craughwell; Níl, Senators Seán Kyne and Lisa Chambers.</summary>
          <summary title="decision" refersTo="#lost" eId="sum_20">Amendment declared lost.</summary>
        </debateSection>
        <summary eId="sum_21">SECTION 39</summary>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_78">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_328">Amendments Nos. 34, 35, 39 and 40 are related and may be discussed together.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LynnRuane" eId="spk_79">
          <from>Senator Lynn Ruane<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_329">I move amendment No. 34:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_330">In page 26, line 7, after “language” to insert “and Irish Sign Language”.</p>
          <p eId="para_331">Amendment No. 34 would provide that recommendations from the commission should reflect the need to ensure a sufficient number of judges with a proficiency in Irish Sign Language, ISL. The Seanad has a proud record when it comes to ISL. It is vital that users of ISL are able to equitably and fully participate in the legal system, both as judicial officers and as members of the public taking cases. There has been a lot of discussion in the debate over the last few weeks regarding equality. This amendment seeks to address issues of both equality and equity in the legal systems of our society.</p>
          <p eId="para_332"> Amendment No. 35 is a consequential amendment to ensure consistency with the insertion proposed by amendment No. 34. Amendment No. 39 would provide that the commission will consult the Courts Service about the needs of users of the court with respect to proceedings being conducted in ISL. This amendment sees to ensure that the Courts Service is accessible for ISL users and that there is consultation by the commission with the service on its requirement to provide for accessibility. Article 13 of the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities provides for access to justice for disabled people. It explicitly states that parties to the convention:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_333">... shall ensure effective access to justice for persons with disabilities on an equal basis with others, including through the provision of procedural and age-appropriate accommodations, in order to facilitate their effective role as direct and indirect participants, including as witnesses, in all legal proceedings, including at investigative and other preliminary stages.</p>
          <p eId="para_334"> I see no reason the Government would oppose these amendments. They are relatively simple and reflect and complement already existing legal obligations that the State has agreed to. Amendment No. 40 would provide that the commission would consult the president of the High Court, Circuit Court or District Court, as the case may be, about the needs of users of the court concerned in respect of proceedings being conducted in ISL.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_80" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_335">I thank the Senator for putting this forward. This group of amendments is proposed in respect of sections 39 and 56. Section 39 specifically deals with the recommendations of the commission being based on merit. Subject to that requirement, account shall be taken of other objectives, which include meeting the needs of users, as the Senator said, of each court in the State with respect to proceedings being conducted in the Irish language. Section 56 deals with consultations and submissions or observations at the request of the commission, including about the needs of users of the court with respect to proceedings being conducted in the Irish language.</p>
          <p eId="para_336"> The effect of these amendments would be to add to these provisions matters relating to proceedings being conducted in ISL. The Irish Sign Language Act 2017 provides for the use of ISL in legal proceedings, including the right of a person to use ISL in any court. It is already the duty of the court to make sure any person may be heard in that language and there is provision of interpretation of proceedings into ISL. What has been set out in these amendments is already set out very clearly in the 2017 Act and there are already provisions whereby this objective can be achieved through an interpreter. A consequence of this proposition could be that proficiency in ISL should be a statutory requirement on members of the Judiciary. I am not sure if that is what is intended but I do not think it would be practicable as a statutory requirement when appointing people to the courts. What we are trying to achieve here is to make sure everyone who has access to the court has access in their own language. The use of interpreters, as already set out in the 2017 Act, will be able to achieve that same overall goal. I fully appreciate the intention behind these amendments but I think what we have in law already makes sure that can be achieved.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulGavan" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Senator Paul Gavan<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_337">Sinn Féin supports amendments Nos. 34 and 35. We believe ISL, which is a native language on the island, should be defended and protected whenever possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_338">I have considerable sympathy for the points made by Senator Ruane. However, I would make one point. The other amendments in this grouping deal with the possibility of conducting the entire proceedings through ISL. Let us be realistic about this. The great majority of participants in most court cases would not be proficient in ISL and are unlikely to ever become proficient in it. We all get ten years of education in the Irish language, whatever effect it has, and there are difficulties for a lot of judges in conducting cases in the Irish language, which is a deep pity. It will inevitably end up that the Minister's remedy of having an interpreter would be the case. There will never be a case where everybody - witnesses, barristers, solicitors, the judge and the registrar or clerk or whatever - will be able to understand what is going as they are all proficient in ISL. In cases where ISL speakers use the provisions the Minister referred to, there is always going to be an interpreter in court. I wonder whether we are asking too much of the commission to first conduct a study to see how many judges would be required to be proficient in ISL. To say that justifies appointing one person rather than another to a position, for instance in the Supreme Court, is pushing things out, especially since the other members of the Supreme Court would not know what was going on unless the matter was interpreted for them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BarryWard" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Senator Barry Ward<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_339">I also have sympathy with these amendments and I understand where the proposers are coming from. It would be wonderful if we had judges who were proficient in ISL. I recognise what the Minister said about the Irish Sign Language Act 2017. I also recognise that even if the judge in a single-judge sitting, or all the judges in a multiple-judge court, was proficient in sign language, the reality is they could do their work through sign language alone. They will always be relying on an interpreter because there would be registrars and other people in the court who will most likely require those interpretation services. As the Minister said, it is important that anybody who is an ISL user will have equal access to justice, just as people who are Irish-language speakers should have equal access to the court. From the point of view of what a judge does in the course of a hearing, he or she will be sitting there and - without wishing to use a term pejoratively - will be listening to the arguments and making notes. If there were a judge or judges who were competent to conduct a hearing through ISL, with the benefit of an interpreter for those who could not understand ISL, it would not be feasible for a hearing to be conducted in that way. For that reason, I do not think it is a relevant consideration, particularly when no similar requirement exists for the registrar, the Courts Service officials or the lawyers. We would still require the facilitation of translation in the courtroom. </p>
          <p eId="para_340">However desirable it might be to have a judge who does not just have a competence in Irish Sign Language but, perhaps more important, an understanding of what it is to communicate through ISL and what that means in the context of a court setting, the reality is that judge would not be able to conduct his or her function through sign language. This is because of the need to take notes, maybe to consult texts, or to read documents that have been presented before the court. That in and of itself means the requirement for a judge to have an ISL competency is negated in real terms, however desirable it might be. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LynnRuane" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Senator Lynn Ruane<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_341">I will briefly respond to those comments. I understand the complexities this requirement would bring in terms of the need for translation and interpretation. Irish Sign Language is recognised by the State as a language. It should not be the case that somebody is not able to fluidly communicate with the most powerful person in the room in a language fully understood by all present because, even if there is interpretation, nuances can be lost. It is about trying to equalise the participation of somebody in the court process.</p>
          <p eId="para_342"> I play football. There is woman who is a deaf player on one of the other teams at my club. I remember watching her team play and the managers communicating with her in Irish Sign Language. I know that took place on a football pitch but I was so impressed. I thought how amazing it was that somebody was equally able to communicate with the managers in the same way everybody else on the team was. I asked the managers how it came about that they knew Irish Sign Language. I wondered if they learned it just to be able to communicate with the football team, but many of them worked in schools or were special needs assistants. The fact is more of us should be proficient in Irish Sign Language in order to be able to equalise some of those interactions to the point where people can communicate in sign language even when they are running around on a football pitch.</p>
          <p eId="para_343"> There is definitely room for us to encourage judges, clerks and anybody else in any sort of institution or public body, and incentivise people, to learn Irish Sign Language and be able to use it every day, especially if they work with people who are already in the vulnerable position of being in court and further feeling that vulnerability because they cannot communicate directly with the judge or other people in the room in their preferred language. I will move the amendment, notwithstanding the contributions made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_344">As Senator Ward was speaking, I wondered where we would be in jury cases? A jury of people who know Irish Sign Language could not be empanelled with any convenience. We have to be realistic. ISL is recognised as a language under the legislation referred to by the Minister but, in its present state of usage, there are limits to how realistic it is to conduct proceedings entirely through that language.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_22"> Amendment put and declared lost.</summary>
        <speech by="#LynnRuane" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Senator Lynn Ruane<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_345">I move amendment No. 35:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_346">In page 26, line 10, after “language” to insert “and Irish Sign Language”.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_23"> Amendment put and declared lost.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_24"> Section 39 agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_25"> Section 40 agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_26">SECTION 41</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_27"> Question proposed: "That section 41 stand part of the Bill."</summary>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_87">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_347">I will raise a few matters relating to section 41 that I want explained as to what they actually mean. There is a prohibition on canvassing in this section that states:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_348">An applicant shall not, in relation to the process of selection and recommendation (including any step that may be taken in consequence of such a recommendation) of ... [any person] for appointment or for nomination for appointment or election to the judicial office to which his or her application relates—</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_349">(a) canvass, or attempt to canvass, support for his or her application from any person involved in that process,</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_350">(b) attempt to improperly influence a decision of any person in that process,</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_351">(c) otherwise interfere with or compromise that process in any way, or</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_352">(d) procure or counsel another person, on his or her behalf, to engage in the conduct referred to in <i>paragraph (a)</i>, <i>(b)</i> or<i> (c)</i>.</p>
          <p eId="para_353">What are we actually saying here? We are creating a criminal offence. Are we saying that somebody who has applied to the commission and has been shortlisted cannot make any representation to the Attorney General or any member of the Cabinet regarding his or her suitability? Is it open, for instance, to the Cabinet to discuss with third parties, on behalf of a person or whatever, whether or not a person on a shortlist would be recommended? I am slightly concerned. Are Ministers to be in a state of <i>omerta </i>about this in that nobody can talk to them about it? The bit that slightly worries me states, "any step that may be taken in consequence of such a recommendation...". Does that mean a decision by the Government to select from among the persons recommended? Is that really what is proposed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_88" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_354">This section sets out exactly what it sets out. It prohibits canvassing for individual positions. It is based on the fact that every person will go through a process. Names will obviously be put forward and the recommendation will be based on those names, the interview process, and the information that has been provided from the commission itself. Yes, the section states that canvassing will be an offence. I do not anticipate that we will go around prosecuting people, but it is very clear in this Bill that canvassing is prohibited and is not something people should engage in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_89">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_355">A point that arises in this context - I have not located it in the Bill and perhaps the Minister could assist me - is whether the shortlist is to be kept secret in all circumstances. Is that provided for in the legislation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_90" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_356">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_91">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_357">Is a Cabinet Minister at liberty to say to Senator Ward, for example, that he is one of the three that may be eligible next time? Is a Minister entitled to have that kind of conversation? If Senator Ward is number 1, 2 or 3 on the list, is he entitled to know that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_92">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_358">He would expect to be number one.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_93">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_359">I know he would.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GerryHorkan" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_94">
          <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Gerry Horkan)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_360">If I were not in the Chair, I would have said that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_95">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_361">I know there is no number 1, 2 or 3 on the shortlist but is somebody who is shortlisted entitled to know it? Is anybody else entitled to know it? Is it a secret and is it an offence to reveal it? That is a point I would love to know about and I do not see it in the legislation. Maybe it is there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_96" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_362">The three individuals who are put forward to be shortlisted will be notified. Anybody who is not shortlisted can request and ask but will not be notified unless he or she requests it. If people are within the top three, they will be notified. A person can request to be notified or not. It applies if an individual requests to be notified. It had been the case that everybody would be notified following discussion and engagement. On a request put forward, it is now the case that if somebody requests to know, that person will get the information, but if they do not request the information they will not get it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_97">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_363">I follow that. A person will know whether they did or did not make the shortlist.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_98" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_364">Some people would want to know and some would not.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_365">Most people who go to the trouble of applying and being interviewed would like to know what happened and whether they were or were not in the top three.</p>
          <p eId="para_366">Some people are so modest that they do not want to know whether they made the shortlist. Assuming that is the case is there some rule that the identity of the persons on the shortlist coming to the Government is to be kept secret except for communicating it to them?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_100" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_367">It is not going to be published beforehand but names will be presented at Cabinet. As Senator McDowell knows anything that comes before Cabinet is bound under Cabinet confidentiality. That is still the case. It is the same if I was-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GerryHorkan" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_101">
          <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Gerry Horkan)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_368"> Senator McDowell probably knows that better than most Senators.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_102" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_369">If I was to bring forward a name now obviously the list of eligible judges or the list of those who applied is set out as well and available for people to see but obviously there is Cabinet confidentiality. That applies in the same way but they are not going to be published prior to Cabinet. They are not going to be made available. As I said we actually had in the Bill that every person would be told and, on further engagement with the Judiciary and with others, it was amended so that if a person asked and wanted to know he or she could be told. If such people did not, and it is their right if they do not want to be informed whether they are on it, they would not be given that information.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_103">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_370">Let me tease this out. If the three names are sent forward to the Minister for Justice where does it say in the Bill that the Minister for Justice is not entitled to tell anybody else who is on the list?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_104" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_371">The Bill sets out that the three names must be given to the Minister for Justice. The Minister will engage as is set out in the handbook and the rule book with the leaders of the coalition or whoever is in Government, with the Attorney General and with Cabinet colleagues. However, names going to Cabinet are bound under Cabinet confidentiality.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_105">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_372">I fully appreciate what the Minister has just said but we need more clarity. The Minister gets a list of three names and goes to the leaders of the coalition parties in Government. Are they prohibited from asking any questions of anybody else as to which of the three is the better or more suitable candidate? I do not think it is in the Bill. This is not a fanciful thought. If I was the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, and the names of three barristers or solicitors appeared in my hands would I be permitted to ask others for their opinion of the three?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GerryHorkan" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Gerry Horkan)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_373">Or forbidden?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_107">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_374">Or forbidden, yes. It is a fairly important point because if there is no secrecy in this it will become known that Judge Lynn Ruane or whoever was rejected by the Cabinet.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LynnRuane" eId="spk_108">
          <from>Senator Lynn Ruane<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_375">That would never happen.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_109">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_376">Such a thing would happen. Let us not cod ourselves. If people ask others for advice as to which of the three should be appointed or what are the qualities of the three as far as the Government is concerned, such issues would involve who is liberal and who is conservative. If they are free to make those inquiries this will leak like a sieve. There is no point in codding ourselves that that will not happen. In what I call the Shane Ross Bill, I thought there was some prohibition on any leakages of this kind but I do not see it here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_110" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_377">We are looking at that in the reverse so that is not somebody canvassing, that a person is free to understand who the individual is or to ask the question, that is currently the case. Names are put forward and there has to be an understanding of who is being put forward, particularly if people do not know all the names, especially as a large number of names are often put forward or a name that has been recommended by myself, just one name. We are not talking about the leaders of parties canvassing. We are talking about them making a decision.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_111">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_378">Consultatively.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_112" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_379">It is outside the scope of this Bill but this specific section is very much around canvassing and individuals taking it upon themselves to talk to somebody else or to canvass. What Senator McDowell is talking about is making a decision. I am not sure if the leader of a party or anybody else is going to make a statement that he or she is asking about an individual who may or may not be on a list. That is a process that is outside the scope of this Bill. I do not see that as canvassing. I see that as somebody making a decision.</p>
          <p eId="para_380"> Going back to the point about the interview process and more information, the process that has been set out here gives the information to those who are making the decisions to the Minister to put forward that name and give that information where it is currently not available, where a person might not know the individual and the name being proposed from Adam, and might not know anything about the person or his or her background. That is already the case now and the system we are putting in place means that there is more information on the individuals who are potentially being put forward for a recommendation. What Senator McDowell is talking about is not within the scope of this Bill. The canvassing is a separate issue. For a person to be asked for an opinion, he or she obviously has an ability to ask questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BarryWard" eId="spk_113">
          <from>Senator Barry Ward<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_381">To my mind section 41(1) only refers to the applicants. There is no restriction. The offence can only be committed by an applicant rather than by a member of Cabinet or anybody else involved in the process. The applicant is the person named so that is the person who is prohibited from doing the things described in section 41(1).</p>
          <p eId="para_382"> What Senator McDowell describes is something that presumably could already happen. He is quite right in being concerned about the confidentiality of the process. That is paramount because if potential applicants or applicants do not have faith in the confidentiality of the process, many of them simply will not apply because they do not want a situation where they are potentially discussed in a negative context of not having been selected. That is the reality of the people we are talking about as potential members of the Judiciary. That is important.</p>
          <p eId="para_383"> I personally do not think this is necessary, certainly not in the very strict terms in which it is described here. I do not think it creates any prohibition either on the Minister making his or her own inquiries if I can put it is those terms. I disagree with the Minister in regard to her statement on the interview process adding to the information available to Cabinet. I have an amendment later to section 46(1)(b) to remove that requirement because the difference between what is being suggested here and what the Minister is suggesting is that the Minister’s suggestion requires the Minister to rely on information that is coming to him or her through the Civil Service process, through the process that is nominated in this Bill which is fine. However, it is a different quality of information from information which a Minister might obtain from somebody he or she trusts, who might perhaps know the individuals or the system. There is a different quality to the information provided through both of those processes, on the one hand through an interview and the competitive Civil Service style process that is envisaged by this Bill and, on the other hand, a person with personal knowledge who might pass it on to somebody he or she knows or trusts in those processes. I do not think section 41 is necessary but maybe I have more faith in the system than I should. In any event I do not believe the problem envisaged by Senator McDowell exists because this section only applies to the applicant.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_114">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_384">I appreciate there is a difference between canvassing and the process whereby the leader of a small party in coalition would receive three names from the Minister for Justice and say "I do not know these three people from Adam and I do not know between them, which of them is the best, because the Bill says there is no order". If I was the leader of a party in the Government I would certainly want to take soundings before walking into Cabinet to be told they are all on a list and they are all of equal standing, all equally eligible for appointment. I would like to know whether a person is liberal or conservative or whatever. In order to do that, even if there were three people there, I would ask somebody I trusted for advice, such as a member of my own party perhaps who was a lawyer if I was not one myself, on which of those three is the best, in his or her view, rather than going to Cabinet and just sitting there in a state of ignorance.</p>
          <p eId="para_385">It is important that we take on board that a consequence of this Bill being drafted in this way is that while it is a criminal offence for the applicant for a position to engage in canvassing, curiously, the wife or husband of the applicant can do it like billy-o. Paragraph (d) states “procure or counsel another person … to engage in the conduct” but an ambitious spouse or ambitious friend can canvass furiously. The only person who is prohibited from doing it is the applicant himself or herself.</p>
          <p eId="para_386"> This has not been thought through. If I inform a politically influential friend that I believe I am shortlisted, and that person on my behalf decides to tap the shoulder of Cabinet members and say “That person would make a good judge”, in those circumstances, is an offence committed? An applicant would be disqualified under subsection (2) but a friend of the applicant who knew that he or she was shortlisted would not be disqualified and no offence would be committed unless it was done at the behest of the applicant. I wonder what we are attempting to achieve here. I believe the absence of a guarantee of secrecy from the whole process is going to deter a lot of people from making applications. If you read on the front of a newspaper that the political correspondent of the <i>Daily Bugle</i> has ascertained that you were turned down by the Cabinet three times in a row, what are you to make of that, what are you to do about it and what right of complaint have you got about it? None.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_115" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_387">What I would say is that people are not put off by the current process. What we are talking about in section 41 is specifically on the issue of canvassing and does not relate to where a person has been put forward or names have been put forward and decisions have to be taken. We are bound by Cabinet confidentiality and the commission is bound by confidentiality as well. I have not seen a scenario where names for a High Court appointment are on the front of a newspaper where people have not been appointed. I do not see that changing with this Bill. The canvassing section, whether people believe it is necessary or not, is based on the advice that this is included in the Bill. I think it is standard practice. It is to try to prevent and prohibit that type of canvassing but, as I said, it is outside the scope of this Bill.</p>
          <p eId="para_388"> The point concerns communications between Cabinet colleagues or, as the Senator said, whether a person might speak to or ask advice of a Cabinet colleague who may have a legal profession or have background information or knowledge. We are not changing the process that currently exists or the option that is there, and we are not prohibiting that. It is specific to canvassing by the individual. As I said, it is the advice that is there and it is standard practice. I cannot see a situation where people will not apply because they are fearful that Cabinet colleagues are going to start breaching confidentiality or that the commission itself, which is yet to even be established, is going to start breaching confidentiality. We need to have trust in the commission that will be chaired by the Chief Justice and assume that these rules that have been set out will not be breached.</p>
          <p eId="para_389"> Again, I go back to the point that if individuals want to know where they came in the process, they can seek to apply and ask. If they do not, that is not going to be forced on them either.</p>
        </speech>
        <debateSection name="division" eId="dbsect_15">
          <summary eId="sum_28">Question put: </summary>
          <summary title="division" eId="sum_29">The Committee divided: Tá, <quantity refersTo="#ta" normalized="20" eId="qty_3">20</quantity>; Níl, <quantity refersTo="#nil" normalized="4" eId="qty_4">4</quantity>.</summary>
          <debateSection name="ta" eId="dbsect_16">
            <p eId="para_390">Tá</p>
            <p eId="para_391">
              <person refersTo="#GarretAhearn">Ahearn, Garret.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_392">
              <person refersTo="#CatherineArdagh">Ardagh, Catherine.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_393">
              <person refersTo="#JerryButtimer">Buttimer, Jerry.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_394">
              <person refersTo="#MichealCarrigy">Carrigy, Micheál.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_395">
              <person refersTo="#LisaChambers">Chambers, Lisa.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_396">
              <person refersTo="#LorraineCliffordLee">Clifford-Lee, Lorraine.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_397">
              <person refersTo="#MartinConway">Conway, Martin.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_398">
              <person refersTo="#OllieCrowe">Crowe, Ollie.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_399">
              <person refersTo="#PaulDaly">Daly, Paul.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_400">
              <person refersTo="#AidanDavitt">Davitt, Aidan.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_401">
              <person refersTo="#AislingDolan">Dolan, Aisling.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_402">
              <person refersTo="#TimDooley">Dooley, Timmy.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_403">
              <person refersTo="#PippaHackett">Hackett, Pippa.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_404">
              <person refersTo="#GerryHorkan">Horkan, Gerry.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_405">
              <person refersTo="#SeanKyne">Kyne, Seán.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_406">
              <person refersTo="#JohnMcGahon">McGahon, John.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_407">
              <person refersTo="#FionaOLoughlin">O'Loughlin, Fiona.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_408">
              <person refersTo="#PaulineOreilly">O'Reilly, Pauline.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_409">
              <person refersTo="#MarySeeryKearney">Seery Kearney, Mary.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_410">
              <person refersTo="#BarryWard">Ward, Barry.</person>
            </p>
          </debateSection>
          <debateSection name="nil" eId="dbsect_17">
            <p eId="para_411">Níl</p>
            <p eId="para_412">
              <person refersTo="#GerardPCraughwell">Craughwell, Gerard P.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_413">
              <person refersTo="#SharonKeogan">Keogan, Sharon.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_414">
              <person refersTo="#MichaelMcDowellPD">McDowell, Michael.</person>
            </p>
            <p eId="para_415">
              <person refersTo="#RonanMullen">Mullen, Rónán.</person>
            </p>
          </debateSection>
          <summary title="tellers" eId="sum_30">Tellers: Tá, Senators Seán Kyne and Lisa Chambers; Níl, Senators Michael McDowell and Gerard P. Craughwell.</summary>
          <summary title="decision" refersTo="#carried" eId="sum_31">Question declared carried.</summary>
        </debateSection>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_116">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_416">I welcome our distinguished visitors, Deputy Michael Ring and his guests, to the Visitors Gallery.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_32">SECTION 42</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_33"> Question proposed: "That section 42 stand part of the Bill."</summary>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_117">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_417">I spoke to the Minister during the earlier stages of this debate about section 42(1), which states:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_418">(1) The Minister may request the Commission to make recommendations for appointment or for nomination for appointment to judicial office, as the case may be, where—</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_419">(a) a judicial office stands vacant, or</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_420">(b) he or she reasonably anticipates that there will be a vacancy in a judicial office.</p>
          <p eId="para_421">It seems to me that the word "may" seems to confer discretion on the Minister on this matter, and that it will not be the duty of the Minister to make recommendations. When it is invited to do so, the commission will issue an invitation through advertisement for applications from persons who wish to be considered for selection. In those circumstances, the commission will issue information, as set out in subsection 4, in addition to the invitation by advertisement. Regarding the phrase "he or she reasonably anticipates that there will be a vacancy in a judicial office", and returning to the point we made earlier, if it is likely that an ordinary judge of the Supreme Court will be made Chief Justice, can the Minister at the same time seek applications to fill any vacancy that would arise from such an appointment or must the Minister wait until the vacancy has actually occurred? On one view of section 42(1)(b), the Minister could reasonably anticipate that there will be an appointment to the position of Chief Justice and, in all likelihood, there will be a vacancy in the Supreme Court. Alternatively, must the Minister bide her time and wait for the actual outcome of the first three-month process before shooting the firing pistol to fill any consequential vacancy?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_118" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_422">We previously discussed the word "may" but a situation has arisen even in my case where a decision was taken not to fill a particular vacancy or a decision was taken by the president of the relevant court that it was not required, so that allows for that discretion. That is not to say that a Minister might randomly decide not to fill positions in the District Court or elsewhere when they might clearly be needed. This just ensures that the Minister may do so if that is what is necessary.</p>
          <p eId="para_423"> On the question of reasonably anticipating that there may be a vacancy, the same is the case at the moment - a person may be appointed by the Cabinet but the official process of going to the President, being officially nominated and moving into that position does not happen immediately. If that person has been appointed by the Cabinet, we know that a vacancy has arisen, which allows the process to start even though the person has not officially been appointed. There is a reasonable understanding that having been appointed by the Cabinet, the person will be appointed. It is often a case of having to work with the President's schedule. Sometimes there is a wait for one or two different appointments to happen at the same time and the ceremony happens in the President's residence at the same time. This allows for a process to start when a person has not officially been appointed but it is reasonable to anticipate that a vacancy will arise once he or she has been appointed. In response to the Senator's previous questions, it allows for a process to start.</p>
          <p eId="para_424"> I anticipate that the commission will be more resourced and, hopefully, more efficient in terms of the process. Therefore, rather than every application taking three months, it could be done much more quickly. That would be set out by the commission. When things start, it might take a bit of time but I anticipate that things will move quickly enough. What this really does is anticipate that a process can start when a person has been appointed but has not officially taken on the role for the reasons I have outlined. This is very similar to what happens now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_119">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_425">I do not think I am exaggerating when I say it is three months, but it certainly must be two months. You must put up your advertisements, give people a reasonable amount of time to consider whether they want to apply and give them time in which to get any requisite references. Then the list comes back. In the case of the District Court, for example, if there are 40 applicants, the first thing is whether all of them get an interview. I wonder if they do. That could take a long time to get through. Decisions then have to be made on who is best suited to be on the shortlist. That must then go to the Cabinet. I would be very surprised if the commission manages to do this in less than two months. Between the jigs and the reels, I think it is most likely that it will take three months.</p>
          <p eId="para_426"> Another point is that as I understand it, the post of Chief Justice is held by a judge for seven years. Is it to be the case that as we come towards the end of the seven-year term, the Minister will advertise for replacements in order to be in a position to fill the position as soon as the Chief Justice steps down? We know that barring accidents, Chief Justices retire at 70 or retire having done their seven-year term. The question that arises is whether, when the current Chief Justice or some other Chief Justice is three months away from retirement, the Minister will start the process of filling the position at that point. Is this eventuality covered by section 42(1)(b), which provides for the Minister to "reasonably [anticipate] that there will be a vacancy in a judicial office"?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_120" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_427">Yes, that is the process that happens now, particularly for the type of vacancy mentioned by the Senator. It ensures there is no gap, particularly for such significant roles. I do not propose to change that. It very seldom happens that a person promoted to a position from one court to the next is automatically appointed or takes up that position immediately for the very simple reason that we must work with the President. </p>
          <p eId="para_428">A process can start quite quickly and leave a relatively short gap between when a person vacates his or her current position and takes up the new one and another person takes it on. I appreciate there can be a gap. There can be a vacancy that needs to be filled immediately but the intention here is to allow that flexibility to make sure that one can plan insofar as possible. It is the case where one knows that a vacancy, whether it is the Chief Justice or potentially president of a court, is coming up that one can plan and prepare. That is exactly what happens now.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_34"> Question put and agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_35">NEW SECTION</summary>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_121">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_429">I move amendment No. 36:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_430">In page 28, between lines 28 and 29, to insert the following:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_431">“Right of Government to advise President</p>
          <p class="indent_3" eId="para_432">43. Notwithstanding the provisions of section 42, nothing in this Part affects, limits or inhibits the right of the Government in any case where it advises the President to appoint any member of the Supreme Court, the Court of Appeal, or the High Court to any judicial office in any of those courts to the vacancy thereby created without seeking any recommendation from the Commission.”.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_36"> Amendment put and declared lost.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_37"> Sections 43 and 44 agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_38">SECTION 45</summary>
        <speech by="#GerryHorkan" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_122">
          <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Gerry Horkan)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_433">Amendment No. 37 in the names of Senators McDowell, Boyhan, Craughwell, Keogan and Mullen cannot be moved.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_39"> Amendment No. 37 not moved.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_40"> Question propose: "That section 45 stand part of the Bill."</summary>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_123">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_434">It seems that the process of filling the position of Chief Justice will be carried out by the commission, normally where the Chief Justice is in office and will participate as one of the four judicial members of the commission making a decision, but if, for instance, there was a resignation or whatever, the next senior judge of that court would carry out that function. Am I correct in thinking that?</p>
          <p eId="para_435"> Section 45(1)(a) envisages the Chief Justice making an application to the commission, and I presume that that would be for appointment to some European court or something of that kind. There is the question that he "shall not attend any meeting of the Commission held for the purpose of the performance of that function". Is it to be the case that meetings can only deal with one application? For instance, the Attorney General might be applying to be a High Court judge and the commission might on a particular afternoon be also considering an appointment to the Circuit Court. Do they have to be separate meetings to ensure that the Attorney General does not participate in any part of the meeting where the Attorney General is under consideration? Should it not be that the Attorney General shall absent himself or herself from any portion of the meeting held for the purpose of the performance of that function?</p>
          <p eId="para_436"> The other matter is that section 45(1)(d) seems to imply that the Attorney General shall not cast a vote but I thought that we had decided in an earlier section for some reason that he or she had not a vote to cast in the first place. Am I right on that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_124" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_437">The answer to the Senator's first question is, "Yes". The second most senior person will take on that position. Obviously, we make no reference to voting and it is "take no part in the performance by the Commission". The performance of the commission is not only to vote but also to discuss the recommendations and the names at hand. That is why the Attorney General would be included.</p>
          <p eId="para_438"> Essentially, this section is around recusal and making sure of that where a conversation takes place. I suppose it would be a decision of the commission to decide what meetings it was having and what positions it was filling. It is not likely to happen too often in all of the various different meetings that the commission will have. If there is a particular meeting happening, I am sure that the commission would be able to figure out how to hold a meeting, either to adjourn it and then to reconvene the same meeting or to have two separate meetings if there were different positions being put forward at the same time or different positions going forward to Cabinet or being requested at the same time. That is a decision that can be taken by the commission. It is something that could probably be resolved quickly.</p>
          <p eId="para_439"> This section is around making sure that if a person who will be on the commission is applying for a job, he or she is not in the room talking about it and discussing it at the same time for obvious reasons.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BarryWard" eId="spk_125">
          <from>Senator Barry Ward<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_440">I had not considered what Senator McDowell has raised there. I am wondering if the Minister can clarify that in the context where the situation under section 45(1)(a) arises and the Chief Justice is an applicant for a position, there is no procedure whereby the Chief Justice can be substituted in relation to that commission meeting. If, for example, the President of the Court of Appeal stepped out, there is a process whereby he or she can be replaced. Perhaps I misread that. In section 9, there appears to be provision for replacement of certain members, and certainly replacement of the Chief Justice as chair if the Chief Justice were there. However, if the Chief Justice is an applicant under section 45(1)(a), am I right in saying, therefore, there are seven voting members of the commission rather than eight?</p>
          <p eId="para_441"> Since we are discussing it, not because it is important but because I see it, section 45(1)(b) appears to contain a typographical error. Just at the beginning, the spacing is wrong. It is not an important point, one way or the other, but I thought I would say it given that I am an uber-pedant.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GerryHorkan" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Gerry Horkan)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_442">Back to our old days of the development plan in Dún Laoghaire-Rathdown.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_127">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_443">I do not know whether the provisions of section 45(2) answer Senator Ward's query.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BarryWard" eId="spk_128">
          <from>Senator Barry Ward<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_444">I think it does.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_129">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_445">I think it does, in fact.</p>
          <p eId="para_446"> On a slightly different point, in relation to subsection (4), the Judicial Council appoints a substitute member if one of its elected members is looking for promotion or whatever. Are they free to nominate any member to be a member of the commission? For instance, if the person for whom the substitution is made was originally a barrister, can he or she appoint a judge who was originally a solicitor as the substitute or does that balance still apply as between solicitor judges and barrister judges?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_130" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_447">It still applies. Secondly, in response to Senator Ward, it is in the next section.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_131">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_448">I do not quite see why it applies in section 45(4). It seems that the board of the Judicial Council is free to appoint anybody who is on the council.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_132" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_449">It refers to the make-up in a separate section, which I do not have-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_133">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_450">That is when they are electing somebody. He or she has to be originally a barrister or originally a solicitor, but where the person is merely acting up for one occasion, does that balance have to be maintained?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#HelenMcEntee" eId="spk_134" as="#Minister_for_Justice">
          <from>Deputy Helen McEntee<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_451">The intention is that it would still be maintained.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMcDowellPD" eId="spk_135">
          <from>Senator Michael McDowell<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_452">I do not think that is right.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_41"> Question put and agreed to.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_42">SECTION 46</summary>
        <speech by="#BarryWard" eId="spk_136">
          <from>Senator Barry Ward<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_453">I move amendment No. 38:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_454">In page 31, to delete lines 27 and 28.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_43"> Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</summary>
        <speech by="#GerryHorkan" as="#Acting_Chairperson" eId="spk_137">
          <from>Acting Chairperson (Senator Gerry Horkan)<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_455">When is it proposed to sit again?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LisaChambers" eId="spk_138">
          <from>Senator Lisa Chambers<recordedTime time="2022-11-15T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_456">At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_44"> Cuireadh an Seanad ar athló ar 8.30 p.m. go dtí 10.30 a.m., Dé Céadaoin, an 16 Samhain 2022.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_45"> The Seanad adjourned at 8.30 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 16 November 2022.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
