<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_scrutiny/2009-07-28/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_scrutiny/2009-07-28/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2009-07-28" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/30/joint_committee_on_european_scrutiny"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_scrutiny/2009-07-28/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_scrutiny/2009-07-28/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2009-07-28" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_scrutiny/2009-07-28/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_european_scrutiny/2009-07-28/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference eId="#vol_None" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None" showAs="Vol. None"/>
          <oir:numberReference eId="#no_None" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None/no/None" showAs="No. None"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AengusOSnodaighSF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aengus-Ó-Snodaigh.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Aengus Ó Snodaigh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DennisODonovan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Denis-O'Donovan.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Denis O'Donovan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DiarmuidWilson" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Diarmuid-Wilson.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Diarmuid Wilson"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeCostelloLAB" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Costello.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Joe Costello"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnMcGuinness" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-McGuinness.D.1997-06-26" showAs="John McGuinness"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnPerry" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Perry.D.1997-06-26" showAs="John Perry"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="KieranPhelan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Kieran-Phelan.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Kieran Phelan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelKitt" href="" showAs=""/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaddyBurke" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paddy-Burke.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Paddy Burke"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanConnick" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Connick.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Seán Connick"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TimDooley" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Timmy-Dooley.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Timmy Dooley"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chair" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chair" showAs="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chairman" showAs="Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>COMHCHOISTE UM GRINNSCRÚDÚ EORPACH</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>JOINT COMMITTEE ON EUROPEAN SCRUTINY</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2009-07-28">Dé Máirt, 28 Iúil 2009</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2009-07-28">Tuesday, 28 July 2009</docDate>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at noon.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#SeanConnick">Deputy Seán Connick,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#PaddyBurke">Senator Paddy Burke,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeCostelloLAB">Deputy Joe Costello,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#DennisODonovan">Senator Denis O’Donovan,*</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#TimDooley">Deputy Timmy Dooley,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#KieranPhelan">Senator Kieran Phelan,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelKitt">Deputy Michael P. Kitt,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#DiarmuidWilson">Senator Diarmuid Wilson.+</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#JohnMcGuinness">Deputy John McGuinness,*</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#AengusOSnodaighSF">Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">*In the absence of Deputy Noel O'Flynn and Senator Terry Leyden, respectively.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_4">+In the absence of Senator Kieran Phelan for part of meeting.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">In attendance: Ms Nessa Childers, MEP, and Ms Marian Harkin, MEP.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_6">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#JohnPerry">DEPUTY JOHN PERRY IN THE CHAIR.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Business of Joint Committee. </heading>
        <speech by="#JohnPerry" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_11">I welcome and heartily congratulate Nessa Childers, MEP, and Marian Harkin, MEP, on their election to the European Parliament.  It is very good to see MEPs attending meetings of the committee, especially in the context of the issues of subsidiarity and the role of directives.  Their involvement in this forum is very important.</p>
          <p eId="para_12">Apologies have been received from Deputy Creighton.  We will go into private session to deal with some housekeeping matters.</p>
          <p eId="para_13">The joint committee went into private session at 12.05 p.m and resumed in public session at 12.20 p.m.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Scrutiny of EU Proposals. </heading>
        <speech by="#JohnPerry" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_14">Category 1 refers to adopted measures.  Measures adopted at the meeting of 14 July include COM (2009) 240, COM (2009) 241, COM (2009) 242, COM (2009) 243, COM (2009) 244, COM (2009) 245 and COM (2009) 246.  These proposals concern the non-inclusion of various substances and the withdrawal of authorisations for plant protection products containing these substances.  It is proposed that the committee note the seven finalised proposals, four of which have been adopted by the Council.  No decision could be agreed on the other three.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_15">COM (2009) 260 relates to the simplification of inspections and formalities in respect of the carriage of goods.  It is proposed to note the adopted measure.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_16">COM (2009) 270 relates to establishing the European Community position within the Ministerial Council of the Energy Community.  It is proposed to note the adopted measure.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">COM (2009) 289-FON relates to the imposition of an anti-dumping duty on imports of certain graphite electrode systems originating in India.  It is proposed to note the adopted measure.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_18">Category 2 proposals are ones which require no further scrutiny.  It is proposed that they be noted.  COM (2009) 229 is a proposal concerning the air transport agreement between the United States of America, for the one part, the European Community and its member states, for the second part, Iceland, for the third part, and the Kingdom of Norway, for the fourth part.  It is proposed that the proposal does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_19">COM (2009) 255 is a proposal regarding the signing of the arrangement for the management of operational co-operation at the external borders of the member states of the European Union.  Given that this proposal has no implications for Ireland due to our non-participation in the Schengen <i>acquis</i>, it is proposed that it does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_20">COM (2009) 287 is a<b> </b>proposal on the conclusion of the interim agreement with Turkmenistan and on trade and trade-related matters.<b>  </b>Given that the Department’s advice is that the proposal has no implications for Ireland, it is proposed it does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_21">COM (2009) 319–FON concerns the imposition of an anti-dumping duty on imports of certain forms of polyethylene terephthalate.  It is proposed that this trade measure does not require further scrutiny by the committee.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_22">COM (2009) 339–FON<b> </b>is a proposal for a Council regulation terminating the partial interim review of the anti-dumping measures applicable to imports of certain plastic sacks and bags originating in the People’s Republic of China.  It is proposed that this trade measure does not require further scrutiny by the committee.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_23">There are no proposals for further scrutiny under category 3 and the relevant documentation will be sent to sectoral committees for their information.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">COM (2009) 122 is a proposal for a Council regulation establishing a long-term plan for the northern stock of hake and the fisheries exploiting that stock.  In the light of the committee's two previous reports which have highlighted the need to protect the interests of the Irish fishing industry, it is proposed to note this measure and request the Department to update the committee on the progress made in the negotiations.  The proposal will also be sent to the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Fisheries and Food for its information.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_25">COM (2009) 275 is a proposal for a Council regulation opening an autonomous tariff quota for imports of high quality beef.  Given that the regulation has been adopted, it is proposed that it be noted by the committee.  However, given that the regulation is of some significance and could have implications for Ireland's beef industry and the Irish agri-food industry more generally, it is proposed to forward the measure to the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Fisheries and Food for its information.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_26">There are no CFSP measures under category 4 and no title VI TEU or title IV TEC measures for consideration under category 5.  Category 6 concerns early warning notes.  EWN C142-05 is a notice of initiation of a partial interim review of the anti-dumping measures applicable to imports of polyester staple fibres originating in the Republic of Korea.  Given that there are no reported difficulties for Ireland, it is proposed that this trade matter does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">EWN C150-15 is a notice of initiation of a partial interim review of the anti-dumping measures applicable to imports of trichloroisyanuric acid originating in the People's Republic of China.  Given that there are no reported difficulties for Ireland, it is proposed that this trade matter does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">There are no proposals proposed for further scrutiny under categories 7, 8 and 9.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Business of Joint Committee. </heading>
        <speech by="#JohnPerry" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_29">Do members have any issue to raise before we adjourn?  If we need to have a meeting to deal with the subsidiarity issue, we can do so.  I hope members enjoy the rest of the summer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Senator Paddy Burke</from>
          <p eId="para_30">Are we not meeting next week?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPerry" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_31">We could have a meeting on the issue of subsidiarity on Thursday, 10 September.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Deputy Joe Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_32">We have a think-in on 9 September and 10 October.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPerry" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_33">The deadline is 14 September.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanConnick" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Seán Connick</from>
          <p eId="para_34">Fianna Fáil is having a think-in on 14 September.  We are waiting until the Labour Party is finished to see what it thinks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Deputy Joe Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_35">Would it be possible to meet the preceding week?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AengusOSnodaighSF" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh</from>
          <p eId="para_36">How about the first week in September?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPerry" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_37">Would Thursday, 3 September, suit?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy Joe Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_38">It would suit me.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelKitt" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Deputy Michael P. Kitt</from>
          <p eId="para_39">I suppose the Chairman will have tickets for the All-Ireland final around that time or for whoever needs them, but that is not something about which I will have to worry.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCostelloLAB" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Joe Costello</from>
          <p eId="para_40">Hurling or football.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPerry" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_41">Many old men — or Kerrymen — will be looking for tickets at the time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelKitt" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Michael P. Kitt</from>
          <p eId="para_42">That is right.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">The joint committee adjourned at 12.30 p.m. until noon on Thursday, 3 September 2009.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
