<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food/2009-10-08/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food/2009-10-08/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2009-10-08" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/30/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food/2009-10-08/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food/2009-10-08/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2009-10-08" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food/2009-10-08/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food/2009-10-08/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference eId="#vol_None" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None" showAs="Vol. None"/>
          <oir:numberReference eId="#no_None" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None/no/None" showAs="No. None"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AndrewDoyle" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Andrew-Doyle.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Andrew Doyle"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BobbyAylward" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Bobby-Aylward.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Bobby Aylward"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ChristyOSullivan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Christy-O'Sullivan.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Christy O'Sullivan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="EamonScanlon" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Eamon-Scanlon.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Eamon Scanlon"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnCartyFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Carty.D.2002-06-06" showAs="John Carty"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnnyBrady" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Johnny-Brady.D.1997-06-26" showAs="Johnny Brady"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MartinFerrisSF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Martin-Ferris.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Martin Ferris"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MattieMcGrath" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mattie-McGrath.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Mattie McGrath"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelCreed" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-Creed.D.1989-06-29" showAs="Michael Creed"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NedOKeeffe" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ned-O'Keeffe.S.1982-05-13" showAs="Ned O'Keeffe"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PJSheenan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/P-J-Sheehan.D.1981-06-30" showAs="P. J. Sheehan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulBradford" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Bradford.S.1987-04-25" showAs="Paul Bradford"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanSherlock" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Sherlock.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Sean Sherlock"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TomMcEllistrimFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Tom-McEllistrim.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Tom McEllistrim"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TomSheahan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Tom-Sheahan.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Tom Sheahan"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chair" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chair" showAs="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chairman" showAs="Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>COMHCHOISTE UM THALMHAÍOCHT, IASCAIGH AGUS BIA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>JOINT COMMITTEE ON AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2009-10-08">Déardaoin, 8 Deireadh Fómhair 2009</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2009-10-08">Thursday, 8 October 2009</docDate>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 11 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#BobbyAylward">Deputy Bobby Aylward,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulBradford">Senator Paul Bradford,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelCreed">Deputy Michael Creed,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#JohnCartyFF">Senator John Carty.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#AndrewDoyle">Deputy Andrew Doyle,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#MartinFerrisSF">Deputy Martin Ferris,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#TomMcEllistrimFF">Deputy Thomas McEllistrim,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#MattieMcGrath">Deputy Mattie McGrath,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#NedOKeeffe">Deputy Edward O’Keeffe,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#ChristyOSullivan">Deputy Christy O’Sullivan,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#EamonScanlon">Deputy Eamon Scanlon,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#TomSheahan">Deputy Tom Sheahan,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_13">
                  <person refersTo="#PJSheenan">Deputy P. J. Sheehan,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#JohnnyBrady">DEPUTY JOHNNY BRADY IN THE CHAIR.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Business of Joint Committee.</heading>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_14">We have a quorum.  I ask all members to ensure their mobile phones are turned off completely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Deputy Seán Sherlock</from>
          <p eId="para_15">I am sorry to interject.  The Communications (Retention of Data) Bill is before the Dáil.  I apologise because I am speaking on the Bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_16">I thank the Deputy.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">The joint committee went into private session at 11.05 a.m. and resumed in public session at 11.15 a.m.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Renewable Energy: Discussion with Micro Electricity Generation Association.</heading>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_18">On behalf of the committee, I welcome Mr. Dudley Stewart, Mr. Oisín McCann, Mr. Paul Carberry and Mr. Roderick Brennan, who are here today to make a presentation on renewable energy to the committee.  I draw to their attention the fact that members of the committee have absolute privilege but the same privilege does not apply to witnesses appearing before the committee.  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.  I now call on Mr. Dudley Stewart to make his opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_19">I thank the committee for allowing us to make our presentation.  When we first approached the committee, we were asked why were not appearing before the subcommittee on climate change and energy security.  We wanted to address this committee because we think the topic is of tremendous importance.  I will use a shortened version of the presentation we gave earlier to committee members.</p>
          <p eId="para_20">The title for our original report was "Rural Enterprise and Natural Energy are Historically Intertwined".  In Ireland we have the finest wind regimes, tremendous rainfall and ideal conditions for biomass, wind energy and water power.  The problem is that over the last few decades there have not been any real advances in these areas from the point of view of electricity generation.  Millions of euro have been wasted as delays continue in this area.</p>
          <p eId="para_21">The main actors in this area are the Departments of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs and Enterprise, Trade and Employment.  Farmers are naturally the main beneficiaries but job creation is a side effect of this industry.  There is an issue that energy is a matter for the Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources but that Department however has not been strong in dealing with rural projects.  It is not empowered to deal with job creation and is not in the business of promoting innovation.  Its job is to produce energy reliably for Ireland and, consequently, if we rely on that Department to provide energy solutions, we will be faced with competing lists of priorities.</p>
          <p eId="para_22">The Department faces challenging international targets for 2020 and 2050, with emissions from ageing fossil fuel stations to be addressed, along with rising costs of imported fuel and security of supply issues, increasing reliance on natural gas for electricity production, large-scale wind farm capacity escalation with growing intermittency problems and the massive emphasis on long-range ocean power projects of an enormous scale.  There are decisions to make about interconnectors and the Department has an underlying vision of Ireland being a net electricity exporter.  Its plate is full.</p>
          <p eId="para_23">We have looked at the Irish energy mix and how we have become dependent on natural gas, with a small contribution from renewables to date.  The contribution is growing but to get to the 2050 zero carbon emissions target set for Ireland, all possible assistance will be needed.  The Micro Electricity Generation Association is arguing for the production of electricity on a micro-level alongside conventional power stations powered by renewables.  We would go up to 1000 MW per producer and as low as 2 kW with microgeneration.  We are in the mixed area, which is not advancing at the pace it should be and we are here to see if we can make a better start.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">The main area of energy growth in Ireland is natural gas and electricity from wind farms.  Wind farms are causing a major problem of intermittency in the system and we have discovered that that intermittency problem is mitigating against other electricity forms.  We have a planned installation of 6,000 MW, which is equivalent to the entire capacity of the grid today.  In fact, if we installed that wind power system without doing anything else we would have massive intermittency problems here.</p>
          <p eId="para_25">While the wind power plans into 2020 are ongoing there is virtually nothing happening in the area of micro-electricity generation other than in the area of autoproducers, to which I will refer later.  There are no structures in place for people to get started in the micro-electricity generation area.  The Micro Electricity Generation Association, MEGA, has grown to plug that gap and provide structures.  It is not just a lobbying organisation.  We do not exist to represent industry bodies.  We exist because there are difficulties holding back the advancement of this industry and we intend to take action to try to remove those difficulties.  MEGA is prepared to go as far as removing the tariff cloud issue, which is causing a delay in this area, but MEGA will be unable to succeed without a proper linkage with the Government in terms of its planning.  We are here to put forward the case for an interdepartmental advisory committee and we would like that area to start here.</p>
          <p eId="para_26">I will now highlight the area of autoproducers.  In the past year the Commission for Energy Regulation has opened up the area of autoproducers.  Autoproducer simply means to install an energy producing device for one's own use only and, consequently, there is no tariff involved.  That has become a suitably Irish solution to an Irish problem.  I am delighted to report that there is major growth in the area of autoproducer machines going into farms and use by dairy producers.  These are large machines ranging from 200 kW to 800 kW.  They have the advantage of scale and the electricity produced from them is cheap and accessible.  However, that is clouding a more complex issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">These autoproducers cause intermittency problems of their own.  It is a fact that the wind blows sometimes and sometimes it does not blow.  This September we had many days without wind.  MEGA is introducing the concept of autoproducing clusters for which we have got support.  Autoproducing clusters are clusters of people from producers of electricity from a wide range of different renewables to users of electricity, all within a local area network, a local area network being the 20 kV system.  Within that system we can use smart technology and new innovations to make it possible for a producer to trade with a user and create a stable and reliable electricity system with non-intermittencies within a cluster area.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">Our objective is to produce 30 of those at 5 MW a shot; that is 150 MW of mixed renewables, "mixed" being wind, water, solar, biomass, biofuels but also electricity recycling, which is battery power and other types of storage.  I have a chart showing the way we look at that.  We look at the electricity intermittency problem in a different way.  We look at the surplus of electricity as a source of cheap electricity to be used and recycled.  The recycling of electricity fills the gaps where production is not available within our clusters.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">What we are offering to the ESB, and we have got good feedback from the ESB on this issue, is that whatever we put in in an autocluster in a local area we will take it out in a local area at the same time and if we cannot take it out, we shall dump it temporarily until we can do so.  If we are short of electricity, we will use conventionals to back up the system.  In other words, we are presenting a solution which is grid neutral and it cannot be refused.  Naturally, we will not be able to do that on our own.</p>
          <p eId="para_30">In terms of what a local area network might look like, the members have the chart supplied in front of them.  The red lines are no longer power lines; they are Internet connections.  At the centre is a square red box.  That is a small digital hub which operates a local area network.  That is basically servers and computers.  Connected to that is a range from small wind farms to small hydro to biofuel combined heat and power to electricity recycling, which could be battery or otherwise, and even electric cars, along with users who are factories, hospitals, households who possibly have a multi-tariffing system depending on their usage.  Differential tariffing is the secret.  For every extra advantage given to a renewable energy source, one should be able to earn an extra award.  With the current tariffing systems in Ireland one can only earn the one tariff so why bother making things better?  We argue that the future in our area will be about differential tariffing.</p>
          <p eId="para_31">Crude electricity will be intermittent.  It will be cheap so that it can go to somebody else.  It can be bought by somebody else to be recycled and turned into a more refined product.  Semi-refined would be a basic mix.  Refined would be a smart mix — highly reliable and compatible with a power station.  Highly refined would be recycled electricity on call, that is, storage, and super refined would be long storage and spinning reserve.</p>
          <p eId="para_32">A smart auto cluster could replace a fossil fuel power station with a total mix of renewables, making the best use of all of our natural energy resources including biomass, wind, water and solar.  Underpinning that will be the need for some form of control system, buy and sell system and a renewable obligation system, that is, a type of payment for renewables.</p>
          <p eId="para_33">Recently, the Commission for Energy Regulation commented on our proposals.  The CER has backed all our proposals, and we appear to have the ESB completely on our side.  The CER recently stated:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_34">Taking account of the views expressed by MEGA the Commission accepts that the potential exists for projects to be clustered together in a complementary manner.... [These products] are pre-approved for processing outside the GPA system.</p>
          <p eId="para_35">That is a major possibility.</p>
          <p eId="para_36">The door appears to be open to move forward but the structures are not in place.  We need those structures to be put in place.</p>
          <p eId="para_37">In the meantime I want to make the following factual statement.  The picture on the slide of a letter is the usual problem entrepreneurs must face.  It is a letter from the Revenue Commissioners stating that a farmer who produces electricity is in a different business from farming and consequently cannot reclaim VAT on the equipment he or she installs.  Ireland is saying, therefore, that electricity is not a legitimate product of a farm.  We intend to take on that issue but how can we move forward if an issue as simple as that arises?  The Revenue Commissioners do not understand that if one produces electricity on a farm it is a farm product.  This is the modern world.</p>
          <p eId="para_38">A range of wind generators continue to be stuck on the grid delivering electricity to the grid.  They get no tariff.  Everyone is confused about who should pay a tariff.  To the outsider it appears as if we have got the worst possible regime for micro-electricity generation in all of Europe, and billions of euro in rewards are going down the drain.  EU Directive 2009/28/EC states that we should not be doing this and we must stop.  Committees we participate in spend all their time working out plans to ensure we can minimise what we have to do and avail of the opportunity we have of using our resources to build our economy, create jobs and exploit all our abundant natural energy resources.</p>
          <p eId="para_39">We want an interdepartmental committee.  We have been through this previously with Pádraig Ó hUigín and Paddy Teahon formerly of the Department of the Taoiseach.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_40">I ask Mr. Stewart to refrain from mentioning any names.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_41">I apologise.  In the years of high emigration and when projects such as the International Financial Services Centre, Temple Bar and so forth were being considered, interdepartmental committees that were enthusiastic about such projects became the way forward.  We suggest that this is the place to start building an interdepartmental committee.  We have spent months trying to get to this table.  We targeted this committee specifically because we believe it is the committee that will understand us best.  However, apart from that, we are calling on senior civil servants who believe in what we are saying to step forward, help us move this important agenda forward and find some way of creating the interdepartmental culture to do that.  The Departments involved are those with responsibility for agriculture, rural enterprise, enterprise, employment, trade, transport, environment and energy.</p>
          <p eId="para_42">I thank the members of the committee for their attention.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_43">Thank you, Mr. Stewart.  I will now take questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_44">I thank Mr. Stewart.  I am also a member of the climate change committee, along with Deputy Aylward.  Has Mr. Stewart spoken to the climate change committee?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_45">Not yet.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_46">I am glad to clarify that as I could not recall having heard this submission previously.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_47">We are a renewable energy development group but we specifically sought a meeting with this committee because of the huge link between rural enterprise and agriculture.  Unless we work with people who understand that area, we do not believe we can advance.  The advantages are huge for rural areas.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_48">I do not disagree with anything Mr. Stewart has said, and I welcome the fact that he has come to inform the agriculture committee today.  There is an issue about land use and the Revenue Commissioners.  They have not moved with the times to understand that there must be a clearer definition of land use instead of strictly defining it as agricultural production.  There is land use production.  The Commission for Energy Regulation has an important role.  If the comments attributed to the commission indicate its genuine belief, it should be the body making the submission to the Revenue Commissioners with regard to how small energy production units such as the ones described are considered for tax purposes.</p>
          <p eId="para_49">With regard to the point Mr. Stewart made about committees, there is a Cabinet sub-committee on climate change and the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food is a member of it, along with the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government and the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources.  There is at least a template there for establishing a working group and the MEGA submission should feed into that.</p>
          <p eId="para_50">There is huge potential.  Does Mr. Stewart envisage the cluster production units replacing some of the existing peat burning stations, which are getting old?  Could they be replaced by such a system?  They seem to have the network in place whereby they could feed into the national network.  Or does he envisage the cluster units becoming more like the combined heat and power plants one sees in Scandinavia and other places, which supply populations of 10,000 or 20,000?  Is it a case of developing new systems or tapping into the existing network and replacing old energy production systems?</p>
          <p eId="para_51">When we met Commissioner Boel she spoke about the areas that must be addressed in the CAP health check.  One of them is forestry as a carbon sink.  She said that agricultural production and renewable energy must be examined together.  People are talking about it at that level, so there is recognition that the roles of agriculture, rural development and energy production can be combined.  Mr. Stewart is probably a little ahead of his time but it seems to be the way forward.  However, the issue is how the logistics of the systems will work when they are put into place.  Will new networks have to be established?  Most people would worry about fluctuations in the supply of power and when there is no power available in the cluster.  Mr. Stewart spoke about stability of production.  The main issue is how to make that work smartly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TomSheahan" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Tom Sheahan</from>
          <p eId="para_52">I know somebody who is involved in this and he told me the ESB is choking this industry.  Can Mr. Stewart confirm or clarify this?  He referred to the tariff.  Let us say somebody generates a certain number of kilowatts and has a surplus that he wishes to supply to the national grid.  There is no way to do that and I am led to believe the ESB is not being co-operative.  The person explained that the ESB is blocking the development of these micro electricity generators.  I know several farmers who made inquiries about having one of the generators on their farms but due to the red tape and bureaucracy involved, they turned their backs on it.  Many other sites have been identified as suitable; for example, a number of the links golf courses throughout the country would be suitable sites as well.  However, there appears to be a blockage.  I believe everything should be done to support this initiative and drive it forward but the blockage appears to be caused by the Department and the ESB.  That is my understanding.  Can Mr. Stewart confirm or deny that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_53">Does Mr. Stewart wish to reply?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_54">Yes.  I will deal with the first questions because they relate to the second one.  With regard to smart autoproducer clusters, there are two phases involved.  One phase involves getting the other stakeholders to understand the reliability of the solutions we are putting forward as an autoproducing cluster.  Autoproducing clusters already exist between farms in Germany.  The technology is already there.  We suggest capping the autoproducing clusters at the CER's cap of 5 MW.  That is not equivalent to a peat powered power station.  However, building an autoproducing cluster around a peat fired power station would eventually provide a solution to replace the station over time.  Our argument is that time is running out.  A long time will be required to prepare for 2050, therefore, we need to learn now how to do the smart clustering.</p>
          <p eId="para_55">Second, once we start smart clustering, we will go into the lead in Europe.  Europe is obsessed with developing smart grids.  We say the short cut to smart grids is through smart clusters because everything in terms of the communications elements involved in smart grids is involved in smart clusters.  The only difference is that we do everything behind the meter.  We do not interfere with the ESB network system.  Whatever stabilisation we need to do, we do it behind the consumer meter.  It is light-footed and means that it does not require ESB networks to get into a big knot over it.  It is a bit of both in that it involves a bit of new and a bit of replacing.</p>
          <p eId="para_56">It is not about self-sufficient communities.  Our members are entrepreneurs and their motivation is business.  An autoproducing cluster is between consenting adults who entered into agreement because, first, they wanted cheaper electricity and, second, they want to make electricity because they have the resources to do it and they are prepared to go into differential tariffing systems.  They are linked immediately to a customer and they have a future they can build together with those customers.  They are replacing power station capacity in that area because their build-up is reliable.  In discussions with the ESB, we said that if we prove to it by doing 150 MW over five years that we can get the stability of supply it needs, including the spinning reserve, then it will be able to look at a situation where one of these things could be seen as a power station.  We are beginning to look at something that can expand and multiply rapidly.  That would also put us ahead of the game.  In fact, it would put us more ahead of the game than Ocean Park because we would be right in the middle of the game.  We would have a field of play that would allow our young engineers and physicists to develop the necessary competitive skills.  Without overemphasising the word "smart", there is a huge amount of computer and networking skills involved.</p>
          <p eId="para_57">Moving on to the issue of ESB choking, the whole ESB thing is terribly frustrating for everyone.  On the other hand, however, we have to look beyond our frustrations to see what is at the source of this problem.  We must remind ourselves that the Competition Authority went into the ESB in 2004 and tore it apart.  Many of the things the ESB was able to do then, it cannot do in the same way now.  There are vacuums all over the place and it is hugely frustrating to fill those vacuums.  That is why the MEGA organisation came together and said it would fill these vacuums, creating a framework, a buyer and seller structure, and putting in those smart things.  We are looking towards a situation whereby we can solve the problem for the ESB so that it is taking less flak</p>
          <p eId="para_58">A typical letter from the ESB said that one can get connected but one cannot get a tariff.  We should be able to respond to that person and say that we will give them a tariff, find a use for their little bit of electricity and will use smart technology for it.  That is what we are proposing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinFerrisSF" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Deputy Martin Ferris</from>
          <p eId="para_59">Go raibh maith agat.  I thank Mr. Stewart for the presentation, which is encouraging from the point of view of rural Ireland.  The movement towards self-sufficiency and security is to be applauded.  I have no doubt that if this gets up and running it will reduce energy costs substantially, which can be beneficial particularly as we have seen so many jobs lost in rural Ireland as a result of current energy costs.  As Mr. Stewart said, it is down to having a structure with all the various Departments working together in harmony towards the ultimate objective of certainty.</p>
          <p eId="para_60">Would I be correct in saying that the problem with wind energy is intermittent production?  Mr. Stewart referred to autoproducer clusters whereby various methodologies of energy production are tied in.  I am well aware of that because I live in an area where there is quite a lot of wind energy development.  I can look out my door and see that on some days the turbines are not turning.  I take it that production is dependent on conventional methods at that point.  Will Mr. Stewart elaborate on the situation concerning autoproducer clusters?  He mentioned wave energy, but not tidal energy.  Is that not factored into this?  Experiments are currently taking place on parts of the Shannon estuary with strong tidal currents, which offer huge potential using reversible turbines.  Perhaps such a scheme could contribute in its own way.</p>
          <p eId="para_61">Mr. Stewart also referred to recycling, as well as wind, wave and solar energy, but he did not mention tidal energy.  Is there a reason for that omission?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulBradford" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Senator Paul Bradford</from>
          <p eId="para_62">I thank the delegation for its excellent presentation, which was most interesting.  May I ask a question about international best practice in this field?  While I would not say the presentation is futuristic, it is a bit aspirational, even though we would love to see that aspiration being fulfilled.  As a small country we often find it difficult to be pioneers — we follow rather than lead.  It would be great if we could become a world leader in this field.  What are the examples of international best practice along the lines Mr. Stewart is suggesting, including his vision or dream?  Where is it currently closest to being realised in other countries with perhaps the same attributes as Ireland's?  Are there some countries to which we can refer as examples of how things could, should or, more important, are being done?  It would be helpful to us if we could share ideas, as well as political and economic approaches, along the lines of countries where this system is effectively up and running.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p class="" eId="para_63">I am sorry for being late, but I am a member of the Committee of Public Accounts, which has clashed with this meeting this morning.  I welcome the delegation.  I am a great believer in alternative energy sources.  The directive is the right way to go and we have to get more support from the Government and public institutions in this regard.  Economics come into everything, which is the way forward.  I come from an intensive farming area with huge dairy herds and pig farms.  The monthly electricity bill for a dairy farm of 200 cows is roughly €1,000.  It could be as high as €10,000 for a large-scale pig farm where there is milling and mixing.  What can such farmers, of whom there are a number in my area, do to reduce their electricity costs by using alternative energy sources?  How viable is a wind turbine and what is the capital cost involved?  We can talk all day about ideas, policies and structures but we have to apply practical economics.  There is a difficult agricultural environment at present with many farmers under pressure in every area.  Can Mr. Stewart identify those two areas and tell me how I can help out farmers in my area of north Cork by reducing energy costs substantially in both dairy and pig farming?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_64">There are three basic issues here.  As regards tidal energy, an autoproducer cluster would maximise whatever renewable assets are there for people who wish to develop them.  Tidal energy is useful.  I was involved in some tidal feasibility studies back in the 1980s, which were good in Ireland.  There are no major complexities, apart from EPA issues.  It is really about being able to use the whole mix in a smart way, whereby the intermittency of one source is taken up by another so one can balance things out.</p>
          <p eId="para_65">The next issue raised was international best practice.  The Irish conditions are unique in that there is no other country in Europe where wind generators are connected to the grid but do not get any money, or where one rings up electricity supply companies who cannot say whether there is a tariff.  The existing autoproducing clusters are friendly ones, such as in farming areas in Germany.  They are also in complexes, estates and domains where they are using the technology to share off from different generation sources.  Nobody has ever had to link it to an end-user consumer.  This innovation is Irish because of the Irish problem whereby nobody wants to pay tariffs.  I have been in this industry since 1976 and nobody has ever wanted to pay tariffs for these things.  Even when the big wind farms got a tariff it was always too low.  In order to get the renewables going we must get into a situation where consenting adults can decide what they are willing to pay for electricity.  We have to create our own market.  The innovation here is not in technology; it is in the introduction of differential tariffing in an autoproducer cluster so that one can incentivise such things as the storage of electricity for reuse later, one can penalise intermittency and one can afford to dump if necessary.</p>
          <p eId="para_66">On the question of economics, I would like to say that the autoproducer route will solve the entire problem but it will not because the economics do not always work out.  If the autoproducer cannot use all of the power from the wind generator, the water turbine or biomass, and if the autoproducer must shut off, the autoproducer is at a massive disadvantage because he or she may be working at half its capacity and, consequently, will not achieve the returns.  This is a stumbling block.</p>
          <p eId="para_67">The issue is, how to get that excess electricity that pig farmer does not want to another place where it is needed.  One such place would be a refrigeration plant — refrigeration plants have built-in storage — or some other kind of business.  The autoproducing cluster, which we cannot roll out without a proper framework structure to do it reliably because certain undertakings would have to be given to the CER and to the ESB about reliability, is not there yet but it does give one the economics needed.</p>
          <p eId="para_68">There is one other matter I must mention.  Under the EU directives it is considered that people who are moving in to replace fossil fuels with renewables should be compensated under a renewable obligation system.  We do not have such a system rolled out properly in Ireland.  We only have it for certain small sectors.  The economics of this requires a renewable obligation system to be included.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_69">We might have it on Monday after the Green Party agreement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_70">Allow Mr. Stewart to continue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_71">I am sure Deputy Creed would be in agreement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_72">At present, we do not have it and we are fighting hard to get it.  Even our autoproducer clusters are depending on having it.  It is an anomaly in Europe.  Ireland is the only country in Europe that has no such thing.  The public services obligation, PSO, legislation was put in place specifically to do this and it is not used for this purpose.  In the recent decision, the CER stated that he thought it should be but that he needs to be instructed by the Minister to move in that direction.  There is a quagmire in that regard that needs to be resolved in order to resolve it for the pig farmer.  We are very close.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_73">I thank Mr. Stewart.  What would be the capital requirement of setting up such a development?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_74">Deputy Doyle has another question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_75">Fifteen or 16 years ago I visited a famous cheesemaker with his own dairy herd in Wexford who was harvesting the slurry gas through his own large digester system.  As I understood, he was able to feed surplus electricity into the grid and draw out of it in the summer time when he needed it.  Maybe it was in its infancy then and the ESB was accommodating an odd person, but there seemed to be some sort of an arrangement where he could do it at the time.  It is possible.  Definitely, my impression was that was happening.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_76">There is a renewable energy feed-in tariff, REFIT, system in place.  There are many gaps in it where it is not certain who should be paying for the electricity.  In one case, for instance, the Minister has involved ESB Networks in making a payment which, in European terms, would be illegal.  A network distributor should not be paying for electricity.</p>
          <p eId="para_77">However, there is a REFIT; the tariff is approximately 7 cent, which is far below its value.  The current cost of production of electricity from a coal-fired station at wholesale prices is 10 cent.  If one has a wind generator providing renewable electricity and reducing emissions, and one is buying from it at 7 cent only, the renewable is being penalised.  It can be convenient to get that income flow if one has an excess, and many water-power generations are operating on 7 cent, but it is not a situation that can mushroom.  It is accidental that this works out for this particular entrepreneur and it does not work out for everybody else because it is not economic.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_78">What would be the capital requirement for the kind of project I mentioned where the monthly ESB bills are €10,000 or €12,000?  If there is surplus electricity on the wind farm with one wind generator, can one supply a neighbour through the existing ESB network?  Will the ESB buy that and transfer it?  Under the deregulation programme of the European Union, there is a regulation under which the ESB must transmit, as in the case of the telephone system.  That is the law of Europe and of Ireland, is it not?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_79">There are new rules in Europe about the obligation to connect to the grid.  There are existing arrangements such as those Airtricity uses in which there is a licence and larger scale dislocation of power from one source to the various different customers, but there is nothing that can be used in the micro electricity generation area because none of the companies wants to play that game because it is a little more complex than the game they themselves are playing and it means engineering, in other words, it is not just buy and sell.</p>
          <p eId="para_80">The capital cost depends on how much of one's other costs a person is trying to displace.  They could range from as low as €60,000 to as high as €2 million.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_81">How many megawatts would one get from wind development?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_82">Some 1,000 MW.  One is displacing €60,000 at that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_83">Could Ireland produce all of its electricity from wind?</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_4">(Interruptions).</summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_84">Should I answer this?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_85">Let Mr. Stewart answer the question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_86">Ireland can probably export wind energy.  It just needs the grid system to do it, but it also needs both local stability and local production in the electricity system so that the grid system will not be taken up totally transporting intermittent electricity.  In terms of supplying all of its energy needs, Ireland could probably do it by exporting, and, certainly, using offshore, but that is a long way off.  What it requires, however, is all of the other mixes to grow and to work in some sort of intelligent way.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_87">What "other mixes" has Mr. Stewart in mind?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_88">There is water — hydro is under-utilised and we must take on courageous measures in that area; biomass; solar, for which there is a role; tidal; wave, when it comes on stream; and food and animal wastes, all of which are sources of energy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_89">Is wave an expensive way of doing it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_90">Wave is probably negligible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Mr. Paul Carberry</from>
          <p eId="para_91">On trying to put a business case together for a number of farms, we have been working with the poultry industry recently and looking at the bills in that sector.  While one can get very near to a business case, there are a couple of matters that will knock it off.  For instance, I have seen the business case of Quest Foods in Lusk which put in an 1,800 kW machine.  Given the investment, they should pay back the capital cost within six years.  The company has 100 jobs created in that.  That has certainly given the company a cheap supply of electricity and it is sustaining a number of jobs.</p>
          <p eId="para_92">When we go to a smaller micro level than that such as, typically, the dairy farmer mentioned whose annual bills are in the region of €7,000 to €8,000, one is probably looking at using a 15 kW to 20 kW machine.  Given their efficiencies and the wind speeds in the area concerned, that type of equipment is what one would need.  The difficulty with that is the VAT issue.  The VAT will make up at least 21% of the overall cost of the project.  It immediately throws the business case out the window as the payback is over too long a period, for instance, if one wanted to look for bankability on it.  I am aware of a case where a dairy farmer in a good area which enjoys high wind speeds could have a wind turbine that would meet his needs.  However, the business case has been overturned because the Revenue has wrongly defined the energy relating thereto, which was actually going into the business.  A letter was actually sent to a dairy farmer who purchased a generator.  Obviously, he is furious.</p>
          <p eId="para_93">The business cases are there to be made.  I am mindful of what happened with REPS in recent years and the payments that were made.  If there was a scheme in place which, through the use of microgrids or whatever, might encourage farmers to take this up, it would be welcome.  As stated earlier, we considered the area of poultry last week and we had a very good case for a 50 kW machine.  That business case came unstuck in respect of two issues, namely, VAT and the fact that for 20% of the time the poultry plant is closed down because of the need to change the batches.  For 12 weeks of the year — approximately 20% — we are exporting with a turbine that has zero or very little tariff.  The tariff definition is extremely difficult.  If, as we have done with some of these, one goes through the normal channels, one must approach the utilities in order to negotiate one's own tariffs.  However, a definition of what constitutes a tariff is not provided.  It could be 7 cent but there is no one to provide guidance.  A tariff of 7 cent would not be good enough.</p>
          <p eId="para_94">We are nearly there.  We have the best energy resource in Europe if not the world.  We have these rural plants which could create jobs and at which electricity could be produced on site.  As Mr. Stewart stated, the anomalies that exist in our system have already been removed in Germany and other countries where the authorities possessed greater foresight.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_95">Is that from wind generation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Mr. Paul Carberry</from>
          <p eId="para_96">Yes, from wind.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_97">We must bring this part of our deliberations to a close.  As members are aware, we have a meeting with Members of the Northern Ireland Assembly at 1 p.m. and we want to conclude this meeting at 12.50 p.m.  In such circumstances, I ask members to be brief.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MattieMcGrath" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Deputy Mattie McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_98">I thank our guests for attending and I compliment MEGA on its work.  What has been the level of take-up in respect of these cluster developments?  Are community groups and organisations interested in becoming involved?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_99">There is huge interest.  Even the EPA has approached us in respect of its desire to be at the centre of a cluster.  A number of county councils have inquired with regard to whether they might establish municipal power companies within autoproducer clusters.  We will be visiting the Aran Islands next week, where the ESB and SEI are involved.  However, we have been asked to intervene in respect of the autoproducer clusters because they think they can move ahead faster with this system, which is easier to implement.</p>
          <p eId="para_100">We are of the view that it should be limited to 30 autoproducing clusters — producing 5 MW each, 150 MW in total — in the first five years.  This would go a long way towards meeting our obligations on renewables.  We need districts to compete.  The sensible thing to do in operating autoproducer clusters is to proceed with the easiest projects first and leave the most difficult until last.  We must, therefore, accept areas on the basis that those who live in such areas are in favour of and excited about autoproducer cluster, that the relevant renewable assets are available and that the type of consumers who would want to obtain this type of differential tariff and enjoy energy savings are present.  Initially, it would not be an ideal roll-out.  It would have to be a roll-out based on candidacies from different areas.  However, everywhere we go there is major interest.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ChristyOSullivan" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Deputy Christy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_101">What is our guests' opinion on the combination of hydro and wind generation?  I refer to installations where water is pumped while the wind blows.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_102">That happens to be my area of speciality.  Once upon a time, the scale involved was an extremely important issue in the economics of pump storage.  Curiously, with the cost of opposition and various other costs coming into play on major projects, micro-pump storage systems are becoming much more viable and easier to put in place.  There is an engineering company in Wexford which is commencing its first prototype micro-electricity storage plants.  These will come in black-box units that will be easy to install and there will be very little engineering required.  Consequently, there will be a growth in very small-scale micro-pump storage.  There must, however, be a market for this.  A person who owns a micro-pump storage unit must be able to buy cheap electricity and sell it at a profit.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ChristyOSullivan" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Deputy Christy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_103">Is there potential for large-scale development in the area of combined hydro and wind generation?  Ireland is probably very suitable for such generation, particularly as there are large valleys which might be dammed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Mr. Dudley Stewart</from>
          <p eId="para_104">Apart from biomass, that is the most exciting area of all.  It is just an accident of history that the harnessing of water power in Ireland did not really happen.  There are countless rivers in this country and these represent a major resource.  We are going to be obliged to deal with some of the cultural and ecological issues in respect of this matter.  People must understand that the putting in place of dams can actually benefit rivers.  In my opinion, development in this area is going to be 50% of the solution.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_105">On behalf of the committee, I thank Mr. Stewart and his colleagues for their presentation and for answering members' questions.  Is it agreed to suspend proceedings for a couple of minutes in order to facilitate their departure and the arrival of the next group?  Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">Sitting suspended at 12.05 p.m. and resumed at 12.10 p.m.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Renewable Energy: Discussion with Green Energy Growers Association.</heading>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_106">I welcome Ms Ann Kehoe and Mr. Robert Ronan from the Green Energy Growers Association, GEGA, who are here to make a presentation on the potential production of renewable energy from agriculture, and I thank them for attending.  Before we commence, I draw their attention to the fact that members of this committee have absolute privilege but the same privilege does not apply to witnesses appearing before it.  Members are also reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House, or an official, by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.  I call on Ms Kehoe to make her presentation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_107">I thank the Chairman for the opportunity to make a presentation to the committee.  We are aware of the time constraints involved and we would like, therefore, to provide a brief background in respect of what we have achieved since our establishment in 2006, outline our targets for the future and indicate a couple of matters regarding which we may seek assistance from members.  The documentation with which members were presented may be missing some of the pictures that I intend to show as part of this PowerPoint presentation.  This is because it takes some time to e-mail such pictures and also photographs.</p>
          <p eId="para_108">The Green Energy Growers Association, GEGA, is a non-profit national organisation which was established by people who own land, namely, farmers.  We wanted to focus on the type of renewable energy the land could be used to produce.  We examined the marketplace carefully and invested our own money in our activities.  We have never asked for or received funding from anyone other than our members.  People such as Mr. Ronan and I invested our money at the outset in order to carry out research, ensure that we were moving in the right direction and obtained the knowledge and information required to make what we set out to do happen.  The primary drivers behind this marketplace were climate change and energy security.  We import billions of euro worth of fossil fuels every year.  This is a good market to head into because it will grow and develop.</p>
          <p eId="para_109">When we examined the sources of renewable energy, we had to look at what farmers can produce efficiently and effectively to generate a commercial return and income into the future.  Bioenergy sources are biomass — farm and forestry — biogas, which is related to using anaerobic digestion as waste, bioliquid, which generally comes from seed crops; and our natural resources, wind and water.  We have to focus on one to proceed.  Even though all the resources will all be part of the answer to the provision of energy long into the future, we focused on biomass as a crop that could be grown and harvested to generate a return every year.  Biomass can be trees, plants, crops, straw and so on.  The harvest is converted into solid bioenergy via pellets, woodchip in bale format, briquettes, etc.  The crops are grown, harvested, chopped and converted into energy.  That was the simple format we wanted to look at.</p>
          <p eId="para_110">Forestry is also a good source of biomass but not every farmer will plant trees.  We looked at what crops could be used.  First, we considered industrial hemp because that is a rotational crop, which can fit into a tillage enterprise.  We grew more than 120 hectares in 2008 as a research project.  We did everything on a substantial basis in order that we could find out as much as we could in one season.  We grew it on a trial basis throughout the country from Wexford to Kerry to Meath.  The crop in the slide was grown in County Tipperary.  It grows to 12 ft.  We very much focused on high yielding crops in order that we would not affect the food-fuel balance.  Some people ask what will happen to our food industry because we produce so much energy from the land through biomass.  We have examined this extremely carefully and that is why we looked at high yielding crops that can produce between 15 and 20 tonnes of biomass per annum.  Industrial hemp can do that but we must conduct more research on it because there are difficulties relating to harvesting it.</p>
          <p eId="para_111">We looked at reed canary grass for marginal land.  Teagasc has taken up the trials and research on this for us and, hopefully, in a few years, it may be a possibility.  We focused on miscanthus, which is growing successfully.  The slide has a picture of Mr. John Stafford in Wexford alongside a miscanthus crop.  He is 6 ft. tall.  Miscanthus is a grass that produces between 15 and 20 tonnes of biomass per annum and takes three years to establish.  For example, if it was planted in 2007, it could not be harvested until this year but could be harvested annually after that.  It continues to grow and produce a yield every year without replanting for more than 20 years.  It is still producing high yields in the UK after 26 years.  When it is being established, one must ensure the proper nutrient is in the ground but the same nutrient is used every day to produce grass or corn.  Once it is fully established, there are no other inputs.  Perhaps after five years, a soil analysis could be conducted to ensure nutrients are still there.  It is a woody type straw or cane.  In other words, when it is harvested, it is like a bamboo.  That can be harvested with existing agricultural machinery.</p>
          <p eId="para_112">Ireland has the potential to produce 11 million tonnes of miscanthus biomass every year.  Given the abolition of set-aside, the cessation of sugar beet production, nutrient cross compliance, many farmers giving up milk production and various other issues, a lot of land is available.  Approximately 700,000 hectares could become efficient at producing biomass without impacting on existing food production.  Miscanthus comes from a seed, is planted and grows vigorously but it takes two years to fill out.  It grows 12 ft. tall every year and, therefore, can produce significant biomass per annum.</p>
          <p eId="para_113">When it comes to harvesting in the spring, the plant dries out, the leaves fall off and when the first cold hits, it becomes like a brown cane.  A conditioner mower is used to cut it down and it is left on the ground for between two and six weeks.  It can rain or snow or anything else because the crop dries from the inside out.  The outside is a glossy material which is not affected by rain.  A farmer has three months, January to March, to do this and must ensure the crop is off the ground by April when it starts to grow again.  If there are a few nice dry windy days, for example, in January or February, it is moved, left on the ground for a few weeks before there are two or three more nice dry, windy days to bale it.  Once it is baled, it is taken in and stored in a shed and this is the raw material ready to be converted into energy.</p>
          <p eId="para_114">As an association at this stage, we knew exactly what we wanted to grow, where and how to grow it and convert it into biomass but we had to ask how this could be done in a commercial fashion while ensuring the rural community and farmers were involved.  We set up and designed the GEGA national framework within which we helped to develop green energy service companies in seven regions.  Each is a private limited company and the first investors were 30 shareholders from the farming community.  They invested to bring the company through its first stage of development.  In other words, they set up the company, bought the equipment and helped to develop the first crops.  The seven companies have more than 1,000 hectares of miscanthus planted.  A green energy service company is a rural-based business that grows, stores and processes biomass into bioenergy products such as chip briquette or bale format.  The bale format can be fed on automatic systems into large commercial boiler systems to produce heat and electricity.</p>
          <p eId="para_115">The group of shareholders elected a board of directors to the seven companies.  Each company has six directors and, therefore, there are more than 40 directors across the country.  We have more than 200 shareholders from the agri-community.  As individuals and groups, we have invested more than €4 million to date in development, equipment, machinery, knowledge research and planting crops.  The Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food has been good in that it put in place an establishment grant for willow and miscanthus, which played a big part in developing the acreage we have.  It was put in place for three years, ending this year, but we were delighted that the Minister has announced a €20 million grant to be put in place for the next three years, 2010-2012.  The grant came under attack from other farm interests who query its provision when REPS is more important.  It is not like that.  The Government is looking far ahead and it is an investment in the future.  We hope we have the support of the committee for the grant when people make this argument.</p>
          <p eId="para_116">We know what we need to do for the future.  The final page lists benefits to the economy of what we have done and of taking it to the next stage, which is straight to the marketplace.  There are a few hurdles, the main one being finance.  Miscanthus, as a biomass material, is not a tried and tested product in this country and, therefore, when we approach financial institutions to put a commercial system in place or our potential customers do so, they say it is a little risky and they are not prepared to fund it.  They will talk about it and bring it to a certain stage, but the money is just not there.  We are encouraging the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food to use 20% of the €20 million budget to develop commercial systems in some of its facilities, such as Moorepark, Kildalton College in County Kilkenny or Johnstown Castle in County Wexford.  It would help to kick start this industry if we were able to bring bank officials and potential customers to such facilities and practically demonstrate how this high-tech business works.  That would create the confidence needed to take the final step.</p>
          <p eId="para_117">I emphasise three things.  First, we need help to hold on to the establishment grant announced.  Second, it would be fantastic if the Department invested in the installation of three systems in its facilities.  Less than €1 million is needed to kick start that process.  Third, the Department should consider using €3 million or €4 million of the existing €20 million budget that has been put aside for the next three years to install commercial systems elsewhere.  That would demonstrate the potential of this industry and help it to grow and develop.  I thank the Chairman and the members for their attention.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_118">I thank Ms Kehoe for her presentation.  I read with interest the document on willow and miscanthus.  Over the years, Professor Hugh Gordon pioneered this approach at Hillsborough.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_119">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_120">I would like to speak about the economic benefits of the work of these companies.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_121">There are seven companies.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_122">Does the Green Energy Growers Association have plants and processes to produce the final energy product?  Is it produced as a bale or as a pellet?  Does the association have a network of boilers?  Has a critical mass been achieved to ensure an economic return?  I am trying to remember where I heard the association's presentation previously.  I do not know whether I saw Ms Kehoe on television or met her at some other forum.  The challenge has always been to strike a balance between producing enough material and ensuring one does not interfere with the supply to the food chain.  We need to use land that was not primarily used for food production in the past.  With that in mind, how big does Ms Kehoe envisage that this sector will get?  If its growth is somewhat limited, can it reach a consistent critical mass?  A few years ago, people were intermittently engaged in the pellet manufacture and pellet boiler businesses.  Problems were encountered with reliability of supply and the market.  Each one needed the other.  It was an example of the "chicken and egg" syndrome.  Can Ms Kehoe give an idea of how she thinks this sector will develop?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MattieMcGrath" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Deputy Mattie McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_123">I welcome Ms Kehoe and Mr. Ronan.  I thank them for their pioneering work in this field.  Perhaps this committee can take up the three important points they made.  What kind of land is suitable for the production of this crop?  Does it have to be good land?  Can hilly land be used?  Can the delegates indicate where the various production companies are located here?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ChristyOSullivan" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Deputy Christy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_124">Deputy McGrath asked one of the questions I had intended to ask.  Where can we see these companies in operation?  Seeing is believing in many cases of this nature.  What is the nearest location to west Cork, which is my part of the country?  I cannot say I have seen this grass growing in west Cork, although it may be there.  Perhaps I am not looking carefully enough.  I am interested in this concept.  Any potential source of energy must be considered seriously.  I am not up to speed on this sector.  I ask the delegates to put me in touch with someone who can show me what is happening.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_125">Does Deputy O'Keeffe wish to ask a question?  I would like to ask many questions on behalf of growers.  Where is the market for miscanthus which achieves a price of between €60 and €65 per tonne?  What transport charges are envisaged for hauling miscanthus to processing facilities?  What processing charges and costings were carried out before the price promise to farmers was determined?  If the market price for a forest residue is approximately €15 or €20 per tonne, can miscanthus compete in the energy market?  Is a take-up pay contract in place to guarantee farmers the price that is being quoted, or is the entire price structure aspirational?  What investment has been made in developing an end use for miscanthus?  Have the growers applied for planning permission for processing plants?  What tonnage is expected to be harvested this winter or spring?  Can the association explain the failure of approximately 20 crops of miscanthus this year?  Reference has been made to a yield of 15 or 20 tonnes per hectare.  The UK's leading research organisation in this area has said that the average yield is approximately 10 tonnes per hectare.  What is the association's claim in this regard based on?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_126">The Chairman has asked all the questions.  He has been very well briefed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_127">I could ask a couple of more questions, but we have time constraints.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_128">I will try to answer most of the Chairman's questions.  He might remind me if I leave any question off the list.  I assure Deputy Doyle that we have researched this area carefully.  As we are investing our money in it, we have taken a very commercial view of it.  The balance between fuel and food is terribly important, as is the balance between supply and demand.  We have taken certain actions to kick start this industry.  In 2006, which was the first year, we planted a small number of acres in County Wexford.  No grant aid was available at that stage.  In 2007, we planted 150 hectares across the south east, in counties Kilkenny, Wexford and Tipperary.  The first three green energy service companies were set up at that time.  The four newer companies were set up at a later stage.  We have planted more than 1,000 hectares of miscanthus over the past three years.  We were keen to demonstrate practically all the things that can go right or wrong.  When we were planting, we imported seed and machinery but it did not work properly.  We then made our own manual planters to ensure that this crop was planted extremely well.  We have learned realistic lessons from our practical experience.  We do not process this plant into pellets.  We originally planned to develop a processing facility to produce pellets.  When the economy changed dramatically, the price of oil dropped.  We decided not to invest millions of euro in a processing plant to turn this material into pellets before selling it, as that would have added costs to the process.  We have worked closely with Carlow Institute of Technology, for example.  We are beginning another technical research programme with the institute at the end of this month.  Technology is very important in this industry.  We have signed a contract with a German company to supply guaranteed top-of-the-range miscanthus boilers.  When the big bales of miscanthus are fed into the boilers, chips will be produced automatically.  Can the members of the committee imagine the cost savings we have achieved from being able to do that?  The miscanthus is transported just once, from the farm to the point at which the energy is burnt.  One can burn miscanthus in chip or briquette form.  A miscanthus briquette processing facility will be developed in County Wexford before Christmas.  Anyone who wants to sell miscanthus briquettes will be able to send miscanthus to Wexgen Limited.  We do not believe in duplication and we will not reinvest in something that has already been done in a certain area.  One makes best use of everything that is available, for example, we make best use of farmer experience.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MattieMcGrath" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Deputy Mattie McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_129">In what areas are the green energy service companies located?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_130">The companies have similar names.  The company in Cork is Leegen Limited.  It has an office rather than a processing plant and is located just outside Cork city.  I will put Deputies in touch with its board of directors.  Members of the association have crops growing all over Cork.  The seven companies have not established separate processing facilities but seven businesses as this keeps costs as low as possible.  Six directors operate each company.  If a grower has a certain number of tonnes of miscanthus in a shed and we install a commercial boiler system in a local swimming pool, hotel or manufacturing facility, the directors of the green energy service company will co-ordinate to ensure that the miscanthus can be delivered straight into the premises provided it is a large bale format facility.  If that is not the case, we can rent a chipping machine for one day — we have carried out trials on this — and the grower can have the miscanthus chipped in a shed as close as possible to the end facility.  The supply chain has been developed in a manner which keeps costs as low as possible.  If we can compete with the current price of oil, the market can develop and provide real returns.</p>
          <p eId="para_131">The Chairman asked an important question about damaged crops.  About 20 crops were damaged this spring.  Teagasc lost one of its crops and all the companies had a damaged crop in 2008.  The damage in 2008 was caused by a combination of factors.  We had severe weather conditions from the time the crops were planted in 2008 which meant they were exposed to cold, wet conditions and were tightly compacted.  When weed control was used in the spring of 2009, the Roundup somehow went into the rhizome and damaged it.  We will re-establish the crops in the coming spring.  We are learning from what has happened and are working particularly closely with Teagasc.  We have also worked closely with other companies, including Quinns of Baltinglass and JHM Crops.  We know what happened and what we need to do to avoid similar cases in future.</p>
          <p eId="para_132">The price of €65 per tonne is not aspirational but is written into a supply contract.  It is the basic price to the grower and probably the lowest rate that will ever be paid to growers.  As the price of energy increases, so too does the price paid to the grower.  We have the interests of growers at heart because we are all growers.  Every shareholder who has invested in these companies is a farmer or grower.  Mr. Ronan and I are both growers.  The grower is our priority and at the core of everything we do.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_67">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_133">Ms Kehoe stated that the seven companies meet on occasion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_134">They meet every week.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_69">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_135">Would it not be preferable to have one national company running the entire operation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_136">The Green Energy Growers Association, a non-profit organisation, is the national body which helps to co-ordinate the companies.  The values of local production, supply, ownership and pride is the reason we have seven individual companies rather than one national company.  Renewable energy, particularly biomass, will depend on local production, supply and delivery to be cost effective.  As the companies develop, we may form one national company.  We have discussed the best way to develop and we have found there is a certain pride in each region to develop their activities at local level.  Community and team spirit is driving this process.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_137">Individuals cannot be a member of more than one board.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_138">They can be a member of more than one board, although it is not common.  I am the national director of the Green Energy Growers Association, a non-profit organisation.  My husband and I are farmers in County Tipperary and shareholders in Tippgen Limited, our local green energy service company.  I am also a director of Tippgen because the shareholders of the company elected me to that position.  It is important for me to keep abreast of the problems and challenges facing the companies.  The other directors are based in the respective regions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_139">Ms Kehoe is a member of all the boards.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_140">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MattieMcGrath" eId="spk_75">
          <from>Deputy Mattie McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_141">Does Ms Kehoe envisage a role for voluntary and community groups in promoting the sector?  Does she expect the sector to provide social capital for communities?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_142">It would be fantastic to provide energy to a school, nursing home or other facility with significant heat demand in every village.  However, there is no point providing heat for a school because it will be closed for two or three months of the year.  Green energy service companies could provide low cost biomass heat in community facilities.  We have been contacted by a Deputy from County Kildare with regard to a community which would like to do something in a community centre, school and crèche in a housing estate.  We will meet the Deputy in question and do what any company would do, that is, carry out a study to determine whether there is a business case for becoming involved in the project.  This would initially mean bringing in the product from outside.  We would then encourage local farmers, located in a cluster around the facility, to become growers and within two years they could be producing the biomass.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MattieMcGrath" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Deputy Mattie McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_143">I asked about the type of land used for miscanthus production.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_144">In the early days, word went out that miscanthus could be grown in any type of soil.  Miscanthus is like any crop.  The Chairman asked about tonnage and yield.  If one grows miscanthus on poor land, it will, like any crop, produce a poor yield.  If one grows it on top class land, one will get a yield of 20 tonnes per hectare.  If one grows it on relatively good ground that produces grass, maize or corn, it will produce a good yield.  We have learned from experience that one does not grow miscanthus on poor land, although it can be grown on damp, moist or heavy land.  However, one must be careful and ensure that it is possible to access and move machinery on the land in March to harvest the crop.</p>
          <p eId="para_145">Miscanthus is planted as a rhizum, a type of root, in the first year.  This root grows underground to one metre in diameter and creates a table under the soil.  While it does not miraculously dry out bogland, it creates a table which makes it much easier to travel on the land.  We may not have been fussy enough in the first year about the type of land on which the crop was planted but we have become much more fussy.  We will visit the farm and dig holes to determine whether the land is suitable for miscanthus.  Those who know land will know immediately whether this is the case.</p>
          <p eId="para_146">Where little is known about land in terms of digging or ploughing, we will subsoil them to loosen up the soil and create oxygen in it.  It does not pay us to plant miscanthus in land that will not produce a very good crop.  The green energy service companies and energy users want a secure, cost-effective supply of biomass provided in a system with effective standards.  There is no single solution to renewable energy.  It will be a combination of biomass, wind energy and other forms of energy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_79">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_147">Miscanthus is obviously cut by a flail mower.  Ms Kehoe stated the root system forms an underground bed or table.  I am interested in the root system.  Does one have to keep planting every year?  Does one have to remove the roots at any stage?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_148">Only if one wishes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_149">Deputy McGrath has more or less asked my question.  I was wondering if the roots caused any difficulty when the land is being reinstated.  Are the roots fibrous and do they have to be removed?  I saw miscanthus growing near Barryroe in west Cork during the summer.  It looked fine.  It looked very good when it was harvested.  I did not know it was a rhizome.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_150">To return to Deputy McGrath's question about the quality of soil, the land is County Meath is as good as one would get in most parts of the country and some of the crops have not done that well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_151">I do not agree with that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_152">Perhaps it is not as good as the Golden Vale.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NedOKeeffe" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Deputy Edward O’Keeffe</from>
          <p eId="para_153">The Chairman should admit defeat.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_154">Will Ms Kehoe give a reason for that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_87">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_155">I know the crops to which the Chairman refers because we know the growers who are involved extremely well.  Some of the crops in County Meath were planted a little later in the year than we would have liked.  We think the rhizomes that were planted were a little small.  We can add to that the cold, wet soil conditions.  In 2008 miscanthus did not grow as well as in 2006 or 2007.  Even though it loves damp, it does not like the cold and the continuous rain.</p>
          <p eId="para_156">Roundup was used for weed control.  Miscanthus crops should be topped before one applies weed control.  Weed control is only necessary in the first and second year.  When Roundup was applied to the crops that had not been topped, it trickled down into the rhizome and damaged them.</p>
          <p eId="para_157">Given that we have invested so much in the development of the crops — it is our own money that we have invested — we have learned the hard way.  We did not sit back and wait three or four years for Teagasc or somebody else to do it.  Teagasc is doing valuable research and we work closely with it, but we have got stuck in and developed the crop ourselves.  It is natural that we made mistakes along the way, but we never made the same mistake a second time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ChristyOSullivan" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Deputy Christy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_158">Does one use special fertiliser or is there a need for any fertiliser?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_89">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_159">We are careful about doing a soil analysis if a person wants to grow the crop.  If it shows the soil is normal in terms of pH and nutrient value, then there is no need to add any fertiliser.  We recommend farmyard manure if it is available because it adds to the organic matter in the soil and oxygenates it, which helps the crop.  After the first harvest if pig slurry or farmyard manure is available it adds a bit of life and gives the crop a kick start to develop.  We do not recommend a chemical fertiliser unless the soil analysis shows the land is devoid of a particular mineral.  If a mineral is lacking we add it before we plant the crop.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_160">Does GEGA, Green Energy Growers Association, see itself expanding beyond miscanthus?  Is there any role for second generation crops such as straw?</p>
          <p eId="para_161">On Ms Kehoe's point about organic matter and the conflict with food production, what about the Bord na Móna peatland in the midlands?  Is it possible to sow miscanthus on that land?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_91">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_162">No.  We have researched the peatland and, unfortunately, peat seems to be unsuitable for the production of miscanthus.  We do not know whether that is due to the acid in the soil.  What was the second question?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_92">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_163">It was about second generation crops and diversifying beyond miscanthus.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_93">
          <from>Ms Ann Kehoe</from>
          <p eId="para_164">We would like to diversify.  Miscanthus can be blended with anything, for example, willow, forestry and straw.  The beauty of a miscanthus-guaranteed commercial heating system is that it will take any other product, including wood chip, willow, straw or any biomass.  A wood chip boiler will not necessarily take miscanthus.  The boiler system must be specifically made for miscanthus.</p>
          <p eId="para_165">We would love to develop into other products.  The reason we developed miscanthus first is because when it goes into the ground it stays there for 20 years, which means a guaranteed supply.  We are considering industrial hemp, which we grew successfully.  It was a brilliant crop, but the problem was that we did not get enough tonnage of biomass from it to give a return to the grower.  Therefore, unless we can take fibre off it first and then use the raw material for biomass it will not be something that we will do again although it grows very well in this country.  If we can find a crop to replace sugar beet in the rotation we will have the problem solved.</p>
          <p eId="para_166">The reason we are looking at crops that produce a big tonnage per acre of ground is to ensure that one has efficient energy production.  Efficient food production works in tandem with that.  We supply the food industry as well.  We are huge supporters of the food industry.  We want it to not alone remain at its current level but to grow.  There is enough good, productive land in this country if we manage it well to produce both energy and food.  That is what we aim to do.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_94">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_167">On behalf of the committee I thank Ms Kehoe and Mr. Ronan for their presentation and for answering questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">The joint committee adjourned at 12.45 p.m. until 11 a.m. on Wednesday, 14 October 2009.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
