<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_the_implementation_of_the_good_friday_agreement/2014-07-03/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_the_implementation_of_the_good_friday_agreement/2014-07-03/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2014-07-03" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/31/joint_committee_on_the_implementation_of_the_good_friday_agreement"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_the_implementation_of_the_good_friday_agreement/2014-07-03/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_the_implementation_of_the_good_friday_agreement/2014-07-03/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2014-07-03" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_the_implementation_of_the_good_friday_agreement/2014-07-03/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_the_implementation_of_the_good_friday_agreement/2014-07-03/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2015-09-04" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="BrendanSmith" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Brendan-Smith.D.1992-12-14" showAs="Brendan Smith"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CharlieMcConalogue" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Charlie-McConalogue.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Charlie McConalogue"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeMcHugh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-McHugh.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Joe McHugh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeOReilly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-O'Reilly.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Joe O'Reilly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaryMWhite" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mary-M-White.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Mary M. White"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelKitt" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-P-Kitt.D.1975-03-04" showAs="Michael P. Kitt"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanConlon" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Sean-Conlan.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Sean Conlan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ThomasPringle" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Thomas-Pringle.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Thomas Pringle"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TonyMcLoughlin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Tony-McLoughlin.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Tony McLoughlin"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>COMHCHOISTE UM FEIDHMIÚ CHOMHAONTÚ AOINE AN CHÉASTA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on the Implementation of the Good Friday Agreement</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2014-07-03">Déardaoin, 03 Iúil 2014</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2014-07-03">Thursday, 03 July 2014</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 10:30 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS  PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#SeanConlon">Deputy Seán Conlan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#MaryMWhite">Senator Mary M. White.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#FrankFeighan">Deputy Frank Feighan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#MartinFerrisSF">Deputy Martin Ferris</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeOReilly">Deputy Joe O'Reilly</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#ThomasPringle">Deputy Thomas Pringle</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#BrendanSmith">Deputy Brendan Smith</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">In attendance: Deputies Charlie McConalogue and Tony McLoughlin, and Mr. Conor Murphy, MLA.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#JoeMcHugh">DEPUTY JOE MCHUGH IN THE CHAIR.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
        <summary eId="sum_5">
          <i>The joint committee met in private session until 10.45 a.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Cross-Border Co-operation in Communications Technology: ERNACT<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T10:40:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_1">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_8">The delegation from the north west is most welcome and we look forward to discussing the work it is involved in on a cross-Border and pan-European basis with regard to advanced communications technology.  I welcome the representatives from the European Regions Network for the Application of Communications Technology, ERNACT, Mr. Colm McColgan, general manager, Councillor Gerard Diver, chairperson of Derry City Council, board member Councillor Rena Donaghey, Donegal County Council, board member and newly elected councillor of Donegal County Council, Niamh Kennedy, and board member Mr. Brian Boyle, Donegal County Council.  I have a good deal of knowledge about the group, having been a former chairperson, and I am familiar with its work.  This is a good opportunity to put the good work it has been involved in on the public record.  From the point of view of the committee, there might be opportunities to explore, in terms of assistance to different parts of the country, both north and south.  The organisation works to develop a number of digital projects and to secure EU funding.  We look forward to exploring with the delegation the importance of technology in driving economic development and supporting business and to discussing how the experience of other regions can be applied in the north west.</p>
          <p eId="para_9">  Before I call on the witnesses to make their introductory comments and presentation, I must warn them about privilege.  I advise witnesses that they are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their utterances at this committee.  However, if they are directed by the committee to cease making remarks on a particular matter and they continue to do so, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their remarks.  They are directed that only comments and evidence related to the subject matter of this meeting are to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against a Member of either House of the Oireachtas, a person outside the Houses or an official by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_10">  I invite Mr. Diver to begin.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from> Mr. Gerard Diver<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_11">I am delighted to be here today as chairperson of the ERNACT network.  We appreciate the opportunity to address the committee.  The work the committee is doing is very important and it has obviously cast the net wide in terms of the matters on which it wishes to be briefed.</p>
          <p eId="para_12">  I have been on the ERNACT network for only a couple of years but the network has been in existence for over 20 years.  It was initiated by the two neighbouring councils on the north west of the island, Derry City Council and Donegal County Council.  They were quite prescient 21 years ago.  The network was founded to look at communications, particularly through information communications technology, ICT, and the application of ICT.  We all know what has happened over the last 20 years.  I do not think the Internet existed 21 years ago, so it was far-seeing to create the network.</p>
          <p eId="para_13">  It was obviously prompted in part by our physical location.  The local authorities are based on the north west of the island, which is on the north west of Europe, so that is a big challenge in terms of our peripherality and the links and relationships we have with places outside our region.  The network has worked very successfully over those 20 years and has received a great deal of co-operation from other regions and municipalities across the European Union.  You will be aware of that, Chairman, as you were directly involved in the network.  It has successfully accessed funding for ICT projects, to develop models of good practice and for different projects that are able to help member states of the EU work together collaboratively on a better footing on the ICT agenda.  We recently returned from a trip to Atlantic Canada, so ERNACT is now looking outside the European Union in terms of its remit through our relationship with our friends across the Atlantic.  That is a very exciting development for the work we will be doing.  As somebody who is a fairly recent addition to the network, it appears to me that part of the difficulty we have had is that we have hidden our light under a bushel with regard to the achievements and the work done over the past 20 years.</p>
          <p eId="para_14">  At this stage I will hand over to Colm McColgan to make the presentation and give an insight into the work that ERNACT has done and plans to do in the future.  I thank the committee for listening to us today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_3">
          <from> Mr. Colm McColgan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_15">Thank you, Chairman, for inviting us to the meeting.  I echo what our chairperson has said.</p>
          <p eId="para_16">  I will focus on high speed broadband and the challenges it presents for rural areas, particularly for rural areas in border regions which tend to be far away from their respective capitals.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">My first slide shows figures that highlight the importance of information technology. We have a lot of SMEs that use information technology and there is evidence to show they grow twice as fast as ones that do not. </p>
          <p eId="para_18"> Another aspect is the fear that information technology destroys jobs. It does but there is evidence that for every job it destroys two and a half new jobs are created. Therefore, information technology cannot be ignored and we must get on board with it. </p>
          <p eId="para_19"> We are delighted that the joint committee specifically mentions communications infrastructure as part of its remit on its website. We feel that the sector is one of the most important assets for an area. One of the main things we want to do today is show the committee what we have learned is happening outside of Ireland, outside the United Kingdom and in other parts of Europe, particularly in the Nordic countries which are very far thinking in their approach to this challenge. </p>
          <p eId="para_20"> As Mr. Diver has said, ERNACT has been around for 20 years. In that period we have engaged with about 130 regions. Today we engage with about 50 regions on a whole range of digital development issues. Of course that work embraces infrastructure but it also deals with services and how they can be used for the good of society, business and education.</p>
          <p eId="para_21"> The next slide gives a flavour of the type of projects we are working on. The top project relates to broadband and refers to ten regions in Europe that have substantial rural areas. They are very concerned that the business case for the private sector does not stack up and, therefore, one must put in public money if one wants to install very good broadband in rural areas. Of course this is a time when national governments are strapped for cash which is the worst situation one can meet. Other projects deal with things like using the Internet to deliver public services and the way different regions can use it, for example, to promote tourism by developing apps. Those are some of the projects that ERNACT is currently involved with and the slides give a flavour of the type of work that we do. </p>
          <p eId="para_22"> A lot of public authorities around Europe are very interested in the concept of open data and how one can better use social media and social media channels to deliver public services. We are working on such a project. </p>
          <p eId="para_23"> Mr. Diver has mentioned that we have started to look to the other side of the Atlantic. That move was prompted by the fact that the European Union has, for the first time, compiled a strategy for its side of the Atlantic. The European Union specifically referenced the Canadian and American side of things so we travelled there to see if there was a basis for co-operation. We were delighted to learn that they were very open to collaboration and that we have a lot of things, including challenges, in common.</p>
          <p eId="para_24"> I have given an introduction to ERNACT and shall now talk about broadband in the Border area. Up until 2007-2008, which was the end of the last INTERREG programme, there was a big emphasis on telecoms. During the period between 2000 and 2007 a lot of good work was done on the north-west corridor, particularly between Derry and Letterkenny. In 2010 there were no cross-Border fibre links in the area but that has changed through a combination of good support from two councils - Derry City Council and Donegal County Council - and the fact that there was, at the time, more funding from national governments, with good support being provided by Dublin and Belfast. At the end of that period there were four cross-Border fibre links and Project Kelvin is one that all the committee Members probably know about. It was well supported by both Governments and other links exist as well. If support had not been provided through cross-Border programmes there would be no links in the region. </p>
          <p eId="para_25"> The programmes run in five to seven-year cycles. Another project has just finished but it had very little provision for broadband. A new programme is being discussed and is under public consultation but it contains no broadband provision. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_4">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_26">Is that the INTERREG programme?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_5">
          <from> Mr. Colm McColgan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_27">Yes.  That is not saying that some broadband things may not be done but it is not mentioned or given the same priority.  We did so well out of the INTERREG programme in terms of improving infrastructure that it might present some kind of a problem for us.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">   In the past the challenge was to get big fibre linked broadband into an area but now the challenge is to bring high speed broadband to houses, farms and small businesses located in rural areas.  The matter is being looked at very seriously in Finland and Sweden and I have an example from the latter.  We know that the market will look after larger towns and cities and the same applies to the Border region.  A lot of people in Donegal and the Derry City Council rural area live in the country where introducing broadband is quite expensive.  There is a view that high speed wireless will be a solution for rural areas.  Yesterday it was announced in the newspapers that parts of Dublin will get 1,000 Mbps.  We think that a problem will be created if one region gets 1,000 Mbps while another gets between 40 or 50 Mbps.  In Sweden researchers have analysed such a challenge because fibre cables are being put into farms and houses.  The Swedish model is quite different from the Irish model.  In Sweden most of the fibre networks are owned by the public sector which leases them back to private telecom operators in order for them to deliver services.  That is quite different from the way the telecom system has evolved here in Ireland.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">  The next slide shows a county located in the north of Sweden which is remote and very sparsely populated when compared with anywhere here in Ireland.  The next slide is a more detailed map and the green spots represent small communities that have built their own fibre network.  Between 80% and 90% of the cost of deploying fibre networks relates to digging and not the fancy technologies or fibre cables.  Typically, in Sweden, a local authority or co-op would take ownership of the project.  Therefore, it would help to plan the route in consultation with local communities, it would ensure there was sufficient backhaul and it would train local people with JCBs and tractors how to dig appropriate sized trenches, how to fit special equipment on the back of their machines and how to do the work.</p>
          <p eId="para_30">In these times when we are strapped for cash at national level, both in the North and in the South, we think this is a model worth trying here. We have engaged and are talking to the Department of Agriculture and Rural Development, DARD, in Northern Ireland and it is taking a good hard look at it. We had the idea of piloting a trial in quite a rural area straddling the Border. We could use the pilot to figure out whether what the Swedes have done would work in Ireland. It does pay for itself over a longer time period than the private sector would demand.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_6">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_31">That is helpful.  This is tangible and we will put it on the desks of people who need to look at this idea as a possibility.  We appreciate Mr. McColgan's presentation.  With the agreement of members, we will open up the discussion to allow them to make observations and ask questions.  We will have an interactive exchange.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_7">
          <from> Mr. Conor Murphy<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_32">I thank Mr. McColgan for this very interesting presentation.  I am very familiar with the issues raised in the area I live in and represent in South Armagh.  We have problems with connections for farms in particular because much of the Department of Agriculture and Rural Development form filling exercises are now done online and many farmers have difficulty accessing proper broadband.  I was dealing with a case last week on the old Belfast to Dublin road, and one would think there would be strong connections on the main route in the island but there are difficulties for small businesses that need high speed connection.  In the North, both the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Investment, DETI and the Department of Agriculture and Rural Development, DARD, have given money to try to give these companies the finance to provide broadband and hit the spots where there is poor connectivity.  This has been going on for a number of years but in my experience it has had a limited impact.  Is Mr. McColgan sensing a different approach when he has conversations with DARD and DETI or is it more of the same?  Essentially, organisations such as BT have been given assistance to try to provide a service.  Some people have got it but it is a slow and patchy process.  We still find there are large parts - I presume if it is happening on my patch of the Border area that it is happening right round the Border area - which have not been hit at all.  The more rural and the more isolated the area, the less likely people are to get a service because it is not economically viable for them to try to make an attempt to connect the person, even though they are getting public funding for that express purpose.  It seems that a pilot scheme that takes a different perspective would offer a solution because what has been tried in the past number of years does not seem to have had the impact that people expected.  In the process of discussions with the Departments in Northern Ireland, whatever about in the South, does Mr. McColgan have a sense that they are taking a different approach?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_8">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_33">I will take a number of participants before I call on Mr. McColgan to respond.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasPringle" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Pringle<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">I thank ERNACT for its presentation.  One slide shows a 75% of value added by the Internet to the traditional sectors.  Has ERNACT done any research work in the north-west gateway in terms of the potential for SMEs to grow job creation and so on from that?  The Western Development Commission had a very interesting report a few years ago in which it estimated that there could be 18,000 to 20,000 jobs created in the north-west region by assisting SMEs in the traditional creative industries to access Internet and broaden their Internet presence.  It is interesting to see that the value added is in the traditional sectors which is where the potential for job creation in the north west would be.  Has Mr. McColgan done any research on SMEs in Donegal and Derry?</p>
          <p eId="para_35">  On the ESB Airtricity announcement yesterday, Letterkenny is one of the towns that will be targeted as part of that initiative.  What are the linkages for people into Project Kelvin and are there cross linkages between all the different providers in the north west?  Are there problems with that and what is evolving?</p>
          <p eId="para_36">  The project in Sweden which was highlighted in the presentation is very interesting.  Some 80% of fibre networks are owned by the public sector, which as Mr. McColgan pointed out is the exact opposite of what we have here.  Obviously, the market has failed in terms of delivering broadband to communities across the country.  We need to reshape public policy in terms of the roll-out of broadband and see it as a public infrastructure that is vitally important for the public good.  Has Mr. McColgan any details on costs?  How much would it cost to roll-out a project like the Swedish project?</p>
          <p eId="para_37">  Finally, in relation to the pilot project, while I think it has some merit, what we should be doing and focusing on is the ESB wrapping fibre and bringing it on a broad scale to every house in the country, which has now been enabled.  The outworking of the ESB-Vodafone partnership is part of that.  We should be focusing on ramping it up and speeding it up and ensuring that it is developed and rolled out across the country.  By 2018 broadband will have been delivered to these 50 towns, which means by the time one gets down to rural Donegal one is looking at 2030 to 2035.  A parallel focus for organisations such as ERNACT is to lobby for the policy change and the policy commitment that would be required to ensure that happens on a broad national scale.  Perhaps it could even look at the North.  Does the ESB own the network in the North and is it something that could be rolled out on an all island basis, which would have more significant and quicker impacts as well?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_10">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_38">I thank  Deputy Pringle.  That is helpful in light of yesterday's announcement by the ESB and the connection with ESB International in the North.  It is something we can explore.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CharlieMcConalogue" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Deputy Charlie McConalogue<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">I join my colleagues in welcoming the delegation from ERNACT.  I thank them for taking the time to make this presentation.  I thank the Chairman, Deputy McHugh, for hosting the delegates.  The role of ERNACT is spelled out in its title, which is the application of technology in the regions.  Will Mr. McColgan comment on his role, and his engagement with the delivery of as opposed to the application of infrastructure?</p>
          <p eId="para_40">  In regard to the €25 million investment in the north-west gateway, will he outline the focus of that investment?  What is the remit of ERNACT and what geographic areas is it covering?  Various programmes have been announced, be it Government investment or otherwise, so could Mr. McColgan outline how this will impact on the ground in places like Donegal?  What does this mean, what is happening and what is likely to happen in the next couple of years?  We have the rural broadband scheme, which has delivered by and large low grade wireless broadband to areas, which can be patchy but is certainly a development on what was there.  That is a long way from achieving real connectivity for rural areas.  In theory, broadband breaks down barriers and breaks down geography and makes it possible to host business or any type of activity in the most remote areas and offers great scope for remote and rural areas in terms of engaging with the wider world and developing economically on a more level playing field.  The reality, however, has been that the advent of broadband has served to cut off rural areas even more so than before because without that broadband infrastructure it highlights the remoteness and disadvantages because the area does not have the broadband to be able to communicate with that infrastructure.</p>
          <p eId="para_41">Something that should give us the opportunity to become mainstream is actually making us more remote. I agree with what has been said about the way we have to go.</p>
          <p eId="para_42"> The witnesses have said that digging accounts for between 80% and 90% of the cost of laying down broadband infrastructure. I ask them to comment on the suggestion that we have the capacity to put fibre on the telephone and ESB poles that go into every house in the country. Yesterday's announcement, which was privately driven, by and large, is further evidence that the infrastructure is there. I understand that Letterkenny is the only town in County Donegal to be included in these new plans. What are the possibilities in this regard? Has there been much engagement between ERNACT and the State? Can the witnesses comment on their awareness of the potential of the discussions that are taking place in this respect? It strikes me that the only real way to do this - it is certainly the most straightforward way - is to put the fibre on a pole, alongside the ESB and telephone lines, so that it can be connected into every house. That is the only way we can make sure this happens. That would be the lowest-cost model of delivery.</p>
          <p eId="para_43"> I ask the witnesses to comment on the role and operation of the metropolitan area networks in towns. What is the current status of those networks? A significant investment was made to provide them. In many cases, the cost of delivering a metropolitan area network service to businesses in towns has proven to be prohibitive. I would be interested to hear anything they might have to say on that issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_44"> I will conclude by asking about the issue of roaming, with particular reference to the delivery of telecommunications infrastructure along the Foyle coast. Mr. McColgan is familiar with the area in question. Is ERNACT in a position to play a role in breaking down barriers there? People living in Border areas are continuing to experience significant cost difficulties. I refer in particular to people on the Republic of Ireland side of Lough Foyle who have no choice other than to operate off a Northern Ireland mobile telephone and pay the significant fees associated with that. For these people, the lack of proper availability of reasonably costed options, like those other people are able to avail of, is a real barrier to the use of telecommunications. Companies are charging more even though, as I understand it, it does not necessarily cost them anything. There are ways around it if the willingness is there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrendanSmith" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy Brendan Smith<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">I thank the Chairman.  I apologise for missing the presentation.  I was attending a meeting of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade.  I welcome the witnesses.  I have known Ms Rena Donaghey for many years.  I met some of the other delegates more recently.  Their project is very interesting.  When I flicked through the briefing we were given, I did not see any mention of the witnesses' interaction with education providers.  The north west is fortunate to be so well served by further and higher education, for example at Letterkenny Institute of Technology.  There is easy access from south Donegal to Institute of Technology, Sligo.  Magee College and other colleges of further education are based in Derry.  As we know, the colleges are playing an increasing and obvious role in regenerating local economies and the national economy.  Are the colleges in places like Letterkenny and Derry centrally involved in the witnesses' proposals for what is needed in the region?  Are they ensuring the potential of the region is maximised to the best extent possible from the point of view of learning, providing services and creating jobs?</p>
          <p eId="para_46">  As Deputy McConalogue said, easy access to adequate broadband is a huge issue in rural areas, particularly for people who are working from home.  Many people, including farmers trying to register their calves with the Department, are frustrated by the lack of adequate broadband.  At a time when many families are under financial pressure, many children stay at home full-time when they are in third level education.  Like Deputy Conlan, I know many people in counties Cavan and Monaghan who are living at home while attending Dundalk Institute of Technology.  If they do not have proper broadband at home, it makes it much more difficult for them to study and to access the documents they need.  I am sorry I missed the witnesses' presentation.  Having made a quick perusal of their document, it seems to me that the central involvement of the education providers is absolutely essential in everything we do to provide better services and develop our economies regionally and nationally.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">I welcome all the witnesses, particularly my very good friend, Councillor Rena Donaghey, who is an outstanding politician on the Inishowen Peninsula.  One might get the impression that broadband services in the north west gateway are highly developed.  Is the high-speed broadband that has been provided in the Letterkenny and Derry area accessible to SMEs and households in all locations?  Does everybody in that area have access?  What is the quality of the mobile phone coverage for businesses, tourists and families?  My experience of going around Ireland is that it is hard to believe how erratic mobile phone coverage is.  Have the witnesses looked at the broadband issues along the other Border counties of Louth, Newry-Mourne, Monaghan, Cavan and Leitrim?</p>
          <p eId="para_48">  Yesterday's extraordinary announcement of a joint venture between the ESB and Vodafone is a magnificent development.  It will mean that regional towns leapfrog over major cities in this respect.  According to the press release, "Ireland will also become the first country in Europe to utilise existing electricity infrastructure ... to deploy fibre directly into homes and businesses".  It is amazing that we will be the first country to use electricity in this way.  This €450 million investment will have a dramatic effect.  I would like to hear the witnesses' comments on it.  I would like to quote from the report on this initiative in <i>The Irish Times</i> which states:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_49">Vodafone chief executive Anne O’Leary said the fibre broadband network will allow people working from home to send very large files to their workplace in seconds.  They will also be able to hold video calls to China without disruption.</p>
          <p eId="para_50">This is a sensational announcement.  I thank the witnesses again.  I appreciate all the work they have been doing over the years.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanConlon" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Seán Conlan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_51">I welcome the witnesses.  I am interested in the work they are doing in the north west.  I live in County Monaghan.  It is clear that the same issues apply along the Border in counties Armagh, Monaghan, Tyrone, Fermanagh and Cavan.  The key for me is that every home in the area should have access to fast broadband.  It has been mentioned that many people commute to institutes of further education each day.  If they do not have decent broadband access when they come home in the evening, it is a major problem.  Over the last two years, the Government has tried to provide extra money to ensure broadband is provided in schools in counties Monaghan and Cavan.  That work is ongoing.  I think a similar investment has to be made in each household.  We should be trying to focus on how that can be done at the lowest possible cost.  I was interested to hear what was said about the Swedish example.  It has been pointed out that we have poles all over the country and that it is not as if we have to start developing new infrastructure in that regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_52">  Roaming charges and poor 3G coverage are other issues for people in Monaghan and the other Border counties.  The nature of the landscape in the Border area where I live tends to lead to a situation where coverage is lost when one goes around every turn.  What kind of solutions have been found in the north west to deal with these challenges?  We need to deal with them across the whole Border region.  I am very interested in Project Kelvin, which goes through Monaghan town right beside the education campus.  We invested €50 million in the development of the campus over the last two years.  Clearly, we want to get the maximum benefit from the education campus in terms of further education for people in the region.  We would like to be able to utilise Project Kelvin.  I would like to know whether the witnesses have found solutions that will facilitate that.  When it was first announced with great fanfare, we felt it would be a panacea to all our ills.</p>
          <p eId="para_53">It seems it does not mesh well with much other infrastructure. Have solutions been found in the region to overcome those problems?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">Letterkenny is one of the towns that ESB and Vodafone have singled out from the 50 regional towns.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_16">
          <from> Mr. Colm McColgan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">There were many questions so I will kick off before letting in others.  I will make some general points before coming to the more specific questions.  We are most concerned about rural areas and we are not really concerned about Letterkenny, Derry or Monaghan town.  Those places will be fine in the medium term, although there are challenges.  Everything will be sorted out with them.  We have discovered with our work in Europe that the debate has moved on.  It is no longer a debate about putting a fibre-optic connection between Letterkenny and Derry or between Monaghan town and Armagh.  That is happening, and I appreciate there are some temporary or short-term challenges but the real debate now has moved to the end users.  These are people in rural houses, farms and small, cultural businesses in very remote areas.</p>
          <p eId="para_56">  The most advanced regions are moving to putting fibre in people's premises, or otherwise they will be left behind.  An article in yesterday's newspaper indicated that parts of Dublin would get 1,000 Mbps into houses but very remote farms in Finland and Sweden are already getting that type of service.  These regions have raised the bar, and as Deputy McConalogue mentioned, rural areas are becoming even more remote, and if drastic action is not taken, the communities will not survive.  I am not suggesting that could happen here, as we are much more densely populated than Finland and Sweden, but that is a driving concept for those countries.  As there is so much fibre going around the place, the mobile telecom operators are asking to put a 3G or 4G antenna on farm buildings, as there is a local fibre-optic cable.  It is a reversal of the thinking behind the concept.</p>
          <p eId="para_57">  In the United Kingdom they have tried to bring fibre to as many places as possible while covering other areas with wireless coverage.  In other countries, fibre is being installed everywhere and operators are using that by paying farmers to host 3G equipment.  Not only do these farmers have fantastic speed into houses because of fibre but they also have magnificent wireless coverage.  The drumlins in Cavan, the hills of Donegal and the Sperrins have very bad coverage but it is becoming less of an issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_58">  We are very interested in what the ESB is doing as a technical solution, and there is an ESB cable going into every house in the South; there is an electricity cable going into every house in the North as well.  It is a way of tackling the technical issue.  In many of the places we work, it is already being done, and although I have noted remarks that a certain party is the first to do it, that is not necessarily true.  People will use the best technical solution and we would love the ESB to do that.  We are talking about a difference in the approach.  If the ESB approach could be applied to every house in Ireland, it would work.  Nevertheless, it is driven from the centre, and with the experience we have had over the past 20 or 30 years, by the time the work hits Malin Head or parts of Kerry, it will be years down the line.  We are suggesting a change in approach, with local communities being given the chance to see if the Scandinavian model will work here.  It could be done more cheaply and faster, and it would not be subject to the vagaries of central government planning.  We know that is very important, as it is in Sweden, but more power is given to local areas.  We saw a slide earlier detailing what we were able to achieve on a cross-Border basis in the north west.  We were able to increase the cross-Border fibre connections from zero to four between 2000 and 2008 with the support of central government and councils getting together.  Many community groups were also involved.</p>
          <p eId="para_59">  This approach will work and we have spoken to people in the Department of Agriculture and Rural Development in the North.  They seem quite receptive to it.  The Department of Enterprise, Trade and Investment in the North deals with telecoms issues, and telecoms regulators are very conservative people.  They have become even more conservative over the past ten years and they do not like these kinds of solutions.  They want to get £500,000 of public money and put a project to tender.  Usually, the existing telecoms operators will win such projects.  That is a good solution for many places but this approach must be allied to this other approach.</p>
          <p eId="para_60">  The announcements by the ESB yesterday will not have any impact in rural areas, and they are designed for towns of above 4,000 people.  We understand the process will only apply in Letterkenny in Donegal, which is a town of 10,000 or 12,000 people.  The announcement by Vodafone and the ESB is totally market-driven, which is welcome, although it will only work in the bigger towns and cities.  They have done their calculations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_61">It is aimed at smaller regional towns rather than large cities.  The focus is on 50 medium-sized towns, including Ballina and Tralee.  It will leap-frog regional towns over larger cities.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_18">
          <from> Mr. Colm McColgan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">Those towns will be okay.  In Donegal, 60% of the population does not live in a town but rather in the countryside.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">It is 75%.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_20">
          <from> Mr. Colm McColgan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">The solution announced yesterday will not benefit those people.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">Is the broadband available in those counties rather than towns?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_22">
          <from> Mr. Gerard Diver<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">It would be very patchy even when one goes outside the main area population of Derry City Council.  It is a matter of mindset in how to provide broadband.  Anything driven from the centre will be fraught with difficulty with regard to potential to impact the most remote people.  We have seen the examples mentioned from Scandinavia first-hand.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">We need to know more about that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_24">
          <from> Mr. Gerard Diver<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">There is a very strong element of community initiative where people have got together and stepped into that vacuum where the market has not been able to do it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">What can this committee do to help?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_26">
          <from> Mr. Gerard Diver<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">It would be hard to over-emphasise the potential impact that could have in rural Ireland where we are losing people.  People are migrating to centres of population because that is where the broadband coverage is and the job opportunities.  In areas such as Sweden and Finland people can live in very remote areas and still work in high tech jobs for Nokia or Microsoft and do exactly what the Senator said earlier about sending large files to their employer or having a conference or a Skype call to somebody in China or Japan.  This is something unseen but it could unlock many of the problems we are facing in Ireland, outside of the major centres of population, to reinvigorate those areas by the application of technology to overcome the peripherality and the problems we have had in the past.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">Through the Chair, what can this committee do to help this initiative?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_28">
          <from> Mr. Gerard Diver<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">In part it is about influencing public policy, it is about a change in public policy that is not coming from the centre and not necessarily influenced by what the market thinks is best and what the telecommunications-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">Can local authorities do it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_30">
          <from> Mr. Gerard Diver<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">Yes, and Government.  One of the powerful things about ERNACT as a network is that it was two local authorities that decided to do something.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_32">
          <from> Mr. Gerard Diver<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">There were questions earlier about what Government policy is and our awareness of that.  This is where two municipalities essentially have taken the lead and have done something which now has a European significance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">What can this committee do to help with this ideal initiative?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_34">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">Deputy Seán Conlan wants to speak.  I will then call Deputy Thomas Pringle followed by Ms Rena Donaghey and Mr. Brian Boyle.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanConlon" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Deputy Seán Conlan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">I think the point was illustrated earlier in terms of coming from the smallest communities up rather than from the centre out.  These initiatives announced yesterday are good for the large regional centres.  In my area, towns such as Monaghan and Cavan will get fast broadband in any event, but I am concerned that towns such as Belturbet, Ballybay, Coothill, Castleblayney and Clones will not get high speed broadband if we do not change our approach.  It is important that these towns get fast broadband and are not left behind.  There are initiatives for the villages but the small towns are being left out and, obviously, the individual units, the individual farms and the individual SMEs in the rural areas are in a predicament.  I think Mr. McColgan's approach is correct, we have to change mindsets.   If we continue to say it is okay that 50 regional towns are getting new infrastructure, that leaves behind all the other small towns.  That is the reality of it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">What happened yesterday was dramatic.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_37">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">I call Deputy Thomas Pringle and then the panel.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasPringle" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Pringle<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">I would caution on one aspect.  In regard to small towns and villages being able to apply to do this themselves, we have a model of that already, which is the group water scheme sector.  Donegal County Council has been frozen for the past eight years in terms of group schemes because it is dependent on Government grants.  I would advise caution because I could foresee a fancy announcement where a Minister would say a fantastic scheme is being rolled out that will bring broadband to every town in the country, for which the Government will allocate €2 million per annum.  That is the solution for a government.  It is a great PR stunt that looks fantastic but does nothing on the ground in terms of delivering for the communities who need it.  As Mr. Brian Boyle is aware, there are group schemes in Donegal that have been trying to get water into their communities for the past 30 or 40 years but cannot do it because they have not been able to access funding.  I agree with much of what Mr. McColgan has said and there is value in it in terms of a real solution, given that the ESB is owned by the citizens of Ireland and the technology is available.  It is feasible, it can be done and it is not hugely expensive.  What is the timescale for the roll-out of the project in Sweden?  What investment was required of the Government to deliver these community projects?  What is the commitment to rolling it out within a reasonable timescale?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_39">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">I thank Deputy Pringle.  I am conscious of the fact that Mr. McColgan has already indicated that the Department of Agriculture and Rural Development is supportive of the idea.  He also made the proposal that perhaps we should look at a pilot or one village or town that straddles both areas.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_41">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">It is only a suggestion but Senator Mary White has asked how we can help.  The job of this committee is to ensure that all the contributions are put on the desk of the Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources on this side of the Border and then, obviously, there is a role for local authorities.  I call Ms Rena Donaghey.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_42">
          <from> Ms Rena Donaghey<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">I am a public representative for the Inishowen Peninsula.  I have been a county councillor for 15 years and I am aware of many of the challenges in Inishowen.  We have a population of more than 40,000.  The peninsula. which is equivalent in size to counties Louth or Leitrim, is very rural.  The lack of broadband is debilitating for primary and secondary schools and students cannot achieve their potential.  I do not want to rehearse what has already been said but these are the problems I am hearing about on the doorsteps on a daily basis.  We have talked about businesses and SMEs.  It is difficult to keep our graduates at home when we have such a poor broadband system.  Yesterday's announcement, while it was welcome, does not do anything for me or the 43,000 people whom Deputy Charlie McConalogue and I represent.  It is for larger towns, it is regional rather than rural.  Buncrana, the town I represent, has a population of 4,000 but is not one of the 50 towns listed.  I am the mother of two students who cannot use the Internet properly because it is too slow for uploading bigger files.  The examples that Mr. Colm McColgan has given are very real.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i>Deputy Joe O'Reilly took the Chair.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_43">
          <from> Ms Rena Donaghey<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">I have been to Sweden and have spoken to politicians there who have outlined exactly how it can be done.  The Chairman, Deputy Joe McHugh, and Deputy Charlie McConalogue are very familiar with a community incentive scheme in which I have been involved in Inishowen, similar to the group water schemes Deputy Thomas Pringle mentioned.  This was a community assist scheme; it is part of the Wild Atlantic Way that was not able to accept coaches or larger buses.  I initiated a scheme last year where I got public money from Donegal County Council and got the community involved with their JCBs, men with shovels and spades, tractor and trailers.  We did a terrific job.  Some members may be aware of it as Eileen Magnier covered it on RTE News.  While I welcome yesterday's announcement, what do I say to the 43,000 people in Inishowen whom I represent as there is nothing in it for them?  It is intended that 100,000 houses will be connected each year under this scheme for the next five years up to 2019.  Do we in Inishowen have to wait until after that time to get broadband for our area?</p>
          <p eId="para_88">  The education and training boards invested very heavily last year and will do so again this year on teaching farmers how to do their business on line.  I am teaching them how to do it but yet when they go home they cannot do it because they do not have the broadband.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_44">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">I thank Councillor Donaghey.  I call Mr. Brian Boyle.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_45">
          <from> Mr. Brian Boyle<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">The collaborative scheme announced yesterday between the ESB and Vodafone is welcome.  Any significant improvement in telecommunications capacity, especially where it involves fibre to the home is welcome.  The limitation of the scheme is that it is intended to be rolled out only to centres of high population of 4,000 to 5,000 plus.  It does, however, answer a question that has been unresolved in that the way to deliver high speed broadband is through fibre to the home.  There has been some discussion, which is still ongoing, as to whether fixed wireless or even 4G could be the answer.</p>
          <p eId="para_91">The experience from Europe and elsewhere is that is not the answer. The answer to delivering high-speed broadband is a fibre-optic network to the home. Perhaps one of the benefits of yesterday's scheme will be to get that argument over the line in this country.</p>
          <p eId="para_92"> Another scheme was announced also, in March or April this year, to bring high-speed broadband - the use of a fibre backbone was mentioned in the initial documentation - to rural areas. A range of townlands was mentioned for each county, with 40 alone in County Donegal. However, there was little detail as to how this scheme would be rolled out. If we have a collective role to play, perhaps the committee could suggest to the Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources that the model being used in the collaborative venture between the ESB and Vodafone in the bigger towns be the model also for the rural areas. As Deputy Pringle said, there is a huge advantage in using the publicly owned ESB network, which services every house in the land, to deliver fibre connectivity. However, it would be a shame if that scheme was delayed pending delivery of this other scheme, because we could be looking at a long timescale.</p>
          <p eId="para_93"> Mention was made of the Scandinavian model and whether the fibre cables should be underground or overhead. I saw an example in Slovenia last year in which one of our partner projects used both models. Networks were built in the ground and fibre was also run on the electricity network, depending on what suited the circumstances. Perhaps a combination of models would be suitable. The important factor from our perspective is that the policy decision is made and that we figure out a way to do it quickly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">Yesterday's announcement is important in the broader sense, as we will be the first country in Europe to do this.  I understand we are focusing on rural areas, but we will be the first country in Europe to use the electricity network.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_47">
          <from> Mr. Gerard Diver<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">We are not.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">According to the ESB and Vodafone, Ireland will become the first country in Europe to utilise existing electricity infrastructure to deploy fibre connections directly to homes and businesses, initially reaching 500,000 premises.  We cannot deflate what happened yesterday, because that is the way we must go.</p>
          <p eId="para_97">  I am disappointed to hear Councillor Donaghey say that so few homes will get high-speed broadband or that it will be so sparse.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_49">
          <from> Ms Rena Donaghey<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">Inishowen is a very rural area.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_50">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_99">We will take the final responses shortly.  Deputy Smith wishes to comment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrendanSmith" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Deputy Brendan Smith<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">Some of the contributions made gave the impression there is no broadband anywhere.  We need to balance our comments.  There is a very good broadband service available in some towns and villages, but the service is patchy.  I did not have the opportunity to read the announcement made yesterday, but we have had numerous initiatives over the past ten or 12 years in regard to rolling out broadband.  Perhaps it is an issue of co-ordination and perhaps an onus should be placed on telecommunications providers to provide broadband to every house in the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_52">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">Sorry for interrupting, Deputy, but will members please turn off their phones?  It seems a phone is interfering with the sound system.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrendanSmith" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Deputy Brendan Smith<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">We have seen various initiatives, but there are still pockets of the country that have been left unprovided for.  I know of some villages and towns in my county that have good broadband, but there is poor coverage just half a mile out the road from them.  Some houses fall between one broadband-enabled exchange and another exchange that is not broadband-enabled.  Small villages near towns often only had small exchanges and these have not been broadband-enabled.  Unfortunately, pockets of the country are being left out.</p>
          <p eId="para_103">  Ms Donaghey made a good point that people can go to classes and get the skills but are not able to use those skills at home to do the practical work.  This is a serious issue.  We need to pull together to resolve the issues.  Local authorities, statutory agencies and national government all have a role to play on this.  It will not happen if each sector leaves it to the other.  Every month that goes by without a broadband service is a huge loss to households and business.  This issue is of utmost importance.  Like our Chairman, I represent a rural area, Cavan-Monaghan, where we have particular problems on account of the drumlins.  It defies logic in this technologically advanced era that a hill can still stop a message from getting across to another area.  This baffles me at times.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_54">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">I can relate to that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CharlieMcConalogue" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Deputy Charlie McConalogue<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">Perhaps Mr. McColgan will respond on some of the points I mentioned.  I thank Ms Donaghey and Mr. Boyle for their contributions.  I would like to acknowledge the work they have done through Donegal County Council.  Ms Donaghey is a long-time member of ERNACT and has been very proactive in this area.  I congratulate Ms Kennedy on her recent election to Donegal County Council and commend Mr. Diver on his work in ERNACT.</p>
          <p eId="para_106">  The problem here is getting a grip on what is required.  Technology is moving along and developments are happening in the larger urban centres.  We hear periodic announcements from the Government on what it says it will deliver to rural areas, but not much is happening outside of what is being driven by companies.  Will Mr. McColgan respond to us in regard to the scope of ERNACT and the counties it covers?  Will he explain what the €25 million invested in the north-west corridor went into?  Does ERNACT have a role, or will it have a role, in regard to roaming?  Mention was made in previous contributions of countries that are providing 3G wireless from fixed-line addresses and paying farmers for it.  This sounds like a simple but exciting idea.  In many rural areas, even good mobile reception is still a problem.  Therefore, this idea sounds as though it could be pushed and could be of value.</p>
          <p eId="para_107">  Mr. Boyle mentioned the announcement made a few months ago regarding delivering broadband to rural areas.  What do we know about that, and what exactly is happening?  Will he elaborate on what he is aware is happening in that regard?  In terms of the north west, nobody knows more about how we can deliver broadband and the current position than the witnesses.  If they cannot explain this or are unclear on what is proposed, there is an issue.  The difficulty relates to what is happening at national level and to the substance behind the announcements that have been made.</p>
          <p eId="para_108">  Where do we need to go from here?  What needs to happen to drive this forward and make it happen?  It seems to me that using poles is the way to go rather than burying the fibre cables.  In Sweden, the fibre cables are being buried, but we already have the electricity poles, so this seems the way to go.  What needs to happen in terms of getting the ESB on board?  Could schemes be developed in local areas or could co-ops put together self-sustaining and self-financing projects which could see investment in ESB poles in areas which would pay back over time?  Do we need to develop models such as this?  I like the ERNACT perspective on that landscape and on what needs to happen.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelKitt" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Michael P. Kitt<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">I welcome the witnesses.  It is worth remembering the good and not-so-good things the ESB has done and is doing.  It is great to have the ESB in terms of the social welfare schemes such as subsidised electricity and heating.</p>
          <p eId="para_110">There is another issue. The ESB has tried a pilot scheme for broadband but it has not really worked. I offer the example of the town of Tuam, County Galway, an area I represent. The company had to abandon the scheme and we had to start all over again. Believe it or not, we had to wait for a water and sewerage scheme in Tuam before we could put the broadband cables underground. We should be careful about that. It is a little like the curate's egg - good in parts.</p>
          <p eId="para_111"> Reference was made to leaving everything to the ESB, but I do not believe we can do that. I applaud what the ESB has done but I advise caution as well. We cannot allow the company to do everything and I do not believe the company should be expected to do everything either. We need more investment and we need to see people working together.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">I thank the Leas-Cheann Comhairle.  We will have a summation from the deputation and then I will respond at that stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_58">
          <from> Mr. Colm McColgan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">The best thing the committee could do is to allow us to try to get policy changed so that we can pilot the Scandinavian model in rural parts of the Border counties.  Many people have asked for this and we believe that is the best thing the committee could achieve for us.  The Northern Ireland Department of Agriculture and Rural Development is considering the matter but it is by no means over the line.  In turn, it must discuss the matter with the more conservative Northern Ireland Department of Enterprise, Trade and Investment.  That is the main point.</p>
          <p eId="para_114">  Donegal County Council and Derry City Council established ERNACT.  The idea was not so much to do major things but to transfer good ideas from other parts of Europe.  This is exactly what we are doing with the Scandinavian model.  Approximately ten years ago we were forced to get involved with the Border corridor when we found out there was no broadband network.  We acquired considerable experience, as did both councils.</p>
          <p eId="para_115">  The €25 million referred to was spent on the four fibre-optic lines that run between Letterkenny and Derry and the wireless city model in the centre of Derry.  INTERREG money was deployed to introduce wireless capability in rural parts of Donegal and the Border areas.  It was done by a local company in Derry and it was a good solution.</p>
          <p eId="para_116">  The main point is that the whole broadband game is moving on.  We are moving to the point at which between 30 and 40 Mbps is becoming the norm, up to 1,000 Mbps.  That is the perspective and that is what we are aiming for.  We are trying to prepare the Border areas, especially in the north west, for that type of scenario.  We believe that if local communities in the Border areas were allowed to pilot this approach we could do a job there, because we have the expertise.  Donegal County Council and Derry City Council have a good deal of expertise in this area as well.  There is a view that perhaps the expertise does not exist outside the Departments, but it does.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_59">
          <from> Mr. Gerard Diver<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">I thank the members of the committee for hearing us today.  This is an essential issue.  People need to start thinking about the provision of broadband in the same way as other basic utilities such as water and electricity, rather than as a luxury service to be procured.  It is something everyone needs to function.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">Can we record our correspondence in the minutes?  The proposals of the group are very interesting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_61">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">Yes; that is no problem.  I thank the witnesses for their very worthwhile presentations.  It has been a very interesting discussion and it is extraordinarily relevant.  This is one area we should be working on to give real effect to and create a real peace dividend.  As we all know, it is a serious problem in rural Ireland and it must be worked on in a collaborative way as much as possible.  The committee, through the secretariat, will raise the matter directly with the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources and his officials as a matter of priority.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">Can we include our correspondence?  We discussed it earlier.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_63">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">Of course; that is no problem.  It is a good point.  Ultimately, we will arrange to have the Minister or senior officials come before the committee to discuss the implementation and an actual product.  Furthermore, we will raise the matter at the North-South Ministerial Council.  Effectively, we are saying to the witnesses that they have not wasted their sweetness on the desert air.  They have made a good presentation and there will be product and an outcome.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">We can meet next week at the North-South Ministerial Council.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_65">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">Thank you, Senator, for your assistance.  We will do so.  Thank you all very much, collectively and individually.</p>
          <p eId="para_124"><i>Sitting suspended at 11.55 a.m. and resumed at noon</i>.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Support for Family Carers on the Island of Ireland: Carers' Cross-Border Consortium<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T11:50:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_66">
          <from> Vice Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T12:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">It is my great pleasure to welcome the Carers' Cross-Border Consortium.</p>
          <p eId="para_126">The delegation includes Ms Rosaleen Doonan from the Carers Association; Mr. Sean Caughey, the Carers Trust Northern Ireland; Ms Maria Mulligan, volunteer and social worker; Ms Jennifer Van Aswegen, Disability Federation of Ireland, and Ms Siobhan McEniff from the Health Service Executive. They are welcome to the meeting. We are all passionate about the invaluable work that carers do every day, caring for family or friends who need help because of frailty, illness or disability. It touches an emotion in everyone. Today we will discuss the supports available for carers across the island and explore the opportunities for greater co-operation in developing policy in this important area of health provision.</p>
          <p eId="para_127"> Before I invite the witnesses to make their presentation I advise them they are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee. However, if a witness is directed by the committee to cease giving evidence in regard to a particular matter and continues to do so, the witness is entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of his or her evidence. Witnesses are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of the meeting is admissible and are asked to respect the parliamentary practice that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against a Member of either House, etc. I do not think these difficulties will arise.</p>
          <p eId="para_128"> I invite Ms Doonan to proceed with her opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_67">
          <from> Ms Rosaleen Doonan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">I thank the committee for inviting us to outline and discuss North-South co-operation in the area of family carers.  I would also like to acknowledge the work of Deputies Joe McHugh and Tony McLoughlin, who have a demonstrated a keen interest in supporting family carers, and I appreciate all the work they have done so far.</p>
          <p eId="para_130">  This cross-Border consortium came together because we recognised that co-operation in this area makes sense as the increasing challenges facing family carers on both parts of the island are similar.  There is no doubt that if we work together, benefits will accrue from pooling expertise, resources and exchanging good practice.  This will achieve a better life for family carers on the island of Ireland.</p>
          <p eId="para_131">  The members of the consortium who are not here today are: Ms Catherine Magowan, Western Trust; Ms Noreen Kettyles, MeUnltd Northern Ireland; Mr. Shane Martin, a psychologist; and Mr. Frank Morrison from the Health Service Executive.  We have received guidance and training from Ms Ruth Taillon of the Centre for Cross Border Studies.</p>
          <p eId="para_132">  A family carer is someone who provides an ongoing significant level of care to a person who is in need of that care in the home due to illness or disability or frailty.  A family carer is not identified by gender, colour, creed or nationality, any more than those facing similar caring situations and feelings, irrespective of where they live.</p>
          <p eId="para_133">  It can be said that there are four kinds of people in the world: those who have been carers; those who will be carers; those who currently are carers; those who need to be cared-for.  It is not something we often consider but it is a fact that, one way or another, “caring” will come into all of our lives at some stage and, as a society, we need to grasp that reality and plan around it.</p>
          <p eId="para_134">  People in both jurisdictions on this island are living longer and it is inevitable that, as this trend continues, the number of family carers will continue to grow, resulting in increased demand for relevant and timely support mechanisms to be in place to provide support to those who have chosen to care for a loved one.  "Chosen" is not a very good word because few people choose to be carers.  It is usually thrust upon them and is not a job that somebody applies for.  There are 396,864 family carers registered on the island of Ireland giving 12,664,644 hours of unpaid care per week.  In the Republic of Ireland the 2011 census recorded 187,000 family carers, of which 4,228 were under the age of 15 years, which is startling, yet in Northern Ireland the 2010 census returned a figure of 214,000.  There is a clear need to research this glaring difference.  Not only do family carers make a profound difference to the health, well-being and quality of life of those for whom they care, but they also make a huge and unacknowledged contribution to the economy.  Family carers in the Republic of Ireland contribute €77 million per week, providing 900,000 hours of care daily to the ill, frail and people with disabilities.  This is equivalent to one third of the total annual cost of the Health Service Executive, HSE, and is five times what family carers cost the Department of Social Protection in income support.  Full-time family carers contribute on average €72,500 a year.  Can committee members imagine what would happen if, like the air traffic controllers in France recently, all these people decided to down tools and go on strike, or bring all the people they care for to our community health centres and hospitals?  The health service would collapse and thousands would die but we all know this will never happen because no matter what stresses or strains carers have to endure, they will never forsake their jobs.  Carers are the backbone of the provision of care in the home and community.  We all talk about care in the community but what is care in the community?  There is no community.  It is individual families and neighbours taking care of people.  We have to ask where is this elusive community.</p>
          <p eId="para_135">  The significant demographic changes to the Irish population structure, expected to occur over the next few years, will have major implications for publicly provided supports and services and, coupled with the reforms in both the structure and delivery model of our health system, this will have profound implications for family carers.  It is expected that Ireland’s ageing population and medical advances in treating disability and chronic illness will result in more people of all ages with longer-term and complex care needs who will, according to Government, be cared for in the community.  We all know that this in reality means cared for at home by family members.  The difference between now and 20 years ago is that people who would be cared for at home would not have a high level of medical intervention or needs.  They might have been frail or have had a mild to moderate disability, but they did not have the complex needs that people can now care for at home.  I am not saying they cannot be cared for at home but they need support.  There is a change and we need to respond to that.</p>
          <p eId="para_136">  We acknowledge there are positive and rewarding aspects to caring but there are also huge challenges and demands.  Research shows that a high percentage of carers experience physical ill health and emotional or psychological problems as a result of long-term caring.  This is a fact no matter where in the world one is working.  I acknowledge the Government's publication in 2012 of the national carers strategy, Recognised, Supported, Empowered, whose vision statement is:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_137">Carers will be recognised and respected as key care partners. They will be supported to maintain their own health and well-being and to care with confidence. They will be empowered to participate as fully as possible in economic and social life.</p>
          <p eId="para_138">We welcome this strategy and its vision, and believe if the four goals and 42 objectives contained therein were delivered, this would go a long way to bringing family carers to centre stage in the delivery of care in the home.  Unfortunately, nearly two years later, with less than two years of the strategy to go, very few of the actions have been delivered.  In fact it is sad to think how little of it has been delivered.</p>
          <p eId="para_139">  I note that in February the committee met high-ranking civil servants from the Department of Health who outlined areas of co-operation they were engaged with.  As is common when the Department of Health and the HSE speak about health, family carers were never mentioned, yet it is the policy of both Governments to progress care in the community, but they ignore the most important resource to deliver this; family carers.  They are ignored mainly because no Department has a remit for family carers.  The Department of Health has a remit to provide services to people who are ill but not for the people who are caring for them outside the paid employees of the Department and HSE.  The Department of Social Protection views family carers as recipients of benefits and not as contributors to the economy when the opposite is the case.  Family carers are the only people who have to work for their benefits.</p>
          <p eId="para_140">  Family carers do not have a recognised status within health provision and therefore do not receive the supports or services they need.</p>
          <p eId="para_141">This is particularly evident when one looks at how Co-operation and Working Together, CAWT, and other INTERREG funding is dispersed within the health sector. Provision is focused on patients and the agencies taking care of them, but little thought goes into the needs of voluntary carers. Some weeks ago, new funding of €50 million was announced under the CAWT initiative. However, while senior health managers in my area of Donegal and Sligo have been briefed on that funding, no representatives of carers were invited to attend the briefing. Once again, carers are on the outside. In fact, carers in the South do not even have a right to an assessment of their needs, even when they are caring for people with high levels of dependency. </p>
          <p eId="para_142"> One of the most remarkable and unusual aspects of family caring in Ireland is that despite being a small island, there is a vast difference in how supports are provided depending on which side of the Border one lives. There is a completely different model for delivering supports in each jurisdiction. In Northern Ireland, the model is services-based with low supports, whereas in the Republic it is based around medium supports and little service provision. I do not know which, if either, of these models is best, but it is striking that they are so different.</p>
          <p eId="para_143"> I will now hand over to my colleague, Mr. Caughey, who has travelled all the way from Belfast this morning.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_68">
          <from> Mr. Sean Caughey<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">In Northern Ireland, according to the 2010 census, there are nearly 214,000 family carers and an estimated 30,000 young carers.  Some 49,412 carers are over the age of 60, with 5,816 of them over the age of 75 and 20,340 caring more than 50 hours per week.  Amazing as it may sound, 319 carers in Northern Ireland are over the age of 90.  When our organisation conducted a snapshot survey recently in the Ballinascreen area of Derry, we found that 71% of carers are caring for more than 20 hours per week.  Research shows that the 20-hours threshold is the acceptable level of caring before one risks damage to one's health.  Other findings were that 50% of carers have been caring for more than five years, 50% described themselves as scared, worried or anxious, 45% help with personal care for a loved one, and 40% care for more than ten hours per day.  These statistics are seen as typical of the situation for carers in rural areas across Northern Ireland.</p>
          <p eId="para_145">  Support funding for carers' services in the North is mainly provided by the five health trusts and varies depending on the trust area.  All areas have a carers co-ordinator.  However, the recent austerity cuts have seen the financial commitment for carers dwindle.  For example, the Southern Health and Care Trust budget for carers was cut from £150,000 to £90,000.  This flies in the face of the recent Compton report, the thrust of which is towards keeping people at home longer.  Carer's allowance in the UK is £61.35 compared with €204.00 per week in the Republic.</p>
          <p eId="para_146">  I will give members testimony from two of the people we have encountered whose circumstances are indicative of the situation for carers in Northern Ireland at this time.  The first is from a woman who is caring for her husband:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_147">My name is Louise and I'm 62.  My husband had a stroke about ten years ago and I gave up work to care for him.  We managed at first but we're struggling to cope financially now.  We desperately needed a shower installed and couldn't get help from anywhere so we had to pay for it ourselves on credit.  I work part-time to try to make ends meet.  I feel like we're in a never-ending downward spiral and we're now in serious debt.  I haven't had a break for as long as I can remember.</p>
          <p eId="para_148">  The second testimony is from a woman who is caring for her husband even though she has had a stroke:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_149">My name is Alice.  I'm 74 and I recently had a stroke.  I've lost the use of my left arm.  I care for my husband who has various medical problems and can't get about on his own.  Since the stroke it's become more difficult to manage the physical things like getting him washed and dressed.  Luckily for us we haven't lost our sense of humour and he will say to me, "Ach, Alice, all this running about after me is keeping you fit, girl!"  I do all the cooking and shopping.  We have a lady comes in to help with cleaning at the moment – we call her Mary Poppins (she doesn't know!) - but this service is being taken away.  I can't really understand why.  The house won't clean itself.</p>
          <p eId="para_150">  No later than last Thursday, 26 June, the Northern Ireland Minister for Health, Social Services and Public Safety, Edwin Poots, said that the transformation of our health and social care system requires good partnership working with carers.  He emphasised the need for greater recognition of the vital role carers play in ensuring people are cared for in their own homes and communities for as long as possible.  Speaking at a conference on the future needs of older carers, he stated: </p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_151">The physical and emotional impact that caring can have on the well-being of individuals should not be underestimated.  With an ageing population, carers will become older and we must ensure that they are properly supported to carry out their role without it negatively affecting their own health and well-being.  Parents of children with learning disabilities worry what about will happen when they are no longer able to care for them.  So it is vital that as carers become older, they are given reassurance and have peace of mind with regard to the future of their dependants.</p>
          <p eId="para_152">  The Minister continued:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_153">Caring for the carer and planning for the future are therefore vitally important.  We must develop new models of services for older carers and their families so they have the knowledge, resources and tools to plan for the future.  We must also ensure that they are given practical help, including respite and short break care if needed.  “Making a difference to the lives of all in our society remains a firm priority for me.  Transforming Your Care [document on reform of health service provision in the North ]means more health and social care services will be provided in the community, therefore carers will play an increasingly important role in providing valuable services that complement those delivered by paid care services.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_69">
          <from> Ms Rosaleen Doonan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">The recent economic collapse in both jurisdictions, north and south, has led to drastic austerity measures by government and health agencies, all of which will have a major impact on family carers throughout the island of Ireland.  Reports on reform of the health service on both sides of the Border - Transforming Your Care in the North, and Future Health in the Republic - have many similar strands which will impact on the lives of carers and future carers in terms of the supports available to them.  In fact, the interesting thing about those two documents is that they are very similar in what they outline, but the way services are delivered on both sides of the Border is very different.</p>
          <p eId="para_155">  The Department of Health published Future Health – A Strategic Framework for Reform of the Health Service 2012–2015 in November 2012.  According to this document, one of the seven tangible changes patients and clients will experience under the reformed service will be, "More people cared for in their homes: The reforms in social care will help older people and people with disabilities to live in their homes for as long as possible rather than go into residential care".  Future Health sets out four pillars of reform, including a commitment by the Government to the development of a comprehensive health and well-being policy framework.  The document further clarifies that:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_156">Health is more than merely the absence of disease; it is physical, mental, and social well-being...  Prevention policies and programmes can be cost-effective, can reduce health care costs, and can improve the health of the population...  The role of the health service must be seen as keeping people healthy as opposed to just treating sick people.</p>
          <p eId="para_157">  It is presumed that this includes the health and well-being of family carers, who have been proven to be at high risk of illness because of their care burdens.  Looking after carers is an example of cost-effective policy.  Indeed, if we do not look after carers, they will, in turn, become sick people who are the responsibility of the health service.  Future Ireland is very detailed in its methodology of approach as to how the four reform pillars will be implemented, in particular how it will achieve a situation where more people will be cared for at home through its new integrated model of care and its proposals for reforming social and continuing care and primary care.  One of the five key principles identified to underpin the delivery of social and continuing care is "[a] shift towards service provision in the community, which includes natural supports (family, friends, etc.) as far as possible".  However, the glaring omission in the document is a lack of detail on how the health service will engage with and support family carers, who will be the cornerstone to the successful implementation of the strategy outlined in Future Care.</p>
          <p eId="para_158">  Mr. Caughey will now outline the situation in Northern Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_70">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">I apologise for interrupting, but I notice there are six pages remaining in the presentation.  Members have all received a copy and we can publish the document to our website.  Perhaps, in the interests of time, Mr. Caughey might summarise the position?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_71">
          <from> Mr. Sean Caughey<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">Certainly, Chairman.  I will just echo the point made by Ms Doonan that Transforming Your Care is very similar to the document produced by the Irish Government.  Unfortunately, these similarities include the omission of any indication as to how supports for carers will be resourced and funded.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_72">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">Perhaps members will now get involved with observations and questions.  Mr. Caughey is free to respond.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrendanSmith" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Deputy Brendan Smith<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">I thank the Chairman, welcome the witnesses and compliment them on their work.  They have given a detailed presentation and we should all appreciate the outstanding work done throughout the island and abroad by carers.  Ms Doonan and Mr. Caughey made clear that we must support carers in the difficult work they do.  Their work is often unsung and unpaid.  Along with giving proper recognition and support to carers we should acknowledge the age profile of people in Ireland is rising because we are living longer.  It follows that there is now a need to care for people for longer periods.  This should be an important element of any proposals on this topic.</p>
          <p eId="para_163">  There should be a simple all-Ireland policy on this as there are no political difficulties relating to different traditions.  The necessary policies and supports in both jurisdictions should apply equally throughout the island.  This issue should be raised at the North-South Ministerial Council.  In recent years the North-South Inter-Parliamentary Association was established, comprising Members of the Northern Ireland Assembly, Dáil and Seanad, and it has discussed health issues, drugs, alcohol abuse and other matters that affect the entire island.  There can be no political difficulties on such matters.  I am part of the North-South Inter-Parliamentary Association with Deputies McHugh and Pringle and perhaps we should try to get this issue on its agenda.  The association is jointly chaired by the Ceann Comhairle, Deputy Seán Barrett and the Speaker of the Northern Ireland Assembly, Mr. William Hay, MLA, and I am sure those of us in the association could seek to have the issue advanced as an item for discussion.  This would bring the focus to the all-Ireland element of the issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_164">  I compliment Ms Doonan, Mr. Caughey and their colleagues on the detailed presentation they gave and their ongoing work.  It is important that carers working on their own, almost as sole-traders, have advocates because they do not have sufficient time.  I apologise because I must leave now to attend another committee meeting but I will read the report of this meeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from> Mr. Conor Murphy<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">I thank the Chair and I thank the witnesses for their presentation.  It is clear that carers are a forgotten aspect of health service provision because they do their work out of a sense of love and duty.  For this reason it is highly unlikely that they will go on strike and this is how they end up exploited by the health systems on either side of the Border.  The point on the Transforming Your Care programme is correct as most people say it is a very good plan, in theory, but no provision has been made to implement it.  The idea was to take people away from acute medical treatment and into the community but this happened at the same time as budget cuts on carers.  In practice the initiative contradicted itself.  This is a tough area and I do not doubt the benefits of an all-Ireland approach, particularly in Border areas where issues such as access to health services, rural transport and so on exacerbate an already difficult situation for carers.</p>
          <p eId="para_166">  I am very interested in the recommendations to the committee.  At the start of the meeting the Chairman said we would focus on health matters and this is one such issue.  Often when there is a focus on health matters carers are ignored so we must ensure this issue is part of our deliberations on all-Ireland health matters.  We must see if pressure on both Departments, North and South, will help them follow through on decent propositions with practical support.</p>
          <p eId="para_167">  I too must apologise because I must attend another engagement but I first wanted to register my support for the witnesses and their presentation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_75">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">If Mr. Murphy is leaving those present will be delighted to take him up on his proposal.  I inform the committee that we are examining a broad spectrum of health matters, not just for one meeting but on an ongoing basis, including cross-Border out-of-hours GP services, cross-Border cardiology services and so on.  If a committee member can second Mr. Murphy's proposal we will include the issue of carers North and South in the wide-ranging report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">I second that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_77">
          <from> Mr. Sean Caughey<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_170">Could I make a point on Mr. Murphy's statement?  According to censuses on both sides of the Border there are 91,000 registered carers in Border areas.  That is a substantial number.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_78">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">Our committee will be in touch with Mr. Murphy at a later date.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_79">
          <from> Ms Maria Mulligan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">Before Mr. Murphy leaves-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_80">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">Is this a personal matter?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_81">
          <from> Ms Maria Mulligan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">I know Mr. Murphy will raise this amazing project on various agendas.  It is a great opportunity to draw the attention of the British and Irish Governments to a policy that is not based on self-interest, making money or saving money.  This issue is about the core values of society and acknowledging that we amount to more as a group.  Very few areas of Government policy allow us to put such matters on the agenda.  This is about who we are as a people - those doing background work matter.  I feel passionate about this and ask Mr. Murphy to push it forward.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_82">
          <from> Mr. Conor Murphy<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">Unfortunately we must face the bean counters in the Department and that is part of the battle.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_83">
          <from> Ms Maria Mulligan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">That is where Mr. Murphy can rattle their jars.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_84">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_177">That is fair enough and I appreciate the intervention, enthusiasm and dedication of Ms Mulligan.  After this meeting we can pass this issue on to whoever is Minister for Health after next Tuesday.  We will also ensure Mr. Edwin Poots, MLA, of the Northern Ireland Assembly, is given a copy of proceedings here.  Ms Mulligan can take it she has the support of the committee on this.  The North-South Ministerial Council is next Thursday and we will raise this issue then also.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_85">
          <from> Ms Rosaleen Doonan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_178">The two health strategies on either side of the Border cannot be implemented without the support of family carers.  They are not at the table at the moment.  It is impossible for me to get an appointment with Co-operation and Working Together, CAWT.  I have tried and I met a person from that organisation but I never heard from the office again and that was 14 months ago.  The person seemed enthusiastic but there has been no contact since.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_86">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">CAWT has been before this committee previously.  We will write directly to CAWT to highlight that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_87">
          <from> Ms Rosaleen Doonan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">That would be great.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_88">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">We are all focused on following up today because Senator Mary M. White was very insistent that this committee should not merely listen to presentations but should use the meetings as a vehicle to follow things up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_89">
          <from> Mr. Sean Caughey<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">The assumption that this is a health issue for carers is wrong, it is much broader than that.  We support young carers up to the age of 18 while they try hard in their leaving certificate or A-level exams.  Often they cannot take positions at university because of their caring responsibilities.  This is an issue facing all of society that spans areas such as housing and education.  It is not only a health issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_90">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">We will make that point at the North-South Ministerial Council.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_91">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">There is big difference between the carer's allowance in the Six Counties and here.  It is €75 there and €204 here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_92">
          <from> Mr. Sean Caughey<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">Some 30,000 people in Northern Ireland care for over 50 hours per week.</p>
          <p eId="para_186">I make the commercial argument that they are working for £1 per hour. If there was a factory anywhere in Ireland where employees were being paid just £1 per hour, there would be uproar.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_93">
          <from> Ms Rosaleen Doonan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">One must also consider the totality of it in the context of how services for family carers on both sides of the Border are delivered.  The services in Northern Ireland are much better than they are here, despite the fact that the support system is not at the same level.  As stated earlier, however, I do not know which model is better.  The best model might be a combination of both.  For example, in Northern Ireland there are carer co-ordinators.  Ms McEniff was a carer co-ordinator with the HSE before she took up another position within the organisation.  Her previous post was not filled.  I accept that we are living in straitened economic times but the position of carer co-ordinator was not considered important enough to fill.  There is no carer co-ordinator in place in the Republic at present.  That tells its own story.  Ms Van Aswegen would have her own insight.  This matter is not about spending money, it is about how it is spent in a way that results in the best value being obtained.</p>
          <p eId="para_188">  If one considers it from an economic perspective, then matters would dictate that the State would seek to begin supporting family carers.  The more they are supported, the more people could be removed from residential care, acute hospitals, etc.  It is a no-brainer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_94">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">Yes, it is a no-brainer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_95">
          <from> Ms Rosaleen Doonan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">Everyone on this side of the table knows the reason why such support is not provided.  It is not because members do not want to help carers.  I know from talking to them that they want to help because they have all had experience of this matter at some stage.  The reason support is not provided is due to the position carers occupy within governmental structures.  They do not, for example, fall within the remit of either the Department of Health or the Department of Social Protection.  That is where the real problem lies.  The Ministers for Health and Social Protection do not have responsibility for them and neither does any other Minister.  They fall between stools.</p>
          <p eId="para_191">  Mr. Caughey and I have discussed this matter and we are of the view that if there were a Minister of State with responsibility for carers or a senior official with a dedication to family carers, we would not be discussing this matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_96">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">Is there no one in the Department of Health who is responsible?  Someone must have some responsibility.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_97">
          <from> Ms Rosaleen Doonan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">It would make sense for the Department of Health to be responsible.  However, let us consider the matter from a different perspective.  If the Department of Health had responsibility and if the supports were coming from the Department of Social Protection - like all supports, these would be viewed as a drain on the economy - how would that sit with people?  I am not even going to discuss paying family carers because that is not the route to go.  I am stating that there needs to be national recognition for what they are doing.  As Ms Mulligan stated, we need, as a society, to step up to the mark.  In fairness, there was never an issue ten or 20 years ago because a grandmother or someone with a mild disability would have been cared for at home.  At that time one did not need the services one requires now.  People used to be transported to hospital on special beds and stretchers in ambulances, now they are being sent home from hospital with all sorts of paraphernalia in tow.  As acting director of nursing in Our Lady's Hospital in Manorhamilton, Ms McEniff is very aware of that and she is very involved in this area.  The position has shifted and we need to catch up.  That is where the real problem lies.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_98">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">I am glad we have gone off script and I thank Ms Doonan for expressing her views with such passion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasPringle" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Pringle<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">I thank our guests for their very interesting presentation.  Ms Doonan already answered one of the questions I intended to pose in the context of what our guests are seeking and their interaction with CAWT in recent times.  I am of the view that the committee should take up the cudgels in the context of having carers included under CAWT because that would also provide some momentum regarding how cross-Border issues might be dealt with.  Like the Chairman, I am a member of the North-South Inter-Parliamentary Association and we will definitely raise the matter with that body in order to increase its profile.</p>
          <p eId="para_196">  I am of the view that carers fall between stools because there is a view that it is nice to keep it that way because their value to society does not need to be recognised and there is no need to take action in respect of them.  The national accounts for the past year were published earlier today and, for the first time, an economic value has been ascribed to prostitution and drug dealing.  Would there be any point in trying to estimate the value of carers in the context of the national accounts in order to raise the profile of carers and the work they do?  One of the things our guests are seeking from the committee is for it to facilitate access to INTERREG funding for family carers.  What do they mean by that?  Are they seeking it for research or is it for actual supports, etc.?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_100">
          <from> Ms Rosaleen Doonan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">Research is extremely important.  Until very good bodies of research are compiled, it is not possible to establish benchmarks in the context of from where we should work.  That is very important.  The way I see it is that there is a circle and inside that is everything to do with the health service.  Outside the circle are the carers.  However, they are central to the success of everything in the health service going forward.  Anything that gets us into the circle as equal partners and which brings about a recognition that we are going to be obliged to deliver on all the new policies the Government is introducing would be welcome.  One cannot do anything without funding, be it from CAWT or INTERREG.  I recognise that we are all trying to do the best we can with what we have but there are external bodies which are providing a great deal of funding for various different things in the area of health.  However, carers are not part of that.</p>
          <p eId="para_198">  I am not sufficiently qualified to understand how these very large European Union funding mechanisms work.  However, I do know INTERREG and CAWT are the mechanisms by means of which funds are disbursed to communities.  I am hung up on the word "community".  We should say it as it is, namely, that those involved are family carers and that we are sending people home to be looked after.  I am not a medical person - I would make a very bad nurse and probably an even worse carer - but I am aware of the extent of the work - such as changing catheters and so on - those involved in care at home must do.  Earlier this week I spoke to a woman whose little boy was born with a stem cell tumour.  He screams all the time and she is expected to look after him 24-7 outside school hours and without any extra help.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_101">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">One of the proposals made by our guests is to have the home recognised as a centre of care.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_102">
          <from> Ms Rosaleen Doonan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">Absolutely.  If I had discussed this matter ten or 15 years ago, people would have said it was off the wall.  There would not have been a need for such recognition because people who required 24-7 medical care would not have been at home.  Times have changed, however.  I have visited houses filled with hoists, wheelchairs and all sorts of medical paraphernalia and seen people traipsing in and out all day expecting cups of tea to be made for them.  Homes must be made centres of care if we are serious about dealing with this matter.  There is another option, namely, to reconsider the health strategies which obtain on both sides of the Border.  However, I do not believe that will happen.</p>
          <p eId="para_201">We will look at the two health strategies, but I do not think that is going to happen on both sides of the Border.</p>
          <p eId="para_202"> Before we write up such health strategies on the way forward we must consider what we intend to do and what that will mean for people. I am not necessarily asking for it to happen. There is a willingness among Irish people to look after their loved ones at home. Their loved ones want to be at home. Furthermore, I think it is the place for them. The doors are open. It is just a matter of having the supports to be able to do that without killing oneself. The statistics on ill health among carers are frightening. When one cares for someone in a full-on manner with very little support over a period of five to 20 years, one's health will be hugely compromised. We have done simple things that have made such a difference. We had a programme that thankfully was supported by the HSE in the west. People go to De Exeter House in Kilmacrenan in Donegal for breaks and that makes such a difference.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_103">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">It is a respite.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_104">
          <from> Ms Rosaleen Doonan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">People can avail of three days of respite.  I cannot describe what it means to the committee.  We have sent more than 100 people.  I have a stack of cards from them.  It made a difference to them and it makes a difference to the economy.  If one wants to be black and white about it, one must look at that.  We sent people there who were at burnout stage.  Following respite, they are no longer burned out, they no longer need a residential place and they are prepared to continue with care at home, thus saving the State huge amounts of money.  The financial and economic rationale for looking after carers is a no-brainer.  It is the way to go.  I am involved at the front line, all day, every day.</p>
          <p eId="para_205">  One Friday morning when I was in the office I got a telephone call from a man who was distressed.  I did not know what was wrong.  I usually ask people for their name first but he would not give me his name.  The reason he was telephoning me was to tell me that he could no longer care for his mother.  He was providing full-on personal care for her but he was giving it up.  For a moment I did not know what he was telling me but he wanted us to be able to support his mother when he was gone.  I was on the telephone to him for an hour.  I will never forget the call.  He was really telling me he had decided to end his life.  He was going to commit suicide.  He had it planned.  He was going to Galway.  I was on the other end of the telephone.  I did not know who he was or where he was from.  I tried to elicit the information from him.  To make a long story short, I had to figure out where he was.  I got on to the public health nurses.  I had other people on the telephone checking to see whether he was a client of theirs.  One person recognised who it could be and got to him while I was still on the telephone to him.  We got him into De Exeter House.  He was there for one month.  He came out of there and he was perfect.  We got supports in to help him.  He is still caring for his mother.  That is  the reality.  That is what it is like out there.  That should never have happened.  It need not have happened.</p>
          <p eId="para_206">  The man was 53 years of age and his mother was 84 or 85.  If that man got the supports he needed the situation would not have arisen.  Perhaps he did not ask for them.  Sometimes people do not ask for them.  One needs to know who those people are.  If the man in that case had got the supports in time I would not have had that telephone call.  They are the things one does not forget.  It is very easy to be isolated from such circumstances when one is not in the business.  What did I know about the situation before I got involved with the Carers Association?  I was lucky.  Those considerations did not come into my sphere of life but now I am acutely aware of them and I know for sure that they will affect me some day.  I definitely know that I am either going to be cared for or I will be caring for someone.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_105">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">In the meantime this committee will look after the aims and objectives outlined by Ms Doonan.  I guarantee her that.  I do not know what will happen in the future.  I am conscious that Ms Van Aswegen has been waiting to contribute.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_106">
          <from> Ms Jennifer Van Aswegen<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">That is okay.  I thank Ms Rosaleen Doonan who has probably covered the area I had intended to address.  The first point is on the economic rationale.  If one looks at page 9 of the report, it reflects the tip of the iceberg of the economic rationale based on investing in carers now in order to prevent them becoming a burden on the health system through burnout and increasing the care burden.  That makes absolute economic sense.  Deputy Murphy referred to it in terms of counting beans.  Such investment makes total financial and economic sense in order to prevent a landslide at the other end and in terms of the burden on the health service.  Ms Doonan covered the topic very well with real examples of what happens on the ground much better than we could outline in a scientific way.  The real life experiences she outlined gave life to the words on page 9.</p>
          <p eId="para_209">  Ms Doonan also mentioned research.  On pages 8 and 9 of our proposal we examine the proposal put forward by the consortium on cross-Border collaboration.  Research plays a key role.  We are mindful that much research exists but there is a gap in the research.  That is probably an area in which Ms McEniff has some expertise.  A core element of the model proposal is around research to inform best practice and policy.  We spoke about the disparities between the models in the North and the South.  We do not have the answer on which is the most appropriate or best model but through research we hope to identify the needs of carers; whether financial support works best or practical hands-on support that might be more prevalent in Northern Ireland.  We are very mindful of the importance of research as an element of any cross-Border collaboration and it is something we will prioritise as part of our project proposal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_107">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">I thank Ms Van Aswegen.  The witnesses might be ahead of themselves.  Ms Van Aswegen might have her homework done.  The new round of INTERREG V has not been finalised yet but four themes emerge.  What I say must be taken with a pinch of salt, as matters will not be finalised until September but the four themes that emerge are first, health; second, research and innovation, including research, health and lifestyle; third, sustainable transport, and; fourth, the environment.  Assuming that this will be the final make-up of the four areas, Ms Van Aswegen might be on the right track.  I hope that is helpful.  The witnesses will watch the space closely in the coming months.  Are there other observations or questions?  We are coming near the conclusion of the meeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TonyMcLoughlin" eId="spk_108">
          <from>Deputy Tony McLoughlin<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">I am not a member of this committee but I would like to compliment you, Chairman, and the committee on bringing carers from the North and South together today.  I spoke to you on a number of occasions about the issue.  Ms Doonan is familiar with my area of Sligo and the north west.  The issue is vitally important.  It was educational to listen to the presentation.  The witnesses are in good hands under the stewardship of the Chairman, Deputy McHugh.  This is the right forum to attend this morning in terms of INTERREG funding.</p>
          <p eId="para_212">  You will appreciate, Chairman, the enthusiasm generated by Ms Doonan.  I have been on the receiving end of it in the north west in recent years.  I see the work at first hand that is being done with the funds that have been allocated by the carers.  Their work and dedication to their loved ones over the years is evident.  At times, carers are taken for granted.  It is vitally important that support can be provided.  I compliment you, Chairman, and the committee for organising this morning’s meeting to bring both groupings together.  The meeting is worthwhile and educational for me and others.</p>
          <p eId="para_213">This is a step in the right direction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_109">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">I am conscious that a vote has been called in the Dáil.  Deputy O'Reilly is going to do something he has never done before and make a contribution in 30 seconds.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeOReilly" eId="spk_110">
          <from>Deputy Joe O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">I want to join others in welcoming the witnesses because what they do is very important.  I sincerely apologise for having to leave earlier.  I had to deal with an unavoidable situation but I will not bore them with the details.  I join Deputy McLoughlin and the Chairman in their comments, and I am glad there will be a proactive response to the witnesses' submission, which I look forward to reading.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_111">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">We must conclude as a vote has been called in the Dáil.  We have made a number of commitments in terms of follow up.  I am conscious that it is not just a health issue but we will give the presentation to the Minister for Health south of the Border and for the information of the Northern Minister, Edwin Poots.  The mechanism that might be important is the North South Ministerial Council, NSMC, and we will use that opportunity.  Senator White will travel to Armagh next Thursday, and the witnesses can take it as read that she will ensure that this item is on the agenda for the joint secretariat.</p>
          <p eId="para_217">  Regarding the wide-ranging issues on health that are part of this committee, we are planning that at the moment and the witnesses can take it as read that their North-South carers issues will be incorporated into that.</p>
          <p eId="para_218">  To recap on INTERREG V, if they are the four emerging thematic areas it will be important to keep a close eye on them.  We said also that we would follow up on writing directly to the Co-operation and Working Together, CAWT.</p>
          <p eId="para_219">  I thank all the witnesses.  I thank also the people who may have wanted to make a contribution for their patience but Ms Doonan's passion and commitment to the cause was visible to all of us.  We appreciate her, and her colleagues both North and South, being here today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_112">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">Without being political, the cut in the respite care grant was heavy stuff.  Does the Chairman recall that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_113">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">Yes, I know.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaryMWhite" eId="spk_114">
          <from>Senator Mary M. White<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">That was hurtful.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_115">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_223">We will end on that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_116">
          <from> Ms Rosaleen Doonan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">It is a bigger issue.  It is about looking at the whole picture.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_117">
          <from> Ms Maria Mulligan<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">It is about the message this sends out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeMcHugh" eId="spk_118">
          <from> Chairman<recordedTime time="2014-07-03T13:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">The meeting is adjourned until 10.15 a.m. on Thursday, 25 September 2014.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7"> The joint committee adjourned at 12.55 p.m. until 10.15 a.m. on Thursday, 25 September 2014.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
