<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_economic_regulatory_affairs/2009-11-04/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_economic_regulatory_affairs/2009-11-04/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2009-11-04" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/30/joint_committee_on_economic_regulatory_affairs"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_economic_regulatory_affairs/2009-11-04/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_economic_regulatory_affairs/2009-11-04/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2009-11-04" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_economic_regulatory_affairs/2009-11-04/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_economic_regulatory_affairs/2009-11-04/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference eId="#vol_None" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None" showAs="Vol. None"/>
          <oir:numberReference eId="#no_None" href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None/no/None" showAs="No. None"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CiaranCuffeGP" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ciarán-Cuffe.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Ciarán Cuffe"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DamienEnglishFG" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Damien-English.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Damien English"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FergusODowdFG" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Fergus-O'Dowd.S.1997-09-17" showAs="Fergus O'Dowd"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="KieranODonnell" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Kieran-O'Donnell.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Kieran O'Donnell"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LeoVaradkar" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Leo-Varadkar.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Leo Varadkar"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelMoynihan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-Moynihan.D.1997-06-26" showAs="Michael Moynihan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NedOSullivan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ned-O'Sullivan.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Ned O'Sullivan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulCoghlan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Coghlan.S.1997-09-17" showAs="Paul Coghlan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PeterKellyFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Peter-Kelly.D.2002-06-06" showAs="Peter Kelly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanSherlock" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Sherlock.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Sean Sherlock"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chair" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chair" showAs="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chairman" showAs="Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>COMHCHOISTE UM GHNÓTHAÍ RIALÁLA GEILLEAGAIR A BHUNÚ</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>JOINT COMMITTEE ON ECONOMIC REGULATORY AFFAIRS</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2009-11-04">Dé Céadaoin, 4 Samhain 2009</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2009-11-04">Wednesday, 4 November 2009</docDate>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 11 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#CiaranCuffeGP">Deputy Ciarán Cuffe,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulCoghlan">Senator Paul Coghlan,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#DamienEnglishFG">Deputy Damien English,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#NedOSullivan">Senator Ned O’Sullivan.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#PeterKellyFF">Deputy Peter Kelly,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#KieranODonnell">Deputy Kieran O’Donnell,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#FergusODowdFG">Deputy Fergus O’Dowd,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#SeanSherlock">Deputy Seán Sherlock,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#LeoVaradkar">Deputy Leo Varadkar,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#MichaelMoynihan">DEPUTY MICHAEL MOYNIHAN IN THE CHAIR.</person>
          </summary>
          <summary eId="sum_4">The joint committee met in private session until 11.10 a.m.</summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Impact of Regulation: Discussion with Professional Insurance Brokers Assocation. </heading>
        <speech by="#MichaelMoynihan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_10">The next item on the agenda is a discussion with the Professional Insurance Brokers Association about the impact of regulation on small and medium enterprises.  On behalf of the committee I welcome the following: Mr. Diarmuid Kelly, CEO; Mr. Michael Hoare, chairman; Ms Anne Hession, chairperson of the legislation sub-committee; Mr. Jack Fitzpatrick, member of the legislation sub-committee; and Ms Elizabeth Smith, compliance manager, of the Professional Insurance Brokers Association Limited.  I draw attention to the fact that while members of the committee have absolute privilege the same privilege does not apply to witnesses appearing before it.  Members are reminded of a long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that Members should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House, or any official by name in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_11">I ask Mr. Kelly to make a presentation after which we will have a discussion between the members and the witnesses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Mr. Diarmuid Kelly</from>
          <p eId="para_12">Ms Elizabeth Smith will make the presentation on behalf of the association.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Ms Elizabeth Smith</from>
          <p eId="para_13">I will begin by introducing the members of the delegation representing the Professional Insurance Brokers Association.  My name is Elizabeth Smith and I am compliance manager.  I am joined by Michael Hoare, PIBA chairman, Diarmuid Kelly, chief executive, Anne Hession, chairperson of the legislation sub-committee, and Jack Fitzpatrick, member of the legislation sub-committee.  We are grateful to the joint committee for this opportunity to address it on the role of PIBA and the current issues which are important to the broker industry.</p>
          <p eId="para_14">The Professional Insurance Brokers Association was established in 1995 as a non-profit association wholly owned by its members.  It has quickly grown to become the largest representative body for small to medium-sized insurance and mortgage intermediaries in Ireland.  PIBA has more than 900 member firms which provide a valuable service to consumers.  Up to 35% of our members are located in the greater Dublin area, with the remaining 65% spread throughout the country.  PIBA has a voluntary executive committee, as well as several voluntary sub-committees covering such issues as legislation, mortgages, life assurance and general insurance.  The legislation sub-committee has seven voluntary members and meets on a monthly basis to highlight and discuss issues facing the broker community, as well as compliance and legislative matters at both an Irish and European level.  The existence of this sub-committee enables PIBA to draw on the expertise of practising brokers and helps to sustain an objective and dynamic approach to the issues affecting the industry.</p>
          <p eId="para_15">Since our inception, the area of legislation and regulation has been a key priority for PIBA.  A primary objective is to collate all applicable legislative requirements to provide brokers with guidelines to assist them in deciding how best to comply with all legislative obligations in their day-to-day business.  To achieve this objective, PIBA has two full-time staff working in the legislation and compliance section, with other members of staff also devoting time to this area.  We provide members with a comprehensive on-line compliance manual which is continuously updated and contains all relevant information, template documents and guidelines to ensure compliance with current rules and regulations in a practical manner.  Another function of the compliance unit is to respond to legislative changes.  We are committed to assisting and providing practical guidance to our members on how to respond to and implement the changes.  PIBA also monitors industry publications and findings of the Financial Services Ombudsman and drafts appropriate guidelines to assist members in, for example, best practice when conducting sales to elderly persons.  We also assist our members with individual compliance queries they may have.</p>
          <p eId="para_16">On a macro level, PIBA lobbies on behalf of members and brings relevant matters to their attention which may affect their business.  PIBA has developed an active co-operative relationship with the Financial Regulator, the Department of Finance and other Government bodies.  It is vital for us to have an interactive relationship with such bodies in order positively to influence impending legislation and regulation and to ensure it does not place an unrealistic or disproportionate burden on independent brokers in the conduct of their day-to-day business.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">Our members support balanced and proportionate regulation.  Such regulation is essential to protect consumers, protect honest companies and uphold the integrity of the financial services industry.  We have consistently sought to achieve a level playing field between all providers of financial services.  However, to date, a heavy handed and over-the-top approach has been applied to small and medium-sized brokers in comparison with the light touch applied to banks, which has since been shown to have been a naive approach.  It seems the Financial Regulator has, to date, only regulated the smaller entities in the financial services industry while neglecting the larger entities, which has ultimately led to the financial crisis in which Ireland now finds itself.  To be clear, PIBA is in favour of regulation that is robust, fair and proportionate.  However, it must be applied with equal vigour to all sectors and must be proportionate, that is, proportionate to the level of risk posed to consumers.</p>
          <p eId="para_18">From 1 April 2001, insurance intermediaries were subject to the extensive supervisory powers of the Central Bank.  Intermediaries were required to be authorised and were also subject to the requirements of the various code of conduct handbooks.  The creation of the Financial Regulator in May 2003 as a single regulatory authority represented a substantial change in the scope and focus of the regulatory infrastructure.  Its remit was to include wide-ranging protection powers and to monitor the financial soundness of individual institutions.  The Financial Regulator, when imposing requirements on brokers, has been detached from how the latter run their businesses in practice.  An example of this is when the terms "authorised adviser" and "restricted activity investment product intermediary" were imposed on brokers.  These terms were utterly confusing for consumers and did not achieve the goal of differentiating between the range of products provided by different intermediaries.</p>
          <p eId="para_19">PIBA has voiced its opposition to these terms for some time and has been working to have the term "broker" reintroduced.  We want clearly defined rules on what the term "broker" means and in what circumstances it can be used.  The working group on the review of the intermediary market, on which PIBA was represented and which reported last year, supports the reintroduction of the term "broker" to the industry.  This unanimous desire for a return to the pre-2001 term clearly illustrates the need for the Financial Regulator to listen to the industry when making changes to the regulatory environment to avoid the introduction of ineffective changes with no benefit to the consumer.</p>
          <p eId="para_20">The consumer protection code was published in August 2006.  Its primary aim was to ensure that the same level of protection was offered to consumers, regardless of the type of firm with which they choose to deal.  However, basic banking products, defined to include current accounts, overdrafts and deposit accounts with a maturity of one year or less, were exempted from the key consumer protections of fact-finding and reasons.  This was done on the basis that they were deemed to be generic products.  This means there is no obligation on the banks to check the requirements of the customer, recommend a suitable product to meet that requirement or explain in writing the reasons for recommendations made.  Therefore, as set out in the Central Bank's updated monthly statistics of last August, more than €94 billion in personal consumer deposits are outside the regulatory loop.</p>
          <p eId="para_21">The fact that a product is deemed to be generic is irrelevant for the purposes of giving advice.  The point should be whether the product is suitable to meet the needs of the customer.  Banks should have an obligation to check the customer's need for liquidity and their risk preference, explain financial markets and recommend an appropriate split of investments for the needs of the customer.  At the very least, the exemption for basic banking products should be capped at €10,000.</p>
          <p eId="para_22">The consumer protection code is a principles-based code but it was not a principles-based code for the broker.  Requirements suitable for large stockbroking firms were imposed on small to medium-sized brokers which were excessive to the nature of the business they conduct.  There has clearly been disconnection to date between the Financial Regulator's understanding of how brokers operate and the reality of the broker business.  Brokers by their nature represent low risk.  They generally do not handle client moneys or premia, except in certain specified limited circumstances where the relevant insurer is responsible for the moneys.</p>
          <p eId="para_23">The delay in the implementation of the revised insurance mediation directive regulations, IMD2, is of great concern to PIBA.  This delay has meant that many insurance intermediaries are subject to both the Investment Intermediaries Act 1995 and the insurance mediation directive regulations.  We have been assured by the Department of Finance on numerous occasions that the revised insurance mediation directive is imminent, but draft regulations have not yet issued.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">I will outline just one of the issues outstanding as a result of the delay in implementation.  Accountants are regulated by their own professional bodies when carrying out investment business services or providing investment advice on what is termed an "incidental basis".  At present, the benchmark for incidental basis is 20% of turnover.  This benchmark for calculating incidental business is arbitrary and unfair in circumstances where it is availed of by large accountancy firms whose income from insurance mediation would be greater than that of a traditional broker.  It is clear that a regulatory gap exists, as accountants may advise on investment and insurance products without being subject to consumer protection frameworks such as the consumer protection code, minimum competency requirements and right of complaint to the Financial Services Ombudsman.  This puts the clients of such accountants at a considerable disadvantage.</p>
          <p eId="para_25">Self-regulation for some categories of persons providing investment business services on a professional basis is incompatible with the concept of a single regulatory role.  It is inappropriate to have a dual regulation system in place whereby consumers are disadvantaged at the outset when dealing with these firms.  It is essential that consumers are entitled to the same level of professional service in regard to financial products.  There should be no regulatory difference whether a consumer approaches an accountant or an insurance broker.  There should not be different sets of rules for persons providing exactly the same services to consumers.  The "incidental" option, which we understand is likely to continue under the forthcoming revised regulations, facilitates part-timers whose core focus is not the financial and insurance sector.  The complexity of that sector and its associated products demands full-time participation in the market.  An individual operating in the market on a part-time basis is at considerable risk of providing inappropriate advice.</p>
          <p eId="para_26">An issue of significant importance being debated within the industry is broker commissions.  It has been widely reported that the UK's Financial Regulatory Authority has proposed under the retail distribution review to in effect ban commissions.  However, it will be permissible for adviser charges to be paid from the policy to the broker.  It will force net pricing by product providers to which adviser charges agreed between the broker and the customer will be added.  It is clear this will represent an important structural change to the nature of commission.  Will it help consumers?  We believe these issues must be carefully considered in order that they do not lead to unintended consequences.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">Brokers in Ireland are currently remunerated in three ways — commission only, fee only or a combination of both.  In the past product providers who had large market share demonstrated poor investment performance.  It is important to bear in mind that commissions paid to brokers are a source of competition among product providers as they compete for broker business.  This ultimately benefits the consumer in product innovation and lower charges and this is exactly what happened in Ireland in recent decades.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">It is clear that the Financial Regulator's primary concern is product bias by advisers.  This is a legitimate concern.  However, in practice, customers only choose fees where this leads to a substantial saving on their overall advice cost.  This is reflected in the fact that significant fees are generally confined to the upper end of the market.  Brokers are required under the consumer protection code to make full disclosure to clients of all commissions-fees received by them at all times.  The issue of commission was also examined by the intermediary working group last year.  One of its recommendations is that for brokers to use the word "independent" they would have to offer a fee-based option to consumers.  PIBA will continue to conduct research into the area of fee charging by brokers and provide guidance to members in the area.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">This has been a challenging year for all sectors of the financial services industry.  Brokers continue to play a decisive role in helping consumers manage their personal finances and reassess their financial goals.  For example, brokers are playing a pivotal role between clients and banks negotiating new terms for making repayments where clients are experiencing difficulty in meeting mortgage loan repayments.  PIBA will continue to support fair and proportionate regulation and we will continue to advocate that the new regulatory environment is based on the reality of the marketplace.  I thank the committee for its time.  We are pleased to take questions from members.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterKellyFF" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Peter Kelly</from>
          <p eId="para_30">I welcome the delegation.  Insurance professionals should be allowed to use the word "broker" because they have always been known as brokers.  The standards and ethics of insurance brokers in Longford are second to none and I have had a pleasant and good business relationship with all brokers in the county.  Brokers operate to the highest standards and they provide a great service to the people.  I support everything PIBA does.  Brokers have made a valuable contribution to financial services, especially in rural Ireland, where they are accessible and available.  They are real people who can be dealt with.  One is not dealing with a large conglomerate in major cities all over the world where one does not know those involved.  I hope the powers that be will take into consideration the reasonable and sensible requests of PIBA.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Deputy Seán Sherlock</from>
          <p eId="para_31">I welcome the delegation.  Ms Smith's contribution suggests that there is a difference in approach to the regulation of brokers compared with the banking sector, which is subject to a lighter touch.  What is the solution?  PIBA is seeking one primary codified set of regulations embodied in legislation.  Ms Smith stated, "A primary objective is to collate all applicable legislative requirements and then provide brokers with guidelines to assist them in how best to ensure that they comply with all legislative obligations in their day-to-day business".  Is current regulation weak in general?  Does legislation need to be changed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Mr. Diarmuid Kelly</from>
          <p eId="para_32">We all feed into a compliance manual, which is supposed to summarise the regulations applicable to insurance brokers, and it is heading for 200 pages.  The Deputy can imagine a small broker with two or three administrative staff trying to look after his customers while researching the latest changes in data protection and so on.  We are engaged in a huge task on an ongoing basis for our members.  We require fair play at industry level whereby the regulations applicable to us are also applicable to, say, accountants.  We never felt there were principles-based regulations for brokers.</p>
          <p eId="para_33">The Financial Regulator's code of conduct devotes five or six pages to brokers but only two or three to banks.  It is a little odd that massive institutions handling billions of euro for clients and engaged in risk-based transactions are subject to a few pages of regulation while we are subject to detailed rules, which are supplemented every quarter by another letter from the regulator.  We want a sense of proportionality to apply.  We are not a substantive risk to consumers.  As Deputy Kelly outlined, we are at the coalface and we are in touch.  We will also be here in five or ten years as we do not move around like bank officials from one branch to another.  That gives us a better connection with the customer.  We only want a little fair play to apply and we have not seen that from the Financial Regulator in the eight or nine years we have been under its wing.  We would like the Oireachtas to say in its approach to financial regulation that the primary risk is where the billions of euros are being handled and it wants detailed rules governing this.  We would like the Oireachtas to be reasonable with our sector.  That is all we are looking for.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Deputy Seán Sherlock</from>
          <p eId="para_34">That is reasonable.  The committee will meet the regulator shortly and we should address this issue with him.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DamienEnglishFG" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Damien English</from>
          <p eId="para_35">I have been approached by PIBA members in my county about this issue.  They are easy to deal with when it comes to clients who need additional help.  It is not just about profit for brokers.  I am familiar with the gist of what is wrong regarding the red tape and hoops brokers are put through compared with banks.  I apologise for missing the presentation but I will go back over the submission to address the specific issues.  I am in favour of addressing them and that is what the committee is here to do.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMoynihan" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_36">I thank PIBA for the presentation.  Almost every Oireachtas Member has dealt with its members on a day-to-day basis over the past 12 months to facilitate constituents who are in difficulty.  We will take on board the association's submission and when the regulator appears before us, we will address the issues raised.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">The joint committee adjourned at 11.40 a.m. until 4 p.m. on Tuesday, 11 November 2009.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
