<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd ">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#source">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food/2008-07-23/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food/2008-07-23/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2008-07-23" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/30/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food/2008-07-23/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food/2008-07-23/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2008-07-23" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="mul"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food/2008-07-23/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_fisheries_and_food/2008-07-23/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-06-25" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="/ie/oireachtas/role/debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <analysis source="#source">
        <otherAnalysis xmlns:oir="https://data.oireachtas.ie/ns/1.0" source="#source">
          <oir:volumeReference href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None" showAs="Vol. None" eId="#vol_None"/>
          <oir:numberReference href="ie/oireachtas/debateRecord/vol/None/no/None" showAs="No. None" eId="#no_None"/>
        </otherAnalysis>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="" showAs="Houses of the Oireachtas"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="generation" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Generation" showAs="Generation"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="reported" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Reported" showAs="Reported"/>
        <TLCConcept eId="publication" href="/ie/oireachtas/ontology#Publication" showAs="Publication"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="AndrewDoyle" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Andrew-Doyle.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Andrew Doyle"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BobbyAylward" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Bobby-Aylward.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Bobby Aylward"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ChristyOSullivan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Christy-O'Sullivan.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Christy O'Sullivan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="EamonOCuiv" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Éamon-Ó-Cuív.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Éamon Ó Cuív"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="EamonScanlon" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Eamon-Scanlon.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Eamon Scanlon"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FrancisOBrien" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Francis-O'Brien.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Francis O'Brien"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnCartyFF" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Carty.D.2002-06-06" showAs="John Carty"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnEllis" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Ellis.S.1977-10-27" showAs="John Ellis"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnnyBrady" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Johnny-Brady.D.1997-06-26" showAs="Johnny Brady"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MattieMcGrath" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mattie-McGrath.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Mattie McGrath"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelAhern" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-Ahern.D.1982-03-09" showAs="Michael Ahern"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelCreed" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-Creed.D.1989-06-29" showAs="Michael Creed"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NedOKeeffe" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ned-O'Keeffe.S.1982-05-13" showAs="Ned O'Keeffe"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PJSheenan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/P-J-Sheehan.D.1981-06-30" showAs="P. J. Sheehan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulBradford" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Bradford.S.1987-04-25" showAs="Paul Bradford"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanSherlock" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Sherlock.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Sean Sherlock"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TomSheahan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Tom-Sheahan.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Tom Sheahan"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chair" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chair" showAs="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/position/chairman" showAs="Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister/community__rural__gaeltacht_affairs" showAs="Minister for Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs"/>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/author" showAs="author"/>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/role/editor" showAs="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>COMHCHOISTE UM THALMHAÍOCHT, IASCAIGH AGUS BIA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>JOINT COMMITTEE ON AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2008-07-23">Dé Céadaoin, 23 Iúil 2008</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2008-07-23">Wednesday, 23 July 2008</docDate>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <heading>Prelude</heading>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">The Joint Committee met at 2 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">MEMBERS PRESENT:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_1">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelAhern">Deputy Michael Ahern,*</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_2">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulBradford">Senator Paul Bradford,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#BobbyAylward">Deputy Bobby Aylward,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#JohnCartyFF">Senator John Carty,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelCreed">Deputy Michael Creed,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#JohnEllis">Senator John Ellis,+</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#AndrewDoyle">Deputy Andrew Doyle,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#FrancisOBrien">Senator Francis O’Brien.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#MattieMcGrath">Deputy Mattie McGrath,</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#NedOKeeffe">Deputy Edward O’Keeffe, </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#ChristyOSullivan">Deputy Christy O’Sullivan, </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#EamonScanlon">Deputy Eamon Scanlon, </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_13">
                  <person refersTo="#TomSheahan">Deputy Tom Sheahan, </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_14">
                  <person refersTo="#PJSheenan">Deputy P. J. Sheehan,  </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_15">
                  <person refersTo="#SeanSherlock">Deputy Seán Sherlock, </person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_3">*In the absence of Deputy Thomas McEllistrim.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_4">+In the absence of Senator Francis O'Brien for part of meeting.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#JohnnyBrady">DEPUTY JOHNNY BRADY IN THE CHAIR.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Business of Joint Committee.</heading>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_1">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_16">Apologies have been received from Deputy Thomas McEllistrim.  Is it agreed that we go into private session to discuss private business?  Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">The joint committee went into private session at 2.05 p.m. and resumed in public session at 2.40 p.m.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_18">Before I welcome the Minister for Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs, I extend a message of sympathy on my own behalf and on behalf of the committee to Deputy Aylward on the death of his mother.  Unfortunately, I was out of the country when the committee received notice of her death.  We are very sorry about the Deputy's bereavement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FrancisOBrien" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Senator Francis O’Brien</from>
          <p eId="para_19">We all wish to be associated with the Chairman's words of condolence.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Leader Programme: Discussion with Minister for Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs.</heading>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_20">I welcome Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív, Minister for Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs to today's meeting to discuss the Leader programme.  The funding aspect of the Leader programme was raised with the former Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Deputy Mary Coughlan, when she was discussing the Estimates.  It was then that the committee decided to invite the Minister, Deputy Ó Cuív, here today.  I believe this is the first occasion for him to address the committee and he is very welcome.</p>
          <p eId="para_21">Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against any person outside the Houses or an official by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.  I invite the Minister to make his opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonOCuiv" as="#Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Minister for Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs (Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív)</from>
          <p eId="para_22">I thank the committee for the invitation to come here.  I shall just say a few brief words on the Leader programme.  We should briefly reflect on the past.  The Leader programme was established on a pilot basis in 1991 and operated in Ireland on that basis from 1992 to the end of 1994 in 16 selected areas.  The programme, which was based on the bottom-up concept of local development, provided an opportunity for companies which chose the projects within rules that were laid down.  At that time the funding was £35 million or €44 million in total.</p>
          <p eId="para_23">Arising from Leader I it was decided that this approach was working well and area-based programmes involving partnerships between the local community and other agencies and interests could play a meaningful role in promoting development.  Following the success of Leader I, the European Commission launched Leader II and then there was Leader Plus and the national Leader programme.  It was important that we adopted an all-area approach.  In other words, when Leader Plus was announced, it was only to cover selected areas of the country and we had a national Leader programme to match it so that all of rural Ireland was covered.  That has been a very important part of our thinking.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">Moving into the new round of the Leader programme, we looked at the structures of development in rural Ireland and decided that every area should have a partnership.  That was not the situation, particularly in Munster, until recently. For example, in Cork I could never understand why the Beara and the Sheep's Head peninsulas were not considered worthy of having a partnership.  We decided to extend the coverage of the local development and social inclusion programme, which is a national initiative, countrywide, but it was also decided that it was sensible for one company to deliver all the initiatives being undertaken nationally as well as the Leader programme in any given area, in other words, a one-stop-shop approach.  That process has been ongoing for some time and will conclude with the designation of 38 integrated Leader partnership companies.  This represents a significant change from the arrangement that applied heretofore.</p>
          <p eId="para_25">Since October 2007, new integrated companies have been established in rural areas.  I have communicated to the boards of these companies that it is now time to finish the process and get on with it.  They have been informed that we will not continue with interim funding if they do not comply with our new requirements.  This process has been ongoing for two years and it is time to call a halt.</p>
          <p eId="para_26">Funding under the new Rural Development Programme 2007-2013 is divided into different axes.  Axis 1 relates to improving the competitiveness of the agriculture sector and comes within the remit of the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food.  Axis 2 involves improving the environment and the countryside and is also within the remit of the same Department.  Axes 3 and 4 are within the remit of my Department.  Axis 3, dealing with quality of life in rural areas and diversification of the rural economy, relates to the operation of the Leader programme, that is, the provision of grants and supports.  Axis 4 relates to the implementation of the Leader programme.  It took me some time to comprehend these different axes.  In the simplest terms, axis 3 provides funding for the grants and supports for applicants, while axis 4 provides the administrative funding.  Although it looks complicated, it is straightforward, once one comprehends what is involved in the different axes.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">The total budget for the rural development programme is €5.7 billion.  Of this, €2.3 billion comes from EU funds and €3.4 billion from the Exchequer.  Funding for the Leader programme, at €425 million, represents a modest subset of less than 10% of the total budget.  However, this is almost three times the €150 million allocation for the 2000-06 period.  There are various estimates as to how much money will be leveraged out of this provision.  Given that the grant often represents less than 50% of total outlay, with a grant of €150,000, for example, towards a €500,000 project, we estimate there will be investment of at least €1 billion.  The Leader companies expect that figure to be €1.7 billion but I prefer to err on the side of caution.  Leader programme activities are funded at a rate of 55% by the European Union.  Of the total public funding available, therefore, €234 million will come from the European Union and the remainder, just less than €200 million, from the Exchequer.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">The new programme offers many challenges and opportunities in addressing the need for improvements in the quality of life in rural areas and providing greater opportunities for farm diversification.  It is focused on the development of small business, rural services, rural recreation and rural tourism.  It is hoped that by focusing on these services, the programme will lead to sustainable development which will, in turn, ensure prosperity for rural areas.  Actions centred on the wider rural community such as the development of rural enterprises based on local natural resources, tourism, village enhancement and environmental initiatives will be delivered in a manner that addresses these challenges and complements on-farm measures.  The measures in the programme remain consistent with the 1999 White Paper on rural development and its commitments relating to the economic and social well-being of rural communities.</p>
          <p eId="para_29">Under the new programme, €16.6 million is provided for diversification into non-agricultural activities for farm families.  These include the development of niche tourism and educational services such as arts and crafts, speciality food provision, open farms and so on.  Some €48.26 million is provided to support business creation and development.  Funding of €45.4 million is provided to encourage tourism activities.</p>
          <p eId="para_30">Basic services for the economy and the rural population have been allocated €49.61 million for measures such as the identification and provision of appropriate cultural and leisure facilities for local communities that are not otherwise available to them.  Village renewal and development have been allocated €54.2 million.  In addition to village renewal, countryside renewal also is included in this regard, as are measures such as walkways along rivers, over mountains etc.  It also pertains to farmers' markets.  Conservation and upgrading of the rural heritage have been allocated €51.7 million.  This could include alternative or renewable energy actions and so on.  Other headings include training and information on adapted and new skills, as well as the implementation of co-operation projects and skills acquisition and animation, which pertains to the development of capacity and so on.</p>
          <p eId="para_31">The process for the selection of the local action groups for the delivery of the new rural development programme commenced on 20 May.  By the closing date for the receipt of applications, 37 business plans had been received.  The plans submitted covered the discrete areas outlined in the application information.  In addition, however, the Department received two business plans from County Clare and two from County Wexford.  All plans are undergoing evaluation.  There is one for every area and parts of counties Clare and Wexford have submitted two applications.</p>
          <p eId="para_32">The evaluation process will result in the selection of groups and allocation of funding on the basis of recommendations from the evaluators.  The final allocations will be subject to Government approval.  It is expected that the programme will be open to applications for grant assistance in late October 2008, after the process for selecting the local action groups to deliver the programme has been completed.</p>
          <p eId="para_33">In general, while the maximum rate of aid under the development programme will be 50%, the following exceptions will apply.  The maximum rates for administration, animation and training will be up to 100%.  The maximum rate for analysis and development will be up to 90% and 75% for community-based projects and private promoters, respectively, subject in all cases to a maximum of €30,000 per project.  Critically, community groups will be eligible for a higher rate of aid of 75% when such a higher rate of grant would not discriminate against private interests or promoters in the same sphere of activity.  Obviously, when one undertakes a project such as the construction of a community hall, there is no question of competition.</p>
          <p eId="para_34">Another initiative that has been taken is the case of a focal community project, where the normal maximum grant aid will be €200,000, whereas the usual maximum will be €150,000.  In certain circumstances, one can receive €200,000.  However, with the permission of the Department, one may receive up to €500,000 in respect of a community not-for-profit project.  This is because certain community facilities are needed and the provision of a grant of €150,000 or even €200,000 would not build anything substantial.  I strongly believe that cases could arise in which one would wish to give a higher grant.  Consequently, such provisions are in place for exceptional circumstances.  However, I stress the pot of money is limited.  Leader groups will not dispense grants of €500,000 to every community group in the country because were they to do so, they would run out of money in jig time.  This presentation has served as a lead-in to the forthcoming discussion.  I expect there will be plenty of questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_35">I thank the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TomSheahan" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Deputy Tom Sheahan</from>
          <p eId="para_36">I welcome the Minister and thank him for his presentation. I should state that in a former life I served as a board member in the Leader group associated with IRD Duhallow.  When I noted this meeting was scheduled, I went to the Department's website and retrieved some information for my own use.</p>
          <p eId="para_37">To break this down, it is full of administration.  First, one of the points is that the Leader programme will be unable to co-fund with other agencies.  While I was a board member in IRD Duhallow, the work we got done through the co-operation of the community, county councils and Leader groups was unbelievable.  Excellent work was done.  Taking this route is a retrograde step.  I know about the volunteer work we got done in our community.  Grant aid will be taken away from the local Leader groups and determined by a civil servant.  Power will be taken away and very little will be done locally by the Leader group.  Everything will have to come to Dublin. If my colleague, Deputy Sheehan, wanted to volunteer, the project would be sent to the departmental offices for approval and that could take up to six months, and if he broke his leg in the meantime while dancing a set at the crossroads and was unable to do volunteer work, the whole project could be in jeopardy. That must be examined.</p>
          <p eId="para_38">Although I do not have a problem with it, the requirements and regulations on the appointment of new Leader boards are strict and tight and one asks why that is so.  When I was on the board I supported certain projects but some were turned down.  Perhaps it was for a good reason.  There was a thorough process of evaluating projects but if they must be adjudicated by civil servants, which will take up to six months, power will be taken from the local Leader groups and the same amount of work will not be done.</p>
          <p eId="para_39">Employment grants to businesses that are labour intensive should be allowed.  This supports small business.  The limit of ten members of staff in a small business to qualify for funding must be examined.  Anything over ten means that the small business does not qualify for funding.  Ten members of staff is a tidy number in any small business nowadays.</p>
          <p eId="para_40">My big fear is the amount of paperwork and bureaucracy involved.  Co-funding is a major issue and the Minister should consider Leader groups getting their grant allocations on a quarterly basis.  There is no point in the Leader board assessing a pile of applications if it is not getting funding quarterly.  This would be more workable.  I am a major supporter of the Leader programme but a few points could be tweaked to make it more consumer friendly and so that it could be dealt with in communities.  We are not availing of joint funding opportunities with different agencies.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Seán Sherlock</from>
          <p eId="para_41">I welcome the Minister and thank him for his contribution.  There is much to digest with axis 1 and axis 4 in respect of what the roll-out of the new programme will mean.  If I understand the Minister correctly, axis 4 will deal with the administrative costs of dealing with axis 3.  The cost of administration and the black hole, which arguably administration has become in some parts of the country, could be tested, quantified and qualified in this context and I welcome a distinction between the two.</p>
          <p eId="para_42">Should this programme be examined in the context of the CAP health check, which I understand will shift investment from direct subsidisation into what Commissioner Fischer Boel refers to as developing the rural economy and rural development, what impact will the programme have on the EU CAP health check proposals?  Are the two interlinked?  Are they coincidental?  Will the Minister give us an insight into this?</p>
          <p eId="para_43">In my area of north Cork, Avondhu Development Group proposes to amalgamate with Blackwater Resource Development.  Avondhu Development Group provides social inclusion programmes and this will be married with rural development programmes.  What is the natural synergy between these groups?  Will the focus shift towards rural development predominantly in the context of the proposals before us?</p>
          <p eId="para_44">The constituency I represent is reflective of many rural constituencies throughout the country.  Programmes such as this have wonderful aspirational views of community centres, leisure facilities and diversifying farm income into tourism.  Not every farmer will be able to provide a tourist product and not every person who benefits from it will be able to travel on a road that is adequate.  My point is that roads in north Cork are in great need of investment but are completely underfunded.  The position is the same throughout County Cork.</p>
          <p eId="para_45">If we discuss the development of a rural economy and infrastructure we must discuss adequate funding for local authorities, either managed by local authorities or co-funded through this programme with local authorities to ensure the infrastructure, including water, roads and sewerage, is there and that it is adequate, prior to discussing value-added projects.  I would heartily welcome the Minister to the part of the country I represent to travel some of the roads I must travel, which are starved of funding.  It is not right to discuss proper rural economy and society without also discussing the facilities provided in that regard.  Will the Minister give us his views on this?</p>
          <p eId="para_46">With regard to improving the quality of life in rural areas, we have a demographic of people who have lived in rural Ireland all their lives and who have farmed and inter-generationally lived in a rural economy or society.  We also have people who are originally of an urban mindset who move into a rural economy, which changes the dynamic.  How does the Minister propose to change and enhance the quality of life?  What practical programmes does he envisage will bring this about?</p>
          <p eId="para_47">I welcome the proposals on funding for community-based facilities, but they need to be teased out a little further.  However, there is still a major deficit and the danger is that much of this funding will go into administration.  We want to see real change and real value added.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MattieMcGrath" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Deputy Mattie McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_48">I welcome the Minister and his officials.  I have been involved with the Leader programme since the start.  It is an excellent programme for rural Ireland.  I compliment the Minister and his officials on their foresight and endurance in bringing forward these changes which have resulted in greater cohesion, with one organisational unit responsible for each county area.  A lot of battles had to be fought and a lot of noise was made.  I thank the Minister for his time and patience and for the level of consultation that took place, certainly in my county.  Much effort was expended by him in getting this process under way.  Now that we have it up and running, I look forward to its full roll-out.</p>
          <p eId="para_49">I do not agree with what some of my colleagues have said with regard to the process being overly bureaucratic.  We are smothered with bureaucracy in this country in general, but this is an effort to reduce bureaucracy by getting rid of five or six agencies dealing with the same issues and overlapping with one another.  I compliment the Minister.  I look forward to the roll-out and to being actively involved on the ground.  I know the Minister is also keen to ensure that the roll-out is successful.  On a recent visit to my constituency he said that he is anxious that there should be periodic checks to determine how the roll-out is progressing.  It is up to all of us to ensure that it is successful and to give the Leader companies as much support as possible.</p>
          <p eId="para_50">While we all have poor roads in our counties, one would think we were living in Cambodia at times, the way members describe our road network.  It is not as bad as some claim.  I compliment the Minister above all others on the efforts he is making--</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy Seán Sherlock</from>
          <p eId="para_51">The Deputy would be more than welcome to come and look at some of our roads.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MattieMcGrath" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Deputy Mattie McGrath</from>
          <p eId="para_52">I will go down some time to see them.  I did not think the roads of north Cork were so bad.  If they are, I sympathise but I do not believe they are as bad as people suggest.</p>
          <p eId="para_53">These changes will get rid of a lot of the bureaucracy.  We do not want agencies tripping over one another.  As I understand it, there will be interaction between the county councils and others who are co-funding projects and delivering results, albeit not fast enough.  I hope this will be a wake-up call.  Some people will obviously be discommoded and rightly so.  Perhaps they were too cosy and the ordinary punter was not getting his or her pound of flesh.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_54">On that issue, I have found with the county council in my area that there is much talk about what the council will do but when it comes to providing matching funds, it does not want to hear about it.  If the Minister does not mind, I will call on all members to pose questions and then allow him to respond.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonOCuiv" eId="spk_13" as="#Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív</from>
          <p eId="para_55">Whichever way the Chairman wants to do it is fine with me.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_56">That is the way we usually proceed because many of the questions will relate to one another.  Deputy Scanlon is next.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonScanlon" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Deputy Eamon Scanlon</from>
          <p eId="para_57">I thank the Minister for his presentation and welcome Mr. O'Reilly to the meeting.  There is no doubt that the Leader programme has been very beneficial for rural Ireland.  As I know from my area, it has made an enormous difference, particularly for those living in isolated areas.</p>
          <p eId="para_58">I welcome the Minister's announcement today of extra funding of €425 million, compared with €150 million in the last programme.  How does the Minister see this Leader programme affecting the CAP health check?  I also welcome the fact that communities with project proposals that can achieve sustainable employment can access a grant of up to €500,000.  While it is not a grant that every village or town will apply for in the first instance, or obtain for that matter, I welcome the fact that it is available.  In tourism, for example, there are many areas where people could provide accommodation where there was none previously, which would be one way of creating jobs.</p>
          <p eId="para_59">The rural social scheme has been the most beneficial scheme ever introduced in rural Ireland.  People who were achieving only marginal incomes from their land were given the opportunity to avail of this scheme, which is very flexible.  I am aware of cases where farmers' wives are taking part in the scheme on behalf of their husbands.  There is no doubt that it has increased the income of such people and were it not for that income, they would not survive.</p>
          <p eId="para_60">I again thank the Minister for his presentation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_61">I welcome the Minister.  As he comes from an area that is similar to my impoverished constituency of Cork South-West.  He represents the impoverished constituency of Galway West he knows only too well the disadvantages under which we have laboured for generations in trying to improve the economy of our areas.  I was delighted by his elaborate plans for the years up to 2012.  Almost two years have passed since the programme was commenced in October 2007.  Improving the competitiveness of the agriculture sector is of paramount importance.</p>
          <p eId="para_62">Huge milk tankers travel along narrow roads and the road surfaces are damaged by their weight.  This causes significant problems but the county council lacks the money for repairs.  I am sure the Minister is aware of similar roads in his area, which I visited several years ago.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_63">We are not talking about the CLÁR programme today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_64">Some of these roads have not seen a shovel of chips or a bit of tar in the past 50 years.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_65">This is not a county council meeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_66">I am speaking about an aspect of infrastructure which is important to agriculture.  We do not have the beautiful motorways that pass through County Meath.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TomSheahan" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Deputy Tom Sheahan</from>
          <p eId="para_67">We have bad roads.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_68">This is not a county council meeting.  We are discussing the Leader programme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_69">Axis 2 provides for improvements to the environment in the countryside.  Axis 1 and 2 are related to what I am discussing.  Axis 3 deals with quality of life in rural areas.  How can we have a good quality of life in rural areas without proper infrastructure?  It is all right for my colleague from south Tipperary, which has good roads and a strong tourist attraction in the Rock of Cashel.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_70">Can the Minister do away with every other programme and put all this money into rural roads?  Is that what members want?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_71">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_72">He wants a county council meeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_73">If that is what members want, they should put forward that proposal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_74">The total funding for the programme is €5.778 billion over a seven-year period, of which €2.339 billion will be funded by the European agricultural fund for rural development and €3.438 billion by the Exchequer.  Will the Exchequer be able to fund its portion over five years?  I thought we were told to cut back on spending.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_75">Does the Deputy want it to go ahead?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_76">I want it to go ahead.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_77">He is in favour of it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_78">I want rural Ireland to be transformed into a decent place in which to live.  I remind Deputy Aylward that a person in Ballydehob is entitled to the same privileges as a person in Ballsbridge.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_79">I do not come from Ballsbridge, I come from a rural area.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_80">I ask Deputy Sheehan to speak about the Leader programme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_81">I want an assurance from the Minister that he will get the moneys he needs in the next three years.  We will not be spending much this year but I want an assurance that we will get €3.438 billion from the Exchequer.  The Minister said the next phase of the cohesion process would involve the transfer of staff and assets from the merging Leader and partnership groups to the new integrated bodies and that with this in mind the Department recently appointed a consultant to assist the new boards in the process of selecting candidates and the position of chief executive.  Will we be top-heavy with executives and programme managers?  The Minister will know what happened to the health boards.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_82">We cannot discuss that issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_83">I am discussing what is before me.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_84">We are discussing the Leader programme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_85">The process involves the merging of the Leader and partnership groups into new integrated bodies.  What percentage of the programme grant will go into that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_86">I request that the Deputy ask a question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_87">The plan focuses on the development of small businesses, rural services, rural recreation and rural tourism.  Rural tourism is finished in my constituency for the lack of a ferry service from Cork to Swansea.  Will the Minister give us an allocation from all his billions of euro to build rural tourism?  What is the purpose of building rural tourism in west Cork?  Is it for the badgers and the foxes?  We want to bring people in but we cannot do so if we have not got the infrastructure.  We have no railway system to west Cork and no airport, yet we are bigger than many counties in Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_88">The Deputy has been speaking for 15 minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_89">How did the Minister get up to Dublin?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_90">I ask the Deputy to conclude.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_91">I want this money to be put into practical measures for the people of rural Ireland to ensure they gain from the extra people it will bring into the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_92">It seems the Deputy is proposing that the Leader programme be done away with.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_93">I am not.  Why did the Department recently appoint a consultant to assist new boards in the process of selecting candidates for the position of chief executive?  Does a board need to be set up to select an executive?  I am afraid all the money will be gobbled up by red tape and bureaucracy.  I will allow the Minister to defend his position.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_94">I ask members to concentrate on the Leader programme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ChristyOSullivan" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Deputy Christy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_95">What we should be trying to do is get as much money as we can for west Cork.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_96">It will be eaten up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_97">Deputy Sheehan, please allow Deputy O'Sullivan to speak.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ChristyOSullivan" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Deputy Christy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_98">I welcome the Minister.  We are lucky to have a Minister who has a good understanding of rural Ireland.  I have no doubt that under his command we will create a very successful Leader programme.  I stress the importance of the programme and its roll-out.  It involves a lot of money and a huge increase on what we received in the past.  The use to which it is put is important for us all.</p>
          <p eId="para_99">I will ask a few questions on the various headings, one of which covers support to start a new business or expand an existing enterprise.  Those headings are being allocated specific funding but is that ring-fenced or is there room for manoeuvre?  There may not be much take-up under some of the various headings.  Where do we go if there is no take-up in specific areas?  Do we move it on or is the funding ring-fenced for the specific heading?</p>
          <p eId="para_100">The Minister mentioned Beara, which is one of the areas one can point to that can avail, and should be able to avail, of this type of funding.  The area is very dependent on it, particularly the fishing industry there, which as we know is on its knees.  There is some reference to the fact that funding can be put in that direction for people who are leaving the industry and want to start up some activity, perhaps related to fishing.  I do not know what specific funding is available for this but I would like to see us concentrating on such initiatives.</p>
          <p eId="para_101">Such action is significant as there is no other chance for those people of getting into any major industry or getting anything worthwhile.  These are small industries.  If we lose those communities and their people, it will be very difficult for us to reinstate them or bring them back into being again.  Will the Minister clarify those few points?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_102">I welcome the Minister and compliment him on his presentation.  I am surprised at how critical my colleagues are of what is proposed today, where we will spend €5.778 billion in the next six years to 2013.  This will be spent on invigorating rural development.  I would think we would welcome that as most of us are from rural Ireland, particularly the farming community.</p>
          <p eId="para_103">With all the cutbacks being proposed by the EU and with us being a prosperous country, the fact that we will still get €2.339 billion from the EU in the next six years should be welcomed with open arms.  I compliment the Minister on that initiative.  Since the Minister first took his role at the Department of Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs, he has always put to the fore the rural well-being of Ireland.  He has always looked to development in rural areas and tried to keep them alive and running.</p>
          <p eId="para_104">Statements were made about rural roads, sewerage and other resources, which are important, although the Leader programme should not be responsible for the make-up of rural roads or providing the resources for sewerage, water etc.  That would come under a different heading.  I have worked in Kilkenny County Council and it is the responsibility of the local authorities to look after the roads.  They receive grants and in Kilkenny many initiatives and other progress have taken place in the resurfacing of roads in recent years, although it is never enough.  There is never enough anywhere and money must be divided equally.</p>
          <p eId="para_105">I welcome the proposal that has been put forward today, which will do away with red tape.  I have experience of the system in Kilkenny, which had four local groups, including CDCD and BNS, all doing different things.  I often found it puzzling to know where I would send people for money and which of the groups would be relevant.  That is now being done away with.</p>
          <p eId="para_106">Instead of having duplication and waste of money, there will be 38 agencies, with one in every county or local authority.  We will send people to the one area or agency and we will know where people need to go for 50%, 75% or 100% funding.  Some €500,000 in funding is possible in certain cases.  We want to do away with duplication and red tape.</p>
          <p eId="para_107">There was mention of a consultant coming in to pick a CEO.  This must happen because we need a good CEO and a good body to run the 38 agencies.  This is important and I welcome it.</p>
          <p eId="para_108">I would like to ask the Minister a few questions about the make-up of the new bodies. There will be a CEO. I believe the boards will be big enough. I would be worried about boards which are too big because the bigger the board the less work is done. It becomes more of a talking shop. I would like more compact boards, with a membership of perhaps 12 or 14. I do not know how many are on the new proposed boards. There should be smaller boards which actually work rather than talking shops in which there is much duplication and people get nowhere. Are local authorities represented on the boards? Who will be on them and what bodies will be represented?</p>
          <p eId="para_109">This is a great boost to rural Ireland. We always need as much money as possible to be spent on rural Ireland in every area. The fact that this much money, almost €5.5 billion, is to be spent in the next six years is to be welcomed. It will be a major boost to rural society which will keep it alive and vibrant.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulBradford" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Senator Paul Bradford</from>
          <p eId="para_110">I welcome the Minister and thank him for his presentation.  I welcome the new programme, which represents a significant amount of funding.  At a time when the country, particularly rural Ireland, appears to have fallen out of love with the European Union, it is significant that the EU is providing 55% of the funding for this programme.  It is important that we consider this and recognise what the EU has done and continues to do for rural Ireland.</p>
          <p eId="para_111">The overall funding should produce great results in rural Ireland.  The two enemies of the progress we hope to make will be the terrible twins of administration and duplication.  I hope we will try to minimise these.  I concur with the previous speaker in this regard.  I am not an expert on the Leader concept in its totality and I am aware there have been difficulties in terms of amalgamations, some of which have been seen as forced.  However, the coming together of groups should work out to everybody's advantage in the long run and should certainly reduce bureaucracy and red tape.</p>
          <p eId="para_112">I would be interested to hear the Minister's thoughts on how the new groupings will work with the local authorities.  Recently we have been considering budgets for local government, the role of county councillors and so on.  If we were starting to build the State from scratch and were realistic about local government, we would ensure the work of the Leader groups was carried out by local authorities.  However, we cannot rewrite history.  How close will be the involvement between local authorities and the Leader groups?  I reiterate that I am not an expert in this area, but I heard recently from some of the people involved in the north Cork Leader groups that the proposed new board would be chaired by the local authority manager.  Is this for an interim period or is it permanent?  It is probably only an interim arrangement.  I would like to hear the Minister's view on how we should liaise with local authorities.</p>
          <p eId="para_113">The programmes and measures outlined by the Minister are significant.  I wish the Minister well and hope we can maximise results and community involvement with the minimum of red tape, bureaucracy and administration.  However, there must be accountability and transparency.  My colleagues have complained about what is being done or not being done by local authorities - I have joined in these complaints - but at least local government, with all its faults, has transparency and accountability.  Every five years councillors must go before the public to be hired or fired.  We need the same level of transparency and accountability in our Leader boards.  We are talking about significant funding - hundreds of millions of euro - and we want that money spent well.  I hope the programmes outlined by the Minister will work because they are important for our rural economy.</p>
          <p eId="para_114">The Minister did not mention modulation and the possibility of fresh new thinking at European level in this area.  Can he let us know where he stands on that issue?  The concept of additional money being poured directly into rural development could be seen as attractive but there are downsides at a time of falling property prices and reducing numbers in agriculture.  What is the Government's thinking on the issue and where does the debate stand at European level?  While it might mean more money for rural development, such as via the Leader programme, there are risks as well.</p>
          <p eId="para_115">I wish the Minister well and I am aware of his deep commitment in this area.  It has been great, in the past seven to ten years, to travel the length and breadth of rural Ireland and see parish halls, village halls and crossroads adorned with plaques celebrating projects of various sizes which had been supported by Europe or the Leader programme.  It shows how small the Continent is becoming and how interdependent we are.  We need to continue that process.  If we can minimise administration, duplication and red tape we will do very well.</p>
          <p eId="para_116">When constituents ask me where they can get grants for projects it is difficult to know what to tell them.  I almost have to have a consultant with me at all times to advise me on how to advise them.  One can immediately think of five or six funding routes for some projects, such as the national lottery, the local authority or the Leader or partnership programmes.  Will we be able to improve the situation so that we can advise on a clear path for people to follow for funding and advice?  If we can make the programme happen it will be a great help to rural Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_117">As I must be last to speak, I will be as quick as possible.  I thank the Minister for his presentation.</p>
          <p eId="para_118">Will the 2007-13 programme have to close in 2013 or is there another year, given the Minister wants the money to be spent wisely?  The cohesion principle is welcome.  If it achieves efficiencies in processing and costs it will be very welcome.  Does the Minister know what percentage of the total €5.7 billion budget is for administration?</p>
          <p eId="para_119">We need clarification on the parameters in respect of co-funding.  For example, the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food has agreed to provide ring-fenced grant aid for abattoirs operating under a small unit base of 1,000 per year.  If a particular abattoir operates in conjunction with a larger project within a community, say to establish a full co-op or farmers' market, will it be compromised in its application for grant aid through another stream?</p>
          <p eId="para_120">Will community employment schemes be permitted or prohibited in any projects funded by a Leader programme?  Anything that develops rural economies is welcome because the cushion provided by off-farm income from the construction industry is in decline.</p>
          <p eId="para_121">Deputy Christy O'Sullivan mentioned the fisheries sector but it has not been mentioned elsewhere.  Was a fisheries operation programme application submitted?  I am given to understand there was but it may not have been approved.</p>
          <p eId="para_122">There has already been a question on the composition of the boards and the make-up with regard to members from the groups which are coming together.  On the point of modulation, there is no fear that money from a CAP health check, if it comes to pass, which modulates money into rural development, will be transferred from one European fund to the other, and the €2.34 billion does not consist of money that is already within the CAP.  There is no fear of that money being directly transferred.</p>
          <p eId="para_123">Everything else has been covered.  I do not want to be seen as a killjoy on this as it is a programme and concept we must work towards.  We have a changing face to rural society and as Deputy Sherlock mentioned, we have rural communities which are much more diverse than they were 25 or 30 years ago.  If we are trying to cut down mileage transport to employment, we have with the addition of broadband and initiatives like this to add to the potential to develop strong rural communities.  Their pillar may still be based on agriculture and its by-products and we must do whatever we can to help.</p>
          <p eId="para_124">I do not want it argued that people on this side of the House are not prepared to work with such a process, as we certainly are.  There are legitimate concerns which need to be addressed.  Now is the time to do this rather than halfway through the programme, when we discover we have made mistakes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_125">I wish to be associated with the other members in welcoming the Minister and complimenting him on the great work he is doing for rural Ireland in keeping it alive.  I will not raise the matter again but I would like the Minister to return to discuss the CLÁR programme.  Many people were talking about roads, which do not concern this particular issue.  We all have concerns about roads where county councils do not match the funding provided by the Minister's Department.  Unfortunately, we are all confronted with that.  That is for a different day and I hope the Minister will come back to discuss CLÁR issues with us.</p>
          <p eId="para_126">I compliment the chief executive of the Meath Leader programme, which has done tremendous work through the years.  As Deputy Aylward said, we had different organisations and one knows the famous north Meath community organisation, which I do not want to discuss today.  It is dead and thanks be to God it is long gone as it caused more friction and problems than it solved with the particular concerns we had with it.</p>
          <p eId="para_127">There are a few areas on which I would like to compliment the Leader groups, such as diversification into non-agricultural activities for farm families.  Many small farmers diversified into other projects such as cheese making and tourism.  It was a great programme for such people and small businesses in different areas.  Village renewal and development has been a fantastic programme.  The amount of work that has been done in villages and rural areas down through the years is tremendous.  There has been much talk and promotion regarding farmers' markets.  What is the uptake in that area?</p>
          <p eId="para_128">I have read that the Minister is leading the annual commemoration of the Famine.  Although it may not be a relevant issue, the Minister is here and I compliment him on the fact we will have an annual commemoration ceremony.  I was recently asked to speak at the annual ceremony in my town of Kells, at the Famine graveyard at the Hill of Lloyd.  We should all get involved in this and I compliment the town council in Kells, which organised the Famine day and asked me to be one of the speakers.  We should all be involved and I compliment the Minister on his work.  When the Minister comes back to the committee to talk about CLÁR funding he might discuss this also.  I thank the Minister and ask him to respond to the various questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonOCuiv" eId="spk_57" as="#Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív</from>
          <p eId="para_129">As many issues have been raised, I will try to cover the points thematically rather than in sequence.</p>
          <p eId="para_130">Regarding programmes, in general, even under the last programme, there was a ban on co-funding with other public money.  That was always so.  However, local authority money was deemed to be private money because in other countries it is provided through rates.  In addition, money from the national lottery is exempt from the co-funding rule because money paid for lotto tickets is not State money.  I asked the Commissioner about development levies and so on and she was fairly negative in this regard.  We are going to a much higher grant percentage; we will have a 75% grant for community projects.  In the last Leader programme it was often the case that 50% of the money came from the  Leader programme and 25% from the local authority, but this time projects will get 75% from one source and the local authority will still have the money in its pocket.  I do not think we should be too negative in this regard.  The total possible grant is also higher.  The last time the maximum grant was €100,000.  Even the ordinary grants now go to €200,000, and with community grants we can go above that.  Much of the reason for co-funding in the past was to do with the severe limits placed on the State aid regime, which have now been dealt with.  We are investigating the possibility of allowing some local authority funding within EU rules.  This is one area in which I would like a breakthrough and I will continue banging away on it.</p>
          <p eId="para_131">I have some general comments on the wider issue of co-funding. Since long before I entered politics I have been unable to see the logic of the State having one source of funding, namely, the taxpayer, from which money comes through the Exchequer and into the Estimates, while people go to six State agencies to put a few hundred thousand euro together and it saves the taxpayer nothing.  It is similar to the Nile delta, which starts with one river that breaks up into many minor rivers and then comes together again into a single river.  Similarly, the money is split and then comes back to one project.  I do not see the logic of this.  From most people's point of view, the fewer bodies involved in funding and the bigger the percentage and total grant that can be given, the better.  In the Gaeltacht, early on, I asked the enterprise boards to get out because Údarás could do the same job and there was no reason to drive people mad going from agency to agency.  I noted what members said about local authority funding and we will work on that issue to see whether we can get a breakthrough.</p>
          <p eId="para_132">Questions were asked about how much power local groups will have.  My Department will be funding these groups to about €200 million every year between partnerships and Leader partnerships.  From the point of view of good spending, the most important factor is accountancy control, rather than the decision on which project to choose.  When we are spending that kind of money we must have accountability.  My Secretary General must answer to the Committee of Public Accounts on the spending of this money.  When it comes to practice in terms of spending money, we must make sure a good process is followed.  That goes without saying.  I read the operating rules in detail and went back with detailed suggestions for amendments to deal with little things I was not happy about.  However, I do not think there is much in the operating rules that does not deal with essential aspects such as tax compliance.  There is nothing in the rules that makes the system unusually bureaucratic.</p>
          <p eId="para_133">The local group will have the same power as ever to decide on projects.  All we have said is that for 5% of projects we will carry out a pre-check to make sure they are eligible.  It will be a very quick pre-check.  There is a certain advantage to this.  If we let things go we may suddenly find ourselves in an argument with those on the European side because they say a project is not eligible.  We will carry out a pre-check on 5% of projects, which will be completed quickly.  It will not be a matter of six months.  My officials can confirm that my Department is not too bad in terms of getting things off desks.  However, only 5% of projects will be subject to this check.  Money for administration will be pre-paid and, in addition, once projects are approved the money will be made available.  The greatest problem for me, as Minister, is all the money I sanctioned for projects up and down the country, between local authorities and others, projects that nonetheless are not happening.  I have put aside the money for these projects and it cannot be allocated to others.  However, because I cannot get those who have signed up to use it, it lies dead.</p>
          <p eId="para_134">I speak here in a wide context.  I am on a mission in terms of "Use it or lose it".  Members will have heard of sunset clauses in projects where there is a year or other fixed time to spend money.  The Department is now looking at the concept of "sunrise" clauses.  If a group declares it wants to do something it must start to do it within three or four months or the money will be taken away.  Our finding was - I believe Leader companies had the same problem - that money was given to someone and written off in the books so that it could not then be given to anybody else.  A year later, however, nothing had been done.  As that was unfair to others who might have done something,  we are pushing this concept of "Use it or lose it" across my Department.  However, if a group has a good reason for requiring extended time that can always be arranged.</p>
          <p eId="para_135">Voluntary labour is allowed.  Why is there a rule of ten staff?  The reason is that ten is what the county enterprise boards allow.  If we were to say that more than ten staff were permitted, the enterprise boards and the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Enterprise, Trade and Employment would be in here taking my head off for queering their pitch.</p>
          <p eId="para_136">Concerning basic infrastructure, I am more than willing to come back and discuss, for example, the CLÁR programme and the rural social scheme, RSS, as two departmental programmes that are totally national.  However, I do not agree with the argument that infrastructure must be in place before development.  In parts of the country there are examples of infrastructure, some better than others, some worse.  It would be lovely to have infrastructure in place before starting a development.  As somebody who started on a mountain boreen and then waited 20 years to get the infrastructure I have no regrets.  If I had waited for the infrastructure to arrive first there would never have been anything where we built.  I will tell a funny story about that.  The first thing we did was to build the lamb fattening station that turned into a timber mill.  One night we blessed it and it turned into a timber mill.  I was very young and innocent and probably did not do enough organising.  We got our planning permission and signed a certain company to put up the steel structure.  The workers arrived with the steel on a big lorry but the lorry could not turn up the boreen which was too narrow.  We had to unload the steel and pull it up by tractor.  Perhaps they have painted it in the past five years but for years there was mud on that steel in the ceiling where we had dragged it along the road.  We got the place built, overcame our problems and the roads were eventually built too.  The mill is there today.  To any community that wants to sit on its hands and wait for the infrastructure to be 100% perfect before starting, good luck to them.  There are other communities in the most unlikely places up boreens who will just get on with the job and spend the money.</p>
          <p eId="para_137">I am not interested in people who see a problem in every opportunity.  I am much more disposed towards those who see opportunities in every issue that arises.  I admire the lady in Kerry who offered herself as a fully licensed sit-by driver to those who did not have a full licence, making herself a few bob from that rule.  There are two mindsets - one always arrives at a problem, the other comes with the solution to the problem.</p>
          <p eId="para_138">The Leader programme ethos is like the old GAA syndrome.  It is about giving money to each group but if one group does not want to spend it we will give it to the one which wants to spend it.  That is fine by me.  There are many examples, for instance, west Cork has its fantastic Fuchsia brand.  The Leader programme in Arrigna had the bank  spending.  Every time another group could not spend its money, this group had its hand out for it.  Nobody could say that the area of north Roscommon and Leitrim is the most favoured geographical part of the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_139">The notion I want to spread is that we are offering groups freedom and money.  They can spend it, but if they cannot spend it they must return it to us so that we can give it to someone who can use the money.  No mercy will be shown.  I am interested in the psychology of motivation.  GAA clubs do not get help from their neighbours, but beat the "you know what" out of them.  The driving force for the GAA is that each club is independent and must paddle its own canoe.  If it does not, all it gets is a hiding from the next club in the next town or parish.  That has driven mega development of sports facilities, coaching and training in Ireland.  Rural areas have not lost out because of that competitive element.  The more competition there is, the better.  Whenever I go into an area and people say they have all sorts of problems I say that is okay, that I will give the funding to the next area.  They always call me back and say they will get on with matters.  It is important to get that kind of motivation.</p>
          <p eId="para_140">Somebody asked whether the money was ring-fenced or could it be moved between headings.  It is allocated under various headings but it can be moved around in time.  If money is not being spent under a particular heading, an application can be made to move it to another heading.  The money relates to the period from 2007 to 2013.  Every project must be approved by the end of 2013, but Leader companies have until 2014 and the beginning of 2015 to make the claim and spend the money.  Europe will have all of the money rebated to us by the end of 2015.  The companies will have to have the job done by the end of 2014.  The final approval will be in 2013 but the companies will have to be given time to complete.  We are probably eight months to a year later starting than we had hoped for but we have the same amount of money and it is not a huge amount to spend when it is divided between 38 groups.  I do not believe there will be any problems spending the money we have, so let us get on with it.  The faster we spend it the better.</p>
          <p eId="para_141">There was a very practical question concerning a large project with several elements to it.  The Leader programme may fund one element of a project and ICP may fund another element of the project.  An element of a project can be funded as long as it is a discrete element in its own right, and it is possible to use voluntary labour or CE and RS schemes.  I hope that answers the questions.  If there are questions I have not answered I am happy to be reminded of them.  There is a fisheries fund but I do not have details of it.  I will ask the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food to submit the information to the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_142">A question in regard to cohesion boards, chief executives and what we are doing was put very eloquently.  I do not develop my policies on Mespil Road, although I come from Ballsbridge originally.  Deputy Sheehan mentioned Ballsbridge.  I am probably the only one here who comes from Ballsbridge.  It is a fine place that also needs a bit of infrastructure.  I develop my policies as a result of meeting constituents at my clinics and in the communities.  All of us who operate out of rural areas day by day encounter the problem, mentioned by Senator Bradford, of people looking for money for a small enterprise only to be sent from one agency to the next and ending up going around in circles.  That is codology.  I cannot eliminate it totally.  However, I will do anything within my power to try to create one body that can say "yes" or "no".  Some people like the idea of having 15 State agencies competing with one another.  I think it is a cod that there should be one State agency to do one thing and it should be the only one doing it.  I decided, therefore, that there should be one Leader partnership company delivering the various schemes in my Department and other Departments where relevant in any given area, so there would be a local authority and a local Leader partnership company.  It will deliver the rural social scheme, the Leader programmes and all the recreation development we are now doing.  In other words, everything we want delivered locally we have added, including parts of the CLÁR programme and the local development social inclusion programme, the LDSIP, known as the partnership process.  That makes sense in my view.  I was involved in development for years in elimination of rural poverty and so on.  That is the second point on which I take issue with Deputy Sheehan.  Connemara is not poor.  West Cork might be.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PJSheenan" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Deputy P. J. Sheehan</from>
          <p eId="para_143">Connemara is not poor because it has Deputy Ó Cuív as Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_144">Please allow the Minister to continue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonOCuiv" eId="spk_60" as="#Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív</from>
          <p eId="para_145">I was involved in development and my experience was that the greatest eliminator of rural isolation, rural poverty and rural disadvantage was economic development.  If we kept the people with their families and they were gainfully employed, it meant the older parents had their families living in the area.  They were bringing them to mass, calling in and out of the houses, and the older people were not lonely.  I do not see the work of the partnership side, the LDSIP side, as being separate from the development work of the Leader programme.  They are complementary.  In my experience of rural development, long before I became a public representative, that was the way we approached it.  What we need is economic development with a social conscience and that is what this programme aims to provide.</p>
          <p eId="para_146">The rural social scheme - I do not want to go into the detail today - is a perfect example of how we can solve what was basically a social problem with people on low incomes being isolated on farms while, on the other hand, provide major economic and physical benefit for the countryside by using the latent labour that was available to provide a significant range of services for the community.  They are not separate.  I want the Leader partnership companies to examine the totality of their areas and develop them economically and socially.  We must then have progress to identify those who, for social or other reasons, do not get picked up, so to speak.  That is what we are trying to do.</p>
          <p eId="para_147">The second issue is to do with the consultants to pick the chief executives.  I never saw so much "bailiwicking" in all of my life between the boards and staff members who were jockeying for position because we cut the number of companies from 95 or 96 to a total nationally of 55.  Approximately 95 chief executives are vying for 55 jobs and one can imagine the scramble that will take place for the prestige job in each case.  To make sure the process was fair and not open to challenge, we offered to give technical advice to the new companies as to how they pick the chief executive to ensure they would not end up in the High Court in cases for not having followed the proper process.  That is what the consultation is about.  It is obvious that when approximately 95 jobs are being reduced to 55, there will be a problem.</p>
          <p eId="para_148">The second issue on which I want to be clear concerns the boards, cohesion and structure.  The resistance of the boards at the last minute to holding open and democratic processes of electing those boards concerns me.  Many of the boards fought a rearguard action in the past year, even though their terms of office had ended before they held elections to the new boards.</p>
          <p eId="para_149">I do not care who is on the boards but I do care, on behalf of Members of the House, about the way they got elected to the boards and that the process was fair, open and transparent.  I have never tried to interfere in terms of the personalities involved but we have been prescriptive on the process.  A total of €200 million of State money per year, that is €1 billion in five years, in addition to all the other programmes they run, means that the boards must be accountable not only in terms of the way they spend the money, but how they got there in the first place.</p>
          <p eId="para_150">There are four local authority representatives on the board, a nominee of the county manager, someone from the county enterprise board, representatives of State agencies and people elected from the community and voluntary sector.  The latter was extremely contentious.  We insisted that the directors of community and enterprise, who were not members of the board, would have a role to play in determining the process by which people from the community and voluntary sector - these include the geographic sector and the interest sector, comprised of members of the Traveller community, lone parents, etc. - would be elected to the board.  The directors, therefore, acted as honest brokers in the process.</p>
          <p eId="para_151">We insisted that the directors submit to the Department for ratification the process by which they would elect those to whom I refer to the board in order that we might be satisfied that the system would be fair and open.  It was the system about which we were concerned.  On many occasions Deputies and Senators approach me and state that the members of a particular board are a clique, that they elected themselves and so on.  What was done in this case was designed to eliminate all of that and to ensure that the system would be fair, open and transparent.  It was extraordinarily difficult to have the system accepted.</p>
          <p eId="para_152">Representatives of the social partners - farmers, employers and the unions - also serve on the board.  It is a partnership board on which 23 or 24 people serve.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_153">It is very big.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonOCuiv" eId="spk_62" as="#Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív</from>
          <p eId="para_154">Yes, but there are many who want me to increase the membership to 30 or 35.  Given that it is a partnership board, it would not have been possible to prevent involvement of local authority representatives or those from the community and voluntary sector.  Following long negotiations, a figure of 23 was arrived at.  The Deputy is welcome to try but I do not believe he would be able to reduce the membership further, particularly if the various sectors are to be represented.  People still approach me seeking to have the number of members increased.  I hope I have covered most of the matters relating to cohesion.</p>
          <p eId="para_155">The Government's position on the health check is that it is not in favour of taking money from farmers and investing it in rural development.  If that position were to change, the agreement of the farming sector would be required.  We must ask ourselves how long the money Ireland receives from Europe - in the form of single farm payments, etc. - will last.  I am making a philosophical point regarding a matter we must contemplate in the near future but the debate has to start somewhere.  Rather than obtaining this money and living off it, will we be obliged in time to consider ways of using it to create new wealth?  That is what farm improvement and other schemes involve.</p>
          <p eId="para_156">I live in an area where the land is poor and I have always believed that the amount one can do to create new wealth from an area of land by using new techniques and making investment is quite limited.  For many farmers, diversifying local economies - through use of the rural social scheme, creating small businesses, etc. - has become a means of sustaining their farms.  We must decide whether, in the long term, this represents a more sustainable way of retaining people on the land than giving them a small extra payment.</p>
          <p eId="para_157">I will provide an example in order to illustrate the point I am making.  Some farmers were seeking money in respect of tourists accessing their land.  If I gave every commonage farmer €1,000 per year, it would not make them millionaires.  Most farmers with whom I am familiar obtain €15,000 to €25,000 in grants.  However, in this instance I refer to small farmers.  A sum of €1,000 would not go very far and would be spent before the end of the year.  If such a farmer on a low income got a job on the RSS it would be worth €15,000 to €20,000 extra per year for him.  If we compare both, it was much better for me to put the money into the rural social scheme and to focus it on low income farmers rather than on giving more to those who were on incomes of €200,000 and who also had a professional job and owned land.  It was better to focus on people at the lower end, family farmers who find it impossible to make a living from their farms.</p>
          <p eId="para_158">We need to have a debate on what is best for farmers and rural Ireland and must consider farm life in its totality.  There are not many full-time farmers left.  The majority of the people we represent who are in agriculture are dependent on off-farm income, whether that of themselves or a partner.  Therefore, we cannot talk about them without looking at the totality of their lives, as if farming was the beginning and end or the only way out of the income dilemma they face.  When the income crunch hits the majority of farm families, an extra €1,000 in direct payment will not sort the problem.  What has happened as a result of the income crunch, regardless of whether we like it, is that farmers or their spouses have walked off the land and got jobs outside, whether it is an RSS job or a commercial job.  They get a job off the farm and bolster their lifestyle.</p>
          <p eId="para_159">We are trying to create jobs with the Leader scheme.  If we do not create jobs, we will block the biggest escape route used.  Some 60% of farmers have off-farm income now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_160">There are 36,000 full-time farmers out of 120,000.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonOCuiv" eId="spk_64" as="#Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív</from>
          <p eId="para_161">That figure of 36,000 is going down.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_162">The number may stabilise soon.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonOCuiv" eId="spk_66" as="#Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív</from>
          <p eId="para_163">They are the commercial guys.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_67">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_164">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonOCuiv" eId="spk_68" as="#Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív</from>
          <p eId="para_165">However, when the majority of farmers run into trouble, they look beyond the farm gate for a solution.  In their interest, we must ensure there is some work available for them outside the farm gate.  It would be worthwhile teasing out those issues with the various organisations.  I have challenged farm organisations on the issue.  I hope I have covered most of the points raised.  The carers are elected by the board.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_69">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_166">On the issue of off-farm income, the Minister mentioned the Fuschia brand in impoverished west Cork.  The French Minister for Agriculture made the point in the debate that we cannot depend on stockbrokers and market investors to determine food supply and we continually hear about food security.  We can build a rural community around a food and tourism economy or around whatever it takes to keep farm production in place.  Perhaps the EU will decide sometime in its wisdom that it is as good to base food security on the small farmer from west Cork or the guy on top of a hill in Austria as on the huge multiples or farm syndicates in South America.</p>
          <p eId="para_167">We must tease out the basic principle on which we will work and base our philosophy.  I believe there is potential in this Leader programme to base rural community sustainability on land and food production.  The single farm payment is too simplistic or is not tailored the right way to provide for this.  Making the moneys available through either the single farm payment or rural development is simplifying its allocation too much.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ChristyOSullivan" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Deputy Christy O’Sullivan</from>
          <p eId="para_168">Is it correct that any member of the board can be the chairman?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonOCuiv" eId="spk_71" as="#Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív</from>
          <p eId="para_169">Yes, anybody.  We have tried to take a broad approach because we want to be able to provide for a project when someone brings forward a great project that does not match this nice fit.  I want the funding open to help anybody who puts forward an eligible project.  If, however, I was asked the three themes or the strategic approach I wanted taken, I would say rural recreation was first.  Rural recreation is not just about tourists.  It is also about Irish people and people from Kilkenny town, for example, visiting other parts of County Kilkenny and enjoying themselves and leaving money behind them.</p>
          <p eId="para_170">Rural tourism is pivotal as a growth service industry.  Complementary to that is the small or niche production of high quality food because people are becoming fussier about where the food they are eating comes from and are willing to pay a premium.  We see significant growth in this market and believe we can exploit it.</p>
          <p eId="para_171">I have a third factor in mind which I believe has a much greater part to play than most people appreciate.  I have seen areas which did not get jobs but got the facilities and quality of life issues 100% correct, and they grew in terms of population.  I have seen areas with jobs but with a very bad quality of life, and they did not thrive despite the employment levels because people just commuted there to work.  I believe, therefore, that the quality of life issue is a major determinant as to why people live in rural Ireland.  I certainly would not move from where I live because of quality of life issues and because it is a great place to live.  It is crucial the rural programme focuses on all those services that improve the quality of life in an area, because people stay where there is good quality of life.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_172">Are the employees of all the amalgamated schemes guaranteed their jobs or will any of them face redundancy under the new regime?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonOCuiv" eId="spk_73" as="#Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív</from>
          <p eId="para_173">As the companies are all independent, they can hire or fire at will, according to the law.  An effort was made to ensure no one would lose his or her job in the short term.  I forgot to mention there is an absolute ceiling of 20% of funding being allocated to administration.  I believe it was 27% on the previous occasion, but the funding was smaller.  It is 20% this time.  That is written into the operational rules and I insisted that there should be a ceiling.  Furthermore, if someone is running a Leader partnership company and gets Leader money, this cannot be used for partnership actions.  If one gets money under the local development and social inclusion scheme, even though it is the one company, that must be used for social inclusion purposes.  The money one gets for one programme must be used for that particular initiative, and the RSS money must be used for that purpose.  The programmes can be complementary, but the money for each must be spent for the purpose specified.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BobbyAylward" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Deputy Bobby Aylward</from>
          <p eId="para_174">Could all the employees of the Kilkenny project be made redundant or will they be guaranteed their jobs under the new Leader programme?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonOCuiv" eId="spk_75" as="#Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív</from>
          <p eId="para_175">It is going to be a new private company and no one is guaranteed a job unless he or she is a permanent civil servant.  These are private companies, but the purpose is not to get rid of people.  That said, in the present economic climate I am not going to tell any company that it can carry on employing people, regardless of the money.  We have three times the money this time because of the extra activity.  However, one would not believe, unless one was very efficient last time, that it could be done with fewer staff.  If one thinks of the extra jobs we have created in terms of administering the rural social scheme, one should not need fewer staff.  However, companies none the less must cut their staff levels as required.  We are here not to provide employment in administration but activity locally, and we expect these companies to be lean, mean machines.  While this was not done for the purpose of downsizing the number of staff, I would not like to give a message to the effect that staff numbers are sacrosanct in the wider scheme of things.</p>
          <p eId="para_176">We have an issue that will impact very soon on members.  The Leader companies are in receipt of interim funding.  That funding was to finish at the end of June.  The Department of Finance gave its approval to continue the funding, at 60% of the previous rate, from June to October because they have run out of work.  All the grants are paid and they cannot do anything new.  To a certain extent, we are fortunate even to have that much.  I also have said about companies that have not got the articles and memoranda of association according to the guidelines we have laid down and who have not elected a board or a chairman after two years that these cannot expect to get interim funding after 24 July.  I informed them at the end of June that they had a month to get their house in order.  Articles and memoranda of association could be obtained and an annual general meeting organised within a week.  The board should have been elected long ago in any case and there is no reason that the chairpersons could not be elected within that timeframe.  The message has been given to these companies that they must deliver.</p>
          <p eId="para_177">I stress that I am not willing, under any section of my Department, to fund any group or agency for the sake of creating employment for employees.  The employees are there to provide services to people at the maximum efficiency and at the minimum cost.  I have sent a clear message that this is how it must be.  If the companies avail of all the schemes, they should not have to let people go.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_178">I asked whether there was much take-up of funding for the establishment of farmers' markets.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonOCuiv" eId="spk_77" as="#Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív</from>
          <p eId="para_179">The initiative on farmers' markets came late in the lifetime of the last programme, which ended in 2006.  A small amount of money was allocated under that programme but I expect a substantial amount to be allocated under the new programme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_180">There is a good deal of interest in it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EamonOCuiv" eId="spk_79" as="#Minister_for_Community,_Rural_and_Gaeltacht_Affairs">
          <from>Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív</from>
          <p eId="para_181">In the last programme, only the major towns and cities such as Galway and Waterford were excluded.  This time, however, the gateway and hub towns are also excluded.  It came down to a choice of either doing that or subjecting the programme to an OECD measure of rurality which would have excluded many more rural areas.  If a company is located in the part of a hub town that elects the town council, it will not be eligible for Leader funding.  I welcome this change because it seemed something of a codology that in the case of County Louth, for example, most of the Leader funding went into the town of Drogheda.  I am all for funding for Galway city when it is funding specifically allocated for Galway city.  However, it is rare that urban funding is diverted into rural areas.  We must ensure rural funding is allocated to what can be reasonably construed as rural areas.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_182">On behalf of the committee, I thank the Minister for his presentation and for answering members' queries.  We look forward to discussing other issues with him.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AndrewDoyle" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Deputy Andrew Doyle</from>
          <p eId="para_183">Before the meeting is adjourned, will the Chairman indicate whether he is willing to convene a special meeting of the committee if there is an unfavourable conclusion to the World Trade Organisation negotiations?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyBrady" as="#Chairman" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Chairman</from>
          <p eId="para_184">Deputy Creed raised that issue at the start of the meeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">The joint committee adjourned at 4.20 p.m. <i>sine die</i>.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
