<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2014-06-05/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2014-06-05/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2014-06-05" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/house/seanad/24"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2014-06-05/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2014-06-05/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2014-06-05" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2014-06-05/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/seanad/2014-06-05/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2018-10-03" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AideenHayden" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aideen-Hayden.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Aideen Hayden"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="BrianODomhnaill" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Brian-Ó-Domhnaill.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Brian Ó Domhnaill"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CaitKeane" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Cáit-Keane.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Cáit Keane"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CatherineNoone" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Catherine-Noone.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Catherine Noone"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DarraghOBrien" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Darragh-O'Brien.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Darragh O'Brien"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DenisODonovan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Denis-O'Donovan.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Denis O'Donovan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DennisODonovan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Denis-O'Donovan.S.1989-10-01" showAs="Denis O'Donovan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DiarmuidWilson" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Diarmuid-Wilson.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Diarmuid Wilson"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="FergalQuinn" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Feargal-Quinn.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Feargal Quinn"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="IvanaBacik" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ivana-Bacik.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Ivana Bacik"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnCrown" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Crown.S.2011-05-25" showAs="John Crown"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnGilroy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Gilroy.S.2011-05-25" showAs="John Gilroy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnKelly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Kelly.S.2011-05-25" showAs="John Kelly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LabhrasOMurchu" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Labhrás-Ó-Murchú.S.1997-09-17" showAs="Labhrás Ó Murchú"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MarcMacSharry" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Marc-MacSharry.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Marc MacSharry"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MarieMoloney" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Marie-Moloney.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Marie Moloney"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MarkDaly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mark-Daly.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Mark Daly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MartinConway" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Martin-Conway.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Martin Conway"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MauriceCummins" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Maurice-Cummins.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Maurice Cummins"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelComiskey" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-Comiskey.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Michael Comiskey"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelMullins" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-Mullins.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Michael Mullins"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelWDArcy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-D'Arcy.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Michael D'Arcy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaddyBurke" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paddy-Burke.S.1993-02-17" showAs="Paddy Burke"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaschalMooney" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paschal-Mooney.S.1987-04-25" showAs="Paschal Mooney"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulBradford" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Bradford.S.1987-04-25" showAs="Paul Bradford"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulCoghlan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Coghlan.S.1997-09-17" showAs="Paul Coghlan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanDBarrett" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Sean-D-Barrett.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Sean D. Barrett"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanSherlock" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Sherlock.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Seán Sherlock"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TerryLeyden" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Terry-Leyden.D.1977-07-05" showAs="Terry Leyden"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ThomasByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Thomas-Byrne.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Thomas Byrne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TrevorOClochartaigh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Trevor-Ó-Clochartaigh.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Trevor Ó Clochartaigh"/>
        <TLCEvent eId="bill.2013.90.seanad.4_sub" href="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2013/90/seanad/4_sub" showAs="Friendly Societies and Industrial and Provident Societies (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2013 [Seanad]: Report and Final Stages (Seanad)"/>
        <TLCEvent eId="bill.2014.49.seanad.2_ord" href="/ie/oireachtas/bill/2014/49/seanad/2_ord" showAs="Parliamentary Scrutiny of Appointments (European Commission) Bill 2014: Order for Second Stage (Seanad)"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Acting_Chairman" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/office/acting_chairman" showAs="Acting Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Jobs,_Enterprise_and_Innovation" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister_state/jobs__enterprise__innovation" showAs="Minister of State at the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>SEANAD ÉIREANN</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>SEANAD ÉIREANN</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2014-06-05">, 05 Meitheamh 2014</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2014-06-05">Thursday, 05 June 2014</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="volume">
        <docNumber refersTo="#vol_231">Vol. 231</docNumber>
      </block>
      <block name="number">
        <docNumber refersTo="#no_13">No. 13</docNumber>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30 a.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">Machnamh agus Paidir.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Reflection and Prayer.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Business of Seanad<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_1">I have received notice from Senator Trevor Ó Clochartaigh that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_2">Go dtabharfaidh an tAire Dlí agus Cirt agus Comhionannais soiléiriú ar an dtógfar san áireamh an chaoi ar láímhseáileadh cás Dhomhnall Uí Lubhlaí mar chuid den obair atá le déanamh ag an gcoiste neamhspleách atá ainmnithe aici le h-athbhreithniú a dhéanamh ar obair na Roinne sin.</p>
          <p eId="para_3">I have also received notice from Senator Cáit Keane of the following matter:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_4">The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to discuss the fact that Firhouse Educate Together national school is operating from a community centre which is most unsuitable and the need to find a suitable school building on a suitable site without delay. </p>
          <p eId="para_5">I have also received notice from Senator Paul Bradford of the following matter:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_6">The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to outline his views on concerns expressed that the change in the pupil-teacher ratio in small national schools is having an adverse effect on the pupils in these schools.</p>
          <p eId="para_7">I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="orderofBusiness" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Order of Business<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:40:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_8">The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re notification of a vacancy in Seanad Éireann arising from the election of a Member to the European Parliament, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of the Order of Business; No. 2, motion re the arrangements for the address to Seanad Éireann by Ms Anne Brasseur, President of the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of No. 1; No. 3, Friendly Societies and Industrial and Provident Societies (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2014 - Report Stage, to be taken at the conclusion of No. 2, with the time allocated for the debate not to exceed one hour; and No. 4, Companies Bill 2012 - Second Stage, to be taken at the conclusion of No. 3, with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed ten minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed eight minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_9">I neglected to congratulate former Senator Deirdre Clune on her election to the European Parliament. I congratulate her on behalf of my colleagues in Fianna Fáil on her successful election.</p>
          <p eId="para_10"> The Leader did not refer to No. 5 on the Order Paper, report of the Committee of Selection, following the meeting which took place last night. Where does the Government stand in that regard? I congratulate Senators Seán D. Barrett and Marc MacSharry on their selection to be members of the banking inquiry committee. The meeting of the Committee of Selection was convened last night in accordance with the motion passed by the Seanad on 14 May. The motion provided:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_11">(1) That, having regard to section 12 of the Houses of the Oireachtas (Inquiries, Privileges and Procedures) Act 2013 and Standing Order 103C, a Select Committee be appointed, to be joined with a similar Select Committee of Dáil Éireann to form the Joint Committee of Inquiry into the Banking Crisis, to develop a relevant proposal for conducting a ‘Part 2 Inquiry’...</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_12">(3) (a) The Select Committee shall consist of two (2) members who shall be nominated in accordance with Standing Order 89 and the provisions of Standing Orders 80(1) and (2) shall not apply.</p>
          <p eId="para_13">Standing Order 89 is very clear. It states: </p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_14">There shall be appointed at the commencement of every Seanad a committee to be known as the Committee of Selection, which, unless it shall have been otherwise ordered, shall nominate the Senators to serve on Select or Special Committees and which shall have power to discharge members of such Committees from time to time for non-attendance or at their own request, and to appoint others in substitution ... The Committee of Selection shall consist of eleven Senators...</p>
          <p eId="para_15">It is clear, therefore, that the decision taken last night by the Committee of Selection is valid and was democratic. What is the Government's position on it? I assume it will accept the democratic decision of an independent committee of the Seanad with representatives drawn from all sides of the House. Based on research we have carried out, I can see evidence that only once - in 1982 - has the decision of the Committee of Selection been challenged in the Seanad Chamber. It is clear from looking at Standing Orders and the Government's motion that the decision on membership has been taken. Will the Leader confirm that the Government will respect the democratic decision of the independent Committee of Selection of the House and ensure Senators Sean D. Barrett and Marc MacSharry are the two selected nominees to serve in the banking inquiry? I would like the Leader to address this issue. I want to deal with it in a proper fashion, as the Leader has always done, and have no reason to think that will not be the case. The Committee of Selection has selected two members who have been selected under Standing Orders, the rules of the House and the Government Act. They have been selected under the Government's motion that was passed in the House with our support. I assume and ask the Leader to confirm that the Government will accept the two Senators elected to the committee from the Seanad, without political interference. This should be done in order that we can move on and have the banking inquiry established.</p>
          <p eId="para_16"> The Government has been at pains to say - I agree with it - that this should not be a political inquiry. It is about getting to the truth of what happened during the banking crisis. I read media reports last night that there was concern that the Government would not have a majority on the committee. I put it to the Leader that this should make no difference if it is to be an independent inquiry. The party affiliations of any member of the committee should make no difference. Will the Leader confirm that the Government will accept the decision of the Committee of Selection and tell us how we will move forward in that regard?</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Visit of Romanian Delegation<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:40:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_4">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_17">Before I call Senator Ivana Bacik, I am sure Members will join me in welcoming a parliamentary delegation from Romania, led by His Excellency Valeriu Zgonea, President of the Chamber of Deputies. He is very welcome and I hope he will have a very successful trip to Ireland. I understand the delegation had a very good night out last night.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#IvanaBacik" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Senator Ivana Bacik<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_18">It sounds like there is a story to be told. I join the Cathaoirleach in welcoming our colleagues from Romania.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="orderofBusiness" eId="dbsect_5">
        <heading>Order of Business (Resumed)<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:40:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#IvanaBacik" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Senator Ivana Bacik<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_19">I congratulate former Senator Deirdre Clune on her election to the European Parliament. I am glad that we have the motion in that regard before us today to formally mark her election.</p>
          <p eId="para_20"> I welcome the announcement made by the Government that it is taking up the issue of the burial of almost 800 babies from the mother and baby home in Tuam between 1925 and 1961. This is an issue that was raised first by Senator Hildegarde Naughton. A number of other Senators and I raised it yesterday on the Order of Business. I am glad that it is being taken up.</p>
          <p eId="para_21"> I ask the Leader to arrange a debate in due course on the issue of policing oversight. The Government will publish legislation on GSOC, while the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality is examining mechanisms for policing oversight. It will undertake a fact-finding exercise in Belfast, Edinburgh and Glasgow to look at the Northern Irish and Scottish policing oversight bodies and at how we can best reform and amend our legislation to ensure better oversight of policing here. I hope we will have a debate on the issue, not just on the legislation on GSOC, but also on the broader and more comprehensive review the joint committee is undertaking of Garda oversight mechanisms.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> I welcome the comments and the news yesterday that the personal insolvency arrangements were being fast-tracked. Under the Personal Insolvency Act 2012, we are seeing an innovative method used, whereby personal insolvency arrangements, PIAs, can be made for as short a period as three months. This clearly will aid distressed debtors. It has been described as a revolution in insolvency arrangements. Perhaps we might have a debate in due course on a review of the Act, how it is being implemented in practice and the innovative arrangements being made.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> In regard to the Committee of Selection, I know the Leader will respond to Senator Darragh O'Brien on behalf of the Government.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanDBarrett" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Senator Sean D. Barrett<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_24">I understand the talks to save Bausch &amp; Lomb in Waterford are at a crucial stage. I welcome the interventions made by two of our stalwarts in the House, Senators Maurice Cummins and David Cullinane, and wish them every success.</p>
          <p eId="para_25"> I also welcome the news to be announced later of the appointment of Mr. Kevin O'Malley as ambassador of the United States to Ireland. This is something for which we have asked. Perhaps we might consider inviting the ambassador to visit the House in the future.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AideenHayden" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Senator Aideen Hayden<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_26">I echo Senator Bacik's approval that some personal insolvency arrangements, or PIAs, have been fast-tracked by agreement with some lenders. I highlight the plight of those who are borrowing from certain financial institutions which have made it abundantly clear that they do not intend to co-operate with the insolvency process and write down debt on family homes. I reiterate the objections I voiced previously to the effect that it is unacceptable that some financial institutions have made it clear that they will not co-operate with a body established statutorily to assist people in mortgage distress.</p>
          <p eId="para_27"> On that note, I raise concerns in relation to the financial ombudsman. It is perfectly clear from appearances before the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform and statements its representatives have made that the ombudsman's office views its remit very narrowly in terms of regulation of the code of conduct on mortgage arrears and any other issues relating to personal debt and mortgage insolvency. It is high time we reviewed the legislation underpinning the ombudsman. It is not acceptable to have an independent ombudsman's office which sees itself as having no remit other than to decide whether procedures have been followed to the letter of the law. It has no remit in relation to fairness and in particular as to whether any option offered by a bank is fair and sustainable. In the current environment where some banks are behaving more responsibly than others, it is not good enough to have a so-called independent ombudsman's office which considers that it has no remit whatsoever in this regard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TerryLeyden" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Senator Terry Leyden<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_28">I note that the President of the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe is coming to the Seanad next week. I thought I might have been informed of the date as the one notified does not suit me. I am surprised I was not consulted about the date as I issued the invitation. People do have other commitments.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_10">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_29">It was agreed with our office.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TerryLeyden" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Senator Terry Leyden<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_30">In any event, I concur with Senator Darragh O'Brien, the Leader of the Opposition, and congratulate Senators Sean Barrett and Marc MacSharry, who are the nominees of Seanad Éireann to sit on the banking inquiry. The Committee of Selection last night made the decision in a democratic manner. The membership of the inquiry will be Deputy Ciarán Lynch, the Chairman and a member of the Labour Party, Deputy Kieran O'Donnell, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, Deputy John Paul Phelan, Deputy Michael McGrath, Deputy Pearse Doherty, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, Senator Sean Barrett and Senator Marc MacSharry. It is a good inquiry and it has the credibility to go forward independently and examine the banking institutions. I have great confidence in it, knowing in particular the calibre of the two Members from this House. I will not speak to the calibre of the Members from the other House, who I am sure are of top quality.</p>
          <p eId="para_31"> I have known Senator Barrett since he entered the House and he has been exemplary in his work in every sphere of the Seanad's activity. He may have contributed more than anyone else in the House to its workings. He is a credit to the House. He was very successful in fighting a campaign for the retention of the Seanad. We owe him a great debt of gratitude in that regard. </p>
          <p eId="para_32"> I have known Senator Marc MacSharry for a very long time. He is a man of the greatest integrity in public life and I have no doubt that he will play a very important role in the committee. I note the work he did in the House during the term of the last Government when he fought for cancer services in Sligo without fear or favour. He stood up and fought, irrespective of who was in government or what Minister was there and he will carry out his work in the banking inquiry in an exemplary manner.</p>
          <p eId="para_33"> Both Government and Opposition Members should be very fearful of any activity to disrupt the decision of the selection committee. If Members engage in such activity, the banking inquiry will have no credibility whatsoever and should be walked away from. If Members interfere with the decision of the selection committee, they will have to take the consequences of that action. The Government is slipping every day. It will slip further and the inquiry will never take place unless Senators Marc MacSharry and Sean Barrett are on it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMullins" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Senator Michael Mullins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">In recent days, the European Commission published country-specific recommendations for each member state's national reform and stability programme. It would be appropriate given that we have recently exited the bailout and will soon be into budget preparation, for the House to discuss the recommendations which have been made. They include implementation of current budgets, correcting the excessive deficit in 2015, reforming elements of the health care sector to increase cost-effectiveness and many other significant recommendations. While we are not unique in that every other member state has received recommendations, it would be an appropriate, worthwhile and meaningful debate to have before the summer recess to ensure we can all feed into the budgetary process for the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FergalQuinn" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Senator Feargal Quinn<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">A couple of years ago, I raised the matter here of an Irish citizen who had been imprisoned without trial in Sri Lanka. Great efforts have been made to find a solution and the great news is that he arrived home this week to his wife and three children. He has been in prison for seven years and his 24 year old, 20 year old, and 16 year old daughters had not seen him in that time. It is a matter for great joy. I raise it to say that the work of the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade and the Irish ambassador in India has been very helpful. The family would wish that to be passed on. Hopefully, this will be the end of these matters.</p>
          <p eId="para_36"> There is a case to be made for having a Minister for pensions. The pensions crisis we are likely to experience in the future will eclipse the banking crisis of a few years ago yet we are not taking the steps we must. As the population grows, the number of young workers being replaced by retired older people will go from five to one to three to one. That will be an impossible situation. The Comptroller and Auditor General estimates that in a number of years time the cost to the State of public sector pensions alone will be €157 billion. This is a huge matter, yet we merely say of pensions "Oh yes, we must do something about that". The case should be made to appoint a Minister for pensions in the very next Cabinet reshuffle or on the formation of the next Government but very shortly in any event. That Minister would concentrate all of his or her efforts on the crisis that is facing us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineNoone" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Senator Catherine Noone<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_37">I welcome the appointment of the new US ambassador to Ireland. The post has been empty for approximately 18 months since Dan Rooney left it. It is a very welcome development. The relationship between Ireland and the USA is very important and the ambassadorial role is a key aspect of it.</p>
          <p eId="para_38"> Colleagues have referred to the banking inquiry. While I congratulate those who have been appointed to it, I am very disappointed that there is no woman among the nine members. I do not mean a woman should be appointed without regard to merit, but it shows that the wheels of power are slow to move, especially when it comes to gender balance. We talk of boards not having enough women on them. I do not often refer to women's issue and having more women on this, that and the other, but it is disappointing that not one woman has been appointed among the nine. It is a damning indictment of politics today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TrevorOClochartaigh" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Senator Trevor Ó Clochartaigh<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">There was a very well known film called "Dead Man Walking". I get the sense that we have a dead man walking in the Cabinet having seen media reports on the Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly. It appears the backbenchers in Fine Gael are finally coming to the conclusion we came to many months ago, which is that it is time for the Minister to go having regard to the number of debacles he has had on his watch. It is a shame it has taken so long for the backbenchers to find their voices.</p>
          <p eId="para_40"> We should not wait for a reshuffle for the decision on the Minister to be made. We see debacles continuing. I call on the Leader to ask the Minister to clarify his relationship with the chair of the west-north-west hospital group in light of the fact that the report on the review of maternity services in the area was commissioned from a company of which that person owns 50%.</p>
          <p eId="para_41">The Minister needs to clarify his own relationship with the person in question.</p>
          <p eId="para_42"> At the Joint Committee on Public Service Oversight and Petitions yesterday, we considered the report of the Ombudsman, Mr. Peter Tyndall, on medical cards. He raised alarming issues arising from the centralisation of the medical card process. He said it appeared that when the system was centralised the files relating to how decisions on discretionary medical cards were made disappeared, or went to a place where they could not be found. He has investigated a number of complaints about this issue on which the reports or files are not available, and he seems to indicate that this is a result of the centralisation process. He also raised the issue of the delay in replacing the mobility and motorised transport grant schemes, which the Government is reviewing. The grants were rescinded because the Ombudsman had highlighted an issue, but now he is concerned that people who need those grants have nothing available, and that needs to be addressed as a matter of urgency. Will the Leader organise a debate on that issue? We also need to find out why the files on discretionary medical cards do not appear to have been centralised when the medical card system was centralised. It will be very difficult to review that system and to ensure that, if the Government is committed to returning medical cards to the people from whom they were taken, the decisions are based on proper information.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Senator Paul Coghlan<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_43">I too welcome the imminent appointment of the new American ambassador. I am sure the Cathaoirleach will be proud of his good strong connections with his own county.</p>
          <p eId="para_44"> We have seen the roll-out of an extensive advertising campaign by the national lottery to play the Lotto online. I think we are all agreed that it is important that we be fully aware of the consequences and implications of the online game formats. We must remember that some are vulnerable to ease of access to gambling opportunities. Earlier in the year, Senator O'Donnell raised concerns about this. The State has yet to appoint a national lottery regulator as required under the relevant Act. The new format of the games is being rushed out in advance of the appointment of a national lottery regulator. We as legislators need to be assured that the new operators of the national lottery do not operate without regard to the common good in an attempt to maximise the return on the substantial investment that has been made. I believe more attention must be paid to responsible gaming and not simply the return on investment. I have written to the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform requesting that representatives of the new operator be invited to appear before committee to outline their values, plans and priorities as we make the transition. This is a very urgent matter, given the rush to secure the maximum online penetration before a national lottery regulator is formally established. I am sure the Leader will agree with me on that point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LabhrasOMurchu" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Senator Labhrás Ó Murchú<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">I join with the sentiments being expressed this morning. I believe the selection of Senators MacSharry and Barrett to sit on the banking inquiry augurs very well for the operation of that committee. I do not have to outline their credentials, as we all know how accomplished and focused they are as members of the Oireachtas. I do not have any doubt that they will fulfil their mandate without fear or favour on behalf of the people.</p>
          <p eId="para_46"> Those who knocked on doors during the recent elections know full well the hurt, the anger and the sense of helplessness that is being experienced by the public. The idea of the banking inquiry has generated significant anticipation. It is therefore vital that the committee does its job, which is to act on behalf of the people of Ireland, including those who cannot pay their mortgages, those who have lost their jobs and those who have emigrated to the four corners of the earth, and for that reason it will be monitored and assessed very carefully. It is most important that it does not become a political quango. It should not be used for political point-scoring. Should that happen, it will lose credibility, and we cannot expect an outcome that will alleviate the suffering I have already mentioned. My hope is that if the committee starts on the right track, leaving party politics aside, and doing one of the most important jobs that will ever have been done in the State, then we can start looking forward in earnest. Although I accept that there have been improvements, we know that the people on the ground are disillusioned at this stage. The only way we can overcome the attitude of the people is by showing them strength of character, honesty, integrity, commitment and focus. It is good for this House that people of the calibre and character of Senators Sean D. Barrett and Marc MacSharry are the nominees of Seanad Éireann to sit on this committee. My hope is that there will be no misrepresentation. If that were to happen - and I do not expect that it will - not only will we have done harm to this House, but we will have done excessive harm to the will of the people. The people are waiting to see the Oireachtas Members doing a good job on their behalf and leaving politics to one side.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnKelly" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Senator John Kelly<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">I agree with Senator Ó Clochartaigh about the debacle over the review of medical cards and the taking of discretionary medical cards from people. It is amusing that people are standing up and listening to Ombudsman reporting on this, while in the past three years I have repeatedly highlighted the issue of files going missing between Clontarf and Finglas. It is time to review and revisit the operation of the PCRS. I never agreed with the centralisation of the medical card system. It is absolutely appalling that the HSE can now bring in a German company to review medical cards. It has acted cynically on these issues.</p>
          <p eId="para_48"> It makes me laugh to see the high moral ground that has been taken by Fianna Fáil on the review of medical cards and discretionary medical cards. Let me remind the Members opposite that when they were in Government - I was a county councillor between 2004 and 2009-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_49">The Senator was handing them out</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_50">He was handing them out to all his constituents.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnKelly" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Senator John Kelly<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_51">May I speak?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_22">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">The Senator without interruption.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnKelly" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Senator John Kelly<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_53">I wrote on numerous occasions to the then Minister for Heath and Children, Mary Harney, and I asked that medical cards be made available to cancer patients. Repeatedly she refused, pointing out that there was very little discretion-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">The person to whom you gave the discretionary medical card.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_25">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">The Senator without interruption</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnKelly" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Senator John Kelly<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_56">-----and that one had to abide by the guidelines.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_27">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_57">Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnKelly" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Senator John Kelly<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">The previous speaker did not have a question for the Leader. Let me conclude with this point. My representations to the Minister were followed a year later by representations from her to me on behalf of a woman who had an underactive thyroid. She could not believe a medical card had not been made available as a matter of course because this person had an underactive thyroid.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">Bring the letters in here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnKelly" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Senator John Kelly<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_60">But she was forgetting about the people who had cancer. These are the people we are talking about today. These people are suffering as their medical cards have been withdrawn-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_61">Bring the letters in here, because there have been a few Labour Party guys who claimed that things happened when they did not actually happen.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnKelly" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Senator John Kelly<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">-----but the Fianna Fáil Party did exactly the same thing when it was in Government.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">Bring them in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_34">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">Senator Crown.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCrown" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Senator John Crown<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">I am sorry; did somebody call my name? There was a bit of a melee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_36">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">The Senator has risen to speak so he must have heard something.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCrown" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Senator John Crown<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">I am sorry to interrupt the latest edition of why we should have abolished the House but I would like to raise three issues, which are interrelated, although at first glance they may not appear to be. We all understand what is going on here. Senator Barrett is the only qualified person in either House to ask the appropriate questions of bankers and regulators at the banking inquiry. He may find himself removed from the committee holding the inquiry for reasons that have nothing to with his competence or the national interest and everything to do with party political interests and pique. I ask Members to look into their hearts for one glorious moment, pretend they are not in a party and look at the 4.6 million people in the country and what they have gone through as a result of the behaviour of the banks and decide who they think are the best people to have on the committee of inquiry and if Senator Barrett is one of them. That is the only question Members should ask.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">He was selected unanimously.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCrown" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Senator John Crown<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">Second, if he is removed, it will be in the crass realm of political stunts. We have witnessed several other examples in recent times. People who supported the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Gilmore, to go into a coalition with a conservative party then criticised and ousted him for having conservative policies at a time when many conservative parties could have gone into opposition if they had not had a disagreement 90 years ago.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_40">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">Has the Senator a question for the Leader on the Order of Business?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCrown" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Senator John Crown<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">The same is happening with respect to the Minister for Health. Everybody knew when he took up office, he had been dealt the worst set of economic cards possible by the outgoing Administration and at a time he was under the thumb of international financial spigot turners who made sure no money was available for anything, he had his own Cabinet colleagues beating him to death to cut back and everyone knew he would cut back. I do not agree with the cutbacks. Everything was done wrong. All these problems began the night the two main parties supported the bank guarantee. That is the reality he found himself in with a legacy problem-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_42">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">Has the Senator a question for the Leader?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCrown" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Senator John Crown<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">Will the Leader pass on my best wishes to the Minister? He is the only one of the past four Ministers for Health who attempted to reform the system. He has made a few awful blunders during his tenure but it is incredibly unfair that he is being held responsible for what is essentially a party political problem.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelComiskey" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Senator Michael Comiskey<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">I join others in congratulating our former colleague, Deirdre Clune, on her election to the European Parliament.</p>
          <p eId="para_75"> I welcome the announcement of Mr. Kevin O'Malley as the new American ambassador to Ireland. I look forward to him visiting the House in the near future.</p>
          <p eId="para_76"> We hear a great deal of negative news but I welcome the news relating to counties Sligo and Leitrim over the past week. Last Friday morning, the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation visited Carrick-on-Shannon in County Leitrim to announce the creation of 125 new jobs, which is welcome in an area from which many people have emigrated. This will give them an opportunity to return to work in their native country. Last Tuesday, the Taoiseach announced the creation of 175 jobs in Sligo, which I also welcome.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulBradford" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Senator Paul Bradford<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">On a technical matter, will the Leader consider an amendment to the Order of Business to allow the taking of No. 16 before No. 1?</p>
          <p eId="para_78"> I refer to the mini-debate on the Committee of Selection. No. 5 is a motion on the report of the committee. There is no requirement for such a motion to come before the House because Standing Orders are prescriptive and we cannot rewrite history. As a member of the committee, I had to make a decision, as did all committee members, and we did so last night arising from a motion passed in the House some weeks ago, which said a select committee carrying out a banking inquiry should include two members nominated in accordance with Standing Order 89. That was in black and white. There was no shade of grey and it was prescriptive. The motion was passed. Seanad Éireann instructed the selection committee by an overwhelming vote of Members not to consider, submit or present two names but nominate two Members to sit on the banking inquiry under Standing Order 89.</p>
          <p eId="para_79"> We need to be cautious about what we do because the Standing Order - we all fought to preserve the House last year on the basis that it is independent, not a creature of Government and stands on its own two feet - does not suggest but simply prescribes that there should be a Committee of Selection and that it shall nominate the Senators to serve on particular committees. That is the job of work which we were asked to do last night and which we completed. Some people are disappointed with the outcome but the Standing Order is clear.</p>
          <p eId="para_80"> It is disturbing to hear on the media and coming from certain sources concerns that the Government would not have a majority on the committee. If the committee is formulated arising from divisions in the Dáil and the Seanad, there would be members of Fine Gael, Fianna Fáil, Sinn Féin, the Labour Party and the Independents on it. The purpose of the select committee should not be that one side or the other has a majority; it should be that the committee comprises people who would do an independent job on behalf of the people. If we look at the committee as being about Government versus Opposition, majority versus minority, it will start in a negative fashion. We have to respect the motion passed in the House some weeks ago. I am sorry for exceeding my time but this is important. We must fully respect a motion passed in the House and we must fully respect the Standing Orders of the House. If we attempt to do other than that, we will create a dangerous precedent.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_46">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">The Senator is way over time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulBradford" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Senator Paul Bradford<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">I concur with Senator Noone's comments about the failure to nominate a female Member but the Dáil had the power to nominate seven members of the committee and this House could only nominate two members. That is where the spotlight should shine. The Dáil was remiss in that regard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineNoone" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Senator Catherine Noone<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">My comment was not aimed at this House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DennisODonovan" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Senator Denis O'Donovan<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">I listened with great interest to Senator Bradford's contribution and I disagree with little of what he said. However, while I have chaired the Committee of Selection, there have been 17 decisions, culminating in last night's decision, which have been put to the House. During my term, last night's meeting was the first at which a democratic voting process took place as set out in the normal circumstances. Will the Leader reflect on the implications of usurping the decision of the committee for Standing Orders? In addition, in the context of precedent, there was only one time in the past 60 years when a decision of the committee was challenged in the House and the outcome was the House upheld the decision following a division. As the committee chairman, I have to be careful not to impose my view and I must be fair and impartial. I ask the Leader and the Government to seriously reflect on any effort to revisit the issue, which, as chairman, I would be slow to do. Any other political attempt to usurp the democratic decision of the committee would want to be carefully thought out.</p>
          <p eId="para_85"> I wish Senator Norris well. He has been out sick and he attended the committee meeting. He came in with one mission in mind, which was to support his TCD colleague, Senator Barrett. That demonstrates his commitment to the task. Whatever about his physical and medical difficulties, there is nothing wrong with his brain. He is still acute and sharp and his comments did not do Senator Barrett harm when he was unanimously accepted as one of the two nominees.</p>
          <p eId="para_86">With that in mind, I hope the issue can be resolved fairly and properly. Senator Maurice Cummins is very fair and a good Leader of the Seanad. I hope he can forget his role on behalf of the Government and do the right thing on behalf of the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinConway" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Senator Martin Conway<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">I welcome the announcement of Ryanair's winter schedule which sees five additional routes compared to its winter schedule in 2013. We will see flights to Paris, Berlin, Warsaw, Fuerteventura and Cracow continuing in the winter schedule. These flights commenced in April and it was intended that they would operate just for the summer period. This is a very significant announcement, given that there will be an extra 24 flights a week during the winter period between Shannon Airport and these European destinations. It is a significant vote of confidence by Ryanair in Shannon Airport. It means that what the Government is doing in having an independent Shannon Airport, with a focused aviation policy and marketing strategy, is working. Coupled with the elimination of the travel tax, the continuation of the 9% VAT rate and the recalibration of the airport structure, these are very positive steps. It will mean the continuation of jobs in the tourism sector and the creation of others during the off season in parts of Couny Clare, Limerick, County Kerry and the wider region. I look forward to further significant announcements by other airlines when they announce their winter schedules in the coming weeks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Senator Mark Daly<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">In regard to the banking inquiry, I welcome the report of the Committee of Selection and look forward to the Government's response. This is a test of the promise to have open and transparent government, a new beginning and a democratic revolution. I hope the Government will see fit to make sure it does not descend into a show trial. A test of that commitment will be whether it seeks to change the decision of the Committee of Selection of the Seanad on the make-up of the Members selected.</p>
          <p eId="para_89"> I welcome the news on the impending appointment of the US ambassador to Ireland. As of last Monday, there were only 14 countries that did not have an ambassador appointed by the United States. At least, we will have a new ambassador from St. Louis. We look forward to his contribution in Ireland, including to the peace process, given the current position in dealing with the issues of parades and the past.</p>
          <p eId="para_90"> While talking about the past, the makers of last night's "Prime Time" programme on RTE should be complimented on their work in highlighting the torture that had taken place in the North of Ireland. The decisions were taken at a high level in the British Government. Prime Ministers and Ministers were aware that the torture of Irish citizens was taking place in the North of Ireland. The matter was raised in the European Union by Jack Lynch. The European Court found that the British had not tortured these citizens, but, of course, this was because information had been withheld from the judges. Therefore, it is open to the Government to have the case reviewed.</p>
          <p eId="para_91"> In regard to the Ballymurphy massacre 40 years ago, when 11 people were killed by British soldiers in west Belfast in a matter of days, the British refuse to conduct any investigation. Due to the work of RTE and the Pat Finucane Centre we are aware that British politicians took decisions to torture Irish citizens. Why has the Government not asked the British ambassador to make available to it files on the bombings in Dublin and Monaghan, the killings in Ballymurphy, the torture of Irish citizens and the ruling of the European Court which was used by the US Government to justify the torture of Iraqi citizens. The stress positions and five techniques used in Derry and Belfast sanctioned by the British Government were used on Iraqi citizens, most recently during the invasion of Iraq.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_52">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">The Senator is way over time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Senator Mark Daly<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">What happened in the past is still happening. I want to know what the Government is doing about it and why it has not asked the British ambassador to explain how sanction was given at the highest levels in the British Government to torture Irish citizens.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelWDArcy" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Senator Michael D'Arcy<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">I raise an issue which has received surprisingly little attention, namely, the good performance of the nation's finances in the first five months of the year. By way of comparison, the deficit in the first five months of last year was €5.3 billion, whereas the deficit in the first five months of this year was €3.5 billion. It is clear, therefore, that the nation's finances are back on track, which is important. That said, it is also important that we do not ignore the difficulties people are experiencing. In that context, I raise the important issue of coastal erosion, particularly where properties are in danger. While funding has been made available for harbours and piers and some coastal erosion projects, there are areas in which private properties are in danger and the works required are beyond the scope of any individual to undertake. This is an issue we should examine. There are thousands of properties from north to south and east to west which need immediate and specific works to be undertaken. I am speaking, in particular, about my own area, County Wexford, which has the softest coastline in the country. We should take the opportunity to bring in both the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine and the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to put some measure in place to help those whose properties are in immediate danger. As I said, we cannot take the nation's finances in isolation and ignore the individual. If possible, we should debate the matter during this summer session in order to deal with it before the winter storms start. There are properties that could fall into the sea in the next 12 months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaschalMooney" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Senator Paschal Mooney<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">I welcome the appointment of a new US ambassador to Ireland. I hope this will accelerate progress on the ongoing issue of immigration reform in the United States now that we will have somebody in place in the Phoenix Park who will be able to act as a conduit, not only for the Government, but also the wider Irish public. This is an issue that may seem to be under the radar, but it is just as hurtful and painful in its own way as many of the other issues raised in the House across the panoply of political activity. I emphasise this is not about striking a separate deal for the Irish, given that some commentators seem to have completely misinterpreted the position, rather it is about comprehensive immigration reform from which I hope the Irish would benefit. I applaud the actions of both the Tánaiste and the Taoiseach in this regard since they took office in that they have kept the issue high on the agenda. I have always believed the absence of an ambassador <i>in situ</i> here at a critical time in Irish-US relations, at a time when discussions on immigration reform were ongoing between Republicans and Democrats, would create a vacuum. Now that we will have somebody in place, I suggest on behalf of this House, that the Leader writes to the incoming ambassador to congratulate him on his appointment and to wish him well. The Leader should also point out that comprehensive immigration reform is a key issue for all sides of the House and one which we hope will be progressed as soon as possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">I join in the words of congratulation to former Senator Deirdre Clune on her election to the European Parliament.</p>
          <p eId="para_97">I also welcome the imminent appointment of Mr. Kevin O'Malley as the US ambassador to Ireland. It is regrettable that it took 18 months for this appointment to be made, given the relationship between this island and the United States.</p>
          <p eId="para_98"> I congratulate Senator Barrett and Senator MacSharry on their appointment to the banking inquiry. They will be excellent representatives of this House and that inquiry is of great importance in addressing the crisis in the Irish banking sector. I join my colleagues in hoping the Government will accept the democratic decision of the Committee of Selection to appoint Senators MacSharry and Barrett and I commend the Leader of the House on ensuring this House will have two representatives on the inquiry.</p>
          <p eId="para_99"> I hope there is not a recurrence of what happened previously when some Government Senators did not toe the line on the so-called Protection of Life during Pregnancy Bill. I do not blame the Leader of the House personally, but on that occasion he was instructed by the Government to suspend Standing Order 89, remove committee members and replace them with others without any input by the democratically elected Committee of Selection. The Government parties allowed this to happen. On behalf of the Fianna Fáil Party, I am putting the Leader of the House on notice that if he attempts to do so again we will not co-operate in the running of this House. I am sad that I had to say this but I feel it is only fair to give warning that our party will not co-operate with the smooth running of business in this House. This is not for party political reasons, it is for democratic reasons and in the interests of democracy. </p>
          <p eId="para_100"> I again commend both Senator MacSharry and Senator Barrett and I second Senator Bradford's proposed amendment to the Order of Business.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">I congratulate Senator MacSharry and Senator Barrett on their appointment by the Committee of Selection last night. I presume the Clerk of the Seanad has notified the clerk of the banking inquiry of the appointments by the Seanad. Senator Bradford is correct that there is no requirement for the Seanad to approve or not approve this decision as that job has been done. There will be a different set-up to other committees as it will be governed by the Oireachtas (Inquiries, Privileges and Procedures) Act, which makes specific statutory reference to our Standing Orders. The Act says Standing Orders must be put in place within 50 days of the passing of the Act. This has been done and I assume our existing Standing Orders, which are now governed by statute, are included.</p>
          <p eId="para_102"> The banking inquiry was set up by a resolution of this House that specifically refers to Standing Order 89 and appointment by the Committee of Selection. The Standing Order refers to the Committee of Selection doing its job of appointing two Members and last night the Committee of Selection complied with the resolution of the House by appointing two Members to the banking inquiry.</p>
          <p eId="para_103"> I would not like to be the lawyer in the Office of the Attorney General who must examine this. This is a highly complex matter and the Government would be best to leave things alone. The reaction I have heard from the public suggests they do not wish for any perception of bias or interference by the Government in appointing members to the inquiry. The members appointed to the banking inquiry last night were appointed in accordance with the law. As far as I am concerned they are now members of the banking inquiry and I wish them every success and good luck in their work.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianODomhnaill" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Senator Brian Ó Domhnaill<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">I call on the Leader to facilitate a debate in this House with the Minister for agriculture present. This should be done ahead of the Minister's submission to the European Commission relating to the new Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, programme and the rural development programme, Pillar 1 and Pillar 2. This is of great importance to the farming sector in this country and to rural Ireland. I understand the Department will make its submission towards the end of June so a debate should to take place here prior to that.</p>
          <p eId="para_105"> I wish to congratulate my colleagues, Senator Barrett and Senator MacSharry, on their successful selection by the Committee of Selection last night. I note the views of Government Senators on the work of the Committee of Selection and I question why any Senator would doubt the ethos or integrity of a House committee, namely, the Committee of Selection. If the Government was to take the view that the democratic decision made by the Committee of Selection last night is voted down in this House it would do the Senate a disservice and totally undermine the Committee of Selection. I hope the Leader will take the pragmatic view that democracy means something. A decision taken by the Committee of Selection under Standing Order 89 should stand. I fail to understand why the Government feels it is necessary to have a controlling majority on the banking inquiry or why the Leader of the Seanad would not facilitate the democratic election of both Senators who were selected last night? I hope the Leader will allow democracy to prevail and will not undermine a House committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">I have listened to much rhetoric relating to Standing Orders from the high moral ground on the other side of the House. There was a general consensus that we would appoint one Government Senator and one non-Government Senator. However, I agree this was not mentioned in the motion that was passed. The motion only mentioned selecting two Senators. I am suggesting, and I am going to ask the Cathaoirleach, that the matter be referred to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges so it can be investigated. I have information that I intend to bring to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges and will do so acting in the best interests of the House at all times. Before any decision is ratified certain matters should be discussed by the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">What matters?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">Whoever suggested I am kicking to touch-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">It is already done.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">It has come to my notice that it has been suggested Senator MacSharry may have a conflict of interest.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">On a point of order, there are very specific statutory procedures.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">I was not going to mention this issue but I am being pressed by the other side of the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">The Leader has been pressed by Deputy Paul Kehoe.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_67">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">I am being pressed by the other side of the House in this matter and thus ask that it be referred to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges. It is important that this House acts properly at all times.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">On a point of order, as the Leader has opted to make such a claim, it is only reasonable that he might do the House the service and me the courtesy of outlining the conflict of interest to which he refers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_69">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">That is not relevant.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">I have no intention of doing that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCrown" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Senator John Crown<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">On a point of order, I second the request made by Senator MacSharry. I have no political dog in this fight but everyone knows what is going on here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_72">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">That is a matter for the legislation that is setting up the inquiry. It is not a matter for this House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">The Cathaoirleach has explained this and that is where the matter will be taken up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">On a point of order, I do not wish to interrupt the Leader but what is happening now is very serious. The Cathaoirleach chairs the CPP. The Committee on Procedure and Privileges has no role in the Committee of Selection. I am putting this question to you, a Chathaoirligh, and this is a point of order.</p>
          <p eId="para_122">I and my group need to know whether the Cathaoirleach is going to accede to the Leader's request-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_75">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">I am not making a decision on that matter now. I have not received any requests and I am not making any decisions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">I am just trying to be helpful. We want this matter to be resolved. A democratic decision was made last night under Standing Order 89 and in the context of a motion tabled by the Government. The Leader is responding by stating that he will make a request to the CPP. Is he making a formal request, on the floor of this House, that the CPP meet?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_77">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">We are not dealing with that issue now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">I am really sorry but we are dealing with it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_79">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">The Leader is responding to the questions that were raised on the Order of Business.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">I am sorry but all Members on this side have done is to simply ask whether the Government is going to abide by the democratic decision taken last night by the Committee of Selection in respect of the Government's motion tabled under Standing Orders.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_81">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">The Senator has made his point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">I have a serious point of order. The Cathaoirleach has never allowed the character of Members to be traduced or defamed in this House. In such circumstances, he must ask the Leader to withdraw-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">I did not question the character of any Member and I want that comment withdrawn.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">The Leader made a very serious allegation against Senator MacSharry and the Cathaoirleach has never allowed that to happen before.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_133">I did not question any Member's character.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_86">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">Senator Byrne should resume his seat.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_87">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">Will the Cathaoirleach ask the Leader to withdrawn the allegation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">I am asking that Senator Byrne to withdraw the comment he made about me. I have not questioned the character of any Member.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_89">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">The Leader made a serious allegation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_90">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">The Leader has not made any allegation yet. He said he was going to request the Chair to hold a meeting of the CPP.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_91">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_139">He said that Senator MacSharry was biased in the context of the banking inquiry.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_92">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_140">This is not a matter to be dealt with on the floor of the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_93">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">Even if he had €1 million outside the House-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_94">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">Legislation and guidelines are to be put in place to deal with the banking inquiry.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_95">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">Will the Cathaoirleach ask the Leader to withdraw the allegation he made? He would not allow me to make such an allegation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_96">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">Senator Byrne should withdraw the allegation he made about me.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_97">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">On a point of order, I am sorry the Leader finds himself in this position. It just goes to show the consequences of the Government putting a gun to the head of the Leader of this House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_98">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">Does the Senator wish to raise a point of order?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">It is my understanding that the Committee on Procedure and Privileges has no function-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaschalMooney" eId="spk_100">
          <from>Senator Paschal Mooney<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_148">None whatsoever.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_101">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">-----in determining whether somebody has a conflict of interests.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">This matter relates to suitability.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaschalMooney" eId="spk_103">
          <from>Senator Paschal Mooney<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">Under the terms of reference of the banking inquiry, it has none.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">What is being done is both a smokescreen and a delaying tactic. It is drawing into question the character and professional and political reputation of a Member of this House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_105">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">I have received no request to hold a meeting of the CPP. Will Members allow the Leader to respond to the questions that were raised?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">The Leader should withdraw his request immediately and accept the democratic decision made by the Committee of Selection which was taken yesterday. What is happening here is disgraceful.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_107">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">The Leader should withdraw his allegation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_108">
          <from>Senator Mark Daly<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">On a point of order, what the Government is doing is engaging in an act of political assassination. It did not get its way and it is now trying to assassinate the good name of a Member of the House, which is absolutely appalling.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_109">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">Can we allow the Leader to respond?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_110">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">The Cathaoirleach cannot allow the defamatory allegation which has been made to stand.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_111">
          <from>Senator Mark Daly<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">The Leader must withdraw the allegation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_112">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">I did not hear any defamatory allegations being made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_113">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">I did not say what I am being accused of saying.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_4">(Interruptions).</summary>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_114">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">I did not hear any defamatory remarks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_115">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">The Leader referred to a conflict of interests.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkDaly" eId="spk_116">
          <from>Senator Mark Daly<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">This is shocking.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_117">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">I formally request that the sitting be suspended right now in order that we might deal with this matter. I am not suggesting that he did so for any particular reason - it may even have been a mistake - but the Leader has called into question the suitability of Senator MacSharry to serve on the bank inquiry.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_118">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">That is a matter for the inquiry, not for the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">(Interruptions).</summary>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_119">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">The Cathaoirleach has a duty to protect the reputation of the Members of this House. In that context, I am asking him to resolve this matter by suspending the sitting for ten minutes in order that we might find out both what the Leader is proposing and the nature of the allegations to which he referred. I formally ask that, in the interests of getting our business done, the sitting be suspended for ten minutes in order to allow the leaders of the groups-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_120">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">This matter is not going to be dealt with on the floor of the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_121">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">It is an extremely serious matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_122">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_170">It will not be dealt with on the floor of the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_123">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">It was raised on the floor of the House. It is a serious matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_124">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">On a point of order, it was the Leader who chose to raise this matter on the floor of the House. As a Member of the House and as a citizen of Ireland, I am entitled to some level of protection from the Chair. The Leader stated that it has come to his attention that I have a conflict of interest. As a result of his choosing to share that information in the House and in front of the media, I am of the view that I, as an individual and as a Member of the Seanad, am entitled to hear from him, as is the House, what is the nature of that conflict of interest.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaschalMooney" eId="spk_125">
          <from>Senator Paschal Mooney<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">Hear, hear.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">I remind the Cathaoirleach-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_127">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">May I explain the position to the Senator?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_128">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_129">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_177">There is a procedure in place-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_130">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_178">The procedure which took place yesterday when I accused a member of the HSE of spending the public's money, was that I was lifted by the Chair for saying something about someone outside the House in a way which could have made that individual identifiable. Here we have the Leader of the Seanad impugning my character-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_131">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">I did not impugn the Senator's character at all.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_132">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">-----and stating there is a conflict of interest. He is not prepared to share it when the reality is quite different.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_133">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">I did not impugn the Senator's character.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_134">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">For my information, will the Leader please place on the record-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_135">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">Senator MacSharry-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_136">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">-----the nature of the conflict of interests to which he refers? Surely I am entitled to that information.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_137">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">Senator MacSharry-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_138">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">If the Leader is not prepared to do that now, I expect a full statement-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_139">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">Will Senator MacSharry resume his seat for a moment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_140">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">-----from the Government clarifying the position.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_141">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">Will the Senator resume his seat?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_142">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">Outside the doors of this Chamber, the Leader will not have the protection of privilege.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_143">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">The Leader should repeat his allegation outside the Seanad.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_144">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">The perception of bias is not a matter to be dealt with on the floor of the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">(Interruptions).</summary>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_145">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">This is an outrage. I accuse you of being partisan in order to protect the Government. What is happening here is a disgrace.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_146">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">Senator MacSharry's comments are outrageous.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_147">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">What is outrageous is what the Chair has allowed to be done to a Member of the House. It is a disgrace.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_148">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_196">That is an outrageous allegation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarcMacSharry" eId="spk_149">
          <from>Senator Marc MacSharry<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">It gives me no pleasure at all to say it, Sir. However, the Cathaoirleach is bringing the Chair and this House into disrepute by allowing this disgraceful impugning of the character of a Member.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_150">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">The Senator should please resume his seat.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineNoone" eId="spk_151">
          <from>Senator Catherine Noone<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">The Senator's accusation is worse than the one to which he is referring.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_152">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">It is not a worse accusation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TerryLeyden" eId="spk_153">
          <from>Senator Terry Leyden<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">On a point of order and from my personal knowledge of him, I am of the view that Senator MacSharry does not have a conflict of interest whatsoever.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_154">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">That is not a point of order.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TerryLeyden" eId="spk_155">
          <from>Senator Terry Leyden<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">If this is a court of law, then I am speaking for the defence of a Senator who has been accused by the Leader of this House of having a conflict of interest.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_156">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">That is not a point of order.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TerryLeyden" eId="spk_157">
          <from>Senator Terry Leyden<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">In Senator MacSharry's defence, I say that he has no such conflict of interest.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_158">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">Will Senator Leyden resume his seat?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_159">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">On a point of order, I have the height of respect for the Cathaoirleach and his impartiality. As Whip of the Fianna Fáil group, however, I must make it quite clear that we cannot allow the reply by the Leader to the Order of Business to continue until this matter has been resolved. I have nothing but the height of respect for the Chair, the Leader and every other Member but we cannot co-operate by allowing the Leader to continue with his reply to the Order of Business until this serious situation - which has serious implications for every Member of the House - has been resolved.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_160">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">I repeat my ruling to the effect that the perception of bias is not a matter to be dealt with on the floor of the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_161">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">Where should it be dealt with?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_162">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">We are talking here about an allegation. The Cathaoirleach should oblige the Leader to withdraw the allegation he made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineNoone" eId="spk_163">
          <from>Senator Catherine Noone<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">Senator MacSharry made a worse accusation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_164">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">There are guidelines which apply in this regard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineNoone" eId="spk_165">
          <from>Senator Catherine Noone<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">Those opposite should respect the Chair.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">(Interruptions).</summary>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_166">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">Could Members please allow the Cathaoirleach to speak?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_167">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">There are guidelines and legislation in place for dealing with this issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_168">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">What about the allegation? The Cathaoirleach does not need any guidelines to rule on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_169">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_217">I already made a ruling in that regard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_170">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">All I am asking is that, for our knowledge, the Cathaoirleach expand on that ruling, explain the nature of the guidelines and indicate how the matter will be dealt with.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_171">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">I am not expanding on my ruling.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_172">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">I need to know the position.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_173">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">On a point of order and as the Cathaoirleach rightly stated, we amended Standing Orders to cover the perception of bias. Those Standing Orders do not, however, cover the Leader of the House making an off-the-cuff allegation about one Member. In fact, I am of the view that the Leader has poisoned the banking inquiry in the context of the defamatory allegation he made. It is the responsibility of the Cathaoirleach to protect both the House and the Member involved by obliging the Leader to withdraw that allegation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_174">
          <from>Senator Paul Coghlan<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">The Leader made no allegation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_175">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_223">The allegation he made has nothing to do with the Standing Orders relating to the perception of bias.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelWDArcy" eId="spk_176">
          <from>Senator Michael D'Arcy<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">On a point of order, I think the Seanad should take some time to consider this matter. I propose, therefore, that the sitting be suspended for 30 minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_177">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">I second that proposal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_178">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">It is a matter for the Leader to propose that proceedings be suspended.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelWDArcy" eId="spk_179">
          <from>Senator Michael D'Arcy<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">I am asking that the Leader-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_180">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">I am not accepting the Senator's proposal. He is not the Leader of the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelWDArcy" eId="spk_181">
          <from>Senator Michael D'Arcy<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_229">I ask that the Leader move the suspension of proceedings for a period of 30 minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnCrown" eId="spk_182">
          <from>Senator John Crown<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">On a point of order, it has been brought to my attention that the only other occasion on which proposals from the Committee of Selection were challenged in the Seanad was when the Labour Party opposed former Senator Joe O'Toole's nomination to the Commission of the Houses of the Oireachtas. The Seanad stood by the committee's decision on that occasion. It should also be noted that Labour was in opposition at the time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_183">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">That is not relevant. I call on the Leader to reply to the Order of Business.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_184">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">I apologise but, with all due respect to the Cathaoirleach, the Leader and other Members, I made it quite clear that our group will not allow the Leader to continue with his reply to the Order of Business until this very serious matter - which relates to a Member of the House - is dealt with to our satisfaction.</p>
          <p eId="para_233">The House and, in particular, the Member are entitled to that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_185">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">A point of order.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulBradford" eId="spk_186">
          <from>Senator Paul Bradford<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_235">You may say it is not a point of order, a Chathaoirligh. Could I ask, as a long-serving Member of this House, that we reflect on the very sensible, wise and calm intervention of Senator Michael D'Arcy? We are all adults and surely if we could suspend for 20 minutes or half an hour it should be possible to resolve this difficulty. We do not want this House brought into disrepute. I formally second the proposal put before the House by Senator Michael D'Arcy, as he is entitled to do.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_187">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">I can only accept a proposal such as that from the Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_188">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">I will agree to a suspension of the House for 30 minutes so that the leaders can discuss this matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_189">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 11.50 a.m. and resumed at 12.20 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_190">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">To clarify the ruling that I made earlier in the House, on 5 February this year, the Seanad adopted Standing Orders which among other things set down procedures for dealing with perception of bias in relation to Members appointed to take part in a Part 2 inquiry under the Houses of Oireachtas (Inquiries, Privileges and Procedures) Act 2013. These procedures allow for written submissions in this regard, with supporting evidence, to be made to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges. A matter of this kind cannot be raised on the floor of the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_191">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">In light of the Chairman's ruling, I ask for a suspension of the House for a further half an hour to enable us to discuss the matter with the leaders.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_192">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">The only person who breached those Standing Orders this morning was the Leader of the House. The Cathaoirleach should ask him as a matter of course to withdraw the allegations that he made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulCoghlan" eId="spk_193">
          <from>Senator Paul Coghlan<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_242">He made no allegations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_194">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_243">Senator, the Leader has made a proposal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_195">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">I agree with the Leader's proposal for a further suspension so that the leaders and the Whips might discuss this matter. We fully understand the gravity of the situation and we shall try to facilitate the Government getting out of the mess that it created this morning.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_196">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">I would not agree with that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_197">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">I welcome the Cathaoirleach's clarification that any comment on any Member who is appointed to serve on the banking inquiry must go in writing to the CPP and cannot be mentioned on the floor of the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasByrne" eId="spk_198">
          <from>Senator Thomas Byrne<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">Will the Leader withdraw the allegation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_199">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T12:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">There was no allegation.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_9">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 12.27 p.m and resumed at 1 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_200">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">I call the Leader.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_201">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">I propose a further suspension of the House until 2 p.m.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_202">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_203">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">I also propose that we defer debate on the Companies Bill until next week.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_204">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T13:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_10">
          <i> Sitting suspended at 1.11 p.m. and resumed at 2.10 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_205">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">I ask the Leader to withdraw the remarks in relation to Senator MacSharry.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_206">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">I have listened to the recording of this morning's proceedings. What I actually said was that I had information of a suggested conflict of interest. It was only ever my intention to have the information I received considered by the Committee on Procedure and Privileges before any appointment to the committee of inquiry was ratified. I had no intention at any stage of impugning any Senator's integrity.</p>
          <p eId="para_256"> In view of the Cathaoirleach's ruling and in the interests of the harmony of the House and to allow today's business as scheduled to proceed, I am prepared to withdraw the words "conflict of interest". I am not prepared to go any further on the matter. I hope that the House will accept my bona fides on this matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_207">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">Is the Order of Business agreed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_208">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">No. What happened here today is most unfortunate. The Committee of Selection met legitimately with a quorum and selected Senators Seán D. Barrett and Marc MacSharry to be members of the banking inquiry. It is not in any way, shape or form coincidental that the statement made earlier by the Leader was directly related to that decision because it suits Government to have a majority on the inquiry and its nominee was not successful in being appointed. That is the background. It cannot be dressed up in any other way, shape or form. No one can disagree with that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_209">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">I can disagree with it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_210">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">Yes, but without credibility.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_211">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">With credibility.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_212">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_262">I have the utmost respect for the Leader. I have worked closely with him over the past three years and have the utmost regard for how he has always conducted himself in this House. For us, what happened this morning was a bridge too far. The Leader has withdrawn the remark of a suggested conflict of interest. I can tell him there is no conflict of interest. As per the Cathaoirleach's ruling, it was highly inappropriate for the Leader to raise this issue on the floor of the House today. That should not have happened.</p>
          <p eId="para_263"> The Leader should apologise to Senator MacSharry and his family for what has been said here today. I put it to him as a respected colleague that at the very least decency requires that he apologise in the House today to our colleague.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#BrianODomhnaill" eId="spk_213">
          <from>Senator Brian Ó Domhnaill<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">Hear, hear.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_214">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">That is appropriate. We all make mistakes. I have said things before that I regretted saying and I have apologised for them. Members here know that. There is no weakness in apologising and admitting one made a mistake. I put it to the Leader that the foundation of the banking inquiry is rocked owing to what happened last night at the Committee of Selection and the manner in which the Government has dealt with it here today, which was unprecedented. The public want a banking inquiry and deserve to have one. They also deserve a non-partisan banking inquiry. An independent committee of the Seanad met and according to procedures, selected two Members of this House for appointment to the inquiry. The Government parties are not happy with that decision. That is politics, life and democracy. That decision stands. It was made under Standing Order 89 and according to the Government's motion which came before this House on 14 May. As far as we are concerned, that is a separate issue. It is done and dusted in that two Members have been selected.</p>
          <p eId="para_266"> I acknowledge that the Leader has withdrawn part of the remarks he made earlier. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_215">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_267">All of them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_216">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_268">Okay. I welcome that. However, I believe it is not too much to ask that the Leader apologise to a colleague in the House for putting those remarks on the record of this House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnGilroy" eId="spk_217">
          <from>Senator John Gilroy<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_269">Be magnanimous.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_218">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_270">Senator O'Brien without interruption, please.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarraghOBrien" eId="spk_219">
          <from>Senator Darragh O'Brien<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_271">The Leader made a very serious charge earlier, which has already had ramifications in terms of the broadcasting of the proceedings of this House and on the Internet and so on. What happened is unfortunate. It should not have happened. It was a mistake. I put it to the Leader that it was an error of judgment. While acknowledging that the Leader has withdrawn the remarks, I ask that he apologise to our colleague. We can then move on to the business of the House and to ensuring that the two selected members, Senators Barrett and MacSharry, fulfil their role on the banking inquiry, as I am certain they will do.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_220">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_272">As I said previously, what I actually said was that based on information I had received, there was a suggested conflict of interest. I am prepared to withdraw those remarks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_221">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_273">Senator Bradford has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 16 be taken before No. 1". Is the amendment being pressed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulBradford" eId="spk_222">
          <from>Senator Paul Bradford<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_274">Is the Leader willing to accept the amendment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_223">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_275">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaddyBurke" eId="spk_224">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">The Leader of the House has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 4 be deleted from today's Order of Business." Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_11"> Question, "That the Order of Business, as amended, be agreed to", put and declared carried.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="motion" eId="dbsect_6">
        <heading>Notification of Vacancy in Seanad Éireann: Motion<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_225">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_277">I move:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_278">That the Clerk of Seanad Éireann do send to the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government notice of a vacancy in the membership of Seanad Éireann occasioned by the election to the European Parliament of Senator Deirdre Clune, a member elected from the Oireachtas Sub-Panel of the Cultural and Educational Panel at the General Election for Seanad Éireann, April, 2011."</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_12"> Question put and agreed to.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="motion" eId="dbsect_7">
        <heading>Address to Seanad Éireann by Ms Anne Brasseur: Motion<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#MauriceCummins" eId="spk_226">
          <from>Senator Maurice Cummins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">I move:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_280">That Seanad Éireann agrees with the recommendation of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges that, in accordance with the provisions for the address to Seanad Éireann by Distinguished Persons, Ms. Anne Brasseur, President of the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe, be invited to address Seanad Éireann on 12th June, 2014 and the following arrangements shall apply: </p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_281">(i) the proceedings at such address shall commence at 12 noon and shall consist of a speech by the Cathaoirleach welcoming President Brasseur, the address by the President at the conclusion of which she will reply to questions from Group Leaders and a speech of thanks by the Leas-Chathaoirleach for the address; </p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_282">(ii) the proceedings shall conclude no later than 1 p.m.” </p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_13"> Question put and agreed to.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" refersTo="#bill.2014.49.seanad.2_ord" eId="dbsect_8">
        <heading>Parliamentary Scrutiny of Appointments (European Commission) Bill 2014: Order for Second Stage<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:20:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <summary eId="sum_14">Bill entitled an Act to provide for the parliamentary scrutiny of the Government's proposed candidate for appointment as a member of the Commission of the European Union and to provide for related matters. </summary>
        <speech by="#PaulBradford" eId="spk_227">
          <from>Senator Paul Bradford<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_283">I move: "That Second Stage be taken next Tuesday, 10 June 2014."</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_15"> Question put and agreed to.</summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="billReport" refersTo="#bill.2013.90.seanad.4_sub" eId="dbsect_9">
        <heading>Friendly Societies and Industrial and Provident Societies (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2013 [Seanad]: Report and Final Stages<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:20:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#DenisODonovan" eId="spk_228">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_284">I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Sherlock, to the House to discuss the Bill.</p>
          <p eId="para_285"> Before we commence, I remind Members that a Senator may speak only once on Report Stage, except the proposer of an amendment, who may reply to the discussion on that amendment. Each amendment on Report Stage must be seconded. </p>
          <p eId="para_286"> Amendment No. 1 is in the name of Senators Barrett, Crown and Quinn and arose out of Committee proceedings. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanDBarrett" eId="spk_229">
          <from>Senator Sean D. Barrett<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_287">I move amendment No. 1:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_288">In page 6, between lines 16 and 17, to insert the following:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_289">“(3) Notwithstanding this section a person who wishes to carry on a regulated business can apply to the Central Bank of Ireland for authorisation to carry on such a business under the Central Bank and Financial Services Act 2003.”.”.</p>
          <p eId="para_290">I welcome the Minister of State to the House. He will be glad to hear that this is a friendly societies Bill. In that spirit, and arising from what we said on the last day, I have proposed amendments for his consideration.</p>
          <p eId="para_291"> Ireland needs a good portfolio of financial institutions, particularly given what has happened to banks, insurance companies, accountancy firms, pension funds, credit unions and building societies. There is an immense array of difficulties in the sector, as he will know because he is part of the work to correct them. Into that mosaic I would place friendly societies.</p>
          <p eId="para_292"> Let me explain what friendly societies do. They provide small life assurance benefits, sick benefits and death benefits to the members. I would not like to close the door on that happening again, particularly in the wake of such uncertainty about financial services. I recall the Minister for Finance's efforts to get new banks into this country, given the pillar banks' obsession with property and the danger of a cartel. Therefore, we need a new landscape for financial services.</p>
          <p eId="para_293"> I propose to amend the first section because it would mean that one could not form a friendly society in the future, ever. The second amendment proposes a restriction on the rating of new capital.</p>
          <p eId="para_294"> My third amendment seeks the following. If the Central Bank agrees to allow a new friendly society to be set up, and agrees to the new capital limits, would that be a way to solve the very slight difference of opinion between myself and the Minister of State, Deputy Sherlock? One of the statements on the Bill that he made on the last day reads:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_295">.... preliminary step in the process of establishing a system of the most appropriate supervision of certain existing societies, especially operating in the area of financial service provision. That is the ethos under which we are trying to introduce the legislation. It is intended that the group of societies would be subject to Central Bank supervision and that this would be the closed group.</p>
          <p eId="para_296">The only words that I differ with him on are "the closed group." What if new people want to set up friendly societies? Such societies have played a major part, and still do, in the adjoining island. They look after the savings and investments of 4.5 million people and have a total fund of £15 billion under investment.</p>
          <p eId="para_297"> As the Minister of State will know, friendly societies have not participated in some of the financial collapses that have occupied so much Government and parliamentary time in recent years. However, they could play a role and be regulated by the Central Bank. It is in the spirit of the very constructive discussion that we had on the last day that these amendments have been tabled for his consideration. Also, I will not push them to a vote. They are available for consideration by him, as the promoter of the Bill, and by his Department. They are also in line with the McDowell report on financial regulation in Ireland. In fact, the Minister of State has spoken about his knowledge of friendly societies in the Mallow area and, I think, Horace Plunkett was mentioned as well. </p>
          <p eId="para_298"> I would not write friendly societies or an expansion of their activities off. As he said himself, there seems to be a movement towards the Central Bank. It was also mentioned in the McDowell report. Would he afford the option as he brings the Bill through Parliament? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#FergalQuinn" eId="spk_230">
          <from>Senator Feargal Quinn<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_299">I am happy to second the amendment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanSherlock" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Jobs,_Enterprise_and_Innovation" eId="spk_231">
          <from>Minister of State at the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation (Deputy Sean Sherlock)<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_300">I thank the Senators for putting forward the amendment.</p>
          <p eId="para_301"> Section 5, which the Senators are proposing to amend, provides for a significant change to the Friendly Societies Act 1896. That is the cessation of registration of any new societies under section 8 of the legislation. The rationale for the change, as I set out on Second and Committee Stages, is twofold. First, the lack of demand for the friendly society model, evidenced by the fact that there have been just three new entrants in the past nine years. That gives a clear indication that the friendly society model is no longer favoured by newly-establishing organisations.</p>
          <p eId="para_302"> Second, current legislation does not provide for prudential supervision of friendly societies by any public authority. This is a source of some concern because there is some potential risk to the interests of certain members of the public where societies offer financial services. </p>
          <p eId="para_303"> Section 8 the 1896 Act sets out the types of society that may be registered. There is currently nothing in the section which would preclude a society from seeking the authorisation of the Central Bank, under the Central Bank and Financial Services Act 2003, to carry on a regulated business as defined in that Act.</p>
          <p eId="para_304"> The Central Bank Acts provide specific exemptions for friendly societies from the requirements that relate to banking. Under sections 7 and 8 of the Central Bank Act 1971 a friendly society is exempt from the requirement to hold a banking licence.</p>
          <p eId="para_305"> Under section 29(<i>a</i>) of the Central Bank Act 1997, a friendly society is exempt from the requirement to hold an authorisation as a retail credit firm. </p>
          <p eId="para_306"> I believe, therefore, that the amendment is unnecessary, and does not add to the Act in terms of clarity. There are no references to a "regulated business" in the Friendly Societies Acts and no definition of what is intended by the term. Introducing such a concept in the manner proposed by the amendment is not practical. Further, the amendment as drafted refers to "a person who wishes to carry on a regulated business" when the Act refers to societies, not persons. In the circumstances, I do not propose to accept the amendment because I do not believe it to be a workable amendment, as currently constituted.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DenisODonovan" eId="spk_232">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_307">Is the amendment being pressed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanDBarrett" eId="spk_233">
          <from>Senator Sean D. Barrett<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_308">I note what the Minister of State has said. Presumably, it is possible for those who wish to set up a friendly society to apply to the Central Bank. I do not know why the Registrar of Friendly Societies does not want to perform the role any more. She does not want anybody to submit an application to her to set up a new friendly society. I know there has not been much demand. We will have to reconfigure financial services here and I hope that fact might influence the Minister. Of all the financial landscapes, I cannot imagine a sector that has done less harm to the economy than the friendly societies but there we are.</p>
          <p eId="para_309">It echoes what we were discussing this morning in regard to banking. I will not press the amendment but I regret it was not accepted. The Parliament is shutting the door on the formation of friendly societies, the registrar does not want to do the task anymore and the Minister of State expressed the sentiment that the Central Bank of Ireland may take over the role. Having expressed my regret, I thank the Minister of State for his consideration but I will not press the amendment.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_16"> Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</summary>
        <speech by="#SeanDBarrett" eId="spk_234">
          <from>Senator Sean D. Barrett<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_310">I move amendment No. 2:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_311">In page 6, between lines 30 and 31, to insert the following:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_312">“(c) the formation of a separate loan fund has received authorisation under the Central Bank and Financial Services Act 2003,”.</p>
          <p eId="para_313">We seek to have the creation of a separate loan fund at the discretion of the Central Bank. The registrar does not wish to see separate loan funds being created and the purpose of this section is to shut it down. We are affording friendly societies that wish to use this way of creating loan funds the possibility to expand under the regulation of the Central Bank. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_235" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Jobs,_Enterprise_and_Innovation">
          <from>Deputy Sean Sherlock<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_314">Section 6, which the Senators are proposing to amend, places restrictions on existing societies establishing a loan fund, as provided for in section 46 of the principal Friendly Societies Act 1896 where they do not already have such a fund in place. The change will not have an impact on existing societies that have a fund in place. This amounts to three societies at present. The rationale behind the change, as mentioned on Committee Stage and on Second Stage, is that such activity where it is operated by any other body, is subject to prudential supervision by the Central Bank. There is no prudential supervision by any public authority in the case of a friendly society. While the number of friendly societies operating a loan fund is very small, it is not in the interests of the members of friendly societies that new funds be permitted to be established without appropriate prudential supervision. I hope that addresses the essential spirit of the overarching point made by Senator Barrett.</p>
          <p eId="para_315"> In section 6, our aim is to prevent friendly societies - apart from the small number already engaged in such activity - from operating a loan fund that is not subject to prudential supervision. The exception provided is to allow any application that may be in hand, where an application to register a rule change has been passed by the society and lodged with the registrar by the operative date, to progress under the current rules so that it will not disadvantaged an existing society. Given the general lack of interest, even among existing societies, in operating in the area, an influx of societies seeking to establish loan funds is not anticipated.</p>
          <p eId="para_316"> The Senator's proposal is worded to amend section 6 and to require that "the formation of a separate loan fund" should receive authorisation under the Central Bank and Financial Services Act 2003. This is not a workable amendment because the Act authorises the carrying on of the financial activity itself, namely, the granting of loans, not formation of the fund. On that basis, I do not propose to accept the amendment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DenisODonovan" eId="spk_236">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_317">If the amendment is being pressed, it will have to be seconded. Is the Senator pursuing the amendment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanDBarrett" eId="spk_237">
          <from>Senator Sean D. Barrett<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_318">I was trying to take up the invitation of the Minister of State to address the fact that we have no prudential supervision of friendly societies by putting it under the Central Bank. The registrar does not want to do it, the Central Bank does not want to do it and the friendly societies cannot set up loan funds. That we run into these culs-de-sac explains the background to some of the financial mess the country is in. Maybe we will refer it onto all the other contentious items before the banking review. It was plain under section 6 that a society may not establish a loan fund after the coming into operation of the section. As the Minister of State said, it does not affect an existing society that currently operates a loan fund. We tried to set up a facility where the friendly society could operate the loan fund under the Central Bank, which is the financial services authority for the country, and the amendment was not acceptable. I accept what the Minister of State said.</p>
          <p eId="para_319"> If there is so little interest and appetite for regulating the sector in respect of the Registrar of Friendly Societies, perhaps it can be transferred to the Central Bank. Maybe the banking committee will look into this matter. I see the sector having a much better future than the Bill envisages and I would not rule it out. I will not press the amendment. Certain contradictions are manifest. This is shutting off options for a sector that might very well have a role to play. I thank the Minister of State.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_17"> Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</summary>
        <speech by="#SeanDBarrett" eId="spk_238">
          <from>Senator Sean D. Barrett<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_320">I move amendment No. 3:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_321">In page 7, between lines 14 and 15, to insert the following:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_322">“(5) The powers, functions and duties of the registrar of friendly societies under sections 5 and 6 shall be transferred to the Central Bank of Ireland from the operative date.”.”.</p>
          <p eId="para_323">Given the lack of interest and lack of appetite from the Registrar of Friendly Societies, the amendment suggests that the Central Bank takes over. This was the intention of the McDowell report in any case. We need financial regulation in the country and it is a matter for the banking inquiry. That is why I tabled the amendment. Friendly societies play a big role in other countries, particularly the United Kingdom, and the sector has not been developed here as I and the Minister of State would wish. Why shut it off rather than have comprehensive regulation of financial services? In the adjoining island, friendly societies have 4.5 million members and total funds of €15 billion. We have a very pessimistic view in the Bill about the possibility of such development. Would it develop better under regulation by the Central Bank? This is the reason behind the amendment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_239" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Jobs,_Enterprise_and_Innovation">
          <from>Deputy Sean Sherlock<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_324">Section 8, which the Senators are proposing to amend, removes the restriction in the current Act providing that the registrar must be absent for the powers, functions and duties to be exercised and performed by such other person as the Minister may authorise, and allows another person to act alongside the registrar. The change is necessary as, for the past number of years, the role of Registrar of Friendly Societies has not been a dedicated role, but has been fulfilled by the Registrar of Companies in addition to her existing duties.</p>
          <p eId="para_325"> The amendment proposed by the Senators, which I understand seeks to transfer powers of the Registrar of Friendly Societies to the Central Bank, will not operate as intended by the Senators because section 5 of the 1977 Act sets out powers of the Minister with regard to the Registrar of Friendly Societies and not the powers of the registrar. There is a reference to the powers, functions and duties of the registrar in section 5 but it relates to who may be authorised by the Minister to perform these powers, rather than setting out the powers themselves. Section 6 of the 1977 Act does relate to a specific power regarding cancellation of the registration of societies but, as I do not believe it to be the intention of the Senators in drafting this amendment to transfer powers solely relating to cancellation of societies to the Central Bank, I do not accept the amendment.</p>
          <p eId="para_326"> It is intended to examine further with the Central Bank and the Department of Finance the issue of appropriate prudential supervision for friendly societies. At present the powers to exercise such supervision do not exist under the friendly societies legislation and therefore appropriate powers must be put in place. No existing powers can be simply transferred. It is considered that the best place to address the matter is under the Central Bank Acts rather than the Friendly Societies Acts.</p>
          <p eId="para_327"> I wish to restate what I said on previous Stages. The Friendly Societies Acts do not confer corporate status on societies or limited liability on members. The evidence in recent years is that it has become common practice for many charities and clubs to register as limited companies. I hope to give some confidence to Senator Barrett in addressing the points he has made by reiterating that the most realistic institutional option for introducing an appropriate system of supervision is the Central Bank, which is at the centre of financial supervision and financial stability oversight. It has a responsibility to provide in a fully integrated and co-ordinated manner for the prudential supervision and stability of all financial services within the financial system as a whole. To avoid the possibility of other bodies moving into this unregulated area it was decided to close registration to new friendly societies.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanDBarrett" eId="spk_240">
          <from>Senator Sean D. Barrett<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_328">Section 8 states, "The powers, functions and duties of the registrar of friendly societies may be exercised and performed by such person or persons as the Minister may for the time being authorise." We have added a subsection that states, "The powers, functions and duties of the registrar of friendly societies under sections 5 and 6 shall be transferred to the Central Bank of Ireland from the operative date." That is what the Minister of State has said and he is working on it. I believe we are far closer than it might appear.</p>
          <p eId="para_329"> I wish the exercise Godspeed. I would prefer if the reference was in the Bill. The Minister of State is thinking about it and I commend him on that. Let us put in a reference such that it will go to the Central Bank since the powers exist under section 8. Our amendment proposes that the issue of new start-ups and loan funds should also be considered by the Central Bank.</p>
          <p eId="para_330"> I am happy to leave that with the Minister of State and his officials for consideration. I hope that the Minister of State and the Governor, Professor Honohan, will bring proposals back to the House soon. That is the logical place to have it. I agree with what the Minister of State has said. I was simply trying to get it down on print in his Bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_18"> Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_19"> Bill received for final consideration.</summary>
        <summary eId="sum_20"> Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</summary>
        <speech by="#SeanSherlock" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Jobs,_Enterprise_and_Innovation" eId="spk_241">
          <from>Minister of State at the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation (Deputy Sean Sherlock)<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_331">I wish to take a few brief moments to thank the Members for their contribution to the debate. In particular, I thank those Senators who put down amendments. I assure them that the area of financial prudential supervision is something that is been taken seriously. This is best carried out through the Central Bank Acts. While I am not accepting the amendment I hope we have addressed adequately the substantive issues in the legislation. I thank the Senators for their co-operation and their time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanDBarrett" eId="spk_242">
          <from>Senator Sean D. Barrett<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_332">I thank the Minister of State and wish him success in any contest in which he might be participating in the near future.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMullins" eId="spk_243">
          <from>Senator Michael Mullins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_333">I pay tribute to the Senators who put down the amendments. The process has given us greater insight into the workings of the friendly societies. Important amendments have been introduced in the area of industrial and providential societies aimed at making the regulatory burden on co-operative societies easier and making examinership, which is currently unavailable to co-operative societies, accessible. This is very much to be welcomed. A good day's work has been done in the passing of this legislation. I thank the Minister of State for steering it successfully through the House.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarieMoloney" eId="spk_244">
          <from>Senator Marie Moloney<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_334">I thank the Minister of State for bringing the Bill through the House. I commend the Independent Senators, in particular, Senator Barrett, who always has a valuable contribution to make and who has a deep knowledge of these issues. I thank Senator Barrett for withdrawing his amendment and not pushing it to a vote. I thank the Minister of State again.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_21"> Question put and agreed to.</summary>
        <speech by="#DenisODonovan" eId="spk_245">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_335">The Companies Bill has been deferred to next week so this concludes the business. When is it proposed to sit again?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMullins" eId="spk_246">
          <from>Senator Michael Mullins<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_336">At 2.30 p.m. next Tuesday, 10 June 2014.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_10">
        <heading>Adjournment Matters<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:40:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_11">
          <heading>Garda Investigations<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:40:00+01:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#TrevorOClochartaigh" eId="spk_247">
            <from>Senator Trevor Ó Clochartaigh<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:40:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_337">Cuirim céad fáilte roimh an Aire Stáit. Seo ábhar a d'ardaigh mé cúpla uair roimhe seo sa Teach, ábhar a bhaineann le hiar-cheannasaí Chumann na bhFiann, Domhnall Ó Lubhlaí. I am raising an issue that has been raised previously in the Houses but time has moved on and there have been many developments in justice issues since the last time we debated the issue.</p>
            <p eId="para_338"> There have been allegations concerning the founder of Cumann na bhFiann, Domhnall Ó Lubhlaí. He was the subject of a TG4 documentary some time back which examined claims that he may have abused dozens of victims in the 1970s and 1980s. It was alleged that Ó Lubhlaí, who has passed away, may have abused up to 100 boys when he was an Irish and religion teacher. Some of the alleged incidents took place in camps, hotels, flats and cinemas in Athlone, Rosmuc, Dublin, Donegal and Tipperary. He died some time back while under investigation for sexually abusing a 13 year old boy in the 1970s.</p>
            <p eId="para_339"> The Garda investigated allegations of abuse in 1988 and in 2002 the teacher faced 56 charges of sexual abuse involving 11 victims. However, the case did not go ahead following a legal challenge. At the time the case was live, the Rape Crisis Centre claimed that the Garda had had two opportunities to investigate the allegations against Ó Lubhlaí, who the centre described as very influential and a powerful figure. The centre called on the Garda Commissioner to ensure a full review to ascertain if the Garda utilised the opportunity of the investigation in 1991 to examine whether abuse had taken place, a procedure practised elsewhere in such cases.</p>
            <p eId="para_340"> Questions also surround the loss of vital evidence from the 1991 case which, in turn, impacted on an investigation in 1998, when five men came forward and reported sexual violence by Ó Lubhlaí. In response to queries about the case at the time, the Garda press office said it did not discuss named individuals. The matter was passed on to the then Commissioner, Mr. Callinan, who said that he had directed a re-examination of the case to identify any issues that needed to be addressed. He also outlined the new policies in place.</p>
            <p eId="para_341"> We know that the allegations against Mr. Ó Lubhlaí date from 1955 and that he had opportunities to work in different areas as well as access to young people. I have been in contact with several of the victims and their families. They remain concerned that the truth has not been given to them around these issues. They are keen to find out what will happen about it at this stage.</p>
            <p eId="para_342"> Several investigations have been instigated relating to the Garda Síochána, the Garda Síochána Ombudsman Commission, the Department of Justice and Equality, etc. I note that the new Minister has called for an independent review group to be put in place to examine issues around the Department of Justice and Equality. In this case the victims believe that they have not got justice. Some people believe not all information has been forthcoming. Several Departments have a role in respect of the questions that they have asked, including the Department of Education and Skills, the Department of Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, the HSE and the Department of Justice and Equality. In the review called for by the Minister, Deputy Fitzgerald, will she include or has she directed that the Ó Lubhlaí case be examined, how it was handled and how the review of the case was handled by the Department of Justice and Equality? Is that included? Can it be included? It is most important for the victims in this case and other cases to get full justice and to be assured that justice has been done.</p>
            <p eId="para_343">If the Department, the Garda or other Departments were remiss in any way in any review undertaken, investigation carried out or evidence that might have gone missing, they deserve to know the truth. I hope the Minister of State will be able to confirm that the Minister will take this on board in the review being carried out.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#SeanSherlock" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Jobs,_Enterprise_and_Innovation" eId="spk_248">
            <from>Minister of State at the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation (Deputy Sean Sherlock)<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:50:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_344">I am speaking on behalf of the Minister for Justice and Equality who is unable to be present as she is attending a meeting of EU Justice and Home Affairs Ministers in Luxembourg. I thank the Senator for raising this important matter and acknowledge the consistency with which he has advocated on it.</p>
            <p eId="para_345"> As the Minister recently announced, an independent review group has been established to undertake a review of the Department of Justice and Equality. The independent review group, chaired by Mr. Kevin Toland, has been asked to undertake a comprehensive review of the performance, management and administration of the Department. It will assess and report on the roles, responsibilities and capabilities of the Department, including the following: concerns in respect of the governance and oversight of external organisations identified in particular in the report of Mr. Sean Guerin, SC; the Department's performance in discharging its responsibilities, implementing its programmes and achieving its desired strategic outcomes, as set out in its statement of strategy; and the effectiveness of the Department's current structure, systems, management and capabilities.</p>
            <p eId="para_346"> In making its recommendations the group will have regard to the policy, legal, institutional and resource framework within which the Department works. It will also draw on international best practice regarding the organisational structures, skills, training and levels required by the Department in order that it can fulfil its roles and responsibilities. It may engage additional expertise to help with its work, as it sees fit. Based on the conclusions and lessons drawn from this assessment, it will make recommendations to the Minister who has already commented that she believes the report will be an important signpost on the path to reform and enable the Department to build on its considerable strengths and fully address areas that need improvement.</p>
            <p eId="para_347"> Before I comment on the specific case referred to by the Senator, I wish to make it clear that the Minister does not wish in any way to pre-empt the work of the independent review group or how it will focus its efforts in the light of its terms of reference. At this stage, she would simply reflect that it was not anticipated that the independent review group would necessarily be the best means to address the detail of specific cases such as the one referred to, although its findings will, of course, be relevant to how the range of the Department's functions are delivered. The Department is not aware of any question having arisen relating to the Department in the context of the case referred to by the Senator. It, of course, is not involved in the investigation of criminal offences.</p>
            <p eId="para_348"> The Garda Commissioner previously directed that an examination be carried out of the procedures surrounding the handling of the complaints against the person in question. The Minister is advised by the Garda authorities that a review has been completed of a number of complaints made against the person concerned. However, further information has recently been provided for the Garda and this has necessitated further examination by gardaí before the review can be finalised. The Minister is advised that this process is ongoing.</p>
            <p eId="para_349"> The Minister wishes to assure the Senator that the need to learn from past child protection failures is a priority for her and the Government. This is reflected in the transformation of child protection arrangements which have taken place since the Government took office. In particular, the Senator will be aware of the recent publication by the Minister when she was Minister for Children and Youth Affairs of the Children First Bill 2014 which will, for the first time, provide for key elements of the Children First guidelines to be put on a statutory basis. This builds on other significant legislative and administrative measures which have been put in place in recent years to better protect children. In the light of the Minister's clear commitment in this regard, she will be asking the acting Garda Commissioner to ensure the review in question is completed as soon as possible.</p>
            <p eId="para_350"> I again thank the Senator for raising the issue. I will convey his comments during this debate to the Minister.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#TrevorOClochartaigh" eId="spk_249">
            <from>Senator Trevor Ó Clochartaigh<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:50:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_351">I appreciate that the Garda has been given further information. That is very important. There is a sense among the victims and observers who have studied the case that the investigation to date has not been up to scratch. We know that there are questions about how the Garda has investigated certain issues in the past and that that is subject to a number of inquiries. I ask the Minister of State to impress on the Minister how important it is for the victims in this case that a full, thorough and rigorous investigation be carried out in order that they can find closure, that the truth can be exposed and that they can move on with their lives.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_250" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Jobs,_Enterprise_and_Innovation">
            <from>Deputy Sean Sherlock<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:50:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_352">I acknowledge the points made by the Senator. I will convey these concerns to the Minister on his behalf.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_12">
          <heading>School Accommodation<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:50:00+01:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#CaitKeane" eId="spk_251">
            <from>Senator Cáit Keane<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T14:50:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_353">I thank the Minister of State for attending to take this matter. I hope he will be able to tell me that he will put children first in terms of the Children First guidelines and the safety of children. The matter I raise concerns the Firhouse Educate Together national school and the premises in which it is located. The school is located in temporary, unsuitable accommodation which was originally built to be a community centre, not a school. The school is housed upstairs. The parents, teachers and local community are all very anxious about the unsuitability of the current premises for it.</p>
            <p eId="para_354"> Firhouse Educate Together national school is a very good one. The education provided and teachers are excellent, but the premises leaves a great deal to be desired, to put it mildly. It is absolutely unsuitable. If a safety analysis was to be conducted, it would not pass. The stairs are very steep and there is no wheelchair access. There is dual usage of the community centre and crowding at times when children are moving from one place to another. It is a serious issue.</p>
            <p eId="para_355"> The Department of Education and Skills is responsible for the safety of children, which is an issue in the school. When the school was accommodated in the premises, the Department stated initially, in September 2013, that it would be for four months. That stretched to six months and then eight. There is overcrowding in the staff room which is shared with learning support staff and when I visited the school, there was a child there who required special support. It is totally unsuitable. There is one toilet which is used by the public also. The community centre and the people in it are fine, but the community is being discommoded by having an educational establishment where there was never meant to be one. The community is very understanding and welcoming of the school, but it was to be temporary. It has been based there too long and, as time passes, is not viable.</p>
            <p eId="para_356"> The school had intended to grow. Owing to its good name, it had sufficient children enrolled to secure another teacher next year, but now parents are starting to look at the long-term position and wonder where their children will be if the school does not have a permanent location very soon. Some are beginning to look at other schools, even schools outside the area, if they wish to have their children attend an Educate Together school. If the school is to be viable, it must receive immediate assistance.</p>
            <p eId="para_357"> I asked the Minister for Education and Skills about this issue last November. In the south Dublin local area plan two sites were designated for education in the Firhouse area. The sites are available. I do not know if they are suitable or whether they are for the Educate Together national school, but perhaps the Minister of State might comment or offer some certainty on where the school will be located next September. Obviously, it cannot continue where it is located at present and operating in very difficult circumstances for the students, staff and parents. The safety issues must also be taken into consideration. The Minister must immediately find suitable accommodation for the school.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_252" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Jobs,_Enterprise_and_Innovation">
            <from>Deputy Sean Sherlock<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T15:00:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_358">I thank the Senator for raising this issue. As a Minister of State in the relevant Department, I am acutely aware of the predicament in which that school community finds itself. I take this opportunity to inform the House that I am not going to read directly from the prepared script.</p>
            <p eId="para_359"> As I understand it, the Firhouse Educate Together school was established to service a specific demographic demand within the Firhouse area. The Senator referred to the South Dublin County Council plan, etc., and in that context, the school should ideally have a permanent home within or as close to the geographical area in which it is currently located as possible in order to meet people's needs. A process is ongoing whereby officials from the Department of Education and Skills are working with their counterparts in South Dublin County Council in order to acquire a suitable site. In the context of the Department's geographical information system and analysis, the Ballycullen-Oldcourt area is considered a separate and distinct geographical area. The local area plan for Ballycullen-Oldcourt refers to the planned future additional population. This means that the area will have educational infrastructural requirements in its own right should the planned housing developments for it materialise.</p>
            <p eId="para_360"> I am given to understand that the process relating to identifying and acquiring a site for Firhouse Educate Together is ongoing. The Senator indicated that she previously raised this matter last November. It has been my experience that the process of acquiring land tends to be open-ended in nature. It is very difficult, for example, to put in place sunset clauses in respect of the acquisition of land or to disregard the commercial sensitivities involved. The process is ongoing and due to the kind of commercial sensitivities to which I refer, it is not possible to provide further information at this time. I am sure the Senator has heard that before and I do not wish to offer her any platitudes in respect of this issue. I am aware, however, from my dealings with the officials in the Department, that when interacting with local authorities, there is a process which must be undergone. The process is not seamless and can involve many twists and turns. That will come as no comfort to Senator Keane in the context of her attempts to represent the interests of the people who made representations to her. I assure her that I will raise the matter with the relevant officials in the Department and that I will exert as much pressure as possible in the context of establishing the current position.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#CaitKeane" eId="spk_253">
            <from>Senator Cáit Keane<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T15:00:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_361">I referred to the two sites in question because I am aware of both. I am also aware that one lies outside the boundary. The Minister of State referred to site selection and indicated that the process of acquiring land is ongoing. I am aware that attempts were made to acquire a public open space, namely, a football field and that the local community was opposed to this. Will the Minister of State confirm that the proposal to purchase this land is no longer on the table? There are several groups involved here, namely, the school community and those who play football and use the land in question for the purpose of engaging in physical exercise. When he refers to commercial sensitivities, I presume the Minister of State is referring to sensitivities which relate to some private as opposed to public land the Department is seeking to acquire. Seeking to acquire land from a local authority such as South Dublin County Council is one thing, whereas seeking to purchase it from a private owner is quite another.</p>
            <p eId="para_362"> I accept that there are commercial sensitivities involved but people must be allowed to know what is happening. In view of what is happening in respect of property throughout Dublin at present, the land is going to be for sale on the open market in any event. I do not want it to be a case that the sale of the land will be signed, sealed and delivered and that the new school will be built there. I want a school to be built which will be within the Firhouse area and which will suit the demographic needs of that area. If the Minister of State has the relevant information about a possible site in his possession, he should make it available. It should certainly be made available before September in order that those at Firhouse Educate Together will know that a site will be acquired for it.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_254" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Jobs,_Enterprise_and_Innovation">
            <from>Deputy Sean Sherlock<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T15:00:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_363">I accept those points and I recognise that Firhouse Educate Together is currently occupying temporary accommodation, which is certainly not ideal. I have come across situations such as this previously whereby schoolchildren are being obliged to learn in what can only be described as Dickensian conditions while they await the provision of permanent accommodation. I wish to give Senator Keane an undertaking to the effect that I will raise this matter within the Department. I must point out, however, that it is not only in respect of the acquisition of privately-owned land that sensitivities arise. I take the Senator's point regarding the upward trajectory of property prices in the Dublin area. However, sensitivities also arise when land is being transferred from one public body, local authority or State entity to another. There are many legalities which must be dealt with in that context. Regardless of whether it is a private or public entity involved, the process is not seamless. As a result, the acquisition of a suitable site is taking some time to bring to a conclusion. I fully acknowledge that. I will bring the points made by Senator Keane to the attention of the officials within the Department.</p>
          </speech>
        </debateSection>
        <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_13">
          <heading>Pupil-Teacher Ratio<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T15:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
          <speech by="#PaulBradford" eId="spk_255">
            <from>Senator Paul Bradford<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T15:00:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_364">I welcome the Minister of State. I am glad he is here to take this matter because, as a result of the fact that he represents the constituency of Cork East, he is aware that the issue of small schools in rural areas is beginning to become one of concern throughout the county.</p>
            <p eId="para_365"> The Minister of State will be aware of the relevant statistics and I am sure he will correct what I am about to say if it is incorrect. The figures available to me seem to suggest that there are approximately 600 schools throughout the country with 50 or fewer pupils. Obviously, this poses a challenge for school authorities, the Department and the Minister, Deputy Quinn, in the context of the allocation of resources. We must acknowledge the very proactive role the schools to which I refer play in small rural communities. Small schools are very much at the centre of life in rural areas, particularly in the context of the number of activities they facilitate.</p>
            <p eId="para_366"> I wish to refer to the challenges that will be faced by some of the schools in question as a result of the change to the pupil-teacher ratio and I appreciate the huge financial constraints under which the Minister, the Department and the Government continue to operate. When Budget 2012 was introduced, it was announced that the pupil-teacher ratio would be changed over a three-year period. The latter is going to place small rural schools at a significant disadvantage because the number of pupils per teacher and per class is obviously going to increase quite significantly. Anyone can romanticise the notion of the small rural school where there are two, three or four classes in a single room and where every child sings along happily with his or her teacher. That is only one side of the story. We live in the modern world and the educational challenges which arise are greater than ever. I refer to the fact that people have high expectations of schools and teachers. We are placing a huge onus on teachers to produce results and to guide young children through their early years in education. It is going to become increasingly difficult for teachers to do their job as they would like to do it if they are going to be obliged to deal with 28 or 29 pupils spread across two or three classes. This is a matter upon which we must reflect.</p>
            <p eId="para_367"> I received correspondence from a teacher - the Minister of State may also have received it - who asked children in senior classes the differences they had noticed a month after class sizes had been increased. The children replied that they needed to do more writing and that if they required help from the teacher, they were obliged to wait longer for it. The teacher in question notes that children who are weaker academically are not served well by larger class sizes because there is little or no time available in which to give them additional attention.</p>
            <p eId="para_368">We must do everything possible to maintain these rural schools, because they play a significant role, not just in the educational but in the broader life of the community. When we have done that and have secured every possible school we can and its future, we must try to ensure the pupil-teacher ratio in that school is appropriate to the needs of the pupils, teachers and community.</p>
            <p eId="para_369"> I am advised that in disadvantaged DEIS areas the maximum pupil-teacher ratio, in infant classes in particular, is 20 pupils. I have no disagreement with that and believe it is appropriate, though perhaps 20 is too many. We are talking about classes in some of our small rural schools which can have 28, 29 or 30 pupils. I ask the Minister of State and the Minister to reflect on this and to try to ensure, in so far as they can, that these schools will receive the teaching allocations they require to allow them continue the fine traditions such schools, communities and parishes have had for generations.</p>
            <p eId="para_370"> I admit we live in a changing time and world, but we need traditional stability. Our schools can provide that, our small rural schools in particular. However, there must be willingness on the part of the Department to provide resources to allow sufficient teachers for those schools. I do not expect a major policy announcement today, but I ask the Minister of State to use his good offices to keep these rural schools and their teachers and communities at the centre of the Department's thinking.</p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#SeanSherlock" eId="spk_256" as="#Minister_of_State_at_the_Department_of_Jobs,_Enterprise_and_Innovation">
            <from>Deputy Sean Sherlock<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T15:10:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_371">I thank Senator Bradford for raising this issue. The criteria used for the allocation of teachers to schools is published annually. I accept the point made by the Senator in regard to budget 2012, whereby as part of that budget there is a phased increase in the number of pupils required to gain and retain a classroom teaching post in small primary schools with four teachers or less. The current system operates on the basis of a general average of one classroom teacher for every 28 pupils, with lower thresholds for DEIS band 1 schools. I have not seen the correspondence Senator Bradford referred to, but I acknowledge pressures are being brought to bear in terms of the classroom experience, both for pupils and for teachers. I acknowledge also that budgetary measures taken in 2012 brought pressure, a result of macro-economic factors.</p>
            <p eId="para_372"> The Department has expanded the existing appeals process so that it is accessible to the schools that are affected by the budget measure. Small schools will not lose their classroom post if they project sustainable increased enrolments in September 2014 that would be sufficient to allow them to retain their existing classroom posts over the longer term. We are all aware of the appeals process and the staffing circulars and the processes involved. </p>
            <p eId="para_373"> I acknowledge the general point being made by the Senator that we must ensure there is a role for small schools within rural communities. Both he and I hail from the same region and such communities. The Department has taken a conscious decision to ensure that schools which had no inward investment for many years, for example, in regard to capital expenditure and bricks and mortar, are seeing investment. Projects are now going on throughout our region and the country to replace prefabs with bricks and mortar. This is part of trying to make the experience for students and school communities better. In rural areas, these schools are the institutions underpinning the community. </p>
            <p eId="para_374"> The Senator will be aware that a value for money review was conducted on small primary schools. The review took account of the ethos of schools and of their locations relative to other similar schools. We are currently considering the value for money reviews, in consultation with Government colleagues, and it is intended to publish the report on completion of the consideration process. We are very mindful of the points raised by Senator Bradford in regard to the budget 2012 measures. We seek to ensure we have a sustainable model for the future, but I acknowledge there are challenges in that regard. </p>
            <p eId="para_375"> The Minister has had initial discussions with the Catholic Primary Schools Management Association, CPSMA, and the Irish National Teachers Organisation in regard to their proposals on the issue of primary school consolidation and reorganisation. We acknowledge that some 48 small schools have had a reduction in enrolments, which means that for September 2014 they will lose a teacher. We acknowledge these losses would not have occurred if the pre-budget 2012 enrolment threshold still applied and if the threshold for a two-teacher school had remained at 12 pupils. We acknowledge the constraints that exist currently. However, the value for money review is under consideration and will be published. </p>
            <p eId="para_376"> Speaking personally, I will advocate strongly for assurances to be given on the future of schools and for consultation and engagement with stakeholders in a meaningful process of dialogue which will ensure a future for these schools. Then we can begin to address the dynamic the Senator outlined in regard to the new pressures that exist in particular schools and classrooms as economic circumstances improve. </p>
          </speech>
          <speech by="#MichaelMullins" as="#Acting_Chairman" eId="spk_257">
            <from>Acting Chairman (Senator Michael Mullins)<recordedTime time="2014-06-05T15:10:00+01:00"/></from>
            <p eId="para_377">Before we finish, I would like to welcome our special visitors to the Gallery.</p>
          </speech>
          <summary eId="sum_22"> The Seanad adjourned at 3.20 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 10 June 2014.</summary>
        </debateSection>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
